<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-141"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-141</statuteno><catchline>Failure to eliminate unlawful practice by conference, conciliation, and persuasion; written notice; hearing; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) In case of failure to eliminate any unlawful practice by informal methods of conference, conciliation, and persuasion, the commission shall cause to be issued and served in the name of the commission a written notice, together with a copy of the complaint, requiring the person named in the complaint, hereinafter referred to as respondent, to answer the charges of the complaint at a public hearing, at a time and place to be specified in the notice. The place of the hearing shall be in the county in which the alleged discrimination occurred.</para><para>(2) The case in support of the complaint shall be presented before the commission by an attorney on the staff of the Attorney General, and the investigator who made the investigation shall not participate in the hearings except as a witness, nor shall he participate in the deliberation of the commission in the case. Evidence concerning endeavors at conciliation may be included.</para><para>(3) The respondent may file a written verified answer to the complaint and appear at the hearing with or without counsel, submit testimony, and compel the appearance of witnesses and records in his behalf. At the discretion of the commission, the complainant may be allowed to intervene and present testimony in person or by counsel. The commission may reasonably and fairly amend any complaint either prior to or during the hearing in accordance with facts developed by the investigation or adduced in evidence at the hearing, and the respondent may amend his answer in the same manner. The testimony taken at the hearing shall be under oath and be transcribed.</para><para>(4) If, upon all the evidence at the hearing, the commission finds that a respondent has engaged in an unlawful discriminatory practice as defined in sections 20-132 to 20-143, the commission shall state its findings of fact and shall issue and cause to be served on the respondent an order requiring the respondent to cease and desist from the unlawful discriminatory practice and to take such affirmative action, including, but not limited to, the extension of full, equal, and unsegregated accommodations, advantages, facilities, and privileges to all persons as in the judgment of the commission will effectuate the purposes of sections 20-132 to 20-143, including a requirement for a report of the manner of compliance.</para><para>(5) If, upon all the evidence, the commission finds that a respondent has not engaged in any unlawful discriminatory practice, the commission shall state its findings of fact and shall issue and cause to be served on the complainant an order dismissing the complaint as to the respondent. A copy of the order shall be delivered in all cases to the Attorney General and such other public officers as the commission deems proper.</para><para>(6) The commission shall establish rules of practice to govern, expedite, and effectuate the procedure set forth in this section and its own actions thereunder. Any complaint filed pursuant to this section must be so filed within ten days after the alleged act of discrimination and the complainant shall give written notice of the filing of the complaint and furnish a copy thereof to the party complained against.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 112, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For provisions of Equal Opportunity Commission,</emphasis> see sections 48-1116 and 48-1117.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>