<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-168"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-168</statuteno><catchline>Employment, dwelling, school district, place of public accommodation; discrimination prohibited; civil action; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) An employer shall not (a) refuse to hire an individual, (b) discharge an individual, or (c) otherwise discriminate against an individual with respect to compensation or terms, conditions, or privileges of employment on the basis that the individual is suffering or is suspected of suffering from human immunodeficiency virus infection or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.</para><para>(2) A seller or lessor shall not refuse to sell or lease a dwelling as defined in section 20-310 to an individual on the basis that the individual, a member of the individual's family, or a person who will be residing with the individual is suffering or is suspected of suffering from human immunodeficiency virus infection or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.</para><para>(3) A school district shall not deny admission to a student on the basis that the student is suffering or is suspected of suffering from human immunodeficiency virus infection or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.</para><para>(4) A place of public accommodation as defined in section 20-133 shall not deny equal access to such public accommodation on the basis that the individual is suffering or is suspected of suffering from human immunodeficiency virus infection or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome.</para><para>(5) Any individual who has been discriminated against in violation of this section may file a civil action to enforce this section in the district court of the county where the discrimination is alleged to have occurred. The remedy granted by this subsection shall be in addition to any other remedy provided by law and shall not be interpreted as denying any other remedy provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 465, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 825, &#167; 48. </para></source></law></legaldoc>