<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-330"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-330</statuteno><catchline>Conciliation proceedings; investigations; restrictions on use of information.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (5) of section 20-327, nothing said or done in the course of conciliation may be made public or used as evidence in a subsequent proceeding under the Nebraska Fair Housing Act without the written consent of the persons concerned. All records compiled in the course of conciliation activities shall be exempt from public release. The commission may release any fully executed conciliation agreement.</para><para>(2)(a) Notwithstanding subsection (1) of this section, the commission shall make available to the aggrieved person and the respondent, upon request, following the completion of an investigation, information derived from an investigation and any final investigative report relating to that investigation.</para><para>(b) The commission's release of information pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section is subject to the federal Privacy Act of 1974, Public Law 93-579, as such act existed on January 1, 2005, and any other state or federal laws limiting the release of confidential information obtained in the course of an investigation under the Nebraska Fair Housing Act.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding subsections (1) and (2) of this section, materials in the investigative file shall be disclosed to the complainant and respondent to the extent reasonably necessary to further the investigation or conciliation discussions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 825, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 625, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 361, &#167; 28.</para></source></law></legaldoc>