<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<sectno id="id21">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Civil Rights" id="id22" statutenumber="20-506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id24">20-506</statuteno><catchline id="id25">Racial Profiling
Advisory Committee; created; members; duties.</catchline><para>(1)
The Racial Profiling Advisory Committee is created.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The committee shall
consist of:</para>
<para>(i) The executive director
of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice, who also
shall be the chairperson of the committee;</para>
<para>(ii) The Superintendent
of Law Enforcement and Public Safety or his or her designee;</para>
<para>(iii) The director of
the Commission on Latino-Americans or his or her designee; and</para>
<para>(iv) The executive director
of the Commission on Indian Affairs or his or her designee.</para>
<para>(b) The committee shall also consist of the
following persons, each appointed
by the Governor from a list of three names submitted to the Governor for each
position:</para>
<para>(i) A representative of the Fraternal Order of Police;</para>
<para>(ii) A representative of the Nebraska County Sheriffs Association;</para>
<para>(iii) A representative of the Police Officers Association of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(iv) A representative of the American Civil Liberties Union of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(v) A representative of the
AFL-CIO;</para>
<para>(vi) A representative of the Police Chiefs Association of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(vii) A representative
of the Nebraska branches of the National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People; and</para><para>(viii)
A representative of the Nebraska State Bar Association appointed by the Governor
from a list of attorneys submitted by the executive council of the Nebraska
State Bar Association.</para><para>(3) The committee
shall meet and organize within thirty days after the appointment of the members.
The committee shall meet semiannually at a time and
place to be fixed by the committee. Special meetings may be called by the
chairperson or at the request of two or more members of the committee.</para>
<para>(4) The committee shall advise the executive director of the
commission in the conduct of his or her duties regarding the review required pursuant to subsection
(6) of section 20-504, provide
an analysis of the review, and make policy recommendations with respect to
racial profiling.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1162, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB746, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>