<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-203</statuteno><catchline>Invasion of privacy; trespass or intrude upon a person's solitude.</catchline><para>Any person, firm, or corporation that trespasses or intrudes upon any natural person in his or her place of solitude or seclusion, if the intrusion would be highly offensive to a reasonable person, shall be liable for invasion of privacy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 394, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>An invasion of privacy pursuant to this section is one consisting solely of an intentional interference with the plaintiff's interest in solitude or seclusion, either as to his or her person or private affairs or concerns, of a kind that would be highly offensive to a reasonable person. Whipps Land &amp; Cattle Co. v. Level 3 Communications, 265 Neb. 472, 658 N.W.2d 258 (2003).</para><para>Trespassing onto real property, without more, is not the form or magnitude of interference into a person's solitude or seclusion that would rise to the level of being highly offensive to a reasonable person, such as might be actionable under this section. Whipps Land &amp; Cattle Co. v. Level 3 Communications, 265 Neb. 472, 658 N.W.2d 258 (2003).</para><para>The accusation of drug use at the workplace, without more, is not the form of interference into a person's solitude or seclusion that would rise to the level of being highly offensive to a reasonable person, such as might be actionable under this section. Polinski v. Sky Harbor Air Serv., 263 Neb. 406, 640 N.W.2d 391 (2002).</para><para>Operation of model airplane airfield was not type of intrusion that this section was designed to protect people from. Kaiser v. Western R/C Flyers, 239 Neb. 624, 477 N.W.2d 557 (1991).</para><para>In an action for invasion of privacy, the damages that a plaintiff may recover are (1) general damages for harm to the plaintiff's interest in privacy which resulted from the invasion; (2) damages for mental suffering; (3) special damages; and (4) if none of these are proven, nominal damages. Sabrina W. v. Willman, 4 Neb. App. 149, 540 N.W.2d 364 (1995).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>