<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-336"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-336</statuteno><catchline>Commission; hearings; hearing officer; appearance; discovery; discontinuance of proceedings; when.</catchline><para>(1) If an election is not made under section 20-335 with respect to a charge issued under section 20-333, the commission shall provide an opportunity for a hearing on the record with respect to the charge. The commission shall delegate the conduct of a hearing under this section to a hearing officer. The hearing officer shall meet the qualifications of a judge of the district court prescribed in section 24-301 or any successor statute. The hearing officer shall be appointed by the commission pursuant to rules and regulations promulgated by the commission. The hearing officer shall conduct the hearing at a place in the vicinity of the place where the discriminatory housing practice is alleged to have occurred or to be about to occur.</para><para>(2) At the hearing each party may appear in person, be represented by counsel, present evidence, cross-examine witnesses, and obtain the issuance of subpoenas under section 20-334. Any aggrieved person may intervene as a party in the proceeding. The rules of evidence shall apply to the presentation of evidence in such hearing as they would in a civil action in district court.</para><para>(3)(a) Discovery in administrative proceedings under this section shall be conducted as expeditiously and inexpensively as possible consistent with the need of all parties to obtain relevant evidence.</para><para>(b) A hearing under this section shall be conducted as expeditiously and inexpensively as possible consistent with the needs and rights of the parties to obtain a fair hearing and a complete record.</para><para>(4) Any resolution of a charge before issuance of a final order under section 20-337 shall require the consent of the aggrieved person on whose behalf the charge is issued.</para><para>(5) A hearing officer may not continue administrative proceedings under this section regarding any alleged discriminatory housing practice after the filing of a civil action by the aggrieved party under state or federal law seeking relief with respect to that discriminatory housing practice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 825, &#167; 37. </para></source></law></legaldoc>