<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-322" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>20-322</statuteno><catchline>Religious organization, private home, private club, or housing for older persons; restricting use not prohibited; local restrictions; how treated; controlled substances; illegal activities; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Nothing in the Nebraska Fair Housing Act shall prohibit a religious organization, association, or society or any nonprofit institution or organization operated, supervised, or controlled by or in conjunction with a religious organization, association, or society from limiting the sale, rental, or occupancy of a dwelling which it owns or operates for other than commercial purposes to persons of the same religion or from giving preferences to such persons unless membership in such religion is restricted on account of race, color, national origin, disability, familial status, or sex.</para><para>(2) Nothing in the act shall prohibit a private club not in fact open to the public, which as an incident to its primary purpose or purposes provides lodgings which it owns or operates for other than commercial purposes, from limiting the rental or occupancy of such lodging to its members or from giving preference to its members.</para><para>(3) Nothing in the act shall prohibit or limit the right of any person or his or her authorized representative to refuse to rent a room or rooms in his or her own home for any reason or for no reason or to change tenants in his or her own home as often as desired, except that this exception shall not apply to any person who makes available for rental or occupancy more than four sleeping rooms to a person or family within his or her own home.</para><para>(4)(a) Nothing in the act shall limit the applicability of any reasonable local restrictions regarding the maximum number of occupants permitted to occupy a dwelling, and nothing in the act regarding familial status shall apply with respect to housing for older persons.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this subsection, housing for older persons shall mean housing:</para><para>(i) Provided under any state program that the commission determines is specifically designed and operated to assist elderly persons as defined in the program;</para><para>(ii) Intended for and solely occupied by persons sixty-two years of age or older; or</para><para>(iii) Intended and operated for occupancy by at least one person fifty-five years of age or older per unit. In determining whether housing qualifies as housing for older persons under this subdivision, the commission shall develop regulations which require at least the following factors:</para><para>(A) The existence of significant facilities and services specifically designed to meet the physical or social needs of older persons or, if the provision of such facilities and services is not practicable, that such housing is necessary to provide important housing opportunities for older persons;</para><para>(B) That at least eighty percent of the units are occupied by at least one person fifty-five years of age or older per unit; and</para><para>(C) The publication of and adherence to policies and procedures which demonstrate an intent by the owner or manager to provide housing for persons fifty-five years of age or older.</para><para>(c) Housing shall not fail to meet the requirements for housing for older persons by reason of:</para><para>(i) Persons residing in the housing as of September 6, 1991, who do not meet the age requirements of subdivision (b)(ii) or (iii) of this subsection if succeeding occupants of the housing meet the age requirements; or</para><para>(ii) Unoccupied units if the units are reserved for occupancy by persons who meet the age requirements.</para><para>(5) Nothing in the act shall prohibit conduct against a person because such person has been convicted by any court of competent jurisdiction of the illegal manufacture or distribution of a controlled substance as defined in section 28-401.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 120, &#167; 6, p. 542; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 67; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 20-110; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 825, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB540, &#167; 23. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>