<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-140"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-140</statuteno><catchline>Unlawful discriminatory practice; complaint; file with commission; contents; resolution of complaint; confidential; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>Any person claiming to be aggrieved by an unlawful discriminatory practice may by himself, his agent, or his attorney file with the commission a verified complaint in writing which shall state the name and address of the person alleged to have committed the unlawful discriminatory practice complained of and which shall set forth the particulars thereof and contain such other information as may be required by the commission. The Attorney General shall, in like manner, make, sign, and file such complaint.</para><para>After the filing of such complaint, the commission shall furnish the person named in the complaint with a copy of the charge and make an investigation of such charge, but such charge shall not be made public by the commission. If the commission determines after such investigation that there is reasonable cause to believe that the charge is true, the commission shall endeavor to eliminate any such alleged unlawful practice by informal methods of conference, conciliation, and persuasion. Nothing said or done during or as a part of such endeavors may be made public by the commission without the written consent of the parties or used as evidence in a subsequent proceeding except as provided in subsection (2) of section 20-141. Any officer or employee of the commission who shall make public in any manner whatever any information in violation of this subsection shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction thereof shall be fined not more than one hundred dollars or imprisoned not more than thirty days.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 112, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For provisions of Equal Opportunity Commission,</emphasis> see sections 48-1116 and 48-1117.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>