<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id366"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-318"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>20-318</statuteno><catchline>Unlawful acts enumerated.</catchline><para>Except as exempted by section 20-322, it shall be unlawful to:</para><para>(1) Refuse to sell or rent after the making of a bona fide offer, refuse to negotiate for the sale or rental of or otherwise make unavailable or deny, refuse to show, or refuse to receive and transmit an offer for a dwelling to any person because of race, color, religion, national origin, disability, familial status, sex, or military or veteran status;</para><para>(2) Discriminate against any person in the terms, conditions, or privileges of sale or rental of a dwelling or in the provision of services or facilities in connection therewith because of race, color, religion, national origin, disability, familial status, sex, or military or veteran status;</para><para>(3) Make, print, publish, or cause to be made, printed, or published any notice, statement, or advertisement with respect to the sale or rental of a dwelling that indicates any preference, limitation, or discrimination based on race, color, religion, national origin, disability, familial status, sex, or military or veteran status or an intention to make any such preference, limitation, or discrimination;</para><para>(4) Represent to any person because of race, color, religion, national origin, disability, familial status, sex, or military or veteran status that any dwelling is not available for inspection, sale, or rental when such dwelling is in fact so available;</para><para>(5) Cause to be made any written or oral inquiry or record concerning the race, color, religion, national origin, disability, familial status, sex, or military or veteran status of a person seeking to purchase, rent, or lease any housing;</para><para>(6) Include in any transfer, sale, rental, or lease of housing any restrictive covenants or honor or exercise or attempt to honor or exercise any restrictive covenant pertaining to housing;</para><para>(7) Discharge or demote an employee or agent or discriminate in the compensation of such employee or agent because of such employee's or agent's compliance with the Nebraska Fair Housing Act; and</para><para>(8) Induce or attempt to induce, for profit, any person to sell or rent any dwelling by representations regarding the entry or prospective entry into the neighborhood of a person or persons of a particular race, color, religion, national origin, disability, familial status, sex, or military or veteran status.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 120, &#167; 3, p. 540; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 64; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 20-107; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 825, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB540, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>