<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Civil Rights" statutenumber="20-202"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>20-202</statuteno><catchline>Invasion of privacy; exploitation of a person for advertising or commercial purposes; situations; not applicable.</catchline><para>Any person, firm, or corporation that exploits a natural person, name, picture, portrait, or personality for advertising or commercial purposes shall be liable for invasion of privacy. The provisions of this section shall not apply to:</para><para>(1) The publication, printing, display, or use of the name or likeness of any person in any printed, broadcast, telecast, or other news medium or publication as part of any bona fide news report or presentation or noncommercial advertisement having a current or historical public interest and when such name or likeness is not used for commercial advertising purposes;</para><para>(2) The use of such name, portrait, photograph, or other likeness in connection with the resale or other distribution of literary, musical, or artistic productions or other articles of merchandise or property when such person has consented to the use of his or her name, portrait, photograph, or likeness on or in connection with the initial sale or distribution thereof so long as such use does not differ materially in kind, extent, or duration from that authorized by the consent as fairly construed; or</para><para>(3) Any photograph of a person solely as a member of the public when such person is not named or otherwise identified in or in connection with the use of such photograph.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 394, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>Invasion of privacy under this section typically applies to cases in which a photograph or other likeness of a person is distributed without that person's consent for commercial gain. Wilkinson v. Methodist, Richard Young Hosp., 259 Neb. 745, 612 N.W.2d 213 (2000).</para><para>Conduct to which one consents cannot constitute an invasion of privacy. Miller v. American Sports Co., 237 Neb. 676, 467 N.W.2d 653 (1991).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>