<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id117"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Civil Rights" id="id119" statutenumber="20-127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id121">20-127</statuteno><catchline id="id122">Rights enumerated.</catchline><para>(1) A blind, visually handicapped, deaf or hard of hearing, or physically disabled person has the same right as any other person to the full and free use of the streets, highways, sidewalks, walkways, public buildings, public facilities, and other public places.</para><para>(2) A blind, visually handicapped, deaf or hard of hearing, or physically disabled person is entitled to full and equal accommodations, advantages, facilities, and privileges of all common carriers, airplanes, motor vehicles, railroad trains, motor buses, street cars, boats, any other public conveyances or modes of transportation, hotels, lodging places, places of public accommodation, amusement, or resort, and other places to which the general public is invited, subject only to the conditions and limitations established by law and applicable alike to all persons.</para><para>(3) A totally or partially blind person, deaf or hard of hearing person, or physically disabled person has the right to be accompanied by a service animal, especially trained for the purpose, and a bona fide trainer of a service animal has the right to be accompanied by such animal in training in any of the places listed in subsection (2) of this section without being required to pay an extra charge for the service animal. Such person shall be liable for any damage done to the premises or facilities or to any person by such animal.</para><para>(4) A totally or partially blind person has the right to make use of a white cane in any of the places listed in subsection (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 496, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1971, &#167; 43-634; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 932, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 254, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 667, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB806, &#167;  6.</para></source><annotation><para>This section is a penal statute, and it must be strictly construed. By the inclusion of the phrase "and other places to which the general public is invited" in subsection (2) of this section, the Legislature evidenced its intent that this statute should apply whenever the general public is invited to a given place at a given time. Softball fields are "places to which the general public is invited" under subsection (2). This section is not limited by considerations of safety. Loewenstein v. Amateur Softball Assn., 227 Neb. 454, 418 N.W.2d 231 (1988).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
