<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Drainage" id="id00" statutenumber="31-766"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>31-766</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Annexation; obligations and assessments; agreement to divide; approval; special assessments prohibited; effect on certain contracts.</catchline><para>(1) If only a part of the territory within any sanitary and improvement district is annexed by a city or village, the sanitary and improvement district acting through its trustees or administrator and the city or village acting through its governing body may agree between themselves as to the division of the assets, liabilities, maintenance, contracts, or other obligations of the district for a change in the boundaries of the district so as to exclude the portion annexed by the city or village or may agree upon a merger of the district with the city or village. The division of assets, liabilities, maintenance, contracts, or other obligations of the district shall be equitable, shall be proportionate to the valuation of the portion of the district annexed and to the valuation of the portion of the district remaining following annexation, and shall, to the greatest extent feasible, reflect the actual impact of the annexation on the ability of the district to perform its duties and responsibilities within its new boundaries following annexation. In the event a merger is agreed upon, the city or village shall have all the rights, privileges, duties, and obligations as provided in sections 31-763 to 31-765 when the city or village annexes the entire territory within the district, and the trustees or administrator shall be relieved of all further duties and liabilities and their bonds exonerated as provided in section 31-764. No agreement between the district and the city or village shall be effective until submitted to and approved by the district court of the county in which the major portion of the district is located. No agreement shall be approved which may prejudice the rights of any bondholder or creditor of the district or employee under contract to the district. The court may authorize or direct amendments to the agreement before approving the same. If the district and city or village do not agree upon the proper adjustment of all matters growing out of the annexation of a part of the territory located within the district, the district, the annexing city or village, any bondholder or creditor of the district, or any employee under contract to the district may apply to the district court of the county where the major portion of the district is located for an adjustment of all matters growing out of or in any way connected with the annexation of such territory, and after a hearing thereon the court may enter an order or decree fixing the rights, duties, and obligations of the parties. In every case such decree or order shall require a change of the district boundaries so as to exclude from the district that portion of the territory of the district which has been annexed. Such change of boundaries shall become effective on the date of entry of such decree. Only the district and the city or village shall be necessary parties to such an action. Any bondholder or creditor of the district or any employee under contract to the district whose interests may be adversely affected by the annexation may intervene in the action pursuant to section 25-328. The decree when entered shall be binding on the parties the same as though the parties had voluntarily agreed thereto. Nothing contained in this section shall authorize any district to levy any special assessments within the annexed area after the effective date of annexation.</para><para>(2) Any contract entered into on or after August 30, 2015, by a sanitary and improvement district for solid waste collection services shall, upon annexation of all or part of such district by a city or village, be canceled and voided as to the annexed areas.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 130, &#167; 4, p. 469; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 255, &#167; 4, p. 927; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 868, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 630, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB324, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB130, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Pursuant to this section, where there is evidence that a partially annexed fire district has assets, those assets should be considered in determining a proper adjustment of those matters growing out of the annexation. Papillion Rural Fire Prot. Dist. v. City of Bellevue, 274 Neb. 214, 739 N.W.2d 162 (2007).</para><para>If an adjustment of matters arising out of an annexation is sought, proceedings under this section must be instituted as soon as it becomes evident that an agreed adjustment cannot be reached. Millard Rur. Fire Prot. Dist. No. 1 v. City of Omaha, 226 Neb. 50, 409 N.W.2d 574 (1987).</para><para>This section does not limit power of a city to annex lands within rural fire protection district. Webber v. City of Scottsbluff, 187 Neb. 282, 188 N.W.2d 814 (1971).</para><para>This section must be construed in light of the intent of the two preceding sections. Abernathy v. City of Omaha, 183 Neb. 660, 163 N.W.2d 579 (1968).</para><para>Rights of district and of a municipality are to be promptly adjusted after annexation of part of the district by the municipality. Sanitary &amp; Improvement Dist. v. City of Ralston, 182 Neb. 63, 152 N.W.2d 111 (1967).</para><para>This section sustained as constitutional. City of Bellevue v. Eastern Sarpy County S. F. P. Dist., 180 Neb. 340, 143 N.W.2d 62 (1966).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>