<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Drainage" statutenumber="31-353"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>31-353</statuteno><catchline>Crossing of highways or railroads; mutual agreement; condemnation.</catchline><para>The board shall have the power to construct the works across any street, avenue, highway, railway, canal, ditch or flume which the route of the ditches may intersect or cross, in such manner as to afford security for life and property, but the board shall restore the same, when so crossed or intersected, to its former state as nearly as may be, or in a manner not to impair its usefulness unnecessarily. Every company whose railroad shall be intersected or crossed by the works shall unite with the board in forming such intersections and crossings, and shall grant the privilege aforesaid. If such railroad company and the board, or the owners and controllers of such property, thing or franchise so to be crossed, cannot agree upon the amount to be paid therefor, or the points or the manner of such crossings, the same shall be ascertained and determined in all respects as is provided in respect to the taking of land.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1905, c. 161, &#167; 23, p. 628; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1848; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1795; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 31-452; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 31-353.</para></source><annotation><para>Where erosion destroys highway and bridges over drainage ditch, drainage district is required to restore bridges and their approaches in such manner as to permit the maintenance of public highway over and across the same. Ritter v. Drainage Dist. No. 1, 148 Neb. 873, 29 N.W.2d 782 (1947).</para><para>If old bridge is rendered unnecessary, county must maintain. Richardson County ex rel. Sheehan v. Drainage Dist. No. 1 of Richardson County, 92 Neb. 776, 139 N.W. 648 (1913).</para><para>District must maintain bridge over a ditch crossing a highway. State ex rel. Hutter v. Papillion Drainage Dist., 89 Neb. 808, 132 N.W. 398 (1911).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>