<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Drainage" statutenumber="31-411.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>31-411.02</statuteno><catchline>Board of directors; plans; adoption; budget; notice; publication; contents; levy; limitation; map; county treasurer; compute tax; additional funds; election.</catchline><para>The board of directors having adopted the plans of public works and the tax levy method of financing shall prepare an itemized budget of funds necessary to carry out the authorities granted under sections 31-401 to 31-450 and transmit such budget to the county board of the county or counties involved. Thereupon the board of directors shall cause to be published, once each week for three consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the district, a copy of the itemized budget of funds necessary to carry out the authorities granted under such sections and a statement of the total taxable value of the taxable property in the drainage district. If portions of the drainage district are in more than one county, the county assessors involved shall ratably apportion such amounts of the total budget requested between the counties based on the total taxable value of the taxable property within the drainage district and transmit and certify the prorated portion to the respective county boards of each county involved. The county board may levy a tax sufficient to raise the amount of funds requested but not to exceed ten and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of the taxable property in the drainage district. Such levy shall be subject to section 77-3443. The tax so levied shall be collected in the same manner as other property taxes, and the proceeds therefrom shall be kept in a separate account identified by the official name of the drainage district. The county treasurer shall transfer such funds to the drainage district as requested by the board of directors.</para><para>The board of directors shall provide a legal description and map of the boundaries of the district and transmit such information to the county assessor of the county or counties involved who shall indicate for the use of the county treasurer such information on the tax rolls. The county assessor shall also provide the county treasurer with the taxable value of the taxable personal property of each property owner within the drainage district which shall also be taxed at the same rate as real property.</para><para>When the property tax rolls and the taxable value of the taxable personal property of each taxpayer are received by the county treasurer from the county assessor as required by sections 31-401 to 31-450, the county treasurer shall compute the tax due the drainage district from each taxpayer in accordance with the rate required to meet the budget request but not to exceed a levy of ten and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of the taxable property of the district. If a drainage district needs additional funds to pay outstanding warrants issued under section 31-416, the property owners within such district may, by majority vote of those voting in an election authorized by the board of directors of such district and conducted according to section 31-407, approve the issuance of bonds which shall be paid by an additional levy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 245, &#167; 4, p. 898; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 723, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1195, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 52. </para></source></law></legaldoc>