<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Drainage" statutenumber="31-787"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>31-787</statuteno><catchline>Trustee; removal by recall; petition;
procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A trustee of a sanitary and improvement district
may be removed from office by recall pursuant to sections 31-786 to 31-793.
A petition for
an election to recall a trustee shall be sufficient if it complies with the
requirements of this section.</para>
<para>(2) The signers of the
petition shall be persons who were, on the date the initial petition papers
are issued under subsection (7) of this section, eligible to vote in a district
election as provided in section 31-735. A person's eligibility to sign a petition
shall be the same as the person's eligibility to cast one or more votes at
a district election under section 31-735. Only one person shall be allowed
to sign on behalf of joint owners of property in the district or on behalf
of a public, private, or municipal corporation that owns property in the district.
If the trustee whose recall is sought was elected by vote of resident owners
only, then only resident owners shall be allowed to sign the petition. If
the trustee whose recall is sought was elected by vote of all owners of property,
then all owners shall be allowed to sign the petition. Resident owner means
qualified resident voter. All owners means all qualified resident voters and
all qualified property owning voters.</para><para>(3) The filing clerk shall assign to each signature
a count equal to the number of votes that the signer was eligible to cast
on the date he or she signed. The number of votes that a signer was eligible
to cast shall be based on section 31-735. If the signature was made by or
for an owner of more than one parcel of property, the signature made by or
on behalf of such owner shall be assigned a count equal to the total number
of votes which the owner was eligible to cast.</para><para>(4) The filing clerk shall total
the count assigned to the signatures on the petition. The petition shall be
sufficient if the total is at least equal to thirty-five percent of the highest
number of votes that were cast for a candidate at the previous district election
for the trustee positions in the same category as the trustee whose recall
is sought by the petition. The categories of trustees shall be the same as
provided in section 31-735.</para><para>(5) The
signatures shall be affixed to petition papers and shall be considered part
of the petition.</para>
<para>(6) The petition papers shall
be procured from the filing clerk. Prior to the issuance of such petition
papers, an affidavit shall be signed and filed with the filing clerk by at
least one qualified resident voter of the district, if the trustee whose recall
is being sought was elected solely by qualified resident voters, or at least
one qualified resident voter or qualified property owning voter, if the trustee
whose recall is being sought was elected by other qualified resident voters
and qualified property owning voters. Such voter or voters shall be deemed
to be the principal circulator or circulators of the recall petition. The
affidavit shall state the name of the trustee sought to be removed and whether
qualified property owning voters participated in the election of the trustee
and shall request that the filing clerk issue initial petition papers to the
principal circulator for circulation. The filing clerk shall notify the principal
circulator or circulators that the necessary signatures must be gathered within
thirty days after the date of issuing the petitions.</para>
<para>(7) The filing clerk, upon
issuing the initial petition papers or any subsequent petition papers, shall
enter in a record, to be kept in his or her office, the name of the principal
circulator or circulators to whom the papers were issued, the date of issuance,
the number of papers issued, and whether qualified property owning voters
may participate in signing the petitions. The filing clerk shall certify on
the papers the name of the principal circulator or circulators to whom the
papers were issued, the date they were issued, and whether qualified property
owning voters may participate in signing the petitions. No petition paper
shall be accepted as part of the petition unless it bears such certificate.
The principal circulator or circulators who check out petitions from the filing
clerk may distribute such petitions to persons who may act as circulators
of such petitions.</para>
</amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 874, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 176, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 444, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1121, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>