<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id5" statutenumber="13-509"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>13-509</statuteno><catchline id="id8">County assessor; certify taxable value; when; annexation of property; governing body; duties.</catchline><para>(1) On or before August 20 of each year, the county assessor shall certify to each governing body or board empowered to levy or certify a tax levy the current taxable value of the taxable real and personal property subject to the applicable levy. The certification shall be provided to the governing body or board (a) by mail if requested by the governing body or board, (b) electronically, or (c) by listing such certification on the county assessor’s website.</para><para>(2) Current taxable value for real property shall mean the value established by the county assessor and equalized by the county board of equalization and the Tax Equalization and Review Commission. Current taxable value for tangible personal property shall mean the net book value reported by the taxpayer and certified by the county assessor.</para><para>(3) If a political subdivision annexes property since the last time taxable values were certified under subsection (1) of this section, the governing body of such political subdivision shall file and record a certified copy of the annexation ordinance, petition, or resolution in the office of the register of deeds or, if none, the county clerk and the county assessor of the county in which the annexed property is located. The annexation ordinance, petition, or resolution shall include a full legal description of the annexed property. If the register of deeds or county clerk receives and records such ordinance, petition, or resolution prior to July 1 or, for annexations by a city of the metropolitan class, prior to August 1, the valuation of the real and personal property annexed shall be considered in the taxable valuation of the annexing political subdivision for the current year. If the register of deeds or county clerk receives and records such ordinance, petition, or resolution on or after July 1 or, for annexations by a city of the metropolitan class, on or after August 1, the valuation of the real and personal property annexed shall be considered in the taxable valuation of the annexing political subdivision for the following year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 391, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 256; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 835, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1986, &#167; 23-927.01; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 829, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 902, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 271, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 813, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 261, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB166, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB217, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB524, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>