<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-315"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-315</statuteno><catchline>Appropriation or expenditure; purposes; method; limitation.</catchline><para>The city commissioners or council of any city, the board of trustees of any village, and the county board of any county in the state shall have the power to appropriate or expend annually from the general funds or from revenue received from any proprietary functions of their respective political subdivision an amount not to exceed four-tenths of one percent of the taxable valuation of the city, village, or county for the purpose of encouraging immigration, new industries, and investment and to conduct and carry on a publicity campaign, including a publicity campaign conducted for the purpose of acquiring from any source a municipal electrical distribution system or exploiting and advertising the various agricultural, horticultural, manufacturing, commercial, and other resources, including utility services, of the city, village, or county. Such sum may be expended directly by the city, village, or county or may be paid to the chamber of commerce or other commercial organization or a similar county organization or multicounty organization or local development corporation to be expended for the purposes enumerated in this section under the direction of the board of directors of the organization. The total amount levied including the appropriation or expenditure made under this section shall not exceed the amount limited by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 187, &#167; 1, p. 699; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4392; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 18-1201; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-1401; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 103, &#167; 1, p. 478; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1261, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 599, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 18-1401; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 840, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 30.</para></source><annotation><para>Provisions under this section for expenditure of tax money and income from proprietary functions for purchase by a municipality or a county of property for industrial development violate the Constitution, but the provisions of expenditures for other purposes by a municipality or county itself or through private organizations are constitutional. Chase v. County of Douglas, 195 Neb. 838, 241 N.W.2d 334 (1976).</para><para>There is no hard and fast rule in determining whether a proposed expenditure of public funds is valid as devoted to a public use or purpose, and each case must be decided with reference to the object sought to be accomplished and to the degree and manner in which that object affects the public welfare. Kalkowski v. Nebraska Nat. Trails Museum Found., 20 Neb. App. 541, 826 N.W.2d 589 (2013).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>