<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id4"><sectno id="id5" opdate="July 18, 2008">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id6" statutenumber="13-206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">13-206</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Director; adopt rules and regulations; tax credits.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the approval or disapproval of the program proposals submitted pursuant to section 13-205 taking into account the economic need level and the geographic distribution of the population of the community development area. The director shall also adopt and promulgate rules and regulations concerning the amount of the tax credit for which a program shall be certified. The tax credits shall be available for contributions to a certified program which may qualify as a charitable contribution deduction on the federal income tax return filed by the business firm or individual making such contribution. The decision of the department to approve or disapprove all or any portion of a proposal shall be in writing. If the proposal is approved, the maximum tax credit allowance for the certified program shall be stated along with the approval. The maximum tax credit allowance approved by the department shall be final for the fiscal year in which the program is certified. A copy of all decisions shall be transmitted to the Tax Commissioner. A copy of all credits allowed to business firms under sections 44-150 and 77-908 shall be transmitted to the Director of Insurance.</para><para>(2) For all business firms and individuals eligible for the credit allowed by section 13-207, except for insurance companies paying premium and related retaliatory taxes in this state pursuant to section 44-150 or 77-908, the Tax Commissioner shall provide for the manner in which the credit allowed by section 13-207 shall be taken and the forms on which such credit shall be allowed. The Tax Commissioner shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the method of providing tax credits. The Director of Insurance shall provide for the manner in which the credit allowed by section 13-207 to insurance companies paying premium and related retaliatory taxes in this state pursuant to sections 44-150 and 77-908 shall be taken and the forms on which such credit shall be allowed. The Director of Insurance may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the method of providing the tax credit. The Tax Commissioner shall allow against any income tax due from the insurance companies paying premium and related retaliatory taxes in this state pursuant to section 44-150 or 77-908 a credit for the credit provided by section 13-207 and allowed by the Director of Insurance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 372, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1114, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 302, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1241, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 300, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 334, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB855, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
