<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-516"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-516</statuteno><catchline>Public power district; public power and irrigation district; rural power district; power project agency; proposed budget; contents; notice; meeting; changes.</catchline><para>A public power district or public power and irrigation district organized pursuant to Chapter 70, article 6, a rural power district organized pursuant to Chapter 70, article 8, or any agency created pursuant to sections 18-2426 to 18-2434 shall prepare in writing each year a proposed budget which shall include at a minimum: Revenue from all sources separately stated as to each source and expenditures from the prior two years; estimates of the current year's revenue from all sources separately stated as to each source and expenditures; and a summary which outlines the fiscal policy of the district or agency for the period covered by the budget. Such proposed budget shall be available for inspection by the general public at each district's or agency's principal headquarters at least seven days prior to the meeting of the board of directors at which such budget is to be adopted. The budget shall be in a form approved by the Nebraska Power Review Board.</para><para>Notice of the place and time of such meeting of the board of directors shall be published at least seven days prior to the date set for such meeting in a newspaper of general circulation within the district or agency. The notice shall include a statement that the proposed budget is available for public inspection and the location where it is available. Any changes to the proposed budget made between the date the proposed budget is made available for public inspection and the date of the board meeting shall be added to the proposed budget at the principal headquarters of the district or agency prior to the board meeting. At such meeting the public shall have an opportunity to testify before the proposed budget is adopted, and a written record shall be kept of such meeting. If the adopted budget reflects a change from that shown in the proposed budget a summary of such changes shall be available for inspection at the principal headquarters of such district or agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 310, &#167; 12.</para></source></law></legaldoc>