<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-512"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-512</statuteno><catchline>Budget statement; taxpayer; contest; basis; procedure.</catchline><para>A taxpayer upon whom a tax will be imposed as a result of the action of a governing body in adopting a budget statement may contest the validity of the budget statement adopted by the governing body by filing an action in the district court of the county in which the governing body is situated. Such action shall be based either upon a violation of or a failure to comply with the provisions and requirements of the Nebraska Budget Act by the governing body. In response to such action, the governing body shall be required to show cause why the budget statement should not be ordered set aside, modified, or changed. The action shall be tried to the court without a jury and shall be given priority by the district court over other pending civil litigation, and by the appellate court on appeal, to the extent possible and feasible to expedite a decision. Such action shall be filed within thirty days after the adopted budget statement is required to be filed by the governing body with the levying board. If the district court finds that the governing body has violated or failed to comply with the requirements of the act, the court shall, in whole or in part, set aside, modify, or change the adopted budget statement or tax levy as the justice of the case may require. The district court's decision may be appealed to the Court of Appeals.</para><para>The remedy provided in this section shall not be exclusive but shall be in addition to any other remedy provided by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 10, p. 674; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 125; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-930; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 360, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>In an action hereunder, the trial court is without authority to award the plaintiff an attorney's fee. Willms v. Nebraska City Airport Authority, 193 Neb. 567, 228 N.W.2d 276 (1975).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>