<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id6" statutenumber="13-503"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>13-503</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Budget Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Governing body means the governing body of any county agricultural society, elected county fair board, joint airport authority formed under the Joint Airport Authorities Act, city or county airport authority, bridge commission created pursuant to section 39-868, cemetery district, city, village, municipal county, community college, community redevelopment authority, county, drainage or levee district, educational service unit, rural or suburban fire protection district, historical society, hospital district, irrigation district, learning community, natural resources district, nonprofit county historical association or society for which a tax is levied under subsection (1) of section 23-355.01, public building commission, railroad transportation safety district, reclamation district, road improvement district, rural water district, school district, sanitary and improvement district, township, offstreet parking district, transit authority, regional metropolitan transit authority, metropolitan utilities district, Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council, and political subdivision with the authority to have a property tax request, with the authority to levy a toll, or that receives state aid;</para><para>(2) Levying board means any governing body which has the power or duty to levy a tax;</para><para>(3) Fiscal year means the twelve-month period used by each governing body in determining and carrying on its financial and taxing affairs;</para><para>(4) Tax means any general or special tax levied against persons, property, or business for public purposes as provided by law but shall not include any special assessment;</para><para>(5) Auditor means the Auditor of Public Accounts;</para><para>(6) Cash reserve means funds required for the period before revenue would become available for expenditure but shall not include funds held in any special reserve fund;</para><para>(7) Public funds means all money, including nontax money, used in the operation and functions of governing bodies. For purposes of a county, city, or village which has a lottery established under the Nebraska County and City Lottery Act, only those net proceeds which are actually received by the county, city, or village from a licensed lottery operator shall be considered public funds, and public funds shall not include amounts awarded as prizes;</para><para>(8) Adopted budget statement means a proposed budget statement which has been adopted or amended and adopted as provided in section 13-506. Such term shall include additions, if any, to an adopted budget statement made by a revised budget which has been adopted as provided in section 13-511;</para><para>(9) Special reserve fund means any special fund set aside by the governing body for a particular purpose and not available for expenditure for any other purpose. Funds created for (a) the retirement of bonded indebtedness, (b) the funding of employee pension plans, (c) the purposes of the Political Subdivisions Self-Funding Benefits Act, (d) the purposes of the Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act, (e) voter-approved sinking funds, or (f) statutorily authorized sinking funds shall be considered special reserve funds;</para><para>(10) Biennial period means the two fiscal years comprising a biennium commencing in odd-numbered or even-numbered years used by a city, village, or natural resources district in determining and carrying on its financial and taxing affairs; and</para><para>(11) Biennial budget means (a) a budget by a city of the primary or metropolitan class that adopts a charter provision providing for a biennial period to determine and carry on the city's financial and taxing affairs, (b) a budget by a city of the first or second class or village that provides for a biennial period to determine and carry on the city's or village's financial and taxing affairs, or (c) a budget by a natural resources district that provides for a biennial period to determine and carry on the natural resources district's financial and taxing affairs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 2, p. 669; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 537, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 510, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 23-922; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 802, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1257, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 299, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 250, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 437, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1116, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 607, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB164, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB492, &#167; 26. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Joint Airport Authorities Act,</emphasis> see section 3-716.</para><para><emphasis>Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act,</emphasis> see section 18-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska County and City Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-601.</para><para><emphasis>Political Subdivisions Self-Funding Benefits Act,</emphasis> see section 13-1601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>