<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-705"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-705</statuteno><catchline>Temporary location of seat of government; conditions; rules and regulations; preliminary plans and preparations; construction permitted.</catchline><para>(1) The official designation of the location or locations of an emergency seat of local government, and the removal thereto of the government of the political subdivision concerned, shall be subject to such rules and regulations as may be promulgated by the then Governor; and shall in no instance precede: (a) The inception of an attack; or (b) the inception of a strategic or tactical warning period duly proclaimed by the President of the United States, the Governor of Nebraska, or both such officials and based on the imminence of an attack.</para><para>(2) Prior to any such attack or warning period, any political subdivision is hereby authorized and empowered to make such preliminary plans and preparations as may be deemed necessary and advisable to facilitate the subsequent accomplishment, during such emergency, of the actions provided in sections 13-701 to 13-706. Such plans and preparations, which likewise shall be subject to such rules and regulations as may be promulgated by the then Governor, may include any or all of the following steps, but shall not necessarily be limited thereto: (a) Selection, by the governing body as mentioned in section 13-703, of a tentative location or locations for an emergency local seat of government, in the event that as provided in subsection (1) of this section, it subsequently becomes necessary and advisable to designate such tentative location or locations as the official location or locations of the emergency local seat of government; (b) negotiation with local authorities, property owners, and other proper persons, for the possible use and occupancy of specific buildings, areas, or buildings and areas, at or near such tentative location or locations, for the purposes mentioned in sections 13-701 to 13-706 during a subsequent emergency; and (c) storing and stockpiling, at or near the tentative location or locations, of essential supplies and equipment, or vital records or duplicates thereof which would be necessary to permit the continuity of the governmental operation of the political subdivision concerned in an emergency.</para><para>(3) Prior to an attack or warning period, as set out in subsection (1) of this section, neither any political subdivision, nor any official or agency of or on behalf thereof, shall, except only for the storage and safeguarding of vital records or duplicates thereof, purchase, contract for the purchase of, or obligate funds of the state or of such political subdivision for the purchase of any real estate or appurtenance thereto, for subsequent use as an emergency local seat of government; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that no political subdivision, nor any official or agency of or on behalf thereof, shall be prevented from constructing an emergency local seat of government on any property owned by such political subdivision or owned jointly with some other political subdivision, and such local seat of government may be constructed as a part of a joint city and county jail authorized under sections 47-302 to 47-308.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 92, &#167; 5, p. 403; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 122, &#167; 1, p. 469; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-2105.</para></source></law></legaldoc>