<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-324" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-324</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; powers and duties; beginning and termination of taxation; procedure; notice; administrative fee; illegal assessment and collection; remedies.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall administer all sales and use taxes adopted under section 13-319. The Tax Commissioner may prescribe forms and adopt and promulgate reasonable rules and regulations in conformity with the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, as amended, for the making of returns and for the ascertainment, assessment, and collection of taxes. The county shall furnish a certified copy of the adopting or repealing resolution to the Tax Commissioner in accordance with such rules and regulations. The tax shall begin the first day of the next calendar quarter which is at least one hundred twenty days following receipt by the Tax Commissioner of the certified copy of the adopted resolution. The Tax Commissioner shall provide at least sixty days' notice of the adoption of the tax or a change in the rate to retailers. Notice shall be provided to retailers within the county. Notice to retailers may be provided through the web site of the Department of Revenue or by other electronic means.</para><para>(2) For resolutions containing a termination date, the termination date is the first day of a calendar quarter. The county shall furnish a certified statement to the Tax Commissioner no more than one hundred eighty days and at least one hundred twenty days before the termination date that the termination date stated in the resolution is still valid. If the certified statement is not furnished within the prescribed time, the tax shall remain in effect, and the Tax Commissioner shall continue to collect the tax until the first day of the calendar quarter which is at least one hundred twenty days after receipt of the certified statement notwithstanding the termination date stated in the resolution. The Tax Commissioner shall provide at least sixty days' notice of the termination of the tax to retailers. Notice shall be provided to retailers within the county. Notice to retailers may be provided through the web site of the department or other electronic means.</para><para>(3) In the rental or lease of automobiles, trucks, trailers, semitrailers, and truck-tractors as defined in the Motor Vehicle Registration Act, the tax shall be collected by the lessor on the rental or lease price at the tax rate in effect on the date the automobile, truck, trailer, semitrailer, or truck-tractor is delivered to the lessee.</para><para>(4) The Tax Commissioner shall collect the sales and use tax concurrently with collection of a state tax in the same manner as the state tax is collected. The Tax Commissioner shall remit monthly the proceeds of the tax to the counties imposing the tax, after deducting the amount of refunds made and three percent of the remainder as an administrative fee necessary to defray the cost of collecting the tax and the expenses incident thereto. The Tax Commissioner shall keep full and accurate records of all money received and distributed. All receipts from the three-percent administrative fee shall be deposited in the state General Fund.</para><para>(5) Upon any claim of illegal assessment and collection, the taxpayer has the same remedies provided for claims of illegal assessment and collection of the state tax. It is the intention of the Legislature that the provisions of law which apply to the recovery of state taxes illegally assessed and collected apply to the recovery of sales and use taxes illegally assessed and collected under section 13-319.</para><para>(6) Boundary changes or the adoption of a sales and use tax by an incorporated municipality that affects any tax imposed by this section shall be governed as provided in subsections (3) through (10) of section 77-27,143.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1177, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 381, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 221; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 887, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>