<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id00" statutenumber="13-303"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>13-303</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Counties, cities, and villages; contract; agreement; hearing; notice; cost; levy; fee.</catchline><para>The county boards of counties and the governing bodies of cities and villages may establish an emergency medical service, including the provision of scheduled and unscheduled ambulance service, as a governmental service either within or without the county or municipality, as the case may be. The county board or governing body may contract with any city, person, firm, or corporation licensed as an emergency medical service for emergency medical care by emergency care providers. Each may enter into an agreement with the other under the Interlocal Cooperation Act or Joint Public Agency Act for the purpose of establishing an emergency medical service or may provide a separate service for itself. Public funds may be expended therefor, and a reasonable service fee may be charged to the user. Before any such service is established under the authority of this section, the county board or the governing bodies of cities and villages shall hold a public hearing after giving at least ten days' notice thereof, which notice shall include a brief summary of the general plan for establishing such service, including an estimate of the initial cost and the possible continuing cost of operating such service. If the board or governing body after such hearing determines that an emergency medical service for emergency medical care by emergency care providers is needed, it may proceed as authorized in this section. The authority granted in this section shall be cumulative and supplementary to any existing powers heretofore granted. Any county board of counties and the governing bodies of cities and villages may pay their cost for such service out of available general funds or may levy a tax for the purpose of providing the service, which levy shall be in addition to all other taxes and shall be in addition to restrictions on the levy of taxes provided by statute, except that when a rural or suburban fire protection district provides the service, the county shall pay the cost for the county service by levying a tax on that property not in the rural or suburban fire protection district providing the service. The levy shall be subject to subsection (10) of section 77-3442 or section 77-3443, as applicable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 111, &#167; 1, p. 359; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 239, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 560, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-378; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 808, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB325, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1002, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>November 14, 2020</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>