<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-327"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-327</statuteno><catchline>County; cede jurisdiction; when; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The governing body of any city of the first class or city of the second class may, by majority vote of its members, request that the county board formally cede and transfer to the city extraterritorial jurisdiction over land outside the area extending two miles from the corporate boundaries of a city of the first class and one mile from the corporate boundaries of a city of the second class. In making its request, the city shall describe the territory over which jurisdiction is being sought by metes and bounds or by reference to an official map.</para><para>(2) Unless prohibited pursuant to section 13-328, the county board may, by majority vote of its members, grant the request with regard to some or all of the requested territory if:</para><para>(a) The county has formally adopted a comprehensive development plan and zoning resolution pursuant to section 23-114 not less than two years immediately preceding the date of the city's request;</para><para>(b) The city, on the date of the request, is exercising extraterritorial jurisdiction over territory within the boundaries of the county;</para><para>(c) The requested territory is within the projected growth pattern of the city and would be within the city's extraterritorial jurisdiction by reason of annexation within a reasonable period of years;</para><para>(d) Not more than a total of twenty-five percent of the territory of the county located outside the corporate boundaries of any city within the county shall be ceded to the jurisdiction of one city within ten years after the date upon which the initial request for the cession of territory to the city was approved by the governing body of the city; and</para><para>(e) No portion of the territory ceded to the city's jurisdiction by the county lies within an area extending one-half mile from the extraterritorial jurisdiction of any other city of the first or second class or village on the date the request is approved by the governing body of the city.</para><para>(3) If the county board approves the cession and transfer of extraterritorial jurisdiction to a city pursuant to this section, such transfer shall take effect on the effective date of the ordinance as provided for in subsection (1) of section 16-902 in the case of a city of the first class or as provided for in subsection (1) of section 17-1002 in the case of a city of the second class. Upon the effective date of such transfer, the transferred jurisdiction shall be treated for all purposes as if such land were located within two miles of the corporate boundaries of a city of the first class or within one mile of the corporate boundaries of a city of the second class.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>