<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-504"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>13-504</statuteno><catchline>Proposed budget statement; contents;
corrections; cash reserve; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) Each governing
body shall annually or biennially prepare
a proposed budget statement on forms prescribed and furnished by the auditor.
The proposed budget statement shall be made available to the public by the
political subdivision prior to publication of the notice of the hearing on
the proposed budget statement pursuant to section 13-506. A proposed budget
statement shall contain the following information, except as provided by state
law:</para>
<para>(a) For the immediately preceding fiscal year or biennial period, the revenue from all sources,
including motor vehicle taxes, other than revenue received from personal and
real property taxation, allocated to the funds and separately stated as to
each such source: The unencumbered cash balance at the beginning and end of
the year or biennial period;
the amount received by taxation of personal and real property; and the amount
of actual expenditures;</para>
<para>(b) For the current fiscal year or
biennial period, actual and estimated revenue from all sources,
including motor vehicle taxes, allocated to the funds and separately stated
as to each such source: The actual unencumbered cash balance available at
the beginning of the year or
biennial period; the amount received from personal and real property
taxation; and the amount of actual and estimated expenditures, whichever is
applicable. Such statement shall contain the cash reserve for each fiscal
year or biennial period and
shall note whether or not such reserve is encumbered. Such cash reserve projections
shall be based upon the actual experience of prior years or biennial periods. The cash reserve shall
not exceed fifty percent of the total budget adopted exclusive of capital
outlay items;</para>
<para>(c) For the immediately ensuing fiscal year or biennial period, an estimate of revenue
from all sources, including motor vehicle taxes, other than revenue to be
received from taxation of personal and real property, separately stated as
to each such source: The actual or estimated unencumbered cash balances, whichever
is applicable, to be available at the beginning of the year or biennial period; the amounts proposed to
be expended during the year or
biennial period; and the amount of cash reserve, based on actual
experience of prior years or
biennial periods, which cash reserve shall not exceed fifty percent
of the total budget adopted exclusive of capital outlay items;</para>
<para>(d) A statement setting out separately the amount sought to be raised
from the levy of a tax on the taxable value of real property (i) for the purpose
of paying the principal or interest on bonds issued by the governing body
and (ii) for all other purposes;</para>
<para>(e) A uniform summary of the proposed budget statement, including each
proprietary function fund included in a separate proprietary budget statement
prepared pursuant to the Municipal Proprietary Function Act, and a grand total
of all funds maintained by the governing body; and</para>
<para>(f) For municipalities, a list of the proprietary functions which are
not included in the budget statement. Such proprietary functions shall have
a separate budget statement which is approved by the city council or village
board as provided in the Municipal Proprietary Function Act.</para>
<para>(2) The actual or estimated unencumbered cash balance required to be
included in the budget statement by this section shall include deposits and
investments of the political subdivision as well as any funds held by the
county treasurer for the political subdivision and shall be accurately stated
on the proposed budget statement.</para>
<para>(3) The political subdivision shall correct any material errors in the
budget statement detected by the auditor or by other sources.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 3, p. 670; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 129, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 932, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 889, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 183, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1987, &#167; 23-923; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 33, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 310, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1310, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1362, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 271, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 86, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 568, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB111, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Municipal Proprietary Function Act,</emphasis> see section 18-2801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>A budget of an airport authority adopted without full compliance with the requirements of the Nebraska Budget Act is void and may be set aside. Willms v. Nebraska City Airport Authority, 193 Neb. 567, 228 N.W.2d 276 (1975).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>