<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1703"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1703</statuteno><catchline>Criteria.</catchline><para>An applicant for siting approval shall submit information to the city council, village board of trustees, or county board of commissioners or supervisors to demonstrate compliance with the requirements of this section regarding a solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility. Siting approval shall be granted only if the proposed area or facility meets all of the following criteria:</para><para>(1) The solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility is necessary to accommodate the solid waste management needs of the area which the solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility is intended to serve;</para><para>(2) The solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility is designed, located, and proposed to be operated so that the public health, safety, and welfare will be protected. The applicant shall provide an evaluation of the potential for adverse health effects that could result from exposure to pollution, in any form, due to the proper or improper construction, operation, or closure of the proposed solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility;</para><para>(3) The solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility is located so as to minimize incompatibility with the character of the surrounding area and to minimize the effect on the value of the surrounding property. The city council, village board, or county board shall consider the advice of the appropriate planning commission regarding the application;</para><para>(4) The plan of operations for the solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility is designed to minimize the danger to the surrounding area from fire, spills, or other operational accidents;</para><para>(5) The traffic patterns to or from the solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility are designed to minimize the impact on existing traffic flows; and</para><para>(6) Information regarding the previous operating experience of a private agency applicant and its subsidiaries or parent corporation in the area of solid waste management or related activities are made available to the city council, village board, or county board. If a corporation, a parent company or subsidiary thereof, or any officer or board member of the corporation or the parent company or subsidiary applying for approval has been convicted of a felony within ten years of the date the application is filed, site approval shall not be granted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 813, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 60.</para></source></law></legaldoc>