<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1106</statuteno><catchline>Refunding bonds; issuance; amount; rights of holders.</catchline><para>Any bonds issued under the provisions of sections 13-1101 to 13-1110 and at any time outstanding may at any time and from time to time be refunded by a municipality or county by the issuance of its refunding bonds in such amount as the governing body may deem necessary but not exceeding an amount sufficient to refund the principal of the bonds to be so refunded, together with any unpaid interest thereon and any premiums and commission necessary to be paid in connection therewith. Any such refunding may be effected whether the bonds to be refunded shall have then matured or shall thereafter mature, either by sale of the refunding bonds and the application of the proceeds thereof for the payment of the bonds to be refunded thereby, or by exchange of the refunding bonds for the bonds to be refunded thereby; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that the holders of any bonds to be so refunded shall not be compelled without their consent to surrender their bonds for payment or exchange prior to the date on which they are payable by maturity date, option to redeem, or otherwise or, if they are called for redemption, prior to the date on which they are by their terms subject to redemption by option or otherwise. Any refunding bonds issued under the authority of sections 13-1101 to 13-1110 shall be subject to the provisions contained in section 13-1103 and may be secured in accordance with the provisions of section 13-1104.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 54, &#167; 6, p. 205; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 77, &#167; 3, p. 283; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 18-1619.</para></source></law></legaldoc>