<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1306"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1306</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; notes; issuance; refunding; interest; payment.</catchline><para>With the prior approval of both the city and the county for which the commission was created, the commission shall have the power and is hereby authorized from time to time to issue its bonds for any corporate purpose in such amounts as may be required to carry out and fully perform the purposes for which such commission is established. The commission shall have power from time to time and when refunding is deemed expedient to issue bonds in amounts sufficient to refund any bonds, including any premiums payable upon the redemption of the bonds to be refunded and interest to their redemption date upon the bonds to be refunded, by the issuance of new bonds, whether the bonds to be refunded have or have not matured. It may issue bonds partly to refund bonds then outstanding and partly for any other corporate purpose. The refunding bonds may be exchanged for the bonds to be refunded with such cash adjustment as may be agreed or may be sold and the proceeds applied to the purchase, redemption or payment of the bonds to be refunded. All bonds shall be general obligations of the commission issuing the same and shall be payable out of the tax and other receipts, revenue, income receipts, profits, or other money of the commission.</para><para>A commission shall have power from time to time to issue bond anticipation notes referred to as notes in this section and from time to time to issue renewal notes, such notes in any case to mature not later than thirty months from the date of incurring the indebtedness represented thereby in an amount not exceeding in the aggregate at any time outstanding the amount of bonds then or theretofore authorized. Such notes shall be general obligations of the commission. Payment of such notes shall be made from any money or revenue which the commission may have available for such purpose or from the proceeds of the sale of bonds of the commission or such notes may be exchanged for a like amount of such bonds.</para><para>All such bonds and notes shall be authorized by a resolution or resolutions of the board and shall bear such date or dates, mature at such time or times, bear interest at such rate or rates, be in such denominations, be in such form, either coupon or registered, carry such exchange privileges, be executed in such manner, be payable in such medium of payment at such place or places within or without the State of Nebraska and be subject to such terms of redemption and at such redemption premiums, as such resolution or resolutions may provide and the provisions of section 10-126, shall not be applicable to such bonds or notes. The bonds and notes may be sold at public or private sale for such price or prices as the commission shall determine. No proceedings for the issuance of bonds or notes of a commission shall be required other than those required by the provisions of sections 13-1301 to 13-1312 and the provisions of all other laws and city charters, if any, relative to the terms and conditions for the issuance, payment, redemption, registration, sale or delivery of bonds of public bodies, corporations or political subdivisions of this state shall not be applicable to bonds and notes issued by commissions pursuant to sections 13-1301 to 13-1312.</para><para>The full faith and credit of the commission shall be pledged to the payment and security of the bonds and notes issued by it, whether or not such pledge shall be set forth in the bonds or notes. So long as any of its bonds or notes are outstanding, the commission shall have the power and be obligated to levy taxes within the limitation as provided in section 13-1304 to the extent required, together with any other money available to the commission therefor to pay the principal of and interest and premium, if any, on such bonds and notes as the same become due and payable.</para><para>All bonds and notes issued pursuant to the provisions of sections 13-1301 to 13-1312 shall be and are hereby made negotiable instruments within the meaning of and for all the purposes of the Uniform Commercial Code subject only to any provisions contained in such bonds and notes for the registration of the principal thereof.</para><para>A commission shall have power to purchase bonds or notes of the commission out of any money available therefor. Any bonds so purchased shall be canceled by the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 1003, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-2606.</para></source></law></legaldoc>