<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1311"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1311</statuteno><catchline>City; county; powers.</catchline><para>With respect to the commission created for the city and county and its projects, the city and the county may each:</para><para>(1) Operate and maintain any project of the commission;</para><para>(2) Appropriate funds for any cost incurred by the commission in acquiring, constructing, reconstructing, improving, extending, equipping, remodeling, renovating, furnishing, operating, or maintaining any project;</para><para>(3) Convey or transfer to the commission any property of the city or the county for use in connection with a project, including real and personal property owned or leased by the city or the county and used or useful in connection therewith. In case of real property so conveyed, the title thereto shall remain in the city or the county as the case may be but the commission shall have the use and occupancy thereof so long as its corporate existence continues. In the case of personal property so conveyed, the title shall pass to the commission;</para><para>(4) Acquire, by purchase or condemnation, real property in the name of the city or the county as the case may be for the projects of the commission, for the widening of existing roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways, for new roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways to a project, or partly for such purposes and partly for other city or county purposes, in the manner provided by law for acquisition. The city or the county may also close any roads, streets, parkways, avenues, or highways as may be necessary or convenient to facilitate the construction of any project of the commission;</para><para>(5) Enter into an agreement with the commission for the use by the city and the county of the project. The agreement shall set forth the respective obligations of the parties thereto as to the operation, maintenance, repair, and replacement of the project; the amount of space in any joint facility to be utilized by the city and county; the method or formula of determining the respective duties and obligations of the city and the county for cost of operation, maintenance, repair, and replacement of the project; and the method or formula for determining the payments to be made by the city to the commission as being applicable to the principal of and interest and premium on the bonds of the commission issued to finance the project. The city shall have the power to levy a tax on all the taxable property in the city sufficient to make the payments to the commission applicable to the principal of and interest and premium on the bonds of the commission issued for the project, which tax shall be in addition to all other taxes now or hereafter authorized by statute or charter. If the city is subject to a limitation by statute or charter on the amount of taxes which may be imposed by the city for its operating expenses, the maximum which may be levied in excess of such limitation pursuant to the authorization of this subdivision shall not exceed one and seven-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of all taxable property; and</para><para>(6) Enter into agreements with each other and with the commission necessary, desirable, or useful in carrying out the purposes of sections 13-1301 to 13-1312 upon such terms and conditions as determined by the governing body.</para><para>If at any time space not for the use and services of any project acquired or constructed or to be acquired or constructed by the commission is in excess of the needs of the city or the county for which the commission was created, the commission with the approval of the city or the county may enter into agreements with the United States of America, the state, or any other governmental unit providing for the use by the United States of America, the State of Nebraska, or such other governmental unit of the project, and such other governmental units shall possess the same powers with respect to the commission and its projects as are possessed by the city and county under the provisions of this section. Any agreement entered into by the state shall be subject to all the terms, provisions, and conditions of sections 72-1401 to 72-1412 with the same effect as though the commission were named as a municipality under such sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 1003, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 127; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-2611; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 33.</para></source><annotation><para>In view of the history recited in this opinion and the provisions of the act itself, it cannot be said the act is beyond a reasonable doubt unconstitutional. Dwyer v. Omaha-Douglas Public Building Commission, 188 Neb. 30, 195 N.W.2d 236 (1972).</para><para>The provision in this section for transfer of any property to the commission does not violate Article XIII, section 2, Constitution of Nebraska. Dwyer v. Omaha-Douglas Public Building Commission, 188 Neb. 30, 195 N.W.2d 236 (1972).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>