<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1901</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska planning and development regions; created.</catchline><para>(1) There are hereby created nine Nebraska planning and development regions as follows:</para><para>(a) Region 1 includes the counties of Sioux, Dawes, Sheridan, Box Butte, Scotts Bluff, Morrill, Garden, Banner, Kimball, Cheyenne, and Deuel;</para><para>(b) Region 2 includes the counties of Cherry, Keya Paha, Boyd, Brown, Rock, Holt, Blaine, Loup, Garfield, Wheeler, Custer, Valley, Greeley, and Sherman;</para><para>(c) Region 3 includes the counties of Grant, Hooker, Thomas, Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Keith, Lincoln, Perkins, Dawson, Chase, Hayes, Frontier, Gosper, Dundy, Hitchcock, Red Willow, and Furnas;</para><para>(d) Region 4 includes the counties of Howard, Merrick, Buffalo, Hall, Hamilton, Phelps, Kearney, Adams, Clay, Harlan, Franklin, Webster, and Nuckolls;</para><para>(e) Region 5 includes the counties of Knox, Cedar, Dixon, Antelope, Pierce, Wayne, Thurston, Boone, Madison, Stanton, Cuming, Burt, Platte, Colfax, Dodge, and Nance;</para><para>(f) Region 6 includes the counties of Polk, Butler, Saunders, York, Seward, Fillmore, Saline, Otoe, Thayer, Jefferson, Gage, Johnson, Nemaha, Pawnee, and Richardson;</para><para>(g) Region 7 includes the county of Lancaster;</para><para>(h) Region 8 includes the counties of Washington, Douglas, Sarpy, and Cass; and</para><para>(i) Region 9 includes the county of Dakota.</para><para>(2) In order to facilitate development of a process which will allow for future changes to the boundaries of the Nebraska planning and development regions, until July 1, 2020, a county, city, village, or development district shall not engage in negotiations to change the boundaries of the planning and development regions. This subsection does not prohibit negotiations relating to implementation of the changes to the boundaries made by Laws 2019, LB334.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 573, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB334, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>