<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1303</statuteno><catchline>Commission; created; membership; expenses; quorum; corporate existence.</catchline><para>There is hereby created and established in each county a commission to be known and designated as (name of city) (name of county) public building commission, except that sections 13-1301 to 13-1312 shall not become operative in any county unless and until the governing body of the county by resolution shall activate the commission for such county. A copy of such resolution certified by the county clerk shall be filed with and recorded by the Secretary of State and also filed with the city clerk. Each such commission shall be a body politic and corporate and an instrumentality of the state.</para><para>Each commission shall be governed by a board of commissioners of five members, two of whom shall be appointed by the governing body of the county from among the members of such governing body, two of whom shall be appointed by the mayor of the city with the approval of the governing body of the city from among the members of such governing body, and the fifth of whom shall be appointed by the other four members. The fifth member shall be a resident of the county in which the commission is established. In the event the four members appointed by the county and the city cannot appoint the fifth member by a majority, the Governor, upon request of such four members, the city, or the county, shall appoint the fifth member. The term of office of each member of the board, except for the initial members, shall be four years or until a successor is appointed and takes office. Any vacancy on the board shall be filled (1) by the governing body of the county if the person whose membership was vacated was appointed by the governing body of the county, (2) by the mayor of the city with the approval of the governing body of the city if the person whose membership was vacated was appointed by the mayor, and (3) by the remaining four members if the person whose membership was vacated was appointed by the members of the board. The members of the board shall not be entitled to compensation for their services but shall be entitled to reimbursement of expenses paid or incurred in the performance of the duties imposed upon them by sections 13-1301 to 13-1312 with reimbursement for mileage to be made at the rate provided in section 81-1176. A majority of the total number of members of the board shall constitute a quorum, and all action taken by the board shall be taken by a majority of such total number. The board may delegate to one or more of the members or to its officers, agents, and employees such powers and duties as it deems proper. Any member of the board may be removed from office for incompetence, neglect of duty, or malfeasance in office. An action for the removal of a member of the board may be brought in the district court of the county upon resolution of the governing body of the city or the county.</para><para>The terms of office of the two persons initially appointed to the board by the governing body of the county shall be for one and four years, and such governing body shall designate which person shall serve for one year and which person shall serve for four years. The terms of office of the two persons initially appointed to the board by the mayor with the approval of the governing body of the city shall be for two and three years, and such governing body shall designate which person shall serve for two years and which person shall serve for three years. The term of office of the person initially appointed by the other members of the board shall be for four years. Terms of office on the board shall expire on the same day of the year, and the governing body of the county in making the first appointments to the board shall designate such expiration date.</para><para>The commission and its corporate existence shall continue until all its liabilities have been met and its bonds have been paid in full or such liabilities and bonds have otherwise been discharged and the governing bodies of the city and county jointly determine that the commission is no longer needed. Upon the commission's ceasing to exist all rights or properties of the commission shall pass to and be vested in the city and county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 1003, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 32; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-2603; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1043, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1011, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB233, &#167; 1.</para></source></law></legaldoc>