<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1403"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1403</statuteno><catchline>Members; terms; organization; records; removal; vacancies, how filled.</catchline><para>When it has been determined by the county board or the governing body of any such municipality that it is expedient to establish such board of public docks the county board or the governing body of such municipality shall appoint as members of the dock board, seven such commissioners who shall have been residents of the county or municipality, as the case may be, in which they are appointed for a period of not less than five years and shall be prominently identified with the commercial and business interests of the county or municipality, as the case may be, and who shall not at the time of their appointment or during their term of office be interested in or be employed by any common carrier; and such board shall act without compensation. Of the commissioners initially appointed, three shall serve for a term of one year, three for a term of two years, and one for a term of three years. As the term of office of each commissioner expires, his successor shall be appointed by the county board or the governing body, and the term of office of such commissioner shall be three years. The commissioners shall qualify by taking oath for the faithful performance of their duties. Within ten days after their appointment the commissioners shall meet and organize such board by the election from among their number of a president, a vice president, and a treasurer of the board, and shall elect a secretary who need not be a member of the board. Any two of the offices except president and vice president may be held by one commissioner. The board shall from time to time adopt rules and regulations, consistent with the provisions of sections 13-1401 to 13-1417, for the government of the board and its proceedings, which shall be adopted by resolution and shall be recorded in a book kept by the board and known as the book of rules and regulations. The rules and regulations shall be in force after one publication in some legal newspaper published in or circulating in the municipality. The board shall maintain an office and keep a record of all its proceedings and acts, and books of accounts shall at all times be open to public inspection. If any commissioner shall at any time during his incumbency cease to have the qualifications required by this section for his appointment or shall willfully violate any of his duties under the law, such commissioner shall be removed by the county board or the governing body after written charges have been preferred against him and a due hearing of such charges shall have been had by the county board or the governing body upon reasonable notice to such commissioner. Vacancies occurring in the board through resignation or otherwise shall be filled by the county board or the governing body for the unexpired term.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 37, &#167; 2, p. 167; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 18-2002; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 18-702; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 20, &#167; 2, p. 103; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 84, &#167; 2, p. 260; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 18-702.</para></source></law></legaldoc>