<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id00" statutenumber="13-1906"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1906</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Distribution of financial assistance.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Economic Development shall distribute financial assistance from the state, if available, to the various development districts as they are certified in the manner prescribed in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2)(a) Fifty percent of the total sum allocated shall be divided equally among the certified development districts. In certified districts formed by regional councils, funds may be prorated among the cooperating regional councils based upon a formula approved by the governing boards of each of the cooperating regional councils and accepted by the department.</para><para>(b) Twenty percent of the total sum allocated shall be divided among the certified development districts based upon their proportional share of the population of all certified development districts in the state. For purposes of this subdivision, population shall mean the number of residents as shown by the latest federal decennial census, except that the population of a county shall mean the number of residents in the unincorporated areas of the county as shown by the latest federal decennial census or as determined by the Department of Economic Development if such census data is not available.</para><para>(c) Thirty percent of the total sum allocated shall be divided among the certified development districts based upon their proportional share of the local governments located within all certified development districts.</para><para>(3) Distributions to newly certified development districts shall not reduce financial assistance to previously funded development districts. State financial assistance shall not exceed the total local dollars received by the development district as verified by the department. For purposes of this subsection, local dollars received shall mean the total local dues received by a development district from any local government as a condition of membership in a development district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 573, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB661, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB355, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>