<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-1704"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-1704</statuteno><catchline>Notice to property owners; publication; failure to notify; effect.</catchline><para>No later than fourteen days prior to a request for siting approval, the applicant shall cause written notice of the request for siting approval to be served either in person or by registered or certified mail on the owners of all property within the proposed site area not solely owned by the applicant and on the owners of all property within one thousand feet in each direction of the lot line of the proposed site if the proposed site is inside or within three miles of the corporate limits of a city or village or on the owners of all property within two miles in each direction of the lot line of the proposed site for all other proposed sites. The owners shall be identified based upon the tax records of the county in which the proposed site is located.</para><para>Written notice shall be published in a newspaper of general circulation in the county in which the proposed site is located. The notice shall state the name and address of the applicant, the location of the proposed site, the nature and size of the solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility, the probable life of the proposed solid waste disposal area or solid waste processing facility, the date when the request for siting approval will be submitted, and a description of the right of persons to comment on the request.</para><para>Failure to notify all landowners and failure to include all information in the publicized notice as required by this section shall not be considered noncompliance if a good faith effort at notice was made by the applicant which results in actual notice to substantially all parties required to be notified.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 813, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 61.</para></source></law></legaldoc>