<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id6" statutenumber="13-2042"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2042</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Landfill disposal
fee; payment; interest; use; grants; department; powers; council; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) A disposal fee of one dollar and twenty-five cents is imposed for
each six cubic yards of uncompacted solid waste, one dollar and twenty-five
cents for each three cubic yards of compacted solid waste, or one dollar and
twenty-five cents per ton of solid waste (a) disposed of at landfills regulated
by the department or (b) transported for disposal out of state from a solid
waste processing facility holding a permit under the Integrated Solid Waste
Management Act. Each operator of a landfill or solid waste processing facility
shall make the fee payment quarterly. The fee shall be paid quarterly to the
department on or before the forty-fifth day following the end of each quarter.
For purposes of this section, landfill has the same definition as municipal
solid waste landfill unit in 40 C.F.R. 258.2.</para>
<para>(2) Each fee payment shall be accompanied by a form prepared and furnished
by the department and completed by the permitholder. The form shall state
the total volume of solid waste disposed of at the landfill or transported
for disposal out of state from the solid waste processing facility during
the payment period and shall provide any other information deemed necessary
by the department. The form shall be signed by the permitholder.</para>
<para>(3) If a permitholder fails to make a timely payment of the fee, he
or she shall pay interest on the unpaid amount at the rate specified in section
45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted.</para>
<para>(4) This section shall not apply to a site used solely for the reclamation
of land through the introduction of landscaping rubble or inert material.</para>
<para>(5) Fifty percent of the total of such fees collected in each quarter
shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Integrated Solid
Waste Management Cash Fund and shall be used by the department to cover the
direct and indirect costs of responding to spills or other environmental emergencies,
of regulating, investigating, remediating, and monitoring facilities during
and after operation of facilities, or of performance of regulated activities
under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, the Nebraska
Litter Reduction and Recycling Act, and the Waste Reduction and Recycling
Incentive Act. The department may seek recovery of expenses paid from the
fund for responding to spills or other environmental emergencies or for investigation,
remediation, and monitoring of a facility from any person who owned, operated,
or used the facility in violation of the Integrated Solid Waste Management
Act, the Nebraska Litter Reduction and Recycling Act, and the
Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Act in a civil action filed in the
district court of Lancaster County.</para>
<para>(6)(a) The remaining fifty
percent of the total of such fees collected per quarter shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive
Fund. For purposes of determining the total fees collected, any amount of
fees rebated pursuant to section 13-2042.01 shall be included as if the fees
had not been rebated, and the amount of the fees rebated pursuant to such
section shall be deducted from the amount to be credited to the Waste Reduction
and Recycling Incentive Fund.</para>
<para>(b) From the fees credited
to the Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Fund under this subsection:</para>
<para>(i)
Grants shall be awarded to counties, municipalities, and agencies
for the purposes of planning and implementing facilities and systems to further
the goals of the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act. The grant proceeds shall
not be used to fund landfill closure site assessments, closure,
monitoring, or investigative or corrective action costs for existing landfills
or landfills already closed prior to July 15, 1992. The council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to carry out this subdivision. Such rules and regulations shall
base the awarding of grants on a project's reflection of the integrated solid
waste management policy and hierarchy established in section 13-2018, the
proposed amount of local matching funds, and community need; and</para>
<para>(ii) The department may
disburse amounts to political subdivisions for costs incurred in response
to and remediation of any solid waste disposed of or abandoned at dump sites
or discrete locations along public roadways or ditches and on any contiguous
area affected by such disposal or abandonment. Such reimbursement shall be
by application to the department on forms prescribed by the department. The
department shall prepare and make available a schedule of eligible costs and
application procedures which may include a requirement of a demonstration
of preventive measures to be taken to discourage future dumping. The department
may not disburse to political subdivisions an amount which in the aggregate
exceeds five percent of total revenue from the disposal fees collected pursuant
to this section in the preceding fiscal year. These disbursements shall be
made on a fiscal-year basis, and applications received after funds for this
purpose have been exhausted may be eligible during the next fiscal year but
are not an obligation of the state. Any eligible costs incurred by a political
subdivision which are not funded due to a lack of funds shall not be considered
an obligation of the state. In disbursing funds under this subdivision, the
director shall make efforts to ensure equal geographical distribution throughout
the state and may deny reimbursements in order to accomplish this goal.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1207, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 495, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 592, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 128, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 143, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB696, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB29, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Litter Reduction and Recycling Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1534.</para><para><emphasis>Waste Reduction and Recycling Incentive Act,</emphasis> see section 81-15,158.01.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>