<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2803"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2803</statuteno><catchline>Council; members; quorum; election; executive officer.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (1)(b) of this section, a municipal county created under section 13-2801 shall be governed by a council of five to nine members, at least two-thirds of whom shall be elected by district. The council members shall be elected on a nonpartisan ballot. The area involved in the consolidation shall be divided into districts of as equal population as possible so that at least a majority of the members of the council are elected by district. The division shall be made by the county board members of each county involved by January 31 of the year in which the council members are to be elected. A majority of the council members shall constitute a quorum for the purpose of transacting business. The council shall annually elect a chairperson from among its members. Each council member shall be elected to a four-year term beginning with the first general election following the formation, except that at the first election, fifty to sixty percent of the members shall be elected to four-year terms and the others shall be elected to two-year terms. If there are to be at-large members, the district-elected members shall be elected to four-year terms and the at-large members shall be elected to two-year terms. If there are to be no at-large members, the members elected to four-year terms and the members elected to two-year terms shall be selected by lot.</para><para>(b) A municipal county created under section 13-2801, in which is situated a city of the metropolitan class, shall be governed by a council of fifteen members who shall be elected by districts. The council members shall be elected on a nonpartisan ballot. The area involved in the consolidation shall be divided into fifteen council districts of compact and contiguous territory. Such districts shall be numbered consecutively from one to fifteen. One council member shall be elected from each district. The division shall be made by the county board members of each county involved, by January 31 of the year in which the council members are to be elected. Each council member shall be elected to a four-year term, except that at the first general election following the formation, the members elected from even-numbered districts shall be elected to four-year terms and members elected from odd-numbered districts shall be elected to two-year terms and to four-year terms thereafter. A majority of the council members shall constitute a quorum for the purpose of transacting business. The council shall annually elect a chairperson from among its members. The council shall be responsible for redrawing the council district boundaries pursuant to section 32-553.</para><para>(c) Initial elections of the council members and the executive officer, if applicable, shall be completed by May 15 of the year the municipal county is created.</para><para>(2) If the plan to create the municipal county provides for an executive officer to operate the executive functions of the municipal county, the executive officer shall be elected to a four-year term beginning with the first general election following the formation of the municipal county.</para><para>(3) The resolution proposing creation of the municipal county may retain, as an elected position, any elected county office in any county to be consolidated into the municipal county. If such elected officials are to be retained, the officials in such offices at the time the municipal county is created may be retained or, if more than one such elected official are in office at the time the municipal county is created, the officials shall be elected together with the council members and executive officer of the municipal county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 3.</para></source></law></legaldoc>