<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<sectno id="id18">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id19" statutenumber="13-2042.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id21">13-2042.01</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Landfill disposal
fee; rebate to municipality or county; application; Department of Environmental
Quality; materiel division of Department of Administrative Services; municipality;
county; duties; suspension or denial of rebate; appeal; rules and regulations.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Department of Environmental Quality shall rebate to
the municipality or county of origin ten cents of the disposal fee required
by section 13-2042 for solid waste disposed
of at landfills regulated by the department or
transported for disposal out of state from a solid waste processing facility
holding a permit under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act and when
such solid waste originated in a municipality or county with a
purchasing policy approved by the department. The fee shall be rebated on
a schedule agreed upon between the municipality or county and the department.
The schedule shall be no more often than quarterly and no less often than
annually.</para>
<para>(2) Any municipality or county may apply to the department
for the rebate authorized in subsection (1) of this section if the municipality
or county has a written purchasing policy in effect requiring a preference
for purchasing products, materials, or supplies which are manufactured or
produced from recycled material. The policy shall provide that the preference
shall not operate when it would result in the purchase of products, materials,
or supplies which are of inadequate quality as determined by the municipality
or county. Upon receipt of an application, the Department of Environmental
Quality shall submit the application to the materiel division of the Department
of Administrative Services for review. The materiel division shall review
the application for compliance with this section and any rules and regulations
adopted pursuant to this section and to determine the probable effectiveness
in assuring that a preference is given to products, materials, or supplies
which are manufactured or produced from recycled material. The materiel division
shall provide a report of its findings to the Department of Environmental
Quality within thirty days after receiving the review request. The Department
of Environmental Quality shall approve the application or suggest modifications
to the application within sixty days after receiving the application based
on the materiel division's report, any analysis by the Department of Environmental
Quality, and any factors affecting compliance with this section or the rules
and regulations adopted pursuant to this section.</para>
<para>(3) A municipality or county shall file a report complying
with the rules and regulations adopted pursuant to this section with the Department
of Environmental Quality before April 1 of each year documenting purchasing
practices for the past calendar year in order to continue receiving the rebate.
The report shall include, but not be limited to, quantities of products, materials,
or supplies purchased which were manufactured or produced from recycled material.
The department shall provide copies of each report to the materiel division
in a timely manner. If the department determines that a municipality or county
is not following the purchasing policy presented in the approved application
or that the purchasing policy presented in the approved application is not
effective in assuring that a preference is given to products, materials, or
supplies which are manufactured or produced from recycled material, the department
shall suspend the rebate until it determines that the municipality or county
is giving a preference to products, materials, or supplies which are manufactured
or produced from recycled material pursuant to a written purchasing policy
approved by the department subsequent to the suspension. The materiel division
may make recommendations to the department regarding suspensions and reinstatements
of rebates. The Department of Administrative Services may adopt and promulgate
rules and regulations establishing procedures for reviewing applications and
for annual reports.</para>
<para>(4) Any suspension of the rebate or denial of an application
made under this section may be appealed. The appeal shall be in accordance
with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
<para>(5) The council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
establishing criteria for application procedures, for accepting and denying
applications, for required reports, and for suspending and reinstating the
rebate. The materiel division shall recommend to the council criteria for
accepting and denying applications and for suspending and reinstating the
rebate. The materiel division may make other recommendations to the council
regarding rules and regulations authorized under this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1207, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB180, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB696, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>