<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2609"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2609</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; duties; certain
retailers and operators; reports required.</catchline><para>(1) If an application
is approved, the Tax Commissioner shall:</para>
<para>(a) Audit or review audits of the approved convention and meeting center
facility, sports arena facility, or associated hotel to determine the state
sales tax revenue collected by retailers and operators doing business at such
facilities on sales at such facilities, state sales tax revenue collected
on primary and secondary box office sales of admissions to such facilities,
and state sales tax revenue collected by associated hotels; and</para>
<para>(b) Certify annually the amount of state sales tax revenue collected
by retailers and operators doing business at such facilities on sales at such
facilities, state sales tax revenue collected on primary and secondary box
office sales of admissions to such facilities, and state sales tax revenue
collected by associated hotels, to the State Treasurer.</para>
<para>(2) State sales tax revenue collected by retailers and operators that
are not eligible facilities but are doing business at eligible facilities
shall be reported on informational returns developed by the Department of
Revenue and provided to any such retailers and operators by the eligible facility.
The informational returns shall be submitted to the department by the retailer
or operator by the twentieth day of the month
following the month the sales taxes are collected. The Tax Commissioner shall
use the data from the informational returns and sales tax returns of eligible
facilities and associated hotels to determine the appropriate amount of state
sales tax revenue.</para>
<para>(3) Changes made to the Convention Center Facility Financing Assistance
Act by Laws 2007, LB 551, shall apply to state sales tax revenue collected
commencing on July 1, 2006.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 382, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB551, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB210, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Limitation on applications,</emphasis> see section 13-2612.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
