
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2525"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2525</statuteno><catchline>Biennial report; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Commencing in 2001 and each odd-numbered year thereafter, each joint public agency shall deliver to the Secretary of State a biennial report on a form prescribed and furnished by the Secretary of State that sets forth:</para><para>(a) The name of the joint public agency;</para><para>(b) The street address of its principal office and the name of its manager or executive director, if any, at the office in this state;</para><para>(c) The names and business or residence addresses of its representatives and principal officers;</para><para>(d) A brief description of the nature of its activities; and</para><para>(e) The names of the participating public agencies.</para><para>(2) The information in the biennial report must be current on the date the biennial report is executed on behalf of the joint public agency.</para><para>(3) The first biennial report must be delivered to the Secretary of State between January 1 and April 1 of the odd-numbered year following the calendar year in which the joint public agency was authorized to transact business. Subsequent biennial reports must be delivered to the Secretary of State between January 1 and April 1 of the following odd-numbered years. The biennial report is due on April 1 of the odd-numbered year in which it must be delivered to the Secretary of State as required by this section.</para><para>(4) If a biennial report does not contain the information required by this section, the Secretary of State shall promptly notify the reporting joint public agency in writing and return the report to it for correction. If the report is corrected to contain the information required by this section and delivered to the Secretary of State within thirty days after the effective date of notice, it is deemed to be timely filed.</para><para>(5) Upon the delivery of the biennial report as provided in this section, the Secretary of State shall charge and collect a fee of thirty dollars if the filing is submitted in writing and twenty-five dollars if the filing is submitted electronically pursuant to section 84-511. The fee is due on April 1 of the odd-numbered year in which the biennial report must be delivered to the Secretary of State as required by this section.</para><para>(6) A correction or an amendment to the biennial report may be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing at any time. The fee for filing a correction or an amendment to the biennial report shall be thirty dollars if the filing is submitted in writing and twenty-five dollars if the filing is submitted electronically pursuant to section 84-511.</para><para>(7) The Secretary of State shall collect all fees imposed in this section and shall remit the fees to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit sixty percent of the fees to the General Fund and forty percent of the fees to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB774, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 2. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>