<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2110</statuteno><catchline>Enterprise zone association; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) An enterprise zone association created pursuant to section 13-2109 shall:</para><para>(a) Approve the application to be submitted by the political subdivision to the department for enterprise zone designation;</para><para>(b) Promote the enterprise zone to outside groups and individuals;</para><para>(c) Establish a formal line of communication with residents and businesses in the enterprise zone;</para><para>(d) Act as a liaison between residents, businesses, and the city, village, county, or tribal government for any development activity that may affect the enterprise zone or zone residents; and</para><para>(e) By majority vote of the full enterprise zone association board:</para><para>(i) Approve the acceptance by the city, village, county, or tribal government of any state or federal grant or loan for the enterprise zone;</para><para>(ii) Approve the purposes for and the conditions surrounding such grants or loans;</para><para>(iii) Approve any expenditures of funds by the city, village, county, or tribal government which are to be made for the purpose of complying with the Enterprise Zone Act; and</para><para>(iv) Approve the appointment of any staff member designated to work exclusively with the enterprise zone association board.</para><para>The city council, village board, county board, or tribal government shall not act affirmatively with regard to any matter requiring the approval of the enterprise zone association board until such time as it has received the approval of the enterprise zone association board.</para><para>(2) An enterprise zone association may:</para><para>(a) Initiate and coordinate any community development activities that aid in the employment of enterprise zone residents, improve the physical environment, or encourage the turnover or retention of capital in the enterprise zone. Such additional activities may include recommendations to the city, village, county, or tribal government and the department; and</para><para>(b) Make recommendations to the city, village, county, tribal government, state agency, or other political subdivision for the establishment of a plan or plans for public improvements or programs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1240, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1259, &#167; 2.</para></source></law></legaldoc>