<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2514"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2514</statuteno><catchline>Representatives; terms; vacancy; expenses.</catchline><para>Each representative shall serve for a term specified in the agreement creating the joint public agency, not to exceed four years, or until his or her successor has been appointed and has qualified in the same manner as the original appointment. A representative shall be eligible for reappointment upon the expiration of his or her term. A certificate of the appointment or reappointment of any representative or alternate representative shall be issued by the governing body and shall be filed with the clerk or secretary of the public agency for which the representative acts and the joint public agency. The certificate shall be conclusive evidence of the due and proper appointment of the representative. A representative may be removed for any cause at any time by the governing body of the participating public agency for which the representative acts. A representative shall be removed if he or she is no longer a member of the governing body of the public agency which makes the appointment. A vacancy shall be filled for the balance of the unexpired term of a person who is no longer eligible to hold office in the same manner as the original appointment, until the term as representative expires, or until removed by the participating public agency which appointed him or her. A representative shall receive no compensation for his or her services but shall be entitled to actual and necessary expenses incurred in the discharge of his or her official duties, including mileage at the rate provided in section 81-1176.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 14.</para></source></law></legaldoc>