<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2810"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2810</statuteno><catchline>Election; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The powers granted by sections 13-2801 to 13-2809 shall not be exercised unless and until the question has been submitted at a primary, general, or special election held within the county or counties involved and in which registered voters within the boundaries of the proposed municipal county are entitled to vote on such question. The ballot question may combine the issues of creation of the municipal county, the merger of the county or counties and its offices, the merger of each municipality proposed to be merged, and the authorization of a local sales and use tax under section 13-2813.</para><para>(2) The officials of each county and each municipality seeking to form the municipal county shall order the submission of the question for creation by submitting a certified copy of the resolution calling for creation to the election commissioner or county clerk. The question may include any terms or conditions set forth in the resolution, such as the timing of the consolidation implementation, the number and method of election of council members, and any proposed name for the municipal county, and shall specifically state any offices to be eliminated.</para><para>(3) The election commissioner or county clerk shall give notice of the submission of the question not more than thirty days nor less than ten days before the election by publication one time in one or more newspapers published in or of general circulation within the boundaries of the proposed municipal county in which the question is to be submitted. This notice is in addition to any other notice required under the Election Act.</para><para>(4)(a) The vote shall be tabulated for (i) all those voting on the question, (ii) those voting who reside in each county and any municipality which would be consolidated into the municipal county, (iii) those voting who reside in each county but outside any municipality, and (iv) those voting who reside in each county but outside any municipality or any sanitary and improvement district.</para><para>(b) If a majority of those voting on the question, a majority of those voting who reside in at least one county to be consolidated, a majority of those voting who reside in at least one municipality which is in one county voting in favor of consolidation, a majority of those voting who reside in areas in the county to be consolidated which are outside any municipality to be consolidated, and a majority of those voting who reside in each county but outside any municipality or any sanitary and improvement district vote in favor of consolidation, the municipal county shall be deemed to be created for each county and municipality which had a majority of those voting in favor of consolidation according to the terms of the resolution. If no date of creation is provided in the resolution, the municipal county shall be deemed to be created on the following July 1. Any county in which a majority of those voting approve the consolidation shall be deemed to be abolished, and any municipality in such county which was proposed to be consolidated and in which a majority of those voting who reside in such municipality approve the consolidation shall be deemed to be abolished.</para><para>(c) The municipal county shall not be created (i) if a majority of those voting on the question are opposed, (ii) if a majority of those voting who reside in every county to be consolidated are opposed, (iii) if a majority of those voting who reside in every municipality to be consolidated which is in a county which approved are opposed, (iv) if a majority of those voting who reside in areas in a county which approved which are outside any municipality are opposed, or (v) if a majority of those voting who reside in a county which approved but outside any municipality or sanitary and improvement district are opposed.</para><para>(5) If a municipality within the boundaries of a municipal county is not a part of the municipal county either because the governing body of the municipality did not approve the resolution seeking inclusion or because the voters of the municipality disapproved the consolidation, the municipality may later seek inclusion into an existing municipal county by passing a resolution seeking inclusion and approval by those voting at a primary, general, or special election. The officials of the municipality shall deliver a certified copy of the resolution to the appropriate officer of the municipal county proposing inclusion. If a majority of those voting in the municipality approve inclusion and a majority of the elected council members of the municipal county vote to approve inclusion of such municipality, the municipality shall be merged into the municipal county. If a majority of those voting in the municipality disapprove or a majority of the elected council members of the municipal county do not vote to approve inclusion of such municipality, it shall not be merged.</para><para>(6) Any election under this section shall be conducted in accordance with the procedures provided in the Election Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 10.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>