<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2104</statuteno><catchline>Application; contents.</catchline><para>An application for designation of an area as an enterprise zone shall contain at least the following:</para><para>(1) A description of the geographic location of the proposed zone;</para><para>(2) Documentation that the area of the proposed enterprise zone represents the area with the greatest level of economic distress within the boundaries of the applying political subdivision;</para><para>(3) An enterprise zone economic development plan containing goals, objectives, and a description of current and new actions to be undertaken to encourage private investment in the area, including: (a) Job training to be provided to new and existing businesses in the zone and to unemployed and displaced worker residents; (b) the provision of technical assistance to businesses in the zone, such as management training, marketing assistance, engineering or technology assistance, and business plan preparation; (c) efforts to be made to assure the safety of businesses and employees in the zone; (d) efforts to be made to market the zone to new and existing businesses as an appropriate place for location or expansion; (e) infrastructure investments to be made to lead to economic development; and (f) organizational structures to be created and processes to be undertaken which will lead toward economic development;</para><para>(4) A plan to insure that resources are available to assist residents of the area with self-help development;</para><para>(5) A description of any projected positive or negative effects of designation of the area as an enterprise zone;</para><para>(6) A plan to provide assistance to persons or businesses displaced as a result of zone activity;</para><para>(7) Documentation of substantial commitments to be made by the private sector of resources and contributions to the operation or development of the zone;</para><para>(8) Documentation that the requirements in sections 13-2106 to 13-2108 have been completed;</para><para>(9) Cities of the metropolitan, primary, and first classes shall provide documentation of the commitment of funds for expenditure in the proposed enterprise zone during the first three years of its existence if it is designated an enterprise zone by the department. Such funds shall be for the purpose of directly or indirectly assisting or enabling businesses to locate or expand existing operations within the area of the proposed enterprise zone. The funds to be committed and expended shall be from revenue of the city or any other local political subdivision, from private nongovernmental sources, or from any other nonstate government sources. For cities of the metropolitan and primary classes, such commitments from all permitted sources shall not be less than five hundred thousand dollars. For cities of the first class, such commitments from all permitted sources shall not be less than one hundred thousand dollars. No application for enterprise zone designation from a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class shall be approved until commitments at the level designated have been documented to the department;</para><para>(10) Counties, tribal governments, cities of the second class, and villages shall document commitments to be made from private sector sources of resources and funds for the operation and development of the enterprise zone and commitments by the applicant and other local political subdivisions of local revenue and other nonstate government resources to encourage economic development in the area. Such commitments of funds shall be consistent with local government capabilities to raise additional funds from local sources and shall reflect the applicant's commitment to the proposed enterprise zone. If a county is making an application for designation of an area located in whole or in part within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class, the county shall provide documentation of the commitment of funds for expenditure in the proposed enterprise zone as provided in subdivision (9) of this section as if the application were being made by the city; and</para><para>(11) A description of any actions to be taken with regard to the removal, reduction, or simplification of any resolutions, regulations, ordinances, fees, or other items pursuant to the authority granted by section 13-2111.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1240, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 5.</para></source></law></legaldoc>