
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2109"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2109</statuteno><catchline>Enterprise zone association; board;
membership; vacancies; powers and duties; dissolution.</catchline><para>(1)
There shall be created an enterprise zone association within each proposed
enterprise zone upon the decision by the political subdivision to submit an
enterprise zone application. Such enterprise zone association shall be governed
by an enterprise zone association board which shall consist of seven members.
The initial members of the board shall be appointed by the mayor of the city
or village with the approval of the city council or village board, by the
county board, or by the tribal chairperson. The city council, village board,
county board, or tribal government shall establish the length of the terms
and shall establish staggered terms so that no more than four members of the
enterprise zone association board shall be appointed in any one-year period.</para>
<para>(2) The city council, village board, county board, or tribal government
shall, by majority vote, nominate candidates and appoint from the candidates
qualified persons to fill each vacant, open, or opening seat on the enterprise
zone association board. A member of the enterprise zone association board,
not otherwise disqualified, whose term of office has ended shall continue
to serve as a member of the board until his or her successor is properly qualified
and appointed.</para>
<para>(3) Vacancies on the enterprise zone association board shall be filled
in the same manner as provided for appointments other than initial appointments,
and such members shall serve for the balance of the unexpired terms. A board
member may serve more than one term. Any board member appointed as a resident
of the area constituting the enterprise zone shall cease to be a member of
the enterprise zone association board at such time as he or she ceases to
be a resident within the area constituting the zone, and at such time his
or her seat shall be vacant.</para>
<para>(4) The enterprise zone association board shall select its own officers
and may exercise such other additional powers and authority as may be granted
it by the department or the city, village, county, or tribal government. The
presence of at least four members of the enterprise zone association board
shall be necessary to transact any business.</para>
<para>(5) Individuals chosen to serve as members of the enterprise zone association
board shall include property owners, business operators, and users of space
within the area of the enterprise zone as well as individuals representing
groups or organizations with an interest in furthering the purposes and goals
of the enterprise zone. Not less than two-thirds of the members of the enterprise
zone association board shall be residents of the area constituting the enterprise
zone. For purposes of this section, residents of the area constituting the
enterprise zone shall be construed to include those persons residing within
a county in which an enterprise zone is located when the enterprise zone is
not located in a city of the primary or metropolitan class.</para>
<para>(6) The city, village, county, or tribal government establishing the
enterprise zone association shall provide appropriate staff assistance and
support to the association.</para>
<para>(7) If an applicant for designation as an enterprise zone does not receive
such designation, the association of such applicant shall be dissolved.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1240, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1259, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB800, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>