<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2911"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2911</statuteno><catchline>Contract proposals; evaluation; selection committee; duties.</catchline><para>(1) In evaluating proposals in accordance with sections 13-2908 and 13-2910, the political subdivision shall refer the proposals for recommendation to a selection committee. The selection committee shall be a group of at least five persons designated by the political subdivision. Members of the selection committee shall include (a) members of the governing body of the political subdivision, (b) members of the administration or staff of the political subdivision, (c) the performance-criteria developer when evaluating proposals from design-builders under section 13-2908 or the political subdivision's architect or engineer when evaluating proposals from construction managers under section 13-2910, (d) any person having special expertise relevant to selection of a design-builder or construction manager under the Political Subdivisions Construction Alternatives Act, and (e) a resident of the political subdivision other than an individual included in subdivisions (a) through (d) of this subsection. A member of the selection committee designated under subdivision (d) or (e) of this subsection shall not be employed by or have a financial or other interest in a design-builder or construction manager who has a proposal being evaluated and shall not be employed by the political subdivision or the performance-criteria developer.</para><para>(2) The selection committee and the political subdivision shall evaluate proposals taking into consideration the criteria enumerated in subdivisions (a) through (g) of this subsection with the maximum percentage of total points for evaluation which may be assigned to each criterion set forth following the criterion. The following criteria shall be evaluated, when applicable:</para><para>(a) The financial resources of the design-builder or construction manager to complete the project, ten percent;</para><para>(b) The ability of the proposed personnel of the design-builder or construction manager to perform, thirty percent;</para><para>(c) The character, integrity, reputation, judgment, experience, and efficiency of the design-builder or construction manager, thirty percent;</para><para>(d) The quality of performance on previous projects, thirty percent;</para><para>(e) The ability of the design-builder or construction manager to perform within the time specified, thirty percent;</para><para>(f) The previous and existing compliance of the design-builder or construction manager with laws relating to the contract, ten percent; and</para><para>(g) Such other information as may be secured having a bearing on the selection, twenty percent.</para><para>(3) The records of the selection committee in evaluating proposals and making recommendations shall be considered public records for purposes of section 84-712.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 391, &#167; 11; R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 79-2011; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB889, &#167;  11.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>