<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<sectno id="id23" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id24" statutenumber="13-2704"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id26">13-2704</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Local Civic,
Cultural, and Convention Center Financing Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline>
<para>(1) The
Local Civic, Cultural, and Convention Center Financing Fund is created. The
fund shall be administered by the department. Transfers may be made from the
fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in
the Local Civic, Cultural, and Convention Center Financing Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act. The fund may be used for assistance for the construction of new centers
or the renovation or expansion of existing centers. The fund may not be used
for planning, programming, marketing, advertising, and related activities. Transfers may be made from the fund to
the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(2) On July 1, 2010,
or as soon thereafter as is administratively possible the State Treasurer
shall transfer seventy-nine thousand three hundred dollars from the Local
Civic, Cultural, and Convention Center Financing Fund to the Department of
Revenue Enforcement Fund.</para><para>(3)
It is the intent of the Legislature that on July 1, 2011, or as soon thereafter
as is administratively possible the State Treasurer shall transfer forty-two
thousand nine hundred dollars from the Local Civic, Cultural, and Convention
Center Financing Fund to the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 382, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167;  5.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>