<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id6" statutenumber="13-2709"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2709</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Information on
grants; department; duties.</catchline><para>The department shall
submit, as part of the department's annual status report under section 81-1201.11,
the following information regarding the Civic and Community Center Financing
Act:</para>
<para>(1) Information documenting the grants conditionally approved
for funding by the Legislature in the following fiscal year;</para>
<para>(2) Reasons why a full application was not sent to any municipality
seeking assistance under the act;</para>
<para>(3) The amount of sales tax revenue generated for the fund
pursuant to subsection (4) of section 13-2610 and subsection (9) of
section 13-3108, the total amount of grants applied for under the act, the
year-end fund balance, and, if all available funds have not been committed
to funding grants under the act, an explanation of the reasons why all such
funds have not been so committed;</para>
<para>(4) The amount of appropriated funds actually expended by
the department for the year;</para>
<para>(5) The department's current budget for administration of
the act and the department's planned use and distribution of funds, including
details on the amount of funds to be expended on grants and the amount of
funds to be expended by the department for administrative purposes; and</para>
<para>(6) Grant summaries, including the applicant municipality,
project description, grant amount requested, amount and type of matching funds,
and reasons for approval or denial based on evaluation criteria from section
13-2707 or 13-2707.01 for every application seeking assistance under the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 382, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB404, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB153, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB867, &#167; 1.</para><operativedate>April 3, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>