<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id31" statutenumber="13-2706"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2706</statuteno><catchline id="id34">Eligibility for grant; grant application.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section for a city of the primary class, any municipality that has applied for and received a grant of assistance under the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act shall not receive state assistance under the Civic and Community Center Financing Act for the same project for which the grant was awarded under the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act.</para><para>(2) A city of the primary class shall not be eligible to receive a grant of assistance from the Civic and Community Center Financing Act if the city has applied for and received a grant of assistance under the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act.</para><para>(3) Any city that has received funding under the Convention Center Facility Financing Assistance Act shall not receive state assistance under the Civic and Community Center Financing Act.</para><para>(4) From July 1, 2023, to June 30, 2024, a municipality shall be eligible for a grant of assistance under the Civic and Community Center Financing Act only if such municipality (a) partners with a certified creative district and (b) is not prohibited from receiving a grant of assistance under subsection (1), (2), or (3) of this section. Notwithstanding the limitations on the amount of grants of assistance in section 13-2705, the amount of any grant of assistance for a municipality partnering with a certified creative district shall not be less than one hundred thousand dollars or more than two hundred fifty thousand dollars, regardless of the population of the municipality. For purposes of this subsection, certified creative district means a creative district certified pursuant to subdivision (5) of section 82-312. After June 30, 2024, this subsection no longer applies.</para><para>(5) Any municipality eligible for a grant of assistance as provided in this section may apply for a grant of assistance from the fund. Any tribal government may apply for a grant of assistance from the fund. Application shall be made on forms developed by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 382, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 385, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB551, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB426, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB927, &#167; 5. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB800, section 3, with LB927, section 5, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB800 became operative July 21, 2022. Changes made by LB927 became effective July 21, 2022.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Convention Center Facility Financing Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2601.</para><para><emphasis>Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 13-3101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>