<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2114"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2114</statuteno><catchline>Report; contents; filing requirements.</catchline>
<para>Within one hundred twenty days after the end of the third
year following the designation of an area as an enterprise zone and at the
end of each two-year period thereafter, the original applying political subdivision
shall file with the department a report on the enterprise zone detailing the
status of the zone on the qualifying economic distress criteria, the current
status of economic activity within the zone, including the number and type
of new business enterprises which have located within the zone and their levels
of employment, the status of local efforts to carry out the enterprise zone
economic development plan outlined in the original application, the status
of local efforts to comply with commitments made under subdivisions (9) and
(10) of section 13-2104, the membership and activities of the enterprise zone
association, and such other items as the department shall request to enable
it to assess the current status of the enterprise zone and to make appropriate
recommendations to the Legislature upon the enterprise zone program as set
out in the Enterprise Zone Act. Prior to filing such report, the applying
political subdivision shall provide copies of the report to its enterprise
zone association which shall attach thereto for filing with the department
such comments or additional information or recommendations as it deems appropriate.
Prior to the commencement of the next following legislative session, the department
shall file electronic copies
of such reports with the Clerk of the Legislature along with any comments
or recommendations it may have with regard thereto or with regard to the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 18.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>