<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2022"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2022</statuteno><catchline>County, municipality, or agency; closure of facility, postclosure care, and investigative and corrective action; powers and duties; tax; special trust funds.</catchline><para>A county, municipality, or agency shall close a facility, provide postclosure care, and undertake investigative and corrective action in accordance with rules and regulations adopted by the council. The costs associated with or reasonably anticipated for such closure, postclosure care, and investigative and corrective action may be included within the rates and charges authorized by section 13-2020 and within the amounts payable under service agreements adopted pursuant to section 13-2024.</para><para>Every county, municipality, and agency may approve, execute, and deliver contractual agreements to assume financial responsibility for the payment of costs of closure, postclosure care, or investigative or corrective action with respect to any facility. Such agreements may provide for a binding general obligation of such county, municipality, or agency obligating payments in future years.</para><para>For the payment or performance of the terms of any such agreement, any county or municipality may agree to levy or cause to be levied an annual tax upon the taxable property within such county or municipality in an amount sufficient for such purposes. Any such tax shall for all purposes of Nebraska law, including limitations upon budget, revenue, and expenditures of public funds, have the same status as a tax levied for the purpose of paying the bonded indebtedness of such county or municipality.</para><para>Every county, municipality, and agency may also approve, execute, and deliver one or more trust agreements, with any bank having trust powers or a trust company, providing for the creation of one or more special trust funds to provide for the payment of costs of closure, postclosure care, or investigative or corrective action.</para><para>No county, municipality, or agency shall be required to provide proof of financial responsibility to obtain or renew a permit for a facility which is not used for disposal of solid waste.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1207, &#167; 6.</para></source></law></legaldoc>