<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2041" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2041</statuteno><catchline>Integrated Solid Waste Management Cash Fund; created; use; investment; application fee schedule; council; establish; permitholder; annual fee.</catchline><para>There is hereby created the Integrated Solid Waste Management Cash Fund. All fees collected by the department pursuant to this section or fees designated pursuant to section 13-2042 or money forfeited under subsection (21) of section 81-1505 shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. Forfeited funds may only be used for purposes specified in the underlying financial assurance instrument. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>The council shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing a fee schedule to be paid to the department by persons applying for a permit to operate a facility pursuant to the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act or the Environmental Protection Act. Payment shall be made in full to the department before the application is processed.</para><para>By October 1 of each year, any person holding a permit under the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act or to operate a solid waste management facility under the Environmental Protection Act shall pay an annual fee in an amount to be determined by the council. The annual fee shall be sufficient to cover the costs of ongoing permit considerations. The fees collected pursuant to this section shall not exceed the amount necessary to pay reasonable costs of administering the permit program pursuant to the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act or the Environmental Protection Act.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer one million three hundred eighty-four thousand four hundred eighty-four dollars from the Integrated Solid Waste Management Cash Fund to the Superfund Cost Share Cash Fund on or before June 1, 2006.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1257, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Environmental Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1532.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>