<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2518"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2518</statuteno><catchline>Dissolution; withdrawal.</catchline><para>Unless the agreement provides for dissolution, a joint public agency shall be dissolved upon the adoption, by the governing bodies of at least one-half of the participating public agencies, of a resolution setting forth the determination that the need for the public agencies to act cooperatively through a joint public agency no longer exists. A joint public agency shall not be dissolved so long as the agency has bonds outstanding unless provision for full payment of the bonds and interest thereon, by escrow or otherwise, has been made pursuant to the terms of the bonds or the resolution, indenture, or security instrument securing the bonds. If the governing bodies of one or more, but less than a majority, of the participating public agencies adopt such a resolution, such public agencies shall be permitted to withdraw from participation in the joint public agency, but withdrawal shall not affect the obligations of the withdrawing public agency pursuant to any contracts or other agreements with the joint public agency. Withdrawal shall not impair the payment of any outstanding bonds or interest thereon. In the event of the dissolution of a joint public agency, its board shall provide for the disposition, division, or distribution of the joint public agency's assets among the participating public agencies by such means as the board shall determine, in its sole discretion, to be fair and equitable or as provided in the agreement for creation of the joint public agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 18.</para></source></law></legaldoc>