<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id19" statutenumber="13-2704"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2704</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Civic and Community Center Financing Fund; created;
use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Civic and Community Center
Financing Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the department.
Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of
the Legislature. Any money in the Civic and Community Center Financing Fund
available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act. The fund may be used for assistance for the construction of
new civic centers, the renovation or expansion of existing civic or community
centers, or the conversion, rehabilitation, or reuse of historic buildings
for purposes consistent with this section. The fund may not be used for programming,
marketing, advertising, and related activities. Transfers may be made from
the fund to the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund and to the State Colleges Sport Facilities Cash Fund at
the direction of the Legislature.</para>
<para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature that on July 1, 2011,
or as soon thereafter as is administratively possible the State Treasurer
shall transfer forty-two thousand nine hundred dollars from the Civic and
Community Center Financing Fund to the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund.</para>
<para>(3) The State
Treasurer shall transfer two hundred fifty thousand dollars from the Civic
and Community Center Financing Fund to the State Colleges Sport Facilities
Cash Fund on October 1 of 2012, 2013, and 2014. Commencing October 1, 2015,
and every year thereafter, the State Treasurer shall transfer four hundred
thousand dollars from the Civic and Community Center Financing Fund to the
State Colleges Sport Facilities Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 382, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB297, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB969, &#167; 4.</para><operativedate>April 3, 2012</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>