<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2910"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2910</statuteno><catchline>Construction management at risk contract; evaluation of proposals; requirements; negotiations.</catchline><para>(1) A political subdivision shall evaluate proposals for a construction management at risk contract in accordance with this section.</para><para>(2) The political subdivision shall evaluate and rank each proposal on the basis of best meeting the criteria in the request for proposals and taking into consideration the recommendation of the selection committee pursuant to section 13-2911.</para><para>(3) The political subdivision shall attempt to negotiate a construction management at risk contract with the highest ranked construction manager and may enter into a construction management at risk contract after negotiations. The negotiations shall include a final determination of the manner by which the construction manager selects a subcontractor. If the political subdivision is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract with the highest ranked construction manager, the political subdivision may terminate negotiations with that construction manager. The political subdivision may then undertake negotiations with the second highest ranked construction manager and may enter into a construction management at risk contract after negotiations. If the political subdivision is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract with the second highest ranked construction manager, the political subdivision may undertake negotiations with the third highest ranked construction manager, if any, and may enter into a construction management at risk contract after negotiations.</para><para>(4) A school district shall file a copy of all construction management at risk contract documents with the State Department of Education within thirty days after their full execution. Within thirty days after completion of the project, the construction manager shall file a copy of all contract modifications and change orders with the department.</para><para>(5) If the political subdivision is unable to negotiate a satisfactory contract with any of the ranked construction managers, the political subdivision may either revise the request for proposals and solicit new proposals or cancel the construction management at risk process under the Political Subdivisions Construction Alternatives Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 391, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2003), &#167; 79-2010; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB889, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
