<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2818"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2818</statuteno><catchline>Sanitary and improvement districts; treatment; payments to municipal county; when; amount; how determined.</catchline><para>(1) Sanitary and improvement districts located within a municipal county created under sections 13-2801 to 13-2819, unless consolidated into a municipal county in accordance with section 13-2819, shall be deemed to be unconsolidated sanitary and improvement districts and shall continue to exist after approval of the formation of the municipal county except as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) An unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district shall have and retain its authority to levy property taxes, and the municipal county shall have no authority to levy property taxes on the lands within an unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district other than for bonded indebtedness incurred by the county prior to creation of the municipal county. The area of the unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district shall not be considered to be within the municipal county except as provided by law.</para><para>(3) Parcels of land which are contiguous to each other and are included within the municipal county, but not included in an unconsolidated municipality, may be included in a sanitary and improvement district with the approval of the council of the municipal county.</para><para>(4) Each unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district shall pay the municipal county for services that were previously provided by the county. The amount paid shall be equal to the attributable cost of county services times a ratio, the numerator of which is the total valuation of all unconsolidated sanitary and improvement districts that are within the boundaries of the municipal county and the denominator of which is the total valuation of the municipal county and all unconsolidated sanitary and improvement districts and unconsolidated municipalities that are within the boundaries of the municipal county, times a ratio the numerator of which is the valuation of the particular unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district and the denominator of which is the total valuation of all unconsolidated sanitary and improvement districts that are within the boundaries of the municipal county, except that the amount paid shall not exceed the total taxable valuation of the unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district times forty-five hundredths of one percent. Any disputes arising under this subsection shall be heard in the district court of such municipal county.</para><para>(5) Unless the unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district is located wholly within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of an unconsolidated municipality, an unconsolidated sanitary and improvement district shall be deemed to be within the zoning jurisdiction of the municipal county.</para><para>(6) Any municipal county sales and use tax that has been approved under section 13-2813 shall be imposed upon transactions within the entire municipal county, including all unconsolidated sanitary and improvement districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 18.</para></source></law></legaldoc>