<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-2509"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-2509</statuteno><catchline>Creation; procedure; appointment of representatives.</catchline><para>(1) The governing body of each public agency participating in the creation of a joint public agency shall adopt a resolution determining that there is a need for a joint public agency and setting forth the names of the proposed participating public agencies. The resolution shall be published in three issues, not less than seven days between issues, of a legal newspaper for each proposed participating public agency or a newspaper having general circulation in the area served by a proposed participating public agency if no legal newspaper exists for the participating public agency and of one or more newspapers of general circulation in the area to be served by the joint public agency. Any such resolution shall not be adopted by a public agency prior to five days after the last publication by the proposed participating public agency. In the case of a state agency, the governing board shall adopt the resolution, or if there is no governing board, the Governor shall issue a proclamation without notice in lieu of a resolution. In the case of a federal agency, the governing board shall adopt the resolution or, if there is no governing board, the President of the United States shall issue a proclamation without notice in lieu of a resolution. The resolution may be adopted by a governing body on its own motion upon determining, in its discretion, that a need exists for a joint public agency. In determining whether such a need exists, a governing body may take into consideration the present and future needs of the public agency with respect to the materials, goods, property, and services which a joint public agency may utilize or provide, the adequacy, suitability, and availability of such materials, goods, property, and services to meet the needs of the participating public agency if no joint public agency is formed, and economic or other advantages or efficiencies which may be realized by cooperative action through a joint public agency.</para><para>(2) Upon issuance of a certificate of creation by the Secretary of State, the Governor in the case of a participating state agency which does not have a governing board, the President of the United States or federal agency head in the case of a federal agency, the mayor or city manager in the case of a city which has not elected to be governed as a village, or the chairperson of the governing body of each participating public agency shall appoint representatives as provided by the agreement for creation of the joint public agency. Representatives, other than representatives appointed by the Governor, the President of the United States, or a federal agency head, must be members of the governing body of the participating public agency which they are appointed to represent. Upon issuance of an amended certificate of creation pursuant to section 13-2513, a representative shall be appointed by each additional participating public agency as provided in this section. An alternate representative with the same qualifications may be appointed in the same manner as a representative and shall serve and exercise all powers of a representative in the absence of the representative for whom he or she is the alternate. The representatives shall constitute the board in which shall be vested all powers of the joint public agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 9.</para></source></law></legaldoc>