<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id904"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3306.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3306.01</statuteno><catchline>Inland port authority; duties; applicability.</catchline><para>An inland port authority located within the boundaries of a city of the metropolitan class shall:</para><para>(1) Create and operate an innovation district;</para><para>(2) Organize and conduct quarterly public input meetings to receive public input regarding concerns, ideas, and priorities for economic development initiatives within the inland port district. The public input meetings shall provide a platform for dialogue and collaboration between residents, the inland port authority, local government officials, and other stakeholders;</para><para>(3) Within ninety days after the receipt of grant funds described in section 13-3314, and annually thereafter, conduct a community survey. Such surveys may be distributed online or through regular United States mail or may be conducted in person to ensure inclusivity and accessibility. The data collected shall help identify key areas for economic development focus within the inland port district and inform decisionmaking processes;</para><para>(4) Only use the grant funds described in section 13-3314 within the inland port district;</para><para>(5) Provide direct oversight of the operation of any innovation hub located within a city of the metropolitan class that is located within two miles of a major airport;</para><para>(6) Create and maintain a community advisory committee consisting of nine members that include (a) at least two owners of residential property located within the inland port district, (b) at least two owners of businesses located within the inland port district, (c) a member of the city council of such city of the metropolitan class whose city council district is located within the inland port district, (d) a member of the Legislature whose legislative district is located within the inland port district, and (e) a youth representative or someone closely involved with youth in the community. A single member may satisfy more than one qualification described in subdivisions (6)(a) through (e) of this section;</para><para>(7) Within one year after the receipt of grant funds described in section 13-3314, hire a consultant to create a financial pro forma and vision and provide recommendations relating to which innovation district model or blended models should be used by the inland port authority;</para><para>(8) Within three years after the receipt of grant funds described in section 13-3314, contract with or provide grants to developers or landowners to construct twenty single-family homes and a minimum of one hundred fifty new housing units within the inland port district; and</para><para>(9) On or before December 31 of each year, electronically submit a report to the Urban Affairs Committee of the Legislature and the Clerk of the Legislature regarding current, completed, and future projects, how such projects relate to the inland port authority's vision and financial pro forma, and other areas of opportunity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB164, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>