<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3107</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; duties; Department
of Revenue; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) If an application
is approved, the Tax Commissioner shall:</para>
<para>(a) Audit or review audits of the approved eligible sports arena facility
to determine the (i) state sales tax revenue collected by retailers doing
business at such facility on sales at such facility, (ii) state sales tax
revenue collected on primary and secondary box office sales of admissions
to such facility, and (iii) new state sales tax revenue collected by nearby
retailers;</para>
<para>(b) Certify annually the amount of state sales tax revenue and new state
sales tax revenue determined under subdivision (a) of this subsection to the
State Treasurer; and</para>
<para>(c) Determine if more than one facility is eligible for state assistance
from state sales tax revenue collected by the same nearby retailers. If the
Tax Commissioner has made such a determination, the facility that was first
determined to be eligible for state assistance shall be the only facility
eligible to receive such funds.</para>
<para>(2) State sales tax revenue collected by retailers that are doing business
at an eligible sports arena facility and new state sales tax revenue collected
by nearby retailers shall be reported on informational returns developed by
the Department of Revenue and provided to any such retailers by the facility.
The informational returns shall be submitted to the department by the retailer
by the twentieth day of the month
following the month the sales taxes are collected. The Tax Commissioner shall
use the data from the informational returns and sales tax returns of both
such categories of retailers and the sports arena facility to determine the
appropriate amount of state sales tax revenue.</para>
<para>(3) The Department of Revenue may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to carry out the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB210, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>