
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection statutenumber="13-3208" chaptername="Cities Counties and Other Political Subdivisions" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3208</statuteno><catchline>Loss reserve fund; created; funding; use.</catchline><para>(1) A municipality that has created a clean energy assessment district shall create a loss reserve fund for:</para><para>(a) The payment of any delinquent annual assessments for qualifying property that is single-family residential property in the event that there is a sale pursuant to a foreclosure or a sale pursuant to the exercise of a power of sale under a trust deed of such qualifying property and the proceeds resulting from such a sale are, after all superior liens have been satisfied, insufficient to pay the delinquent annual assessments. Payments from the loss reserve fund under this subdivision may only be made with respect to delinquent annual assessments imposed upon qualifying property that is single-family residential property, with no more than one such payment to be made for the same qualifying property; and</para><para>(b) The payment of annual assessments imposed upon qualifying property that is single-family residential property subsequent to a sale pursuant to a foreclosure or a sale pursuant to the exercise of a power of sale under a trust deed in which the mortgagee or beneficiary becomes the owner of such qualifying property. Payments from the loss reserve fund under this subdivision may only be made with respect to annual assessments imposed upon qualifying property that is single-family residential property subsequent to the date on which the mortgagee or beneficiary became the owner of such qualifying property and until the qualifying property is conveyed by the mortgagee or beneficiary, with no more than one such payment to be made for the same qualifying property.</para><para>(2) The loss reserve fund may be funded by state and federal sources, the proceeds of bonds issued pursuant to the Property Assessed Clean Energy Act, third-party capital, and participating property owners. The loss reserve fund shall only be used to provide payment of annual assessments as provided in this section and for the costs of administering the loss reserve fund.</para><para>(3) The loss reserve fund shall not be funded by, and payment of annual assessments and costs of administering the loss reserve fund shall not be made from, the general fund of any municipality.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1012, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2016, &#167; 18-3208; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB625, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>