
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, And Other Political Subdivisions" id="id19" statutenumber="13-3107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3107</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Tax Commissioner;
duties; Department of Revenue; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1)
If an application is approved, the Tax Commissioner shall:</para>
<para>(a) Audit or review audits of the approved eligible sports
arena facility to determine the (i) state sales tax revenue collected by retailers
doing business at such facility on sales at such facility, (ii) state sales
tax revenue collected on primary and secondary box office sales of admissions
to such facility, and (iii) new state sales tax revenue collected by nearby
retailers;</para>
<para>(b) Certify annually the amount of state sales tax revenue
and new state sales tax revenue determined under subdivision (a) of this subsection
to the  Legislature; and</para>
<para>(c) Determine if more than one facility is eligible for state
assistance from state sales tax revenue collected by the same nearby retailers.
If the Tax Commissioner has made such a determination, the facility that was
first determined to be eligible for state assistance shall be the only facility
eligible to receive such funds.</para>
<para>(2) State sales tax revenue collected by retailers that are
doing business at an eligible sports arena facility and new state sales tax
revenue collected by nearby retailers shall be reported on informational returns
developed by the Department of Revenue and provided to any such retailers
by the facility. The informational returns shall be submitted to the department
by the retailer by the twentieth day of the month following the month the
sales taxes are collected. The Tax Commissioner shall use the data from the
informational returns and sales tax returns of both such categories of retailers
and the sports arena facility for purposes of the Sports Arena Facility
Financing Assistance Act.</para>
<para>(3) On or before
April 1, 2014, the Tax Commissioner shall certify to the State Treasurer,
for each eligible sports arena facility for which state assistance has been
approved, the total amount of state sales tax revenue and new state sales
tax revenue described in subdivisions (1)(a)(i) through (iii) of this section
that was collected from July 1, 2013, through December 31, 2013. The certified
amount shall be used for purposes of making the transfer required under subdivision
(2)(a) of section 13-3108 and making the distribution of state assistance
described in subsection (4) of section 13-3108.</para><para>(4) Beginning in 2014,
the Tax Commissioner shall use data from the informational returns and sales
tax returns described in subsection (2) of this section to certify quarterly,
for each eligible sports arena facility for which state assistance has been
approved, the total amount of state sales tax revenue and new state sales
tax revenue described in subdivisions (1)(a)(i) through (iii) of this section
that was collected in the preceding calendar quarter. The Tax Commissioner
shall certify such amount to the State Treasurer within sixty days after the
end of each calendar quarter, and such certification shall be used for purposes
of making the transfers required under subdivision (2)(b) of section 13-3108
and making the quarterly distributions of state assistance described in subsection
(5) of section 13-3108.</para><para>(5) The
Department of Revenue may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry
out the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB210, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB867, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>