<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id802"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3304.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3304.01</statuteno><catchline>Inland port authority; creation by nonprofit economic development corporation; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) In the event that a city, a city and one or more counties, or a county, as such are described in subsections (1), (2), and (3) of section 13-3304, has or have not proposed to create an inland port authority as provided in such section, a nonprofit economic development corporation which serves such city, such city and one or more counties, or such county may propose to create an inland port authority using the criteria in subsection (1), (2), or (3) of section 13-3304, whichever is applicable, by submitting an application to the Department of Economic Development.</para><para>(2) Following the submission of an application from a nonprofit economic development corporation proposing the creation of an inland port authority, the Department of Economic Development shall evaluate the proposed inland port authority to determine whether the proposal meets the criteria in subsection (1), (2), or (3) of section 13-3304, whichever is applicable, as well as any prioritization criteria developed by the department. Upon a determination that the proposed inland port authority sufficiently meets such criteria, the Director of Economic Development shall certify to the nonprofit economic development corporation and the city clerk or county clerk or clerks whether the proposed creation of such inland port authority exceeds the cap on the total number of inland port districts pursuant to subsection (4) of section 13-3304. If the proposed inland port authority sufficiently meets such criteria and does not exceed such cap, such city, such city and one or more counties, or such county shall create an inland port authority pursuant to subsection (1), (2), or (3) of section 13-3304, whichever is applicable, based on the criteria utilized by the nonprofit economic development corporation pursuant to subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB998, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>