<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<sectno id="id41" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id42" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="13-3102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3102</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the
Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act:</para>
<para>(1) Board means
a board consisting of the Governor, the State Treasurer, the chairperson of
the Nebraska Investment Council, the chairperson of the Nebraska State Board
of Public Accountancy, and a professor of economics on the faculty of a state
postsecondary educational institution appointed to a two-year term on the
board by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education. For administrative
and budget purposes only, the board shall be considered part of the Department
of Revenue;</para><para>(2) Bond means a general obligation bond, redevelopment bond, lease-purchase
bond, revenue bond, or combination of any such bonds;</para><para>(3) Eligible sports arena
facility means:</para><para>(a)
Any publicly owned, enclosed, and temperature-controlled building primarily
used for sports that has a permanent seating capacity of at least three thousand
but no more than seven thousand seats and in which initial occupancy occurs
on or after July 1, 2010. Eligible sports arena facility includes stadiums,
arenas, dressing and locker facilities, concession areas, parking facilities,
and onsite administrative offices connected with operating the facilities;
and</para><para>(b)
Any racetrack enclosure licensed by the State Racing Commission in which initial
occupancy occurs on or after July 1, 2010, including concession areas, parking
facilities, and onsite administrative offices connected with operating the
racetrack;</para><para>(4) General obligation bond means any bond or refunding bond issued
by a political subdivision and which is payable from the proceeds of an ad
valorem tax;</para><para>(5) Increase in state sales tax revenue means the amount of state
sales tax revenue collected by a nearby retailer during the fiscal year for
which state assistance is calculated minus the amount of state sales tax revenue
collected by the nearby retailer in the fiscal year that ended immediately
preceding the date of occupancy of the eligible sports arena facility, except
that the amount of state sales tax revenue of a nearby retailer shall not
be less than zero;</para><para>(6) Nearby retailer means a retailer as defined in section 77-2701.32
that is located within six hundred yards of an eligible sports arena facility,
measured from the facility but not from any parking facility or other structure.
The term includes a subsequent owner of a nearby retailer operating at the
same location;</para><para>(7) New state sales tax revenue means:</para><para>(a) For nearby retailers
that commenced collecting state sales tax during the period of time beginning
twenty-four months prior to occupancy of the eligible sports arena facility
and ending twenty-four months after the occupancy of the eligible sports arena
facility, one hundred percent of the state sales tax revenue collected by
the nearby retailer and sourced under sections 77-2703.01 to 77-2703.04 to
a location within six hundred yards of the eligible sports arena facility;
and</para><para>(b) For nearby retailers that commenced collecting state sales tax
prior to twenty-four months prior to occupancy of the eligible sports arena
facility, the increase in state sales tax revenue collected by the nearby
retailer and sourced under sections 77-2703.01 to 77-2703.04 to a location
within six hundred yards of the facility;</para><para>(8) Political subdivision means any city,
village, or county; and</para><para>(9) Revenue bond means any bond or refunding bond issued by a political
subdivision which is limited or special rather than a general obligation bond
of the political subdivision and which is not payable from the proceeds of
an ad valorem tax.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>