<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" id="id00" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="13-3207" chaptername="Cities Counties and Other Political Subdivisions"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3207</statuteno><catchline>Municipality; raise capital; sources; bonds; issuance; statutory lien; vote; when required.</catchline><para>(1) A municipality may raise capital to finance energy projects undertaken pursuant to an assessment contract entered into under the Property Assessed Clean Energy Act. Such capital may come from any of the following:</para><para>(a) The sale of bonds;</para><para>(b) Amounts to be advanced by the municipality through funds available to it from any other source; or</para><para>(c) Third-party lending.</para><para>(2) Bonds issued under subsection (1) of this section shall not be general obligations of the municipality, shall be nonrecourse, and shall not be backed by the full faith and credit of the issuer, the municipality, or the state, but shall only be secured by payments of annual assessments by owners of qualifying property within the clean energy assessment district or districts specified who are subject to an assessment contract under section 13-3205.</para><para>(3) Any single bond issuance by a municipality for purposes of the Property Assessed Clean Energy Act shall not exceed five million dollars without a vote of the registered voters of such municipality.</para><para>(4) A pledge of annual assessments, funds, or contractual rights made in connection with the issuance of bonds by a municipality constitutes a statutory lien on the annual assessments, funds, or contractual rights so pledged in favor of the person or persons to whom the pledge is given without further action by the municipality. The statutory lien is valid and binding against all other persons, with or without notice.</para><para>(5) Bonds of one series issued under the Property Assessed Clean Energy Act may be secured on a parity with bonds of another series issued by the municipality pursuant to the terms of a master indenture or master resolution entered into or adopted by the municipality.</para><para>(6) Bonds issued under the act, and interest payable on such bonds, are exempt from all taxation by this state and its political subdivisions.</para><para>(7) Bonds issued under the act further essential public and governmental purposes, including, but not limited to, reduced energy costs, reduced greenhouse gas emissions, economic stimulation and development, improved property valuation, and increased employment.</para><para>(8) The Property Assessed Clean Energy Act shall not be used to finance an energy project on qualifying property owned by a municipality or any other political subdivision of the State of Nebraska without having first been approved by a vote of the registered voters of such municipality or political subdivision owning the qualifying property. Such vote shall be taken at a special election called for such purpose or at an election held in conjunction with a statewide or local primary or general election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1012, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2016, &#167; 18-3207; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB625, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>April 28, 2017</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>