<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id744"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3405"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3405</statuteno><catchline>Property tax request authority; election to exceed; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A political subdivision may increase its property tax request authority over the amount determined under section 13-3403 if such increase is approved by a majority of legal voters voting on the issue at an election described in subsection (2) of this section. Such issue shall be placed on the ballot (a) upon the recommendation of the governing body of such political subdivision or (b) upon the receipt by the county clerk or election commissioner of a petition requesting such issue to be placed on the ballot which is signed by at least five percent of the legal voters of the political subdivision. The recommendation of the governing body or the petition of the legal voters shall include the amount by which the political subdivision would increase its property tax request authority over and above the amount determined under section 13-3403.</para><para>(2) Upon receipt of such recommendation or legal voter petition, the county clerk or election commissioner shall place such issue on the ballot at the next regularly scheduled election or a special election called for such purpose and held on the first Tuesday after the second Monday in May of an odd-numbered year. The election shall be held pursuant to the Election Act, and all costs shall be paid by the political subdivision. The issue may be approved on the same question as a vote to exceed the levy limits provided in section 77-3444. If a majority of the votes cast on the issue are in favor of increasing the political subdivision's property tax request authority, the political subdivision shall be empowered to do so.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB34, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>