<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id100">
<sectno id="id101" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 15.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id102" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="13-3109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3109</statuteno><catchline>Bonds and refunding bonds; issuance;
procedure; security; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) The applicant political subdivision may issue from time
to time its bonds and refunding bonds to finance and refinance the acquisition,
construction, improving, and equipping of eligible sports arena facilities.
The bonds may be sold by the applicant in such manner and for such price as
the applicant determines, at a discount, at par, or at a premium, at private
negotiated sale or at public sale, after notice published prior to the sale
in a legal newspaper having general circulation in the political subdivision
or in such other medium of publication as the applicant deems appropriate.
The bonds shall have a stated maturity of twenty years or less and shall bear
interest at such rate or rates and otherwise be issued in accordance with
the respective procedures and with such other terms and provisions as are
established, permitted, or authorized by applicable state laws and home rule
charters for the type of bonds to be issued. Such bonds may be secured as
to payment in whole or in part by a pledge, as shall be determined by the
applicant, from the income, proceeds, and revenue of the eligible sports arena
facilities financed with proceeds of such bonds, from the income, proceeds,
and revenue of any of its eligible sports arena facilities, or from its revenue
and income, including its sales, use, or occupation tax revenue, fees, or
receipts, as may be determined by the applicant. The applicant may further
secure the bonds by a mortgage or deed of trust encumbering all or any portion
of the eligible sports arena facilities and by a bond insurance policy or
other credit support facility. No general obligation bonds, except refunding
bonds, shall be issued until authorized by greater than fifty percent of the
applicant's electors voting on the question as to their issuance at any election
as defined in section 32-108. The face of the bonds shall plainly state that
the bonds and the interest thereon shall not constitute nor give rise to an
indebtedness, obligation, or pecuniary liability of the state nor a charge
against the general credit, revenue, or taxing power of the state. Bonds of
the applicant are declared to be issued for an essential public and governmental
purpose and, together with interest thereon and income therefrom, shall be
exempt from all state income taxes.</para>
<para>(2) All payments
to political subdivisions under the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance
Act are made subject to specific appropriation for such purpose.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167;  15.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>