<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id48">
<sectno id="id49">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id50" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="13-3005"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3005</statuteno><catchline>City of first class and county sheriff;
adopt rules and regulations governing peace officer removal, suspension, or
demotion.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as otherwise provided in a collective-bargaining agreement, Chapter
19, article 18, or Chapter 23, article 17, any city of the first class and
all county sheriffs shall adopt rules and regulations governing the removal,
suspension with or without pay, or demotion of any peace officer, including
the chief of police. Such rules and regulations shall include: (a) Provisions
for giving notice and a copy of the written accusation to the peace officer;
(b) the peace officer's right to have an attorney or representative retained
by the peace officer present with him or her at all hearings or proceedings
regarding the written accusation; (c) the right of the peace officer or his
or her attorney or representative retained by the peace officer to be heard
and present evidence; (d) the right of the peace officer as well as the individual
imposing the action or their respective attorneys or representatives to record
all hearings or proceedings regarding the written accusation; and (e) a procedure
for making application for an appeal. Nothing in this section shall be construed
to prevent the preemptory suspension or immediate removal from duty of an
officer by the appropriate authority, pending the hearing authorized by this
section, in cases of gross misconduct, neglect of duty, or disobedience of
orders.</para>
<para>(2) This section
does not apply to a peace officer during his or her probationary period.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB158, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>