<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3305</statuteno><catchline>Designation of area; criteria; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The city council of any city which has created an inland port authority pursuant to subsection (1) of section 13-3304 shall designate what areas within the corporate limits, extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction, or both of the city shall comprise the inland port district, subject to the limitations of the Municipal Inland Port Authority Act. The boundaries of any inland port district shall be filed with the city clerk and shall become effective upon approval of the city council. The city council may from time to time enlarge or reduce the area comprising any inland port district, except that such district shall not be reduced to an area less than three hundred acres. Any change of boundaries shall be filed with the city clerk and become effective upon such filing.</para><para>(2) The city council of any city and county board or boards of any county or counties which have created an inland port authority pursuant to subsection (2) of section 13-3304 shall designate what areas within the corporate limits, extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction, or both of the city or within the county or counties shall comprise the inland port district, subject to the limitations of the Municipal Inland Port Authority Act. The boundaries of any inland port district shall be filed with the city clerk and the county clerk or clerks and shall become effective upon approval of the city council and the county board or boards. The city council and the county board or boards may from time to time enlarge or reduce the area comprising any inland port district, except that such district shall not be reduced to an area less than three hundred acres. Any change of boundaries shall be filed with the city clerk and the county clerk or clerks and become effective upon such filing.</para><para>(3) The county board of any county which has created an inland port authority pursuant to subsection (3) of section 13-3304 shall designate what areas within the county shall comprise the inland port district, subject to the limitations of the Municipal Inland Port Authority Act. The boundaries of any inland port district shall be filed with the county clerk and shall become effective upon approval of the county board. The county board may from time to time enlarge or reduce the area comprising any inland port district, except that such district shall not be reduced to an area less than three hundred acres. Any change of boundaries shall be filed with the county clerk and become effective upon such filing.</para><para>(4) Not more than twenty-five percent of the area within an inland port district designated pursuant to this section may be noncontiguous with the remaining portions of such inland port district. Such noncontiguous area shall be no more than one-quarter mile from the remaining portions of such inland port district for an inland port district located within a city of the metropolitan class and no more than fifteen miles from the remaining portions of such inland port district for any other inland port district.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall require that any real property located within the boundaries of an inland port district be owned by an inland port authority or the city or county or counties in which such real property is located.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB156, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB998, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB164, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>