<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id934"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3304</statuteno><catchline>Inland port authority; creation; limitation; criteria; certification; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any city which encompasses an area greater than three hundred acres eligible to be designated as an inland port district may propose to create an inland port authority by ordinance, subject to the cap on the total number of inland port districts provided in subsection (4) of this section. In determining whether to propose the creation of an inland port authority, the city shall consider the following criteria:</para><para>(a) The desirability and economic feasibility of locating an inland port district within the corporate boundaries, extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction, or both of the city;</para><para>(b) The technical and economic capability of the city and any other public and private entities to plan and carry out development within the proposed inland port district;</para><para>(c) The strategic location of the proposed inland port district in proximity to existing and potential transportation infrastructure that is conducive to facilitating regional, national, and international trade and the businesses and facilities that promote and complement such trade;</para><para>(d) The potential impact that development of the proposed inland port district will have on the immediate area; and</para><para>(e) The regional and statewide economic impact of development of the proposed inland port district.</para><para>(2) Any city and one or more counties in which a city of the metropolitan class, city of the primary class, or city of the first class is located, or in which the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of such city is located, which encompass an area greater than three hundred acres eligible to be designated as an inland port district may enter into an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act to propose joint creation of an inland port authority, subject to the cap on the total number of inland port districts provided in subsection (4) of this section. In determining whether to propose the creation of an inland port authority, the city and counties shall consider the following criteria:</para><para>(a) The desirability and economic feasibility of locating an inland port district within the corporate boundaries or extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction or both of the city, or within both the corporate boundaries or extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction or both of a city and the boundaries of one or more counties;</para><para>(b) The technical and economic capability of the city and county or counties and any other public and private entities to plan and carry out development within the proposed inland port district;</para><para>(c) The strategic location of the proposed inland port district in proximity to existing and potential transportation infrastructure that is conducive to facilitating regional, national, and international trade and the businesses and facilities that promote and complement such trade;</para><para>(d) The potential impact that development of the proposed inland port district will have on the immediate area; and</para><para>(e) The regional and statewide economic impact of development of the proposed inland port district.</para><para>(3) Any county with a population greater than twenty thousand inhabitants according to the most recent federal census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census which encompasses an area greater than three hundred acres eligible to be designated as an inland port district may propose to create an inland port authority by resolution, subject to the cap on the total number of inland port districts provided in subsection (4) of this section. In determining whether to propose the creation of an inland port authority, the county shall consider the following criteria:</para><para>(a) The desirability and economic feasibility of locating an inland port district within the county;</para><para>(b) The technical and economic capability of the county and any other public or private entities to plan and carry out development within the proposed inland port district;</para><para>(c) The strategic location of the proposed inland port district in proximity to existing and potential transportation infrastructure that is conducive to facilitating regional, national, and international trade and the businesses and facilities that promote and complement such trade;</para><para>(d) The potential impact that development of the proposed inland port district will have on the immediate area; and</para><para>(e) The regional and statewide economic impact of development of the proposed inland port district.</para><para>(4) No more than five inland port districts may be designated statewide. No inland port authority shall designate more than one inland port district, and no inland port authority may be created without also designating an inland port district.</para><para>(5) Following the adoption of an ordinance, resolution, or execution of an agreement pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act proposing creation of an inland port authority, the city clerk or county clerk shall transmit a copy of such ordinance, resolution, or agreement to the Department of Economic Development. Upon receipt of such ordinance, resolution, or agreement, the department shall evaluate the proposed inland port authority to determine whether the proposal meets the criteria in subsection (1), (2), or (3) of this section, whichever is applicable. Upon a determination that the proposed inland port authority sufficiently meets such criteria, the Director of Economic Development shall certify to the city clerk or county clerk whether the proposed creation of such inland port authority exceeds the cap on the total number of inland port districts pursuant to subsection (4) of this section. If the proposed inland port authority sufficiently meets such criteria and does not exceed such cap, the inland port authority shall be deemed created. If the proposed inland port authority does not sufficiently meet such criteria or exceeds such cap, the city shall repeal such ordinance, the county shall repeal such resolution, or the city and county or counties shall rescind such agreement and the proposed inland port authority shall not be created.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB156, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>August 28, 2021</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>