<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3310"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3310</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; appointment; term; vacancy, how filled.</catchline><para>(1) An inland port authority shall be administered by the board which shall consist of:</para><para>(a) If created by a city of the metropolitan class, nine members that include (i) the mayor or the mayor's designee, (ii) at least two members with experience in large-scale residential, commercial, industrial, or general real estate development, (iii) at least one member with experience in community organizing and development, advocating for inclusive economic development strategies, addressing systemic barriers, and promoting equitable opportunities for all community members, and (iv) at least one member with experience in financial services and budget oversight, financial planning, and ensuring accountability in resource allocation for economic development projects. A single member may satisfy more than one qualification described in subdivisions (1)(a)(i) through (iv) of this section;</para><para>(b) If created by a city of the primary class, seven members;</para><para>(c) If created by a city of the first class, five members;</para><para>(d) If jointly created by a city of the metropolitan class and one or more counties, eleven members;</para><para>(e) If jointly created by a city of the primary class and one or more counties, nine members;</para><para>(f) If jointly created by a city of the first class and one or more counties, seven members; or</para><para>(g) If created by a county, nine members.</para><para>(2) Upon the creation of an inland port authority under subsection (1) or (2) of section 13-3304, the mayor of the city that created the authority, with the approval of the city council, and, if the authority is created under subsection (2) of section 13-3304, with the approval of the county board or boards, shall appoint a board to govern the authority. Members of the board shall be residents of the city or of the county in which such city that created the authority under subsection (1) of section 13-3304 is located, or, if the authority is created under subsection (2) of section 13-3304, members of the board shall be residents of the county or counties jointly creating such authority or of any county located adjacent to any such county.</para><para>(3) Upon the creation of an inland port authority under subsection (3) of section 13-3304, the chairperson of the county board, with the approval of the county board, shall appoint a board to govern the authority. Members of the board shall be residents of the county or of any county located adjacent to such county.</para><para>(4) The members of the board of any inland port authority created under section 13-3304 shall be appointed to staggered terms of four years in such a manner to ensure that the terms of no more than three members expire in any one year.</para><para>(5) Any vacancy on the board of an inland port authority shall be filled in the same manner as the vacating board member was appointed to serve the unexpired portion of the board member's term.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB156, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB164, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>