<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id386"><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities, Counties, and Other Political Subdivisions" statutenumber="13-3311"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3311</statuteno><catchline>Commissioner; employee; eligibility to serve; acts prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) No individual may serve as a commissioner or an employee of an inland port authority if:</para><para>(a) The individual or a family member of the individual owns an interest in any real property located within the boundaries of the inland port district; or</para><para>(b) The individual or a family member of the individual owns an interest in, is directly affiliated with, or is an employee or officer of a private firm, company, or other entity that the individual reasonably believes is likely to:</para><para>(i) Participate in or receive a direct financial benefit from the development of the inland port district; or</para><para>(ii) Acquire an interest in any facility located within the inland port district.</para><para>(2) Before taking office as a commissioner or accepting employment with an inland port authority, an individual shall submit to the authority a statement verifying that the individual's service as a commissioner or an employee will not violate subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) An individual shall not, at any time during the individual's service as a commissioner or an employee of an inland port authority, acquire or take any action to initiate, negotiate, or otherwise arrange for the acquisition of an interest in any real property located within the boundaries of the inland port district.</para><para>(4) A commissioner or an employee of an inland port authority shall not receive a direct financial benefit from the development of any real property located within the boundaries of the inland port district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB156, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>