<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Counties and Other Political Subdivisions" id="id00" statutenumber="13-3202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>13-3202</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(1) Energy efficiency and the use of renewable energy are important for preserving the health and economic well-being of Nebraska’s citizens. Using less energy decreases the cost of living and keeps the cost of public power low by delaying the need for additional power plants. By building the market for energy efficiency and renewable energy products, economic development will be encouraged and new jobs will be created for Nebraskans in the energy efficiency and renewable energy job sectors;</para><para>(2) To further these goals, the state should promote energy efficiency improvements and renewable energy systems;</para><para>(3) The upfront costs for energy efficiency improvements and renewable energy systems prohibit many property owners from making improvements. Therefore, it is necessary to authorize municipalities to implement an alternative financing method through the creation of clean energy assessment districts; and</para><para>(4) Public purposes will be served by providing municipalities with the authority to finance the installation of energy efficiency improvements and renewable energy systems through the creation of clean energy assessment districts. Such public purposes include, but are not limited to, reduced energy and water costs, reduced greenhouse gas emissions, economic stimulation and development, improved property valuation, and increased employment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB1012, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2016, &#167; 18-3202; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB625, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB23, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>May 2, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>