<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id6" statutenumber="85-502.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-502.01</statuteno><catchline>Public college or university; veteran; spouse or dependent of veteran; eligible recipient under federal law; person entitled to rehabilitation under federal law; resident student; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) A person who enrolls in a public college or university in this state and who is (a) a veteran as defined in Title 38 of the United States Code and was discharged or released from a period of not fewer than ninety days of service in the active military, naval, air, or space service, (b) a spouse or dependent of such a veteran, or (c) an eligible recipient entitled to (i) educational assistance as provided in 38 U.S.C. 3319 while the transferor is on active duty in the uniformed services, (ii) educational assistance as provided in 38 U.S.C. 3311(b)(8), (iii) rehabilitation as provided in 38 U.S.C. 3102(a), or (iv) educational assistance as provided in 38 U.S.C. 3510, as such sections existed on January 1, 2023, shall be considered a resident student notwithstanding section 85-502 if the person is registered to vote in Nebraska and demonstrates objective evidence of intent to be a resident of Nebraska, except that a person who is under eighteen years of age is not required to register to vote in Nebraska.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, objective evidence of intent to be a resident of Nebraska includes a Nebraska driver's license, a Nebraska state identification card, a Nebraska motor vehicle registration, or documentation that the individual is registered to vote in Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB740, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB109, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB512, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB122, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB669, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 111. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>