<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-1,119"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1,119</statuteno><catchline>Kearney State College; transfer of property, obligations, and employees; collective bargaining.</catchline><para>(1) On July 1, 1991, all property rights, titles, assets, contracts, obligations, and choses in action of any kind existing as of June 30, 1991, owned, held, or controlled by Kearney State College or the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges for the benefit of Kearney State College shall be transferred to, assumed by, and carried out by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska for the operation and benefit of the University of Nebraska at Kearney subject, however, to the following:</para><para>(a)(i) Title to (A) facilities on the campus of Kearney State College and all or any portion of the revenue derived from such facilities which have been pledged to the payment of the principal of and interest on revenue bonds of the board of trustees or (B) facilities on the campus of Kearney State College which have been constructed, repaired, or renovated with the proceeds of revenue bonds payable from student fees shall remain vested in the board of trustees until the bonds outstanding with respect to such facilities have been discharged. Upon the discharge of the bonds outstanding with respect to any such facility, title to such facility shall be transferred to and vested in the Board of Regents without any further or additional action by the board of trustees or the Board of Regents.</para><para>(ii) All facilities specified in subdivision (a)(i) of this subsection shall be leased by the board of trustees to the Board of Regents as of July 1, 1991, upon such terms and conditions as the board of trustees and the Board of Regents shall determine, except that (A) payments from the Board of Regents to the board of trustees pursuant to such leases shall be sufficient to pay the principal of and interest on the bonds outstanding with respect to such facilities and shall include a reasonable fee set by and paid to the board of trustees to cover actual and necessary expenses incurred by the board of trustees for managing the bond program of the University of Nebraska at Kearney until all bonds which are outstanding as of July 1, 1991, and which were issued with respect to the leased facilities have matured and are retired, (B) the Board of Regents shall have the right to establish rents, charges, rates, and fees for the use of such facilities and to receive and collect all revenue, rents, fees, income, profits, and charges of whatever nature and howsoever derived from such facility, and (C) the Board of Regents shall keep, perform, satisfy, and comply with all terms, covenants, conditions, and agreements contained in the documents relating to the issuance of the bonds outstanding with respect to each such facility;</para><para>(b) The obligations for the payment of money of the board of trustees incurred pursuant to Laws 1983, LB 410, Laws 1987, LB 218, and Laws 1987, LB 784, shall remain the obligations of the board of trustees. All other obligations of the board of trustees incurred pursuant to such laws shall, upon July 1, 1991, be and become obligations of the Board of Regents. Unless title to the property acquired and the facilities constructed, repaired, remodeled, or renovated pursuant to such laws is required to remain vested with the board of trustees pursuant to subdivision (a)(i) of this subsection, title to such property and facilities shall vest in the Board of Regents on July 1, 1991; and</para><para>(c) Prior to July 1, 1991, the board of trustees and the Board of Regents shall enter into such agreements as they deem necessary and appropriate to carry out the provisions of sections 85-1,119 to 85-1,123 for the conveyance and transfer of the properties, rights, and obligations provided under such sections, to make appropriate provisions with respect to existing debt obligations, including revenue bonds, of the board of trustees and the Nebraska State Colleges Facilities Corporation pertaining to Kearney State College, and to provide for an orderly transition and assumption by the Board of Regents of the activities and operations of Kearney State College. The board of trustees, acting as a corporation for the revenue bond program for Kearney State College or the Nebraska State College Facilities Corporation, and its officers and staff shall be reimbursed for any expenses incurred in carrying out any action modifying the revenue bond program pursuant to sections 85-1,119 to 85-1,123.</para><para>(2)(a) On July 1, 1991, all employees of Kearney State College shall be transferred to the University of Nebraska. The transferred employees shall retain all benefits and status of employment accrued through June 30, 1991, including retirement benefits not vested.</para><para>(b) On July 1, 1991, the transferred employees, except academic, faculty, and teaching employees who are included in a collective-bargaining unit and represented by a certified collective-bargaining agent, shall cease participation in the employee fringe benefit programs of Kearney State College and shall begin participation in the University of Nebraska systemwide fringe benefits program and be entitled to receive the same fringe benefits of employment made available to other employees of the University of Nebraska under such program.</para><para>(c) On July 1, 1990, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska shall have authority to enter into a collective-bargaining agreement with any certified collective-bargaining agent for academic, faculty, and teaching employees of Kearney State College who are represented by a certified collective-bargaining agent covering any period beginning on or after July 1, 1991. The Board of Regents shall bargain and negotiate in good faith with any such bargaining agent pursuant to the State Employees Collective Bargaining Act. On July 1, 1991, all academic, faculty, and teaching employees of the University of Nebraska at Kearney shall cease participation in the retirement program of Kearney State College and shall begin participation in the systemwide retirement program of the University of Nebraska on the same basis as other academic, faculty, and teaching employees of the University of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 247, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 68, &#167; 9. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Employees Collective Bargaining Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1369.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Since five judges of the court do not hold that this section is unconstitutional, the section is constitutional. State ex rel. Spire v. Beermann, 235 Neb. 384, 455 N.W.2d 749 (1990).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>