<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id21" statutenumber="85-1,123"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1,123</statuteno><catchline id="id24">University of
Nebraska at Kearney Cash Fund; University of Nebraska at Kearney Trust Fund;
created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created
the University of Nebraska at Kearney Cash Fund. The fund shall consist of
all fees and other money collected from students at the University of Nebraska
at Kearney by authority of the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska
for university purposes, all receipts from all university activities at the
University of Nebraska at Kearney collected in connection with the operation
of such university, and the money and funds received at the time the University
of Nebraska at Kearney was established. A record shall be kept separating
the money and funds into appropriate and convenient accounts. All money and
funds accruing to the fund shall be used for the maintenance
and operation of the University of Nebraska at Kearney and shall at all times
be subject to the orders of the Board of Regents. The fund shall be in the custody of the State Treasurer,
and any money in such fund available for investment shall be invested by the
state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and
the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, except that there may be retained
at the University of Nebraska at Kearney a sum not to exceed two percent of
the fund, which shall be available to make settlement and equitable adjustments
to students entitled thereto, to carry on university activities contributing
to the fund, and to provide for contingencies. No warrant shall
be issued against the fund unless there is money sufficient to pay the same.</para>
<para>(2) There is hereby created the University of Nebraska at
Kearney Trust Fund, which fund shall consist of all property, real or personal,
acquired as of July 1, 1991, or at any time thereafter by or for Kearney State
College by donation or bequest to it, which property shall be held and applied
in the manner and according with the provisions of the will, deed, or instrument
making such donation or bequest. All future donations or bequests to the University
of Nebraska at Kearney shall be a part of such fund. The fund shall be held
and managed in such manner as the Board of Regents shall determine. The holdings
and management shall be in strict accordance with all terms of the donation
or bequest, except that in the absence of any investment instructions, the
funds may be invested by or at the direction of the Board of Regents in such
investments as are authorized for trustees, guardians, personal representatives,
or administrators under the laws of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 247, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 34.</para><effectivedate>May 18, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Since five judges of the court do not hold that this section is unconstitutional, the section is constitutional. State ex rel. Spire v. Beermann, 235 Neb. 384, 455 N.W.2d 749 (1990).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>