<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-403.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-403.01</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature hereby finds and determines: It has been the experience of both the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges that the lack of facilities of the types authorized by section 85-403, to be constructed, purchased, or otherwise acquired, remodeled, repaired, furnished and equipped by such boards, has deterred many individuals from attending the institutions under the control of the boards or added increased burdens upon many individuals in attending such institutions. With the continuation of the trend of more high school graduates enrolling and remaining in the institutions under the control of the boards and the normal population growth of the state, the lack of such facilities may continue to deter many individuals from attending such institutions or may add additional burdens upon those who do attend. The powers granted to both boards under sections 85-401 to 85-411, and the exercise by the boards of such powers, are for educational purposes, being not only directly related to the carrying out by the boards of their functions in supplying higher education but in fact necessary to the carrying out of such functions to the greatest possible benefit of the people of the state. In connection with certain grants or contributions to the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, that board heretofore has been created a public corporation for educational purposes. It is necessary, advisable and desirable that its status as a public corporation organized for educational purposes specifically include the exercise by it of the powers granted to it under sections 85-401 to 85-411 and that the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges also be created a public corporation organized for educational purposes for the exercise of the powers granted to it under such sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 845, &#167; 1, p. 3183. </para></source></law></legaldoc>