<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>85-301</statuteno><catchline>State colleges; official names; board of trustees; appointment; expenses.</catchline><para>The existing institutions known as the state colleges located at Chadron, Peru, and Wayne shall hereafter be known and designated as Chadron State College, Peru State College, and Wayne State College, respectively. The general government thereof shall be vested, under the direction of the Legislature, in a board of seven members, to be known as the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, six of whom shall be appointed by the Governor, with the advice and consent of the Legislature, two each for terms of two, four, and six years and two each biennium thereafter for terms of six years, and the Commissioner of Education shall be a member ex officio. The duties and powers of the board shall be prescribed by law, and the members thereof shall receive no compensation for the performance of their duties but may be reimbursed for actual expenses incurred therein.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 78, sub. XIII, &#167; 1, p. 372; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7057; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 67, &#167; 1, p. 257; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6692; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-301; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 96, &#167; 25, p. 402; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 180, &#167; 13, p. 708; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 85-301; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-301; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 315, &#167; 1, p. 1035; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 542, &#167; 1, p. 1689; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 852, &#167; 2, p. 3200; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 247, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 138; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB887, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Terms of office are established for members of board. State ex rel. Johnson v. Hagemeister, 161 Neb. 475, 73 N.W.2d 625 (1955).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>