<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-931"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-931</statuteno><catchline>Graduate degree programs, defined.</catchline><para>Graduate degree programs shall mean those programs for which the following degrees are awarded:</para><para>(1) First professional degree being the first earned degree in the following fields: (a) Dentistry; (b) medicine, general; (c) optometry; (d) osteopathic medicine; (e) pharmacy; (f) podiatry; (g) veterinary medicine; (h) chiropractic; (i) law, general; (j) theology, general; and (k) architecture, general;</para><para>(2) Master's degree being the earned degree carrying the title Master. The master's degree is the first advanced graduate degree conferred in professional programs and general academic and occupational programs.</para><para>Master's degree professional programs include but are not limited to: (a) Engineering; (b) education; (c) allied health professions; (d) nursing; (e) architecture, specialties; (f) community and regional planning; (g) dentistry; (h) medicine, specialties; (i) optometry; (j) osteopathic medicine; (k) pharmacy; (l) podiatry; (m) social work; (n) veterinary medicine; (o) chiropractic; (p) law, specialties; and (q) theology, specialties.</para><para>Master's degree programs in general academic and occupational areas include but are not limited to: (a) Mathematics; (b) languages; (c) biological and physical sciences; (d) letters; (e) fine arts; (f) social sciences; (g) agriculture and natural resources; (h) communications; (i) business and management; (j) computer and information sciences; (k) home economics; and (l) fine and applied arts; and</para><para>(3) Doctoral degree being an earned academic degree conveying the title of Doctor. Doctoral degrees include but are not limited to: Doctor of Philosophy; Doctor of Education; and Doctor of Arts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 756, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>