
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-9,178"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-9,178</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings and intent.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Legislature finds that the State of Nebraska has a compelling
interest to provide access to the University of Nebraska, the state colleges,
and the community colleges for students from diverse backgrounds who
often find that the financial requirements of postsecondary education are
a major obstacle. The Legislature further finds that the State of Nebraska
has a compelling interest in attaining greater diversity in the makeup
of the student bodies at the University of Nebraska, the state colleges, and
the community colleges because of the educational benefits that a diverse
educational environment will produce for all students attending the University
of Nebraska, the state colleges, and the community colleges.</para>
<para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature:</para>
<para>(a) To appropriate funds to support a student diversity scholarship program for the purpose of developing
more diverse student bodies at the state's public postsecondary
educational institutions;</para>
<para>(b) That the student diversity scholarship program be designed and implemented
so as to achieve a greater diversity in student populations in fulfillment
of the compelling interest found by the Legislature pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section; and</para>
<para>(c) That all funds appropriated by the Legislature for student diversity
scholarships at the University of Nebraska, the state colleges, and the community
colleges shall be used in coordination with private donations for such scholarships
and in consultation with the major donors thereof and in coordination with
federal grant funds available to students at the University of Nebraska, the
state colleges, and the community colleges so as to maximize the level of
benefits and accomplish the purposes of the Student Diversity Scholarship
Program Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1379, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB440, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>