<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id665"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-608"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>85-608</statuteno><catchline>Report; contents; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) On or before September 15, 2021, and September 15 of each odd-numbered year thereafter, each public postsecondary institution shall electronically submit a report regarding sexual harassment and Title IX compliance to the Clerk of the Legislature and the Education Committee of the Legislature. The report shall include:</para><para>(a) Results of any campus climate survey related to sexual harassment;</para><para>(b) Information related to the training provided to Title IX coordinators, investigators, and decisionmakers regarding sexual harassment;</para><para>(c) Any policies, initiatives, or grievance procedures the postsecondary institution has adopted to address sexual harassment;</para><para>(d) Information on where the postsecondary institution's students and employees may receive immediate emergency assistance to address instances of sexual harassment;</para><para>(e) Information on how the postsecondary institution's students and employees may report concerns of sexual harassment to the postsecondary institution;</para><para>(f) Information on resources, programs, and support available to the postsecondary institution's students and employees to address concerns of sexual harassment;</para><para>(g) Information on any of the postsecondary institution's student or employee-led organizations engaged in supporting victims of sexual harassment; and</para><para>(h) Any agreement between the postsecondary institution and a local law enforcement agency or the county attorney related to addressing instances of sexual harassment.</para><para>(2) The report shall not include any personally identifiable information, information that is subject to a privilege arising under state or federal law, or records that may be withheld from disclosure under section 84-712.05.</para><para>(3) On or before December 15, 2021, and on or before December 15 of each odd-numbered year thereafter, the Education Committee of the Legislature shall hold a public hearing to review all reports submitted under this section.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Postsecondary institution has the same meaning as in section 85-2403;</para><para>(b) Sexual harassment means conduct that satisfies one or more of the following:</para><para>(i) An employee conditioning the provision of an aid, benefit, or service on an individual's participation in unwelcome sexual conduct;</para><para>(ii) Unwelcome conduct on the basis of sex determined by a reasonable person to be so severe, pervasive, and objectively offensive that it effectively denies a person equal access to the education program or activity;</para><para>(iii) Sexual assault as defined in 20 U.S.C. 1092(f)(6)(A)(v);</para><para>(iv) Dating violence as defined in 34 U.S.C. 12291(a)(10);</para><para>(v) Domestic violence as defined in 34 U.S.C. 12291(a)(8); or</para><para>(vi) Stalking as defined in 34 U.S.C. 12291(a)(30); and</para><para>(c) Title IX means Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972, Public Law 92-318, 20 U.S.C. 1681 to 1688, and its accompanying regulations and guidance documents, as amended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB534, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>