<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-125</statuteno><catchline>University Cash Fund; source; use.</catchline><para>The University Cash Fund shall consist of the matriculation and diploma fees, registration fees, laboratory fees, tuition fees, summer session or school fees, all other money or fees collected from students by the authority of the Board of Regents for university purposes, and receipts from all university activities collected by the board in connection with the operation of the university. A record shall be kept by the board separating such money into appropriate and convenient accounts. All money accruing to the University Cash Fund shall become available when appropriated by the Legislature for the use of the university and its activities and shall at all times be subject to the orders of the Board of Regents accordingly. No warrant shall be issued against such fund unless there is money in the hands of the State Treasurer sufficient to pay the same. The board shall cause all money belonging to this fund, which is received by its authority at the university, to be paid over from time to time, as the same is received, to the State Treasurer, to be placed to the credit of this fund, except that the board may retain in its possession a sum, not to exceed four hundred seventy-five thousand dollars, out of which money at least fifty thousand dollars shall be available during the first two weeks of each term to make advances to students who have financial aid in excess of tuition and fees, and the remainder of which money shall be available to make settlement and equitable adjustments with students entitled thereto, to carry on university activities contributing to this fund, and to provide for contingencies. The board may require its secretary, in addition to his or her other duties, to perform all acts necessary to carry into effect the provisions of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 21, p. 177; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 57; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 76, &#167; 1, p. 325; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7103; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6735; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-121; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-125; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 1031; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 623, &#167; 1, p. 2087; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 248, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 151, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Funds herein, not derived from taxation, are considered "appropriated" by section 85-131, and are under direct control of Board of Regents. Board of Regents v. Exon, 199 Neb. 146, 256 N.W.2d 330 (1977).</para><para>Mandatory fees for support of a student newspaper and other activities are public funds for which reasonable supervision by university authorities is required, and their use will not be enjoined except in a clear case. Larson v. Board of Regents, 189 Neb. 688, 204 N.W.2d 568 (1973).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>