<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-324"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-324</statuteno><catchline>State College Facilities Improvement Fund; created; authorized uses.</catchline><para>There is hereby created the State College Facilities Improvement Fund. All money accruing to the fund is hereby appropriated to the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges and shall be used exclusively for those construction projects of the state colleges authorized pursuant to this section. No expenditure may be made from such fund without prior approval by a resolution of the board of trustees.</para><para>The board of trustees may make expenditures from the State College Facilities Improvement Fund for the following projects: (1) Renovation of the T.J. Majors Education Building at Peru State College, two million twenty-five thousand dollars; and (2) renovation of, and construction of an addition to, Cushing Coliseum at Kearney State College, eight million five hundred and ninety-eight thousand ninety-eight dollars. The board of trustees may make additional expenditures for the project listed in subdivision (2) of this section in an amount not to exceed two million two hundred and ninety-five thousand dollars from private sources and non-state-aided institutional sources. The cost for each project listed in this section shall be exclusive of sums previously expended for planning and any administrative costs and financing costs associated with any contract which the board of trustees may enter into pursuant to this section and section 85-325 to implement any of the projects listed in this section.</para><para>The board of trustees may make expenditures for the purposes stated in this section from investment income balances in the State College Facilities Improvement Fund. The board of trustees may make expenditures from such fund in amounts which, in combination with interest accrued on any construction funds and reserve funds created as part of a long-term contract entered into by the board of trustees pursuant to section 85-325, are sufficient to satisfy the financial obligations incurred in such contracts entered into by the board of trustees. Any balance existing in the State College Facilities Improvement Fund, any reserve funds, or any other funds created as part of a long-term contract entered into by the board of trustees pursuant to section 85-325 shall be transferred to the General Fund either on June 15, 1998, or when all financial obligations incurred in the contracts entered into by the board of trustees pursuant to section 85-325 are discharged, whichever occurs first.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 218, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 38, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>