
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id6" statutenumber="85-505.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-505.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Nebraska National Guard; tuition assistance program; limitations; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) The tuition assistance program prescribed in sections 85-505 to 85-508 shall not be available to:</para><para>(a) More than one thousand two hundred members during any fiscal year; and</para><para>(b) Any member who has not exhausted any available federal tuition assistance benefits.</para><para>(2) Only credit-bearing courses which meet program requirements shall be approved for tuition assistance under sections 85-505 to 85-508. Members shall not receive tuition assistance for any noncredit courses.</para><para>(3) If a member of the Nebraska National Guard voluntarily withdraws from a course for which tuition assistance is being received, the member shall be liable for all costs relating to such withdrawal, including, but not limited to, all of the costs billed by the educational institution to the Nebraska National Guard. Reimbursement shall be in accordance with section 72-1601.</para><para>(4) Any member of the Nebraska National Guard who receives tuition assistance shall agree in writing to serve in the Nebraska National Guard for three years after the completion of the courses for which tuition assistance was given. Any member who receives tuition assistance may be asked to reimburse the State of Nebraska if any such member leaves the Nebraska National Guard during such three-year period. Reimbursement shall be in accordance with section 72-1601.</para><para>(5) The Military Department shall retain the responsibility and authority to establish any limitations and controls it deems necessary to ensure maximum fiscal efficiency and productivity of the tuition assistance program prescribed in sections 85-505 to 85-508.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 931, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 436, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 866, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 13, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 286, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB746, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB766, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB450, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB779, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>