<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-328"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>85-328</statuteno><catchline>State College Capital Improvement Fee Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The State College Capital Improvement Fee Fund is created. Revenue credited to the fund shall include amounts generated through assessment of a capital improvement fee under the authority of the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges. Amounts accumulated in the fund are authorized to be expended for the purpose of paying the cost of capital improvement projects approved by the board of trustees for any facilities on campuses or lands owned or controlled by the board, except that no such amounts shall be expended for capital improvement projects relating to facilities from which revenue is derived and pledged for the retirement of revenue bonds issued under sections 85-403 to 85-411. All money accruing to the fund is appropriated to the board of trustees and shall be used for capital improvement projects authorized by the board. No expenditure may be made from the fund without prior approval by a resolution of the board of trustees. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. All revenue, fund balances, and expenditures shall be recorded in the Nebraska State Accounting System.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1129, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 110. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>