<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-402</statuteno><catchline>Campus buildings and facilities; pledge of income and appropriations authorized; limitations.</catchline><para>The Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges are hereby authorized:</para><para>(1) To expend on the amortization plan any part of the rentals on any and all rooms, dormitories, dining rooms, and housing or student activity facility buildings or parking buildings or facilities constructed or established pursuant to section 85-401 and any part of the revenue of any athletic structure so constructed or established;</para><para>(2) In the case of the construction of buildings for dormitories and for boarding and housing purposes, to expend any part of the net rentals received from other buildings, theretofore constructed on the same campus for dormitories and for boarding and housing purposes, connected with the respective institutions under their control;</para><para>(3) In the case of the construction or establishment of buildings or facilities for parking, to expend any part of the net revenue received from other parking buildings and facilities, including parking registration fees, theretofore constructed or established on the same campus, connected with respective institutions under their control, in the payment of the construction or establishment charges and interest thereon; and</para><para>(4) To pledge on behalf of the respective institutions the net income from the rentals for the payment of such construction or establishment charges and interest.</para><para>In no case shall the contracts run for a longer period than forty years, and in no case is the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska or the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges authorized to pledge the credit of the State of Nebraska for the payment of any sum or sums over and above the net income derived from the use of the building or buildings or facility or facilities, except that there may be pledged for the payment of such contracts any appropriations specifically made for such purposes by the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 199, &#167; 2, p. 688; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-402; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 192, &#167; 1, p. 761; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 85-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-402; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 561, &#167; 2, p. 1845; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 852, &#167; 19, p. 3206; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1433, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>