<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-168"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-168</statuteno><catchline>Bessey Memorial Fund; purpose; amount; investment.</catchline><para>There is appropriated out of any money in the treasury belonging to the General Fund, and not otherwise appropriated, for the creation of the Bessey Memorial Fund the sum of four thousand dollars. The fund shall be and constitute a perpetual memorial fund evidencing the high esteem in which the people of this state hold the memory of the late Professor Charles E. Bessey, who for more than thirty years was closely identified with our state university as professor of botany, Dean of its agricultural college, Dean of Deans, and repeatedly for years its acting chancellor. He was a conspicuous figure in American science and education, one of the great teachers of his age whose work and spirit have been the inspiration of thousands of students, a leader in the development of scientific agriculture, and the value of whose life and service to Nebraska and the West cannot be estimated in terms of money. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 239, &#167; 3, p. 577; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6781; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-171; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-168; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 125, p. 2426; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 151. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>