<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-105</statuteno><catchline>Board of Regents; organization; property; powers.</catchline><para>The Board of Regents shall have full power to appoint its own presiding officer and secretary. It shall constitute a body corporate, to be known as the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, and as such may sue and be sued and may make and use a common seal and alter the same at pleasure. It may acquire real and personal property for the use of the university and may dispose of the same whenever the university can be benefited thereby, except that it shall never dispose of grounds upon which a building of the university having a market value in excess of one million dollars is located without the consent of the Legislature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 5, p. 173; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 56; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7085; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6717; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-105; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 656, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 68, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>The University of Nebraska is a body corporate that may sue and be sued. Stadler v. Curtis Gas, Inc., 182 Neb. 6, 151 N.W.2d 915 (1967).</para><para>Legislature could require Board of Regents to establish experimental stations. State ex rel. Bushee v. Whitmore, 86 Neb. 399, 125 N.W. 606 (1910), modifying 85 Neb. 566, 123 N.W. 1051 (1909).</para><para>Board of Regents has no power to disburse endowment fund without appropriation. State ex rel. Bessey v. Babcock, 17 Neb. 610, 24 N.W. 202 (1885).</para><para>Article VII, section 10, Constitution of Nebraska, and this section do not grant power to waive immunity from suit in federal court. Board of Regents of University of Nebraska v. Dawes, 370 F.Supp. 1190 (D. Neb. 1974).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>