
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id6" statutenumber="85-404"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-404</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Dormitories; housing
facilities; parking facilities; other facilities; revenue bonds; issuance; approval by Legislature.</catchline>
<para>Either of the boards referred to in section 85-403 is hereby
specifically authorized and empowered, by resolution or agreement, to pledge
all or any part of the revenue and fees derived from the operation of the
dormitories, residence halls, single-dwelling or multiple-dwelling units,
buildings, and facilities for parking and other facilities for housing, boarding,
athletic purposes, medical care, and physical development and other activities
of students, faculties, or employees of such institutions referred to in section
85-403, or any of them, erected or acquired, or previously erected or acquired
by such board, and contract as to the care, insurance, management, and operation
of such buildings and facilities and the charges to be made and the rights
of the holders of the revenue bonds. When the board contracts that the operation
of any building or facility or part thereof shall be performed other than
by the board itself, the board shall at all times maintain supervision thereof
and control over the fees and charges imposed for the use thereof.</para>
<para>When such board proposes to pledge all or any part of the
revenue and fees from buildings and facilities other than the building or
facility to be constructed, the plans for such building or facility to be
constructed, including financing plans, shall be reviewed and approved or disapproved by
the Legislature or, if the Legislature is not in session, the Executive Board
of the Legislative Council.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 352, &#167; 2, p. 1076; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 581, &#167; 4, p. 1875; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 995, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB546, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>