<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-401</statuteno><catchline>Board of Regents; Board of Trustees; campus buildings and facilities; lease-purchase agreements authorized; conditions.</catchline><para>Subject to subsection (10) of section 85-1414, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges are authorized to lease to any person, firm, or corporation such portions of the campus of the respective institutions under their control as may be necessary to be used as sites for the construction of fireproof buildings for dormitories and for boarding, housing, and student activity purposes, for athletic structures, and for parking or as sites for the establishment of parking facilities, and they may acquire lands adjacent to the campus of any such institution by donation or purchase with any funds they may have available for that purpose to be leased as sites for such buildings and facilities. Subject to subsection (10) of section 85-1414, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges may also lease from any person, firm, or corporation an athletic structure or structures constructed on a site or sites owned by the State of Nebraska when the person, firm, or corporation has the permission of the Legislature to construct on such site or sites.</para><para>The State of Nebraska shall incur no liability by reason of the exercise of the authority granted in this section to the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges other than is hereinafter specifically set forth. The buildings and facilities so erected or established shall be used solely for dormitories and for boarding, housing, and student activity purposes, for athletic structures, and for parking, as the case may be.</para><para>Subject to subsection (10) of section 85-1414, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges are hereby authorized to contract with the owners of the buildings and facilities so erected or established on the leased grounds or state sites to pay as rental or otherwise for the use of the buildings and facilities a sum sufficient to pay, on the amortization plan, the principal and interest thereon of the cost of construction or establishment of the buildings and facilities, such contracts to run not over forty years.</para><para>The rate of interest allowed on the cost of construction or establishment shall be fixed by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska or Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, payable annually or semiannually as may be determined by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska or the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges. The contract shall provide that when the cost of construction or establishment has been paid, together with interest thereon, the buildings and facilities so constructed or established shall become the property of the State of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 199, &#167; 1, p. 687; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-401; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 581, &#167; 1, p. 1872; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 852, &#167; 18, p. 3205; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1433, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>