<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-103.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>85-103.01</statuteno><catchline>University of Nebraska; Board of
Regents; districts; numbers; boundaries; established by
maps; Clerk of Legislature; Secretary of State; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) For the
purpose of section 85-103, the state is divided into eight districts. Each district shall be entitled to one
regent on the board.</para>
<para>(2)
The numbers and boundaries of the districts are designated and established
by maps identified and labeled as maps REG11-1, REG11-2, REG11-3, REG11-4,
REG11-5, REG11-5A, REG11-6, REG11-7, and REG11-8, filed with the Clerk of
the Legislature, and incorporated by reference as part of Laws 2011, LB701.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The Clerk of the
Legislature shall transfer possession of the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section to the Secretary of State on May 27, 2011.</para>
<para>(b) When questions of
interpretation of district boundaries arise, the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section in possession of the Secretary of State shall serve as
the indication of the legislative intent in drawing the district boundaries.</para>
<para>(c) Each election commissioner
or county clerk shall obtain copies of the maps referred to in subsection
(2) of this section for the election commissioner's or clerk's county from
the Secretary of State.</para><para>(d)
The Secretary of State shall also have available for viewing on his or her
web site the maps referred to in subsection (2) of this section identifying
the boundaries for the districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 847, &#167; 3, p. 3189; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 1035, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 553, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 617, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 854, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB701, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Constitutional provisions,</emphasis> see Article VII, section 10, Constitution of Nebraska.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
