<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-107</statuteno><catchline>University of Nebraska; colleges and institute; enumerated; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) The University of Nebraska may embrace the colleges and institute listed in this section and any other colleges and institutes as may be established by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska with the approval of the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education.</para><para>(2) The colleges and institute of the University of Nebraska-Lincoln shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) Architecture;</para><para>(b) Arts and Sciences;</para><para>(c) Business Administration;</para><para>(d) Engineering and Technology;</para><para>(e) Home Economics;</para><para>(f) Journalism;</para><para>(g) Law;</para><para>(h) Teachers; and</para><para>(i) University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources which shall embrace divisions and administrative units as provided in section 85-1,104.</para><para>(3) The colleges of the University of Nebraska at Omaha shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) Arts and Sciences;</para><para>(b) Business Administration;</para><para>(c) Continuing Studies;</para><para>(d) Education;</para><para>(e) Fine Arts; and</para><para>(f) Public Affairs and Community Service.</para><para>(4) The colleges of the University of Nebraska at Kearney shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) Business and Technology;</para><para>(b) Education;</para><para>(c) Fine Arts and Humanities; and</para><para>(d) Natural and Social Sciences.</para><para>(5) The colleges of the University of Nebraska Medical Center shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) Dentistry;</para><para>(b) Medicine;</para><para>(c) Nursing; and</para><para>(d) Pharmacy.</para><para>(6) In addition to the colleges and institute listed in this section, there shall be a graduate college which shall exist and be administered as a university-wide college.</para><para>(7) Nothing contained in this section shall be construed to limit the authority of the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska to (a) merge existing colleges established on a campus level into systemwide administrative units, (b) merge or eliminate existing colleges established on a campus level, or (c) merge or eliminate divisions and administrative units of the University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture and Natural Resources.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 7, p. 173; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 56; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 141, &#167; 1, p. 499; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7084; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 127, &#167; 1, p. 287; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 164, &#167; 1, p. 368; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6716; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-107; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 360, &#167; 1, p. 1140; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 350, &#167; 2, p. 1071; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 540, &#167; 1, p. 1686; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 850, &#167; 1, p. 3197; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1237, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 275, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 995, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 28, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 204, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 60. </para></source><annotation><para>Board of Regents is charged with management of operation of University Hospital. Board of Regents v. County of Lancaster, 154 Neb. 398, 48 N.W.2d 221 (1951).</para><para>Experiment stations may be maintained in connection with the College of Agriculture. State ex rel. Bushee v. Whitmore, 85 Neb. 566, 123 N.W. 1051 (1909).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>