<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1,123"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1,123</statuteno><catchline>University of Nebraska at Kearney Cash Fund; University of Nebraska at Kearney Trust Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the University of Nebraska at Kearney Cash Fund. The fund shall consist of all fees and other money collected from students at the University of Nebraska at Kearney by authority of the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska for university purposes, all receipts from all university activities at the University of Nebraska at Kearney collected in connection with the operation of such university, and the money and funds received at the time the University of Nebraska at Kearney was established. A record shall be kept separating the money and funds into appropriate and convenient accounts. All money and funds accruing to the fund when appropriated by the Legislature shall be used for the maintenance and operation of the University of Nebraska at Kearney and shall at all times be subject to the orders of the Board of Regents. No warrant shall be issued against the fund unless there is money sufficient to pay the same. There may be retained at the University of Nebraska at Kearney a sum not to exceed one hundred seventy-five thousand dollars out of the fund to make settlement and equitable adjustments to students entitled thereto, to carry on university activities contributing to the fund, and to provide for contingencies. The University of Nebraska at Kearney Cash Fund shall be in the custody of the State Treasurer.</para><para>(2) There is hereby created the University of Nebraska at Kearney Trust Fund, which fund shall consist of all property, real or personal, acquired as of July 1, 1991, or at any time thereafter by or for Kearney State College by donation or bequest to it, which property shall be held and applied in the manner and according with the provisions of the will, deed, or instrument making such donation or bequest. All future donations or bequests to the University of Nebraska at Kearney shall be a part of such fund. The fund shall be held and managed in such manner as the Board of Regents shall determine. The holdings and management shall be in strict accordance with all terms of the donation or bequest, except that in the absence of any investment instructions, the funds may be invested by or at the direction of the Board of Regents in such investments as are authorized for trustees, guardians, personal representatives, or administrators under the laws of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 247, &#167; 11. </para></source><annotation><para>Since five judges of the court do not hold that this section is unconstitutional, the section is constitutional. State ex rel. Spire v. Beermann, 235 Neb. 384, 455 N.W.2d 749 (1990).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>