
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id00" statutenumber="85-424"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-424</statuteno><catchline id="id00">State College Facilities Program; appropriations; legislative intent; projects enumerated; accounting; reports; long-term capital plan.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature shall appropriate from the General Fund (a) an amount not less than one million one hundred twenty-five thousand dollars to the State College Facilities Program for each fiscal year for the period commencing July 1, 2006, and continuing through the fiscal year ending June 30, 2040, and (b) an amount not less than two million two hundred sixteen thousand dollars in each fiscal year for the appropriations referred to in subsection (5) of section 85-419, which shall be continued through the fiscal year ending June 30, 2040, to the State College Facilities Program to be used by the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges to accomplish projects as provided in this section. Through the allotment process established in section 81-1113 the Department of Administrative Services shall make appropriated funds available. Undisbursed appropriations balances existing in the State College Facilities Program at the end of each fiscal year until June 30, 2041, shall be and are hereby reappropriated.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds and determines that the projects funded through the State College Facilities Program are of critical importance to the State of Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the appropriations to the program shall not be reduced until all contracts and securities relating to the construction and financing of the projects or portions of the projects funded from such funds or accounts of such funds are completed or paid but in no case shall such appropriations extend beyond the fiscal year ending June 30, 2040.</para><para>(3) Subject to the receipt of project approval from the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education as required by subsection (10) of section 85-1414 for each of the following state college projects, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges is authorized to make expenditures from the State College Facilities Program for the following state college projects: (a) Deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College Academic/Administration Building; (b) design and placement of a new Peru State College emergency power generator; (c) replacement of existing Peru State College Al Wheeler Activity Center bleachers; (d) addition to and deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Peru State College Al Wheeler Activity Center; (e) addition to and deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Campus Services Building; (f) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Rice Auditorium; (g) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Memorial Stadium; (h) replacement of or deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College stadium; (i) addition to and deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Peru State College Theatre/Event Center; (j) construction of a facility to replace Wayne State College Benthack Hall applied technology programmatic space; (k) systemwide miscellaneous fire and life safety, energy conservation, deferred repair, federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, and asbestos removal projects; (l) construction of the Math Science Facility at Chadron State College; (m) construction and renovation of the Indoor/Outdoor Recreation Complex at Peru State College; (n) addition to and renovation of Wayne State College Rice Auditorium and Kirk Gardner Indoor Athletic Complex; and (o) any renewal, renovation, replacement, or repair of existing state college facilities.</para><para>(4) Expenditures of matching funds provided for the projects listed in this section by the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges as provided for in section 85-419 shall be accounted for in the Nebraska State Accounting System through the State College Facilities Program or according to some other reporting process mutually agreed upon by the state colleges and the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(5) The Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges shall record and report, on the Nebraska State Accounting System, expenditure of amounts from the State College Facilities Program and expenditure of proceeds arising from any contract entered into pursuant to this section and section 85-425 in such manner and format as prescribed by the Department of Administrative Services or according to some other reporting process mutually agreed upon by the state colleges and the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(6) At least once every two fiscal years beginning with fiscal year 2023-24 for the biennial period from fiscal years 2023-25, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges shall report to the Legislature (a) the projects expected to be constructed or newly financed in the next biennium from the State College Facilities Program and (b) the projects that were constructed or newly financed in the previous biennium from the State College Facilities Program. In addition, at least once every ten fiscal years beginning with fiscal year 2022-23, the Board of Trustees shall provide to the Legislature a copy of its current long-term capital plan for projects to be constructed or newly financed from the State College Facilities Program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 605, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB384, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 30. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>