<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-417"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-417</statuteno><catchline>State College Facilities Program; funding; intent; Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning with the fiscal year commencing July 1, 1999, and continuing through the fiscal year ending June 30, 2009, the Legislature shall appropriate each fiscal year from the General Fund an amount not less than four hundred thousand dollars to the State College Facilities Program to be used by the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges to accomplish projects as provided in this section. Through the allotment process established in section 81-1113, at a minimum, the Department of Administrative Services shall make appropriated funds available. Undisbursed appropriations balances existing in the State College Facilities Program at the end of each fiscal year until June 30, 2012, shall be and are hereby reappropriated.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds and determines that the projects funded through the program are of critical importance to the State of Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the appropriations to the program shall not be reduced until all contracts and securities relating to the construction and financing of the projects or portions of the projects funded from such funds or accounts of such funds are completed or paid but in no case shall such appropriations extend beyond the fiscal year ending June 30, 2009, nor shall the cumulative total of the General Fund appropriations for the program exceed four million dollars.</para><para>(3) Subject to the receipt of project approval from the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education as required by subsection (10) of section 85-1414 for each of the following state college projects, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges is authorized to make expenditures from the State College Facilities Program for the following state college projects: (a) Deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College Administration Building; (b) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College Memorial Hall; (c) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College Math and Science Building; (d) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College Old Library; (e) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Chadron State College Reta King Library; (f) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Peru State College Library; (g) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Peru State College Hoyt Science Hall; (h) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Peru State College Old Gymnasium; (i) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Peru State College Power Plant; (j) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Broadcast Studio; (k) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Hahn Administration Building; (l) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Memorial Stadium; (m) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Ramsey Theater; (n) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Rice Auditorium; (o) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of Wayne State College Telecommunications Classrooms; and (p) systemwide miscellaneous fire and life safety, energy conservation, deferred repair, federal Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, and asbestos removal projects.</para><para>(4) Expenditures of matching funds provided for the projects listed in this section by the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges as provided for in section 85-412 shall be accounted for in the Nebraska State Accounting System through the State College Facilities Program or according to some other reporting process mutually agreed upon by the state colleges and the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(5) The Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges shall record and report, on the Nebraska State Accounting System, expenditure of amounts from the State College Facilities Program and expenditure of proceeds arising from any contract entered into pursuant to this section and section 85-418 in such manner and format as prescribed by the Department of Administrative Services or according to some other reporting process mutually agreed upon by the state colleges and the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(6) The Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges shall provide to the Task Force for Building Renewal semiannual reports concerning the status of each project authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>