<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id468"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-905"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-905</statuteno><catchline>Tribal regalia; permitted; school policy.</catchline><para>(1) A person who is a member of an indigenous tribe of the United States or another country and is a student attending any Nebraska public postsecondary institution may wear traditional tribal regalia in any public or private location where the person is otherwise authorized to be on such school grounds or at any school function. Nothing in this section limits the authority of administrative and teaching personnel of a Nebraska public postsecondary institution to regulate student behavior to further school purposes or to prevent interference with the educational process.</para><para>(2) A Nebraska public postsecondary institution may adopt a policy to accommodate this section. Such policy may specify the characteristics of any garment, jewelry, other adornment, or object that such school finds will endanger the safety of a student or others or interfere with school purposes or the educational process if worn by such student during a specified activity.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Nebraska public postsecondary institution has the same meaning as in section 85-2403; and</para><para>(b) Tribal regalia means traditional garments, jewelry, other adornments, or similar objects of cultural significance worn by members of an indigenous tribe of the United States or another country. Tribal regalia does not include any firearm or other dangerous weapon. Tribal regalia also does not include, except in compliance with an appropriate federal permit, any object that is otherwise prohibited by federal law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB43, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>