<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-606.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-606.01</statuteno><catchline>University of Nebraska; state colleges; community colleges; retirement annuity contracts; purchase.</catchline><para>The Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges, any community college area board, and the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska shall have the authority to purchase retirement annuity contracts for any or all of their employees at the direction of the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act and may enter into contracts with their employees providing for the purchase of such retirement annuity contracts under the provisions of the Internal Revenue Code. Such employment contracts may provide that the amounts contributed by the employer for such annuity contracts shall be the result of an agreement of the employee to take a reduction in salary or to forego an increase in salary, but only to the extent such amounts are earned by the employee after the agreement becomes effective. Such an agreement must be legally binding and irrevocable with respect to amounts earned while the agreement is in effect. The right of an employee to such an annuity contract is nonforfeitable, except for failure to pay future premiums. Such an annuity contract is nontransferable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 256, &#167; 1, p. 677; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 851, &#167; 1, p. 3198; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 852, &#167; 1, p. 3199; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 849, &#167; 3, p. 3194; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 129, p. 2429; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 54, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 756, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 817, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 85-195; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 153; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 91. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>