<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-414"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-414</statuteno><catchline>University of Nebraska Facilities Program; funding; intent; Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning with the fiscal year commencing July 1, 1999, and continuing through the fiscal year ending June 30, 2009, the Legislature shall appropriate each fiscal year from the General Fund an amount not less than five million five hundred thousand dollars to the University of Nebraska Facilities Program to be used by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska to accomplish projects as provided in this section. Through the allotment process established in section 81-1113, the Department of Administrative Services shall make appropriated funds available. Undisbursed appropriations balances existing in the University of Nebraska Facilities Program at the end of each fiscal year until June 30, 2012, shall be and are hereby reappropriated.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds and determines that the projects funded through the University of Nebraska Facilities Program are of critical importance to the State of Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the appropriations to the program shall not be reduced until all contracts and securities relating to the construction and financing of the projects or portions of the projects funded from such funds or accounts of such funds are completed or paid but in no case shall such appropriations extend beyond the fiscal year ending June 30, 2009, nor shall the cumulative total of the General Fund appropriations for the program exceed fifty-five million dollars.</para><para>(3) Subject to the receipt of project approval from the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education as required by subsection (10) of section 85-1414 for each of the following University of Nebraska projects, the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska is authorized to make expenditures from the University of Nebraska Facilities Program for the following projects: (a) Deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska at Kearney Bruner Hall; (b) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska at Kearney Otto Olson Vocational Arts Building; (c) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska-Lincoln Love Library; (d) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska-Lincoln Snyder Building at the West Central Research Extension Center; (e) construction of a facility to replace University of Nebraska-Lincoln Lyman Hall and Bancroft Hall; (f) construction of a facility to replace University of Nebraska-Lincoln Biochemistry Building; (g) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska-Lincoln Hamilton Hall; (h) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska-Lincoln Avery Hall; (i) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska Medical Center Poynter Hall; (j) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska Medical Center Swanson Hall, Bennet Hall, and Service Building; (k) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska Medical Center Library housed in Wittson Hall; (l) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska at Omaha Allwine Hall; (m) deferred maintenance, repair, and renovation of University of Nebraska at Omaha Arts and Sciences Hall, and (n) demolition of University of Nebraska Miller Hall.</para><para>(4) Expenditures of matching funds provided for the projects listed in this section by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska as provided for in section 85-412 shall be accounted for in the Nebraska State Accounting System through the University of Nebraska Facilities Program or according to some other reporting process mutually agreed upon by the University of Nebraska and the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(5) The Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska shall record and report, on the Nebraska State Accounting System, expenditure of amounts from the University of Nebraska Facilities Program and expenditure of proceeds arising from any contract entered into pursuant to this section and section 85-415 in such manner and format as prescribed by the Department of Administrative Services or according to some other reporting process mutually agreed upon by the University of Nebraska and the Department of Administrative Services.</para><para>(6) The Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska shall provide to the Task Force for Building Renewal semiannual reports concerning the status of each project authorized by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1100, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1092, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc>