
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id6" statutenumber="85-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-125</statuteno><catchline id="id9">University Cash
Fund; source; use; investment.</catchline>
<para>The University Cash Fund shall consist of the matriculation
and diploma fees, registration fees, laboratory fees, tuition fees, summer
session or school fees, all other money or fees collected from students by
the authority of the Board of Regents for university purposes, and receipts
from all university activities collected by the board in connection with the
operation of the university. A record shall be kept by the board separating
such money into appropriate and convenient accounts. All money and funds accruing to the
University Cash Fund shall be used for the maintenance and operation of
the university and its activities and shall at all times be subject to the
orders of the Board of Regents accordingly. The
fund shall be in the custody of the State Treasurer, and any money in the
fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act, except that there may be retained by the Board of Regents
a sum not to exceed two percent of the fund, which shall be available to make
settlement and equitable adjustments to students entitled thereto, to carry
on university activities contributing to the fund, and to provide for contingencies. No
warrant shall be issued against such fund unless there is money in the hands
of the State Treasurer sufficient to pay the same.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 21, p. 177; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 57; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 76, &#167; 1, p. 325; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7103; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6735; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 85-121; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 85-125; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 313, &#167; 1, p. 1031; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 623, &#167; 1, p. 2087; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 248, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 151, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB378, &#167; 32.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Funds herein, not derived from taxation, are considered "appropriated" by section 85-131, and are under direct control of Board of Regents. Board of Regents v. Exon, 199 Neb. 146, 256 N.W.2d 330 (1977).</para><para>Mandatory fees for support of a student newspaper and other activities are public funds for which reasonable supervision by university authorities is required, and their use will not be enjoined except in a clear case. Larson v. Board of Regents, 189 Neb. 688, 204 N.W.2d 568 (1973).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>