<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-9,170"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-9,170</statuteno><catchline>Violation; complaint; filing; disposition; procedure; governing board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person aggrieved by a violation of the Nebraska Equal Opportunity in Postsecondary Education Act or any rule, regulation, or procedure adopted pursuant to the act may file a complaint with the governing board of the educational institution committing such violation. Such complaint shall be made in writing, under oath, within one hundred eighty days after such alleged violation, and shall set forth the claimant's address and the facts of such alleged violation with sufficient particularity as to permit the governing board to understand and investigate the conduct complained of.</para><para>(2) The governing board may take such action as may be necessary to correct such violation, including, but not limited to, (a) terminating the discriminatory practice or policy complained of and (b) awarding to the aggrieved person or persons such compensatory money damages as the particular facts and circumstances may warrant.</para><para>(3) The governing board shall dispose of the complaint and shall notify the claimant of its finding. All dispositions of such complaints shall be in writing and signed by the chief officer of the governing board, and a true copy of such disposition shall be mailed by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the claimant at the address set forth on the complaint or at such other address as may be filed by the claimant with the governing board. The claimant shall notify the governing board of any change of address, and the governing board has no duty to attempt to locate any claimant who has failed to advise such board of a change of address.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1090. </para></source></law></legaldoc>