<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id00" statutenumber="85-106.06"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>85-106.06</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of Regents; chief executive officer; chief administrative officers; appointment; public notice.</catchline><para>(1) The chief executive officer of the University of Nebraska shall be appointed by the Board of Regents using the enhanced public scrutiny process in subsection (3) of this section, hold office at the pleasure of the board, and receive such compensation as the board may prescribe.</para><para>(2) The University of Nebraska-Lincoln, the University of Nebraska at Omaha, the University of Nebraska at Kearney, the University of Nebraska Medical Center, and any other postsecondary educational institution designated by the Legislature to be a part of the University of Nebraska shall be governed by the Board of Regents, and each shall be managed and administered in the manner prescribed by the board. The chief administrative officer of each such postsecondary educational institution shall be appointed, hold office, and be compensated as prescribed by the Board of Regents. The appointment shall be made using the enhanced public scrutiny process in subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(3)(a) The Board of Regents shall provide public notice of a priority candidate for the position of chief executive officer of the University of Nebraska to be appointed pursuant to subsection (1) of this section. The public notice shall be provided at least thirty days before the date of the public meeting of the Board of Regents at which a final action or vote is to be taken on the employment of the priority candidate. The Board of Regents shall make available the employment application, resume, reference letters, and school transcripts related to the priority candidate prior to or at the time of providing such public notice.</para><para>(b) Prior to such public meeting and after the notice is provided, the Board of Regents shall provide a public forum at each campus of the University of Nebraska for the priority candidate for the position of chief executive officer to provide the public, including the media and students, faculty, and staff of the University of Nebraska, with an opportunity to meet and ask questions or provide input regarding the priority candidate.</para><para>(4)(a) The chief executive officer of the University of Nebraska shall provide public notice of a priority candidate for a position appointed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. The chief executive officer shall not make a final appointment for any such position until at least thirty days have elapsed after the notice is provided. The chief executive officer shall make available the employment application, resume, reference letters, and school transcripts related to the priority candidate prior to or at the time of providing such public notice.</para><para>(b) The chief executive officer shall, within such thirty-day period, provide a public forum at the applicable campus of the University of Nebraska for the priority candidate for a position appointed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section to provide the public, including the media and students, faculty, and staff of the University of Nebraska, with an opportunity to meet and ask questions or provide input regarding the priority candidate.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, priority candidate means an individual preliminarily selected to fill a vacancy in a position appointed pursuant to subsection (1) of this section subject to a final vote of the Board of Regents or to fill a vacancy in a position appointed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 68, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1109, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>