<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id00"  statutenumber="85-419"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>85-419</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Construction and improvement projects; legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds and determines that protecting investments in buildings through the completion of deferred maintenance, repair, renovation, and facility replacement construction projects is of critical importance to the State of Nebraska. The Legislature further recognizes that arresting the continued deterioration of buildings, limiting the effects of inflation on the costs of such deferred maintenance, repair, renovation, and facility replacement construction, and bringing such buildings into compliance with current health and safety requirements at the earliest possible time is necessary for protecting such investment in the buildings of the State of Nebraska. In order to accomplish these goals, it is necessary, desirable, and advisable that the Legislature provide for the receipt of funds for such purposes as soon as practicable with the repayment of such funds to be made over a period of years. The Legislature recognizes the commitment of (a) the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska to provide matching funds up to eleven million dollars per year for the period beginning with the fiscal year commencing July 1, 2009, and continuing through the fiscal year ending June 30, 2030, for a total of up to two hundred twenty-five million eight hundred thousand dollars to supplement amounts appropriated from the General Fund pursuant to section 85-421 and (b) the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges to provide matching funds up to one million four hundred forty thousand dollars per year for the period beginning with the fiscal year commencing July 1, 2006, and continuing through the fiscal year ending June 30, 2030, for a total of up to twenty-eight million eight hundred thousand dollars to supplement amounts appropriated from the General Fund pursuant to section 85-424.</para><para>(2) Sections 85-419 to 85-425 do not modify, reduce, or eliminate any provision of subsection (10) of section 85-1414 requiring the approval of the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education for any deferred maintenance, repair, renovation, facility addition, or facility replacement construction project authorized by section 85-421 or 85-424 and undertaken by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska or the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 605, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>