<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id189" statutenumber="85-1511"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1511</statuteno><catchline id="id192">Board; powers and duties;
enumerated.</catchline><para>In addition to any other powers and duties imposed
upon the community college system or its areas, campuses, or boards by the
Community College Aid Act, sections 85-917 to 85-966 and 85-1501 to 85-1540,
and any other provision of law, each board shall:</para>
<para>(1) Have general supervision, control, and operation of each community
college within its jurisdiction;</para>
<para>(2) Subject to coordination by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary
Education as prescribed in the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education
Act, develop and offer programs of applied technology education, academic
transfer programs, academic support courses, and such other programs and courses
as the needs of the community college area served may require. The board shall
avoid unnecessary duplication of existing programs and courses in meeting
the needs of the students and the community college area;</para>
<para>(3) Employ, for a period to be fixed by the board, executive officers,
members of the faculty, and such other administrative officers and employees
as may be necessary or appropriate and fix their salaries and duties;</para>
<para>(4) Subject to coordination by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary
Education as prescribed in the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education
Act, construct, lease, purchase, purchase on contract, operate, equip, and
maintain facilities;</para>
<para>(5) Contract for services connected with the operation of the community
college area as needs and interest demand;</para>
<para>(6)(a) Cause a comprehensive audit of the books, accounts, records,
and affairs to be made annually covering the most recently completed fiscal
year. The audit of each area shall include all sources of revenue used to
finance operating expenditures and capital improvements and the county-certified
property valuation for the community college for the fiscal year for which
such audit is being performed. Such audit of the books, accounts, records,
and affairs shall be completed and filed with the Auditor of Public Accounts,
the commission, and the Department of Administrative Services on or before November 15 of each year; and</para>
<para>(b) Cause a comprehensive audit of the full-time equivalent student
enrollment totals and reimbursable educational unit totals to be made annually
covering the most recently completed fiscal year. The audit of each area shall
include a report of full-time equivalent student enrollment totals and reimbursable
educational unit totals verified by such audits for the three most recently
completed fiscal years which shall be used for calculation of aid to the community
college areas for fiscal year 2013-14 and each fiscal year thereafter pursuant
to subdivisions (3)(b) and (c) of section 85-2234. The audit of the full-time
equivalent student enrollment totals and reimbursable educational unit totals
shall be completed and filed with the Auditor of Public Accounts, the commission,
and the Department of Administrative Services on or before August 15 of each
year;</para>
<para>(7) Establish fees and charges for the facilities authorized by sections
85-1501 to 85-1540. Such fees and charges shall be identified as facility
fees at the time they are assessed. The revenue from such fees and charges,
other than revenue pledged to retire bonds issued pursuant to sections 85-1515
and 85-1520 to 85-1527 and deposited in a separate bond sinking fund, shall
be deposited in the capital improvement and bond sinking fund provided for
in section 85-1515. Each board may enter into agreements with owners of facilities
to be used for housing regarding the management, operation, and government
of such facilities and may employ necessary employees to govern, manage, and
operate such facilities;</para>
<para>(8) Receive such gifts, grants, conveyances, and bequests of real and
personal property from public or private sources as may be made from time
to time, in trust or otherwise, whenever the terms and conditions thereof
will aid in carrying out the community college programs as specified by law.
Each board may sell, lease, exchange, invest, or expend such gifts, grants,
conveyances, and bequests or the proceeds, rents, profits, and income therefrom
according to the terms and conditions thereof and adopt and promulgate rules
and regulations governing the receipt and expenditure of such proceeds, rents,
profits, and income, except that acceptance of such gifts, grants, or conveyances
shall not be conditioned on matching state or local funds;</para>
<para>(9) Prescribe the courses of study for any community college under its
control and publish such catalogs and bulletins as may be necessary;</para>
<para>(10) Grant to every student upon graduation or completion of a course
of study a suitable diploma, associate degree, or certificate;</para>
<para>(11) Adopt and promulgate such rules and regulations and perform all
other acts as the board may deem necessary or appropriate to the administration
of the community college area. Such rules and regulations shall include, but
not be limited to, rules and regulations relating to facilities, housing,
scholarships, discipline, and pedestrian and vehicular traffic on property
owned, operated, or maintained by the community college area;</para>
<para>(12) Employ, for a period to be fixed by the board, an executive officer
for the community college area and, by written order filed in its office,
delegate to such executive officer any of the powers and duties vested in
or imposed upon it by sections 85-1501 to 85-1540. Such delegated powers and
duties may be exercised in the name of the board;</para>
<para>(13) Acquire real property by eminent domain pursuant to sections 76-701
to 76-724;</para>
<para>(14) Acquire real and personal property and sell, convey, or lease such
property whenever the community college area will be benefited thereby. The
sale, conveyance, or lease of any real estate owned by a community college
area shall be effective only when authorized by an affirmative vote of at
least two-thirds of all the members of the board;</para>
<para>(15) Enter into agreements for services, facilities, or equipment and
for the presentation of courses for students when such agreements are deemed
to be in the best interests of the education of the students involved;</para>
<para>(16) Transfer tribally controlled community college state aid amounts
to a tribally controlled community college located within its community college
area;</para>
<para>(17) Invest, after proper consideration of the requirements for the
availability of money, funds of the community college in securities the nature
of which individuals of prudence, discretion, and intelligence acquire or
retain in dealing with the property of another;</para>
<para>(18) Establish tuition rates for courses of instruction offered by each
community college within its community college area. Separate tuition rates
shall be established for students who are nonresidents of the State of Nebraska.
Each board may also establish fees to support the operating expenditures of
the community college area if such fees are accounted for separately from
the fees and charges established for facilities pursuant to subdivision (7)
of this section and are identified as operating fees at the time they are
assessed;</para>
<para>(19) Establish a fiscal year for the community college area which conforms
to the fiscal year of the state;</para>
<para>(20) Enter into a memorandum of understanding with the State Board of
Education to adopt a policy to share student data. At a minimum, the policy
shall ensure that the exchange of information is conducted in conformance
with the requirements of the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy
Act of 1974, as amended, 20 U.S.C. 1232g, and all federal regulations and
applicable guidelines adopted in accordance with such act, as such act, regulations,
and guidelines existed on January 1, 2010; and</para>
<para>(21) Exercise any other powers, duties, and responsibilities necessary
to carry out sections 85-1501 to 85-1540.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 344, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 459, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 756, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 363, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 30, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 802, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 47; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2644; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB781, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community College Aid Act,</emphasis> see section 85-2231.</para><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This section charges the board of governors of a technical community college with the power, duty, and responsibility of establishing curriculum and employing members of the faculty. Cross v. Board of Governors, 204 Neb. 383, 281 N.W.2d 925 (1979).</para><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of Article VIII, section 1A, of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>