<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id605"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-1439"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1439</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska public postsecondary institutions; prior learning examinations; policies and procedures; requirements; commission duties.</catchline><para>(1) On or before October 1, 2026, each Nebraska public postsecondary institution shall develop and implement written policies and procedures for awarding academic credit based on prior learning examinations. The policies and procedures shall:</para><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in this section, award academic credit to students for each distinct prior learning examination for which the student met or exceeded the cut score;</para><para>(b) Prioritize application of credit toward courses that meet general education, major, or degree requirements over application of credit towards courses that are elective for the student;</para><para>(c) Establish the process through which credits awarded under this section shall be recorded on transcripts and transferred to other Nebraska public postsecondary institutions; and</para><para>(d) Ensure that policies and procedures are publicly posted on the institution's website in a location accessible to prospective students and families.</para><para>(2) With approval from the commission, a Nebraska public postsecondary institution may require a higher minimum score than the cut score approved by the commission pursuant to section 85-1438 if the chief academic officer of such institution determines, based on evidence of student performance or course success rates, that a higher score is necessary for success in a specific course or sequence.</para><para>(3) On or before October 15, 2026, each Nebraska public postsecondary institution shall submit its policies and procedures adopted under this section to the commission. The commission shall compile all such policies and procedures and post a statewide summary on the commission's website, including the justification for any higher minimum score requirements approved by the commission pursuant to subsection (2) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB937, &#167; 23. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>