<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id364"><amendatorysection statutenumber="85-1438" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1438</statuteno><catchline>Prior learning examinations; list; cut scores; commission duties.</catchline><para>(1) On or before September 1, 2026, the commission shall, in consultation with Nebraska public postsecondary institutions, approve a list of prior learning examinations and the cut score for each such examination. The list shall include commonly recognized prior learning examinations, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(a) Prior learning examinations that are associated with participation in high school courses specifically designed to prepare students for such examinations;</para><para>(b) Prior learning examinations that are associated with participation in high school courses using international curriculum frameworks;</para><para>(c) Prior learning examinations that are not associated with high school courses endorsed by the provider of the prior learning examination; and</para><para>(d) Prior learning examinations that assess and certify foundational workplace skills and are not associated with a specific high school course.</para><para>(2) The commission shall, in consultation with Nebraska public postsecondary institutions, set cut scores in a manner consistent with national practices and shall utilize recommendations for such cut scores contained in any comprehensive guide maintained by a national organization recognized for expertise on the topic of appropriate cut scores for prior learning examinations in the context of awarding postsecondary academic credit.</para><para>(3) The commission shall, in consultation with Nebraska public postsecondary institutions, update the list of prior learning examinations and cut scores as necessary to provide options for students while maintaining the academic integrity of such institutions.</para><para>(4) The commission shall post and maintain the list of prior learning examinations and cut scores on the commission's website in a location accessible to prospective postsecondary students and families.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB937, &#167; 22. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>