<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1620"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1620</statuteno><catchline>School; authority to award associate or baccalaureate degrees; commissioner; authorize.</catchline><para>(1) A school which has been accredited pursuant to section 85-1619 may apply to the department for authority to award associate degrees. Upon determining that the quality of the courses of instruction at the applicant school meets the standards established in the department's rules and regulations, the commissioner may grant the applicant the authority to award an associate degree and shall issue a certificate setting forth the programs for which the associate degree may be awarded. Such authorization shall continue so long as the school remains accredited.</para><para>(2) A school which has been accredited pursuant to section 85-1619 may apply to the department for authority to award baccalaureate degrees. The department shall refer such degree applications to the commission for its review and approval. Within ninety days after receipt of such referral, the commission shall make a determination setting forth the specific program area and the name of the baccalaureate degree program. The commission shall report its determination to the commissioner who shall issue a certificate setting forth the programs for which the baccalaureate degree may be awarded. Such authorization shall continue so long as the school remains accredited.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 370, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 488, &#167; 20; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2820.01; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 4, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 32. </para></source></law></legaldoc>