<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-1512"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1512</statuteno><catchline>Boards; establish election districts;
nomination and election of members; qualifications.</catchline><para>Each
board shall divide the community college area into five election districts
as nearly equal in population as may be practicable and shall transmit the
appropriate information pertaining to such election districts to the Secretary
of State and to the appropriate election officials within the area. Board
members shall be nominated and elected as provided in section 32-514. To be
eligible for membership on the board, a person shall be a registered voter
and shall have been a resident of the area for six months and, for members
representing a district, a resident of the district for six months. No person
shall be eligible for membership on a community
college board of governors who is an elected or appointed member of any other
board relating to education. No
member of a community college board of governors shall be employed by the
community college area for which he or she serves as a board member. Each
member elected to represent a district shall be a resident of the district.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 344, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 446, &#167; 35; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 79-2646; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 612; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB135, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of Article VIII, section 1A, of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>