<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-1008"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1008</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Safety Center Advisory Council;
membership; appointment.</catchline><para>(1) To assist the center in carrying
out its purposes and functions, the Board of Regents may establish a Nebraska
Safety Center Advisory Council composed of the following members:</para>
<para>(a) One representative from the Department of Roads;</para>
<para>(b) One representative from the Department of Motor Vehicles;</para>
<para>(c) One representative from the State Department of Education;</para>
<para>(d) One representative from the Game and Parks Commission;</para>
<para>(e) One representative from the Department of Labor;</para>
<para>(f) One person representing the community college areas;</para>
<para>(g) One person representing private business and industry;</para>
<para>(h) One person representing the University of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(i) One person representing the medical profession;</para>
<para>(j) One person representing the area of law enforcement in this state;</para>
<para>(k) One person representing the Safety Council of Nebraska, Inc.;</para>
<para>(l) One person representing the area of transportation;</para>
<para>(m) One person representative of emergency medical services;</para>
<para>(n) One person representing the judiciary in the State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(o) One person representing city government;</para>
<para>(p) One person representing county government;</para>
<para>(q) One person representing the area of agriculture;</para>
<para>(r) One person representing the local public school system;</para>
<para>(s) One person representing
fire safety;</para><para>(t) One representative of
the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education;</para>
<para>(u) One person representing
the Red Cross; and</para>
<para>(v) One person representing
the state colleges.</para>
<para>(2) Representatives selected to serve on the council shall have appropriate
education, training, and experience in the field of fire safety, industrial safety, recreational
safety, domestic safety, or traffic safety.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 693, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB299, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>