<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id178" statutenumber="85-1412"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1412</statuteno><catchline id="id181">Commission; additional
powers and duties.</catchline><para>The commission shall have the following
additional powers and duties:</para>
<para>(1) Conduct surveys and studies as may be necessary to undertake the
coordination function of the commission pursuant to section 85-1403 and request
information from governing boards and appropriate administrators of public
institutions and other governmental agencies for research projects. All public
institutions and governmental agencies receiving state funds shall comply
with reasonable requests for information under this subdivision. Public institutions
may comply with such requests pursuant to section 85-1417;</para>
<para>(2) Recommend to the Legislature and the Governor legislation it deems
necessary or appropriate to improve postsecondary education in Nebraska and
any other legislation it deems appropriate to change the role and mission
provisions in sections 85-917 to 85-966.01. The recommendations submitted
to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(3) Establish any advisory committees as may be necessary to undertake
the coordination function of the commission pursuant to section 85-1403 or
to solicit input from affected parties such as students, faculty, governing
boards, administrators of the public institutions, administrators of the private
nonprofit institutions of postsecondary education and proprietary institutions
in the state, and community and business leaders regarding the coordination
function of the commission;</para>
<para>(4) Participate in or designate an employee or employees to participate
in any committee which may be created to prepare a coordinated plan for the
delivery of educational programs and services in Nebraska through the telecommunications
system;</para>
<para>(5) Seek a close liaison with the State Board of Education and the State
Department of Education in recognition of the need for close coordination
of activities between elementary and secondary education and postsecondary
education;</para>
<para>(6) Administer the Integrated Postsecondary Education Data System or
other information system or systems to provide the commission with timely,
comprehensive, and meaningful information pertinent to the exercise of its
duties. The information system shall be designed to provide comparable data
on each public institution. The commission shall also administer the uniform
information system prescribed in sections 85-1421 to 85-1427 known as the
Nebraska Educational Data System. Public institutions shall supply the appropriate
data for the information system or systems required by the commission;</para>
<para>(7) Administer (a) the
Access College Early Scholarship Program Act, (b) the Community College Aid Act, (c) the Nebraska Community College Student
Performance and Occupational Education Grant Fund under the direction of the
Nebraska Community College Student Performance and Occupational Education
Grant Committee, (d) the Nebraska Opportunity Grant Act, and (e) the Postsecondary Institution
Act;</para>
<para>(8) Accept and administer loans, grants, and programs from the federal
or state government and from other sources, public and private, for carrying
out any of its functions, including the administration of privately endowed
scholarship programs. Such loans and grants shall not be expended for any
other purposes than those for which the loans and grants were provided. The
commission shall determine eligibility for such loans, grants, and programs,
and such loans and grants shall not be expended unless approved by the Governor;</para>
<para>(9) On or before December 1 of each even-numbered year, submit to the
Legislature and the Governor a report of its objectives and activities and
any new private colleges in Nebraska and the implementation of any recommendations
of the commission for the preceding two calendar years. The report submitted
to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(10) Provide staff support for interstate compacts on postsecondary
education; and</para>
<para>(11) Request inclusion of the commission in any existing grant review
process and information system.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 93, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 816, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 7, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB192, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB340, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB956, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB637, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 234; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB211, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Access College Early Scholarship Program Act,</emphasis> see section 85-2101.</para><para><emphasis>Community College Aid Act,</emphasis> see section 85-2231.</para><para><emphasis>Integrated Postsecondary Education Data System,</emphasis> see section 85-1424.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Opportunity Grant Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1901.</para><para><emphasis>Postsecondary Institution Act,</emphasis> see section 85-2401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>