<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" id="id217" statutenumber="85-1502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1502</statuteno><catchline id="id220">Area governance
and statewide coordination; legislative intent; voluntary membership in boards or associations of community
colleges; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that a clear distinction between
area governance and statewide coordination for the community college areas
be recognized and that such coordination is appropriate in order to provide
the most cost-effective programs for residents of each community college area.
It is further the intent of the Legislature that coordination of the community
colleges by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education be conducted as provided in Article VII, section 14,
of the Constitution of Nebraska and the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary
Education Act. It is further the intent of the Legislature that such coordination
not be conducted through a board or association representing all the community
colleges and that membership in any boards or associations of community colleges
be voluntary.</para>
<para>(2) The board of governors
of any community college area may pay from college funds an amount to be determined
by the board of governors for membership in boards or associations of community
colleges.</para><para>(3) Nothing
in this section shall be construed to require or provide for state control
of the operations of any community college area or to abridge the governance
ability, rights, or responsibilities of any board. Nothing in this section
shall be construed to limit the ability or authority of the commission to
fulfill its responsibilities and duties regarding the individual community
college areas and the individual community college area campuses.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 625, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 46; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2636.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB211, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>