<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1103.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1103.01</statuteno><catchline>Out-of-state institution of higher education; authorized to offer telecommunications course or degree program; registration required; exemption; commission; duties.</catchline><para>An out-of-state institution of higher education which will offer a course or degree program via telecommunications within Nebraska and which will have a physical presence in Nebraska shall register with and seek approval of the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education prior to offering such course or program in Nebraska. Such institution shall be exempt from this section if the offering is in the nature of a short course or seminar and instruction for the segment takes not more than twenty classroom hours or each course or program offered by it in this state is offered on a military installation solely for military personnel or civilians employed on such installations.</para><para>For purposes of this section, physical presence in Nebraska is evidenced by arrangements for sites where such an institution offers one or more courses for college credit on an established schedule at locations other than the personal residence of individual students.</para><para>The commission shall establish standards for approval of telecommunications-based courses or programs to be offered in the state by such institutions as prescribed in section 85-1103. Alternatively the commission may enter into reciprocal agreements to review degree programs offered via telecommunications if the standards for review in the state of origin are at least equivalent to the standards prescribed in such section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 93, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>