<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id88" statutenumber="85-1809"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1809</statuteno><catchline id="id91">Ownership rights under participation agreement.</catchline><para>(1) A participant retains ownership of all contributions made under a participation agreement up to the date of utilization for payment of qualified higher education expenses for the beneficiary or, in the case of a qualified education loan payment, for the beneficiary or a sibling of the beneficiary. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any amount credited to any account is not susceptible to any levy, execution, judgment, or other operation of law, garnishment, or other judicial enforcement, and the amount is not an asset or property of either the participant or the beneficiary for the purposes of any state insolvency or inheritance tax laws. All income derived from the investment of the contributions made by the participant shall be considered to be held in trust for the benefit of the beneficiary.</para><para>(2) If the program created by sections 85-1801 to 85-1817 is terminated prior to payment of qualified higher education expenses, the participant is entitled to receive the fair market value of the account established in the program.</para><para>(3) If the beneficiary graduates from an eligible educational institution and a balance remains in the participant's account, any remaining funds may be used to make qualified education loan payments for siblings of the beneficiary or transferred as allowed by rule or regulation, subject to the provisions of section 529 of the Internal Revenue Code, as well as any other applicable state or federal laws or regulations.</para><para>(4) The eligible educational institution shall obtain ownership of the payments made for the qualified higher education expenses paid to the institution at the time each payment is made to the institution.</para><para>(5) Any amounts which may be paid to any person or persons pursuant to the Nebraska educational savings plan trust but which are not listed in this section are owned by the trust.</para><para>(6) A participant may transfer ownership rights to another eligible participant, including a gift of the ownership rights to a minor beneficiary. The transfer shall be made and the property distributed in accordance with the rules and regulations or with the terms of the participation agreement.</para><para>(7) A participant shall not be entitled to utilize any interest in the Nebraska educational savings plan trust as security for a loan.</para><para>(8) The Nebraska educational savings plan trust may accept transfers of cash investments from a custodian under the Nebraska Uniform Transfers to Minors Act or any other similar laws under the terms and conditions established by the trustee.</para><para>(9) A participant may designate a successor account owner to succeed to all of the participant's rights, title, and interest in an account, including the right to change the account beneficiary, upon the death or legal incapacity of the participant. If a participant dies or becomes legally incapacitated and has failed to name a successor account owner, the account beneficiary shall become the account owner.</para><para>(10) Upon the death of a beneficiary, the participant may change the beneficiary on the account, transfer assets to another beneficiary who is a member of the family of the former beneficiary, or request a nonqualified withdrawal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1003, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 750, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1104, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB296, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB610, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB864, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Transfers to Minors Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>