<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1711"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1711</statuteno><catchline>Authority; members; qualifications; appointment; terms; removal.</catchline><para>The authority shall consist of seven members, to be appointed by the Governor, who shall be residents of the state, not more than four of whom shall be members of the same political party. At least one of the members shall be a trustee, director, officer, or employee of one or more private institutions of higher education in the state. At least one shall be a person having a favorable reputation for skill, knowledge, and experience in the field of finance. At least one shall be a person experienced in and having a favorable reputation for skill, knowledge, and experience in the educational building construction field. At least one shall be a person experienced in and having a favorable reputation in the field of public accounting. The members of the authority first appointed shall serve for terms expiring as follows: One on December 31, 1982; two on December 31, 1983; two on December 31, 1984; and two on December 31, 1985, respectively, the term of each such member to be designated by the Governor. Upon the expiration of the term of any member, his or her successor shall be appointed for a term of four years and until a successor has been appointed and qualified. The Governor shall fill any vacancy for the remainder of the unexpired term. Any member of the authority may be removed by the Governor for misfeasance, malfeasance, or willful neglect of duty or other cause after notice and a public hearing unless such notice and hearing shall be expressly waived in writing by the accused member. Each member shall be eligible for reappointment to a successive term but shall be declared ineligible for three consecutive full terms.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 321, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 644, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2911; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 5, &#167; 11. </para></source></law></legaldoc>