<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id26">
<sectno id="id27" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id28" statutenumber="85-1807"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id30">85-1807</statuteno><catchline id="id31">Deposit of funds; College Savings Plan Administrative Fund;
College Savings Plan Expense Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The State Treasurer shall deposit money received by the
Nebraska educational savings plan trust into three funds: The College
Savings Plan Program Fund, the College Savings Plan Expense Fund, and the
College Savings Plan Administrative Fund. The State Treasurer
shall deposit money received by the trust into the appropriate fund. The State
Treasurer and Accounting Administrator of the Department of Administrative
Services shall determine the state fund types necessary to comply with section
529 of the Internal Revenue Code and state policy. The money in the funds
shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to policies established
by the Nebraska Investment Council. The
program fund, the expense fund, and the administrative fund shall be separately
administered. The Nebraska educational savings plan trust shall be operated
with no General Fund appropriations.</para>
<para>(2) All money paid by participants
in connection with participation agreements and all investment income earned
on such money shall be deposited as received into separate accounts within
the program fund. Contributions to the
trust made by participants may only be
made in the form of cash. All funds generated in connection with participation
agreements shall be deposited into the appropriate accounts within the program
fund. A participant or beneficiary shall not provide investment direction
regarding program contributions or earnings held by the trust. Money accrued by participants in the program fund may be
used for payments to any institution of higher education.</para>
<para>(3) The College
Savings Plan Administrative Fund is created. Money from the trust transferred
from the expense fund to the administrative fund in an amount authorized by
an appropriation from the Legislature shall be utilized to pay for the costs
of administering, operating, and maintaining the trust, to the extent permitted
by section 529 of the Internal Revenue Code. The administrative fund shall
not be credited with any money other than money transferred from the expense
fund in an amount authorized by an appropriation by the Legislature or any
interest income earned on the balances held in the administrative fund. The
State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the administrative fund on July
1, 2010, to the expense fund on July 1, 2010, or as soon as administratively
possible. Any money in the administrative fund available for investment shall
be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital
Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>

<para>(4) The College
Savings Plan Expense Fund is created. The expense fund shall be used to pay
costs associated with the Nebraska educational savings plan trust and shall
be funded with fees assessed to the program fund. The State Treasurer shall
transfer from the expense fund to the State Investment Officer's Cash Fund
an amount equal to the pro rata share of the budget appropriated to the Nebraska
Investment Council as permitted in section 72-1249.02, to cover reasonable
expenses incurred for investment management of the Nebraska educational savings
plan trust. Annually and prior to such transfer to the State Investment Officer's
Cash Fund, the State Treasurer shall report to the budget division of the
Department of Administrative Services and to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst
the amounts transferred during the previous fiscal year. The State Treasurer
shall transfer any money in the endowment fund on July 1, 2010, to the expense
fund on such date. Transfers may be made from the expense fund to the General
Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the expense fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1003, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB197, &#167;  5.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>