<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1415">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1415</statuteno><catchline>Capital construction projects proposed
by Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska, Board of Trustees of the
Nebraska State Colleges, and certain nonprofit corporations; review; commission;
duties; approval by Legislature.</catchline><para>(1) Consistent with the
authority granted to the Legislature pursuant to Article XIII, section 1,
of the Constitution of Nebraska, the commission shall review all capital construction
projects proposed by the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska and
the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges pursuant to sections
85-404 and 85-408 and by any nonprofit corporation created by the Board of
Regents of the University of Nebraska or the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska
State Colleges when (a) state general funds, (b) funds received by the University
of Nebraska or any state college for the purposes of reimbursing overhead
costs and expenses in connection with any federal or other grant or contract,
(c) tuition, or (d) the state's operating investment pool investment income
constitute all or any part of the funds used for the repayment of all or any
part of the bonds of such nonprofit corporation. Such boards shall submit
all such projects, including applicable financing plans, to the commission
for review.</para>
<para>(2) Within sixty days after the date of submission
of a proposed project, the commission shall take action by recommending that
the Legislature or the Executive Board of the Legislative Council either approve
or disapprove the project. Following such action by the commission, each such
proposed project together with the commission's recommendation of approval
or disapproval shall be submitted electronically by
the board concerned to the Legislature or to the Executive Board of the Legislative
Council. The Legislature or, if the Legislature is not in session, the Executive
Board of the Legislative Council shall thereafter take action to approve or
disapprove the proposed project.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 976, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1071, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 237.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>