<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1808">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1808</statuteno><catchline>Participation agreement; cancellation;
when; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A participant may cancel a participation
agreement at will. The trustee shall determine and collect a refund penalty
by deducting the refund penalty from the returned funds. Collected refund
penalties shall be deposited in the expense fund.</para>
<para>(2) Upon the occurrence of any of the following circumstances, no refund
penalty shall be levied by the trust in the event of a refund or termination
of a participation agreement:</para>
<para>(a) Death of the beneficiary;</para>
<para>(b) Permanent disability or mental incapacity of the beneficiary;</para>
<para>(c) The beneficiary is awarded a scholarship as defined in section 529
of the Internal Revenue Code, but only to the extent the refund of earnings
does not exceed the scholarship amount; or</para>
<para>(d) A qualified rollover is made as permitted by section 529 of the
Internal Revenue Code, except that if a qualified rollover is made into a
plan sponsored by another state or entity, the participation agreement shall
be deemed to have been canceled for purposes of subdivision (8)(c) of
section 77-2716 and federal adjusted gross income shall be increased to the
extent previously deducted as a contribution to the trust.</para>
<para>(3) In the event of cancellation of a participation agreement for any
of the causes listed in subsection (2) of this section, the participant shall
be entitled to receive the principal amount of all contributions made by the
participant under the participation agreement plus the actual program fund
investment income earned on the contributions, less any losses incurred on
the investment. Notwithstanding
any other provisions of this section, under no circumstances shall a participant
or beneficiary receive a refund or distribution that is more than the fair
market value of the specific account on the applicable liquidation date.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1003, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 750, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 574, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB197, &#167;  6.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>