<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id215">
<sectno id="id216">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id217" statutenumber="85-1502"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id219">85-1502</statuteno><catchline id="id220">Area governance
and statewide coordination; legislative intent; association of boards; powers
and duties; section, how construed.</catchline><para>(1) It is
the intent of the Legislature that a clear distinction between area governance
and statewide coordination for the community college areas be recognized and
that such coordination is appropriate in order to provide the most cost-effective
programs for residents of each community college area. It is further the intent
of the Legislature that coordination of the community colleges by the Coordinating
Commission for Postsecondary Education be conducted through an association
of the boards.</para>
<para>(2) Through June 30, 2011, all of
the boards shall be a part of and shall be represented by such association.
Coordination services provided by such association shall include (a) preparation
of a system strategic plan, (b) coordination of the budget request for the
biennium, (c) facilitation of program-needs assessment and articulation, (d)
recommendation and facilitation of the appointment of representatives to committees,
boards, commissions, task forces, and any other state-level bodies requesting
or requiring participation from the community college system, and (e) facilitation
of responses to data and information requests for the system.</para>
<para>(3) All activities conducted pursuant to this section by
such association shall be conducted in accordance with the Open Meetings Act.</para>
<para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to require
or provide for state control of the operations of any community college area
or to abridge the governance ability, rights, or responsibilities of any board.
Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the ability or authority
of the commission to fulfill its responsibilities and duties regarding the
individual community college areas and the individual community college area
campuses.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 625, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 46; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2636.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>