<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id249">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id251" statutenumber="85-1517"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1517</statuteno><catchline id="id254">Board; power
to certify tax levy; limit; purposes; approval required
to raise levy over limit; how collected.</catchline><para>(1) For fiscal years
2011-12 and 2012-13:</para>
<para>(a) The board may certify to the county board of equalization
of each county within the community college area a tax levy not to exceed
ten and one-quarter cents on each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation
of all property subject to the levy within the community college area, uniform
throughout the area, for the purpose of supporting operating expenditures
of the community college area;</para>
<para>(b) In addition to the levies provided in subdivisions (1)(a)
and (c) of this section, the board may certify to the county board of equalization
of each county within the community college area a tax levy not to exceed
one cent on each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation of all property
within the community college area, uniform throughout such area, for the purposes
of paying off bonds issued under sections 85-1520 to 85-1527 and establishing
a capital improvement and
bond sinking fund as provided in section 85-1515. The levy provided by this
subdivision may be exceeded by that amount necessary to retire the general
obligation bonds assumed by the community college area or issued pursuant
to section 85-1515 according to the terms of such bonds or for any obligation
pursuant to section 85-1535 entered into prior to January 1, 1997; and</para>
<para>(c) In addition to the levies provided in subdivisions (1)(a)
and (b) of this section, the board may also certify to the county board of
equalization of each county within the community college area a tax levy on
each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation of all property within the
community college area, uniform throughout such area, in the amount which
will produce funds only in the amount necessary to pay for funding accessibility
barrier elimination project costs and abatement of environmental hazards as
such terms are defined in section 79-10,110. Such tax levy shall not be so
certified unless approved by an affirmative vote of a majority of the board
taken at a public meeting of the board following notice and a hearing. The
board shall give at least seven days' notice of such public hearing and shall
publish such notice once in a newspaper of general circulation in the area
to be affected by the increase. The proceeds of such tax levy shall be deposited
in the capital improvement and bond sinking fund provided for in section 85-1515
for use in funding the projects authorized pursuant to this subdivision.</para>
<para>(2) For fiscal year 2013-14 and each fiscal year thereafter:</para>
<para>(a) The board may certify to the county board of equalization
of each county within the community college area a tax levy not to exceed
the difference between eleven and one-quarter cents and the rate levied for such fiscal year pursuant
to subdivision (b) of this subsection
on each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation of all property subject
to the levy within the community college area, uniform throughout the area,
for the purpose of supporting operating expenditures of the community college
area. For purposes of calculating the amount of levy authority available for
operating expenditures pursuant to this subdivision, the rate levied pursuant
to subdivision (b) of this subsection shall not include amounts to retire
general obligation bonds assumed by the community college area or issued pursuant
to section 85-1515 according to the terms of such bonds or for any obligation
pursuant to section 85-1535 entered into prior to January 1, 1997;</para>
<para>(b) In addition to the levies provided in subdivisions (a)
and (c) of this subsection, the board may certify to the county board of equalization
of each county within the community college area a tax levy not to exceed
two cents on each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation of all property
within the community college area, uniform throughout such area, for the purposes
of paying off bonds issued under sections 85-1520 to 85-1527 and establishing
a capital improvement and bond sinking fund as provided in section 85-1515.
The levy provided by this subdivision may be exceeded by that amount necessary
to retire general obligation bonds assumed by the community college area or
issued pursuant to section 85-1515 according to the terms of such bonds or
for any obligation pursuant to section 85-1535 entered into prior to January
1, 1997; and</para>
<para>(c) In addition to the levies provided in subdivisions (a)
and (b) of this subsection, the board of
a community college area with a campus located on the site of a former ammunition
depot may certify to the county board of equalization of each
county within the community college area a tax levy not to exceed three-quarters of one cent on
each one hundred dollars on the taxable valuation of all property within the
community college area, uniform throughout such area, to pay for funding accessibility barrier elimination
project costs and abatement of environmental hazards as such terms are defined
in section 79-10,110. Such tax levy shall not be so certified unless approved
by an affirmative vote of a majority of the board taken at a public meeting
of the board following notice and a hearing. The board shall give at least
seven days' notice of such public hearing and shall publish such notice once
in a newspaper of general circulation in the area to be affected by the increase.
The proceeds of such tax levy shall be deposited in the capital improvement
and bond sinking fund provided for in section 85-1515 for use in funding accessibility
barrier elimination project costs and abatement of environmental hazards as
such terms are defined in section 79-10,110.</para>
<para>(3) The taxes provided by this section shall be levied and assessed
in the same manner as other property taxes and entered on the books of the
county treasurer. The proceeds of the tax, as collected, shall be remitted
to the treasurer of the board not less frequently than once each month.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 344, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 922, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 363, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 251; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 599, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 824, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 320, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 881, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 796, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 38, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1050, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 197; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1001, &#167; 35; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2650; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 299, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1084; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 38, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB59, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1104, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of Article VIII, section 1A, of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>