<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id11">
<sectno id="id12">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id13" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="85-1402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id15">85-1402</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary
Education Act:</para>
<para>(1)(a) Capital construction project shall mean a project which
utilizes tax funds designated by the Legislature and shall be: Any proposed
new capital structure; any proposed addition to, renovation of, or remodeling
of a capital structure; any proposed acquisition of a capital structure by
gift, purchase, lease-purchase, or other means of construction or acquisition
that (i) will be directly financed in whole or in part with tax funds designated
by the Legislature totaling at least the minimum capital expenditure for purposes
of this subdivision or (ii) is likely, as determined by the institution, to
result in an incremental increase in appropriation or expenditure of tax funds
designated by the Legislature of at least the minimum capital expenditure
for the facility's operations and maintenance costs in any one fiscal year
within a period of ten years from the date of substantial completion or acquisition
of the project. No tax funds designated by the Legislature shall be appropriated
or expended for any incremental increase of more than the minimum capital
expenditure for the costs of the operations and utilities of any facility
which is not included in the definition of capital construction project and
thus is not subject to commission approval pursuant to the Coordinating Commission
for Postsecondary Education Act. No institution shall include a request for
funding such an increase in its budget request for tax funds designated by
the Legislature nor shall any institution utilize any such funds for such
an increase. The Governor shall not include in his or her budget recommendations,
and the Legislature shall not appropriate, such funds for such increase.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of this subdivision:</para>
<para>(i) Directly financed shall mean funded by:</para>
<para>(A) Appropriation of tax funds designated by the Legislature
for the specific capital construction project;</para>
<para>(B) Property tax levies used to establish a capital improvement
and bond sinking fund pursuant to section 85-1515; or</para>
<para>(C) That portion of tax funds designated by the Legislature
and appropriated by the Legislature for the general operation of the public
institution and utilized to fund the capital project;</para>
<para>(ii) Incremental increase shall mean an increase in appropriation
or expenditure of tax funds designated by the Legislature of at least the
minimum capital expenditure for a facility's operations and maintenance costs,
beyond any increase due to inflation, to pay for a capital structure's operations
and maintenance costs that are a direct result of a capital construction project;
and</para>
<para>(iii) Minimum capital expenditure shall mean:</para>
<para>(A) For purposes of subdivision (a)(i) of this subdivision,
a base amount of two million dollars;
and</para>
<para>(B) For the facility's operations and maintenance costs pursuant
to subdivision (a)(ii) of this subdivision, a base amount of eighty-five thousand
dollars for any one fiscal year.</para>
<para>The base amount for the facility's operations
and maintenance costs shall be subject to any inflationary or
market adjustments made by the commission pursuant to this subdivision. The
commission shall adjust the base amount on a biennial basis
beginning January 1, 2010. The adjustments shall
be based on percentage changes in a construction cost index and any other
published index relevant to operations and utilities costs, both as selected
by the commission in cooperation with the public institutions. The index or
indices shall reflect inflationary or market trends for the applicable operations
and maintenance or construction costs;</para>
<para>(2) Commission shall mean the Coordinating Commission for
Postsecondary Education;</para>
<para>(3) Coordination shall mean:</para>
<para>(a) Authority to adopt, and revise as needed, a comprehensive
statewide plan for postsecondary education which shall include (i) definitions
of the role and mission of each public postsecondary educational institution
within any general assignments of role and mission as may be prescribed by
the Legislature and (ii) plans for facilities which utilize tax funds designated
by the Legislature;</para>
<para>(b) Authority to review, monitor, and approve or disapprove
each public postsecondary educational institution's programs and capital construction
projects which utilize tax funds designated by the Legislature in order to
provide compliance and consistency with the comprehensive plan and to prevent
unnecessary duplication; and</para>
<para>(c) Authority to review and modify, if needed to promote compliance
and consistency with the comprehensive statewide plan and prevent unnecessary
duplication, the budget requests of the governing boards or any other governing
board for any other public postsecondary educational institution which may
be established by the Legislature;</para>
<para>(4) Education center shall mean an off-campus branch of a
public institution or cooperative of either public or public and private postsecondary
educational institutions which offers instructional programs to students;</para>
<para>(5) Governing board shall mean the Board of Regents of the
University of Nebraska, the Board of Trustees of the Nebraska State Colleges,
or the board of governors for each community college area;</para>
<para>(6) Program shall mean any program of instruction which leads
directly to a degree, diploma, or certificate and, for purposes of section
85-1414, shall include public service programs and all off-campus instructional
programs, whether or not such programs lead directly to a degree, diploma,
or certificate. Program shall also include the establishment of any new college,
school, major division, education center, or institute but shall not include
reasonable and moderate extensions of existing curricula which have a direct
relationship to existing programs;</para>
<para>(7) Public institution shall mean each campus of a public
postsecondary educational institution which is or may be established by the
Legislature, which is under the direction of a governing board, and which
is administered as a separate unit by the board; and</para>
<para>(8) Tax funds designated by the Legislature shall mean all
state tax revenue and all property tax revenue.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 683, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 816, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 196, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB440, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>