<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id225">
<sectno id="id226">Sec. 7.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id227" statutenumber="85-1503"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id229">85-1503</statuteno><catchline id="id230">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of sections 85-1501 to 85-1540, unless the context
otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Community college means an educational institution operating
and offering programs pursuant to such sections;</para>
<para>(2) Community college area means an area established by section
85-1504;</para>
<para>(3) Board means the Community College Board of Governors
for each community college area;</para>
<para>(4) Full-time equivalent student means, in the aggregate,
the equivalent of a registered student who in a twelve-month period is enrolled
in (a) thirty semester credit hours or forty-five quarter credit hours of
classroom, laboratory, clinical, practicum, or independent study course work
or cooperative work experience or (b) nine hundred contact hours of classroom
or laboratory course work for which credit hours are not offered or awarded.
Avocational and recreational community service programs or courses are not
included in determining full-time equivalent students or student enrollment;</para>
<para>(5) Contact hour means an educational activity consisting
of sixty minutes minus break time and required time to change classes;</para>
<para>(6) Credit hour means the unit used to ascertain the educational
value of course work offered by the institution to students enrolling for
such course work, earned by such students upon successful completion of such
course work, and for which tuition is charged. A credit hour may be offered
and earned in any of several instructional delivery systems, including, but
not limited to, classroom hours, laboratory hours, clinical hours, practicum
hours, cooperative work experience, and independent study. A credit hour shall
consist of a minimum of: (a) Ten quarter or fifteen semester classroom contact
hours per term of enrollment; (b) twenty quarter or thirty semester academic
transfer and academic support laboratory hours per term of enrollment; (c)
thirty quarter or forty-five semester vocational laboratory hours per term
of enrollment; (d) thirty quarter or forty-five semester clinical or practicum
contact hours per term of enrollment; or (e) forty quarter or sixty semester
cooperative work experience contact hours per term of enrollment. An institution
may include in a credit hour more classroom, laboratory, clinical, practicum,
or cooperative work experience hours than the minimum required in this subdivision.
The institution shall publish in its catalog, or otherwise make known to the
student in writing prior to the student enrolling or paying tuition for any
courses, the number of credit or contact hours offered in each such course.
Such published credit or contact hour offerings shall be used to determine
whether a student is a full-time equivalent student pursuant to subdivision
(4) of this section;</para>
<para>(7) Classroom hour means a minimum of fifty minutes of formalized
instruction on campus or off campus in which a qualified instructor applying
any combination of instructional methods such as lecture, directed discussion,
demonstration, or the presentation of audiovisual materials is responsible
for providing an educational experience to students;</para>
<para>(8) Laboratory hour means a minimum of fifty minutes of educational
activity on campus or off campus in which students conduct experiments, perfect
skills, or practice procedures under the direction of a qualified instructor;</para>
<para>(9) Clinical hour means a minimum of fifty minutes of educational
activity on campus or off campus during which the student is assigned practical
experience under constant supervision at a health-related agency, receives
individual instruction in the performance of a particular function, and is
observed and critiqued in the repeat performance of such function. Adjunct
professional personnel, who may or may not be paid by the college, may be
used for the directed supervision of students and for the delivery of part
of the didactic phase of the experience;</para>
<para>(10) Practicum hour means a minimum of fifty minutes of educational
activity on campus or off campus during which the student is assigned practical
experiences, receives individual instruction in the performance of a particular
function, and is observed and critiqued by an instructor in the repeat performance
of such function. Adjunct professional personnel, who may or may not be paid
by the college, may be used for the directed supervision of the students;</para>
<para>(11) Cooperative work experience means an internship or on-the-job
training, designed to provide specialized skills and educational experiences,
which is coordinated, supervised, observed, and evaluated by qualified college
staff or faculty and may be completed on campus or off campus, depending on
the nature of the arrangement;</para>
<para>(12) Independent study means an arrangement between an instructor
and a student in which the instructor is responsible for assigning work activity
or skill objectives to the student, personally providing needed instruction,
assessing the student's progress, and assigning a final grade. Credit hours
shall be assigned according to the practice of assigning credits in similar
courses;</para>
<para>(13) Full-time equivalent student enrollment total means
the total of full-time equivalent students enrolled in a community college
in any fiscal year;</para>
<para>(14) General academic transfer course means a course offering
in a one-year or two-year degree-credit program, at the associate degree level
or below, intended by the offering institution for transfer into a baccalaureate
program. The completion of the specified courses in a general academic transfer
program may include the award of a formal degree;</para>
<para>(15) Applied technology or occupational course means a course
offering in an instructional program, at the associate degree level or below,
intended to prepare individuals for immediate entry into a specific occupation
or career. The primary intent of the institutions offering an applied technology
or occupational program shall be that such program is for immediate job entry.
The completion of the specified courses in an applied technology or occupational
program may include the award of a formal degree, diploma, or certificate;</para>
<para>(16) Academic support course means a general education academic
course offering which may be necessary to support an applied technology or
occupational program;</para>
<para>(17) Class 1 course means an applied technology or occupational
course offering which requires the use of equipment, facilities, or instructional
methods easily adaptable for use in a general academic transfer program classroom
or laboratory;</para>
<para>(18) Class 2 course means an applied technology or occupational
course offering which requires the use of specialized equipment, facilities,
or instructional methods not easily adaptable for use in a general academic
transfer program classroom or laboratory;</para>
<para>(19) Full-time equivalent student means a full-time equivalent student
subject to the following limitation: The number of credit and contact hours
which shall be counted by any community college area in which a tribally controlled
community college is located shall include credit and contact hours awarded
by such tribally controlled community college to students for which such institution
received no federal reimbursement pursuant to the Tribally Controlled Community
College Assistance Act, 25 U.S.C. 1801;</para>
<para>(20) Full-time equivalent total means the total of all full-time
equivalents accumulated in a community college area in any fiscal year;</para>
<para>(21) Reimbursable educational unit means a full-time equivalent
student multiplied by (a) for a general academic transfer course or an academic
support course, a factor of one, (b) for a Class 1 course, a factor of one
and fifty-hundredths, (c) for a Class 2 course, a factor of two, (d) for a
tribally controlled community college general academic transfer course or
academic support course, a factor of two, (e) for a tribally controlled community
college Class 1 course, a factor of three, and (f) for a tribally controlled
community college Class 2 course, a factor of four;</para>
<para>(22) Reimbursable educational unit total means the total
of all reimbursable educational units accumulated in a community college area
in any fiscal year;</para>
<para>(23) Special instructional term means any term which is less
than fifteen weeks for community colleges using semesters or ten weeks for
community colleges using quarters;</para>
<para>(24) Statewide reimbursable full-time equivalent total means
the total of all reimbursable full-time equivalents accumulated statewide
for the community college in any fiscal year;</para>
<para>(25) Tribally controlled community college means an educational
institution operating and offering programs pursuant to the Tribally Controlled
Community College Assistance Act, 25 U.S.C. 1801; and</para>
<para>(26) Tribally controlled community college state aid amount
means:</para>
<para>(a) For fiscal years before fiscal year
2010-11, the quotient of the amount of state aid to be distributed
pursuant to the Community College Foundation and Equalization Aid Act for
the current fiscal year to a community college area in which a tribally controlled
community college is located divided by the reimbursable educational unit
total for such community college area for the immediately preceding fiscal
year, with such quotient then multiplied by the average reimbursable educational
units derived pursuant to subdivision (19) of this section for the immediately
preceding fiscal year; and</para>
<para>(b) For fiscal year 2010-11,
the amount of state aid provided to a tribally controlled community college
pursuant to section 90-517.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 344, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 459, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 363, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 890, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 329, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 802, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 921, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2637; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 241, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 67, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 38, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167;  7.</para><effectivedate>April 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community College Foundation and Equalization Aid Act,</emphasis> see section 85-2201.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of Article VIII, section 1A, of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>