<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id935"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-1440"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1440</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska public postsecondary institutions; submit data; requirements; commission duties.</catchline><para>(1) On or before December 31, 2028, and on or before December 31 of each even-numbered year thereafter, each Nebraska public postsecondary institution shall submit data to the commission including:</para><para>(a) The number of students awarded academic credit based on prior learning examinations during the two preceding academic years; and</para><para>(b) The total number of academic credits awarded based on prior learning examinations during the two preceding academic years.</para><para>(2) The commission shall post the data reported pursuant to subsection (1) of this section on the commission's website.</para><para>(3) On or before December 31, 2029, the commission shall analyze the prior learning examination cut score policies and procedures of each Nebraska public postsecondary institution and the research used by each Nebraska public postsecondary institution in determining the level of credit and the number of credits provided for each prior learning examination qualifying score and file a report that includes findings and recommendations to the Education Committee of the Legislature.</para><para>(4) Each Nebraska public postsecondary institution shall provide the commission with the data necessary to conduct the analysis required pursuant to subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(5) Data shall be provided, analyzed, and posted pursuant to this section in a manner that complies with the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974, as such act existed on January 1, 2026.</para><para>(6) The commission may request the assistance of the Nebraska Statewide Workforce and Education Reporting System for analysis and reporting under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB937, &#167; 24. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>