<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1111"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1111</statuteno><catchline>Private college; provisional accreditation; procedure.</catchline><para>The Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education may provisionally accredit a private college which has not previously been accredited by any regional accrediting association as follows:</para><para>(1) The college shall first make application for such provisional accreditation in such form as the commission may prescribe;</para><para>(2) The commission shall consider the following criteria before taking action on such application:</para><para>(a) The instructional program of the college, which must be similar in quality and content to that offered in accredited public and private colleges within the state;</para><para>(b) The educational and experience qualifications of the administrative and instructional staff must be adequate to fulfill the purposes of the college;</para><para>(c) The physical plant, including provisions for housing and student services, and the instructional equipment of the college must be adequate to carry out the educational program;</para><para>(d) The college must be financially sound and capable of carrying out its commitments; and</para><para>(e) It must be the intent of the college to become accredited by a regional accrediting association and any necessary action to obtain such accreditation must have been taken; and</para><para>(3) Such provisional accreditation shall remain in effect for not more than three years but may be renewed for a like period in the manner provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 513, &#167; 7, p. 1720; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 79-2407; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 141, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 132. </para></source></law></legaldoc>