<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id136">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id138" statutenumber="85-1418"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1418</statuteno><catchline id="id141">Program or
capital construction project; state funds; restrictions on use; district court
of Lancaster County; jurisdiction; appeals; procedure.</catchline><para>(1)
No state warrant shall be issued by the Department of Administrative Services
or used by any public institution for the purpose of funding any program or
capital construction project which has not been approved or which has been
disapproved by the commission pursuant to the Coordinating Commission for
Postsecondary Education Act. If state funding for any such program or project
cannot be or is not divided into warrants separate from other programs or
projects, the department shall reduce a warrant to the public institution
which includes funding for the program or project by the amount of tax funds
designated by the Legislature which are budgeted in that fiscal year by the
public institution for use for the program or project.</para>
<para>(2) The department may reduce the amount of state aid distributed
to a community college area pursuant to the Community College Aid Act, or for
fiscal years 2010-11, 2011-12, and 2012-13 pursuant to section 90-517, by
the amount of funds used by the area to provide a program or capital construction
project which has not been approved or which has been disapproved by the commission.</para>
<para>(3) The district court of Lancaster County shall have jurisdiction
to enforce an order or decision of the commission entered pursuant to the
Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act and to enforce this
section.</para>
<para>(4) Any person or public institution aggrieved by a final
order of the commission entered pursuant to section 85-1413, 85-1414, 85-1415,
or 85-1416 shall be entitled to judicial review of the order. Proceedings
for review shall be instituted by filing a petition in the district court
of Lancaster County within thirty days after public notice of the final decision
by the commission is given. The filing of the petition or the service of summons
upon the commission shall not stay enforcement of such order. The review shall
be conducted by the court without a jury on the record of the commission.
The court shall have jurisdiction to enjoin enforcement of any order of the
commission which is (a) in violation of constitutional provisions, (b) in
excess of the constitutional or statutory authority of the commission, (c)
made upon unlawful procedure, or (d) affected by other error of law.</para>
<para>(5) A party may secure a review of any final judgment of
the district court by appeal to the Court of Appeals. Such appeal shall be
taken in the manner provided by law for appeals in civil cases and shall be
heard de novo on the record.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 360, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB59, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 14.</para><effectivedate>February 14, 2012</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community College Aid Act,</emphasis> see section 85-2231.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>