<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id14">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id16" statutenumber="85-1539"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1539</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Nebraska Community
College Student Performance
and Occupational Education Grant Committee; created; duties.</catchline>
<para>There is hereby created the Nebraska Community College Student Performance and Occupational Education
Grant Committee. The committee shall
consist of (1) a representative of the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary
Education, (2) a representative of the Department of Economic
Development, (3) a representative of the Department of Labor, (4) a representative
of the State Department of Education, (5)
a representative affiliated
with one of the two community college areas with the two smallest full-time
equivalent student enrollment totals for the most recent fiscal year, (6)
a representative affiliated with one of the two community college areas with
the two largest full-time equivalent student enrollment totals for the most
recent fiscal year, and (7) a representative affiliated with one of the two
community college areas not included in the categories provided in subdivisions
(5) and (6) of this section. Each member shall be appointed by the agency
or community college areas being represented. The representatives appointed
pursuant to subdivisions (5) through (7) of this section shall serve terms
of two years and shall be succeeded by a representative affiliated with the
community college areas not represented for the preceding term.</para>
<para>The committee shall develop guidelines for
and annually determine the allocation of the Nebraska Community
College Student Performance and Occupational Education
Grant Fund and any other funds appropriated to Program 99 in Agency
83, Aid to Community Colleges, pursuant to this section and section 85-1540. The
total amount allocated for a fiscal year shall not exceed the amounts appropriated
from the fund and such other funds as may be appropriated by the Legislature
for such fiscal year. The commission shall certify the allocation determined
by the committee on or before September 10 of the fiscal year for which such
allocation is being certified and shall report such allocation to the Department
of Administrative Services. The department shall distribute the total of such
appropriated and allocated funds to the selected community college board or
boards in a single payment between the fifth and twentieth day of October
of the fiscal year for which such allocation is certified.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 305, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2663; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 22.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>