<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-1504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1504</statuteno><catchline>Community college areas, designated.</catchline><para>The state is hereby divided into six community college areas as follows:</para><para>(1) The Western Community College Area shall consist of the following counties: Sioux, Dawes, Sheridan, Box Butte, Scotts Bluff, Banner, Kimball, Morrill, Cheyenne, Garden, Deuel, and Grant and the voting districts of Merriam, Russell, King, Mother Lake, Cody, Barley, Gillaspie, Lackey, and Calf Creek in Cherry County as such voting districts existed on July 1, 1975;</para><para>(2) The Mid-Plains Community College Area shall consist of the following counties: Cherry except as provided in subdivision (1) of this section, Hooker, Thomas, Blaine, Loup, Arthur, McPherson, Logan, Custer, Keith, Lincoln, Perkins, Chase, Hayes, Frontier, Dundy, Hitchcock, and Red Willow;</para><para>(3) The Northeast Community College Area shall consist of the following counties: Keya Paha, Brown, Rock, Boyd, Holt, Garfield, Wheeler, Knox, Cedar, Antelope, Pierce, Madison, Wayne, Stanton, Dixon, Dakota, Thurston, Burt, and Cuming and the precincts of North Oakland, South Oakland, Ashland, North Branch, Shell Creek, and Midland in Boone County as such precincts existed on July 1, 1975;</para><para>(4) The Central Community College Area shall consist of the following counties: Valley, Greeley, Platte, Colfax, Sherman, Howard, Nance, Merrick, Polk, Butler, Dawson, Buffalo, Hall, Hamilton, Gosper, Phelps, Kearney, Adams, Clay, Furnas, Harlan, Franklin, Webster, and Nuckolls and all of Boone County except as provided in subdivision (3) of this section;</para><para>(5) The Southeast Community College Area shall consist of the following counties: Saunders, Cass, York, Seward, Lancaster, Otoe, Fillmore, Saline, Thayer, Jefferson, Gage, Johnson, Nemaha, Pawnee, and Richardson; and</para><para>(6) The Metropolitan Community College Area shall consist of the following counties: Dodge, Washington, Douglas, and Sarpy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 344, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 79-2638; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 596, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of Article VIII, section 1A, of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>