<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1103</statuteno><catchline>Out-of-state institution of higher education; authorized to offer courses or degree programs; conditions; fee; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education shall consider the following factors in determining whether to authorize an out-of-state institution of higher education to offer courses or degree programs in this state:</para><para>(a) The financial soundness of such institution and its capability to fulfill its proposed commitments;</para><para>(b) The quality of teaching faculty, library, and support services, commensurate with tuition or fees charged;</para><para>(c) The demonstrated need and demand for the program in the area to be served;</para><para>(d) The quality of the programs to be offered in the state, including courses, programs of instruction, and degrees;</para><para>(e) The specific locations where programs will be offered or planned locations and a demonstration that facilities are adequate at the locations for the programs to be offered. When an out-of-state institution of higher education designates a planned program location, approval shall be contingent upon designation of a specific location or locations where programs will be offered within a reasonable period of time following commission approval;</para><para>(f) Adequate assurances regarding transfer of credits earned in the program to the main campus of such institution and to other institutions located in Nebraska and elsewhere; and</para><para>(g) Whether such institution and, when appropriate, the program are fully accredited by an accrediting body recognized by the United States Department of Education.</para><para>(2) The commission may charge a reasonable fee based on its administrative costs for registration and authorization and may also adopt and promulgate rules and regulations as may be necessary to carry out this section.</para><para>(3) The commission may revoke or suspend any authorization of an out-of-state institution of higher education to offer a course or degree program in this state upon violation of this section or any agreement submitted for authorization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 141, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 126; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 93, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>