<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-1108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-1108</statuteno><catchline>Proposed college; factors considered; fee; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) In considering the feasibility of the college proposed in a petition under section 85-1105, the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education shall take into account the following factors:</para><para>(a) The need for and the objectives of the proposed college;</para><para>(b) The proposed instructional program and the plan for staffing such a program, including staff qualifications;</para><para>(c) The financial soundness and capability to fulfill its proposed commitments;</para><para>(d) Affirmation of intent to seek appropriate accreditation of the institution by an entity recognized by the United States Department of Education. When any new private college or private postsecondary career school petitions the commission to offer degrees at the baccalaureate or higher degree level, it shall seek accreditation by an accrediting agency which has been approved by the United States Department of Education with the scope to accredit institutions offering programs at such degree levels; and</para><para>(e) Such other pertinent factors as relate to the potential of the proposed college to achieve its objectives or as may be developed at the hearing.</para><para>(2) The commission may charge a reasonable fee based on its administrative costs for review and authorization of petitions and applications made pursuant to sections 85-1105 to 85-1111 and may also adopt and promulgate such rules and regulations as may be necessary to carry out sections 85-1105 to 85-1111.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 513, &#167; 4, p. 1719; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1976), &#167; 79-2404; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 141, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 93, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 816, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 28. </para></source></law></legaldoc>