<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id90"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="85-2002"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2002</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Community College Gap Assistance Program Act:</para><para>(1) Committee means the Nebraska Community College Student Performance and Occupational Education Grant Committee;</para><para>(2) Community college gap assistance program means the program created pursuant to section 85-2003;</para><para>(3) Eligible program means a program offered by a community college that is not offered for credit but is aligned with training programs with stackable credentials that lead to a program awarding college credit, an associate's degree, a diploma, or a certificate in an in-demand occupation, has a duration of not less than sixteen contact hours in length, and does any of the following:</para><para>(a) Offers a state, national, or locally recognized certificate;</para><para>(b) Offers preparation for a professional examination or licensure;</para><para>(c) Provides endorsement for an existing credential or license;</para><para>(d) Represents recognized skill standards defined by an industrial sector; or</para><para>(e) Offers a similar credential or training; and</para><para>(4) In-demand occupation means:</para><para>(a) Financial services;</para><para>(b) Transportation, warehousing, and distribution logistics;</para><para>(c) Precision metals manufacturing;</para><para>(d) Biosciences;</para><para>(e) Renewable energy;</para><para>(f) Agriculture and food processing;</para><para>(g) Business management and administrative services;</para><para>(h) Software and computer services;</para><para>(i) Research, development, and engineering services;</para><para>(j) Health services;</para><para>(k) Hospitality and tourism; and</para><para>(l) Any other industry designated as an in-demand occupation by the committee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB519, &#167; 28. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>