<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id21" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="85-2234"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2234</statuteno><catchline>Allocation of aid.</catchline><para>Aid appropriated pursuant
to the Community College Aid Act for fiscal year 2013-14 and each fiscal year
thereafter shall be allocated among community college areas and tribally controlled
community colleges as follows:</para>
<para>(1) The initial
$87,870,147 appropriated pursuant to the act shall be allocated to community
college areas based on the proportionate share of aid received by each community
college area for fiscal year 2012-13. If the amount appropriated for such
fiscal year exceeds $87,870,147, the excess amount shall be allocated as provided
in subdivisions (2) and (3) of this section. If the amount appropriated for
such fiscal year is less than or equal to $87,870,147, the amount appropriated
shall be allocated to community college areas based on the proportionate share
of aid received by each community college area for fiscal year 2012-13;</para>
<para>(2) Of any amount
remaining after the allocation of aid pursuant to subdivision (1) of this
section, the next amount, up to but not to exceed $500,000, shall be transferred
to the Nebraska Community College Student Performance and Occupational Education
Grant Fund provided for in section 85-1540; and</para><para>(3) Any amount remaining
after the allocations provided for in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section
shall be allocated among the community college areas on the following basis:</para>
<para>(a) Twenty-five
percent of such amount shall be divided equally based on the number of community
college areas designated pursuant to section 85-1504;</para><para>(b) Forty-five percent of
such amount shall be divided based on each community college area's proportionate
share of three-year average full-time equivalent student enrollment. A community
college area's proportionate share of three-year average full-time equivalent
student enrollment shall equal the sum of a community college area's full-time
equivalent student enrollment total for the three fiscal years immediately
preceding the fiscal year for which aid is being calculated divided by three,
with such quotient divided by the quotient resulting from the sum of the full-time
equivalent student enrollment total of all community college areas for the
three fiscal years immediately preceding the fiscal year for which aid is
being calculated divided by three; and</para><para>(c) Thirty percent of such amount shall
be divided based on each community college area's proportionate share of three-year
average reimbursable educational units. A community college area's proportionate
share of three-year average reimbursable educational units shall equal the
sum of a community college area's reimbursable educational unit total for
the three fiscal years immediately preceding the fiscal year for which aid
is being calculated divided by three, with such quotient divided by the quotient
resulting from the sum of the reimbursable educational unit total of all community
college areas for the three fiscal years immediately preceding the fiscal
year for which aid is being calculated divided by three.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>