<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" statutenumber="85-2222"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2222</statuteno><catchline>Legislature; appropriate funds; legislative intent; Department of Revenue; Department of Administrative Services; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature, in an effort to promote quality postsecondary education and to avoid excessive and disproportionate taxation upon the taxable property of each community college area, may appropriate each biennium from such funds as may be available an amount for aid and assistance to the community colleges. The Legislature recognizes that education, as an investment in human resources, is fundamental to the quality of life and the economic prosperity of Nebraskans and that aid to the community colleges furthers these goals. It is the intent of the Legislature that such appropriations reflect the commitment of the Legislature to join with local governing bodies in a strong and continuing partnership to further advance the quality, responsiveness, access, and equity of Nebraska's community colleges and to foster high standards of performance and service so that every citizen, community, and business will have the opportunity to receive quality educational programs and services regardless of the size, wealth, or geographic location of the community college area or tribally controlled community college as defined in section 85-1503 by which that citizen, community, or business is served. Such funds so appropriated by the Legislature shall be allocated, adjusted, and distributed to the community college boards of governors as provided in the Community College Foundation and Equalization Aid Act. </para><para>(2) The Department of Revenue shall certify aid amounts pursuant to the act and report such amounts to the Department of Administrative Services. The Department of Administrative Services shall distribute the total of such appropriated and allocated funds to the boards of governors in ten as nearly as possible equal monthly payments between the fifth and twentieth day of each month beginning in September of each year.</para><para>(3) The Department of Administrative Services shall reduce the amount of the distribution to a board of governors by the amount of funds used by the community college area to provide a program or capital construction project as such term is defined in section 85-1402 which has not been approved or has been disapproved by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education pursuant to the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 344, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 903, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 7, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 459, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 363, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 816, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 890, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 143, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 663, &#167; 48; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 79-2651; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 239, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 241, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 67, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 85-1536; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 22.</para><terminationdate>June 30, 2011</terminationdate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Chapter 79, article 26, the Technical Community College Area Act, is not in violation of Article VIII, section 1A, of the Constitution. State ex rel. Western Technical Com. Col. Area v. Tallon, 196 Neb. 603, 244 N.W.2d 183 (1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>