<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id336"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-2616"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2616</statuteno><catchline>Qualifying child; tuition waiver; conditions; application.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (3) and (4) of this section, a qualifying child of a first responder who satisfies section 85-2612 or of an eligible disabled person who satisfies section 85-2614 shall be entitled to a tuition waiver as provided in section 85-2620 from any state university, state college, or community college for an associate or baccalaureate degree program if the qualifying child:</para><para>(a) Meets all admission requirements of the state university, state college, or community college;</para><para>(b) Executes an agreement in accordance with section 85-2617;</para><para>(c) Has not previously earned a baccalaureate degree;</para><para>(d) Completes and submits to the United States Department of Education a Free Application for Federal Student Aid;</para><para>(e) Submits a document to the state university, state college, or community college confirming that the qualifying child has satisfied subdivision (1)(d) of this section. Such document shall be submitted in a form and manner as prescribed by the university, college, or community college;</para><para>(f) Submits the certificate of verification required by subsection (2) of this section; and</para><para>(g) Files with the Department of Revenue documentation showing proof that, for each year in which the qualifying child applies for and receives the tuition waiver, the first responder or eligible disabled person through whom the qualifying child is claiming the tuition waiver:</para><para>(i) Is employed as a first responder or is an eligible disabled person, as applicable; and</para><para>(ii) Resides in Nebraska.</para><para>(2)(a) An application for the tuition waiver shall include a certificate of verification from:</para><para>(i) The first responder's superior officer attesting to such first responder's satisfaction of section 85-2612; or</para><para>(ii) The eligible disabled person's former superior officer attesting to such person's satisfaction of section 85-2614.</para><para>(b) The applicant shall include the certificate of verification when applying to the state university, state college, or community college in order to obtain a tuition waiver upon initial enrollment.</para><para>(3) The death of a first responder in the line of duty that occurs after submission of an application for a tuition waiver shall not disqualify such first responder's otherwise eligible qualifying child from receiving the tuition waiver. In such case:</para><para>(a) In lieu of submitting the certificate of verification provided for in subsection (2) of this section, the qualifying child shall submit a certificate of verification from the first responder's superior officer attesting that:</para><para>(i) At the time of such death, such first responder satisfied section 85-2612; and</para><para>(ii) Such first responder died in the line of duty; and</para><para>(b) In lieu of making the filing required by subdivision (1)(g) of this section, the qualifying child shall file with the Department of Revenue documentation showing proof that, at the time of such death:</para><para>(i) Such first responder was employed as a first responder; and</para><para>(ii) Such first responder resided in Nebraska.</para><para>(4) For a qualifying child of a first responder who is a correctional officer or a youth detention officer or of an eligible disabled person who was a correctional officer or a youth detention officer, the tuition waiver shall only be available beginning July 1, 2027, and shall only be available for attendance at a state university.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB608, &#167; 9. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>