<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id930"><amendatorysection statutenumber="85-2603" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2603</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officer; waiver of tuition; application; certificate of verification; notice of eligibility or ineligibility; contents.</catchline><para>(1) A law enforcement officer shall be entitled to a waiver of thirty percent of the resident tuition charges of any state university, state college, or community college if the officer:</para><para>(a) Maintains satisfactory performance with his or her law enforcement agency;</para><para>(b) Meets all admission requirements of the state university, state college, or community college; and</para><para>(c) Pursues studies leading to a degree that relates to a career in law enforcement from an associate degree program or a baccalaureate degree program.</para><para>The officer may receive the tuition waiver for up to five years if he or she otherwise continues to be eligible for participation.</para><para>(2) The state university, state college, or community college shall waive thirty percent of the officer’s tuition remaining due after subtracting awarded federal financial aid grants and state scholarships and grants for an eligible law enforcement officer during the time the officer is enrolled. To remain eligible, the officer must comply with all requirements of the institution for continued attendance and award of an associate degree or a baccalaureate degree.</para><para>(3) An application for the tuition waiver shall include a verification of the law enforcement officer’s satisfactory performance as a law enforcement officer. It shall be the responsibility of the officer to obtain a certificate of verification from his or her superior officer in such officer’s law enforcement agency attesting to such officer’s satisfactory performance. The officer shall include the certificate of verification when applying to the state university, state college, or community college in order to obtain tuition waiver upon initial enrollment.</para><para>(4) Within forty-five days after receipt of a completed application, the state university, state college, or community college shall send written notice of the law enforcement officer’s eligibility or ineligibility for the tuition waiver. If the officer is determined not to be eligible for the tuition waiver, the notice shall include the reason or reasons for such determination and an indication that an appeal of the determination may be made pursuant to the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB906, &#167; 3. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para> </crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>