
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" id="id127"  statutenumber="85-2418"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2418</statuteno><catchline>Complaint authorized; commission;
hearing; notice; cease and desist order; additional actions authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any person claiming damage or loss as a result of any act or practice
by a postsecondary institution which is a violation of the Postsecondary Institution
Act, of the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, or
of standards established pursuant to section 85-2406 may file with the commission
a complaint against such institution. The complaint shall set forth the alleged
violation and shall contain such other information as may be required by the
commission. A complaint may also be filed with the commission by the executive
director or the Attorney General.</para>
<para>(2) If efforts by the commission to resolve the complaint are not successful
and if the commission deems it appropriate, the commission may hold a hearing
on such complaint after ten days' written notice by certified mail, return
receipt requested, to such institution, giving notice of a time and place
for the hearing on such complaint. Such hearing shall be conducted in accordance
with the Administrative Procedure Act. If, upon all evidence at the hearing,
the commission finds that a postsecondary institution has engaged in or is
engaging in any act or practice which violates the Postsecondary Institution
Act, the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, or the
standards established pursuant to section 85-2406, the commission shall issue
and cause to be served upon such institution an order requiring such institution
to cease and desist from such act or practice. The commission may also, as
appropriate, based on its own investigation or the evidence adduced at such
hearing or both, commence an action:</para>
<para>(a) To revoke an institution's recurrent authorization
to operate; or</para>
<para>(b) To refer the complaint and all related evidence to the Attorney
General.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB637, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1104, &#167; 24.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>