<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id57" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="85-2406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2406</statuteno><catchline>Rules and regulations; minimum standards;
established.</catchline><para>The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules
and regulations to establish minimum standards according to which a postsecondary
institution shall have a recurrent authorization to
operate within the state, and upon failure to operate according to such standards,
the postsecondary institution shall be subject to the suspension or revocation
of the authorization to operate. An institution shall demonstrate that it
can be maintained and operated in accordance with such standards. The standards
shall include, but not be limited to:</para>
<para>(1) The financial soundness of the institution and its capability to
fulfill its proposed commitments and sustain its operations;</para>
<para>(2) The quality and adequacy of teaching faculty, library services,
and support services;</para>
<para>(3) The quality of the programs offered, including courses, programs
of instruction, degrees, any necessary clinical placements, and the institution's
ability to generate and sustain enrollment;</para>
<para>(4) The specific locations where programs will be offered or planned
locations and a demonstration that facilities are adequate at the locations
for the programs to be offered;</para>
<para>(5) Assurances regarding transfer of credits earned in the program to
the main campus of such institution and clear and accurate representations
about the transferability of credits to other institutions located in Nebraska
and elsewhere;</para>
<para>(6) Whether such institution and, when appropriate, the program, are
fully accredited, or seeking accreditation, by an accrediting body recognized
by the United States Department of Education;</para>
<para>(7) The institution's policies and procedures related to students, including,
but not limited to, recruiting and admissions practices;</para>
<para>(8) The tuition refund policy for an institution that does not participate
in federal financial aid programs described in Title IV of the federal Higher
Education Act of 1965, 20 U.S.C. 1001 et seq., as such act existed on January
1, 2011; and</para>
<para>(9) Any other standards deemed necessary by the commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB637, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1104, &#167; 15.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>