<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id125">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id127" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="85-2418"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>85-2418</statuteno><catchline>Complaint authorized; commission;
hearing; notice; cease and desist order; additional actions authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any person
claiming damage or loss as a result of any act or practice by a postsecondary
institution which is a violation of the Postsecondary Institution Act, of
the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, or of standards
established pursuant to section 85-2406 may file with the commission a complaint
against such institution. The complaint shall set forth the alleged violation
and shall contain such other information as may be required by the commission.
A complaint may also be filed with the commission by the executive director
or the Attorney General.</para>
<para>(2) If efforts
by the commission to resolve the complaint are not successful and if the commission
deems it appropriate, the commission may hold a hearing on such complaint
after ten days' written notice by certified mail, return receipt requested,
to such institution, giving notice of a time and place for the hearing on
such complaint. Such hearing shall be conducted in accordance with the Administrative
Procedure Act. If, upon all evidence at the hearing, the commission finds
that a postsecondary institution has engaged in or is engaging in any act
or practice which violates the Postsecondary Institution Act, the rules and
regulations adopted and promulgated under the act, or the standards established
pursuant to section 85-2406, the commission shall issue and cause to be served
upon such institution an order requiring such institution to cease and desist
from such act or practice. The commission may also, as appropriate, based
on its own investigation or the evidence adduced at such hearing or both,
commence an action:</para><para>(a) To revoke an institution's authorization to operate if the
institution does not have an authorization to operate on a continuing basis;
or</para><para>(b)
To refer the complaint and all related evidence to the Attorney General.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB637, &#167; 18.</para><effectivedate>May 5, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>