<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id31">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Uni., State Colleges, and Post. Education" id="id33" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="85-2233"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2233</statuteno><catchline id="id36">Legislative intent;
Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education; duties; reduction of
distribution; when.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Legislature recognizes
that education, as an investment in human resources, is fundamental to the
quality of life and the economic prosperity of Nebraskans and that aid to
the community colleges furthers these goals.</para>
<para>(b) It is the intent of the Legislature that such appropriations
reflect the commitment of the Legislature to join with local governing bodies
in a strong and continuing partnership to further advance the quality, responsiveness,
access, and equity of Nebraska's community colleges and to foster high standards
of performance and service so that every citizen, community, and business
will have the opportunity to receive quality educational programs and services
regardless of the size, wealth, or geographic location of the community college
area or tribally controlled community college by which that citizen, community,
or business is served.</para>
<para>(c) In order to promote quality postsecondary education and
to avoid excessive and disproportionate taxation upon the taxable property
of each community college area, the Legislature may appropriate each biennium
from such funds as may be available an amount for aid and assistance to the
community colleges. Such funds so appropriated by the Legislature shall be
allocated, adjusted, and distributed to the community college boards of governors
as provided in the Community College Aid Act.</para>
<para>(2) The Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education
shall certify aid amounts attributable to the allocations pursuant to subdivisions
(1) and (3) of section 85-2234 and report such amounts to the Department of
Administrative Services. The commission shall certify such aid amounts on
or before September 1 of the fiscal year for which aid is being certified and shall distribute the total
of such appropriated and allocated funds to the boards in ten as nearly as
possible equal monthly payments between the fifth and twentieth day of each
month beginning in September of each year.</para>
<para>(3) Beginning July 1, 2013, the commission shall
reduce the amount of the distribution to a board by the amount of funds used
by the community college area to provide a program or capital construction
project as defined in section 85-1402 which has not been approved or has been
disapproved by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education pursuant
to the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB211, &#167; 6.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2013</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education Act,</emphasis> see section 85-1401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>