<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, And Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-2009"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2009</statuteno><catchline>Community College Gap Assistance Program Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Community College Gap Assistance Program Fund is created. The fund shall be under the direction of the committee and shall be administered by the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education. The fund shall consist of money received pursuant to section 79-3501, any other money received by the state in the form of grants or gifts from nonfederal sources, such other amounts as may be transferred or otherwise accrue to the fund, and any investment income earned on the fund. The fund shall be used to carry out the community college gap assistance program pursuant to the Community College Gap Assistance Program Act. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) In addition to community college gap assistance awarded to students, money in the fund may also be used by the committee:</para><para>(a) To establish application and funding procedures; and</para><para>(b) To assist other eligible institutions as specified in contracts entered into pursuant to subsection (4) of section 85-2010 in defraying the costs of direct staff support services, including, but not limited to, marketing, outreach, applications, interviews, and assessments related to the community college gap assistance program.</para><para>(3) Each community college may use up to ten percent of any money received from the fund to defray the costs of direct staff support services, including, but not limited to, marketing, outreach, applications, interviews, and assessments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB519, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB528, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 121. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>