<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id527"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-2703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2703</statuteno><catchline>Veteran and Active Duty Supportive; designation; department; establish process; criteria; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall establish a process for a postsecondary institution to apply to the director to be designated as Veteran and Active Duty Supportive.</para><para>(2) To be eligible to be designated as Veteran and Active Duty Supportive, a postsecondary institution shall meet at least five of the following criteria, with respect to its operations in this state:</para><para>(a) The institution shall have personnel specifically trained and assigned to work with military students and veteran students;</para><para>(b) The institution shall have a student organization that is dedicated to helping veterans, active duty military, and their families;</para><para>(c) The institution shall give college credit for certain types of military training;</para><para>(d) The institution shall have a military leave-of-absence policy;</para><para>(e) The institution shall have counseling and advising services for military students and veteran students;</para><para>(f) The institution shall have an accredited Reserve Officer Training Corps program;</para><para>(g) The institution shall have clearly identifiable on its website a listing of services provided to military students and veteran students; and</para><para>(h) The institution shall specially recognize military students and veteran students during graduation or in other ways which are intended to demonstrate the institution's respect for such students' service.</para><para>(3) The department shall maintain on its website a list of postsecondary institutions designated as Veteran and Active Duty Supportive pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB486, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>