<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" id="id5" statutenumber="85-2105"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>85-2105</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Applicant; application;
contents; commission; powers and duties; educational institution receiving
payment; report required.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for the
Access College Early Scholarship Program shall complete an application form
developed and provided by the commission and shall submit the
form to his or her guidance counselor or
other official designated by the school. Such application shall
include, but not be limited to, the applicant's high school, social security
number, date of birth, grade point average, grade level, qualified postsecondary
educational institution, and information necessary to determine the student's
eligibility. The guidance counselor or
other official designated by the school shall verify the student's
eligibility under the Access College Early Scholarship Program Act and shall
forward the application to the commission for review within fifteen days following
receipt of the form from the student. Notification of tuition and mandatory
fees to be accrued by the student shall be provided to the commission by the
student, high school, or qualified postsecondary educational institution as
determined by the commission.</para>
<para>(2) The commission shall review the application and verify
the student's eligibility under the act. The commission shall notify the student
and the student's guidance counselor or
other official designated by the school of the verification of
eligibility and the estimated award amount in writing within thirty days following
receipt of the form from the student's guidance counselor or other official designated by the school.
The scholarship award shall equal the lesser of tuition and mandatory fees
accrued by the student after any discounts applicable to such student from
the qualified postsecondary educational institution or the tuition and mandatory
fees that would have been accrued by the student for the same number of credit
hours if the student were taking the course as a full-time, resident, undergraduate
student from the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. The commission shall forward
such amount directly to the qualified postsecondary educational institution
as payment of such student's tuition and mandatory fees.</para>
<para>(3) The commission shall make such payments in the order the
applications are received, except that the commission may limit the number
of scholarships awarded in each term.</para>
<para>(4) The commission may limit the number of scholarships a
student may receive.</para>
<para>(5) For any student receiving a scholarship pursuant to the
act for tuition and mandatory fees, the qualified postsecondary educational
institution receiving the payment shall report either the student's grade
for the course or the student's failure to complete the course to the commission
within thirty days after the end of the course or within one hundred eighty
days after receipt of a payment pursuant to the act if the course for which
the scholarship was awarded does not have a specified ending date. The commission
shall keep the identity of students receiving scholarships confidential, except
as necessary to comply with the requirements of the act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB192, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB20, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB637, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB332, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>