<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State University State Colleges and Postsecondary Education" id="id71" statutenumber="85-3105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-3105</statuteno><catchline id="id74">Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program; administration; eligible students.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall administer the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program either directly or by contracting with public or private entities.</para><para>(2) To be eligible for the program, an eligible student shall:</para><para>(a) Graduate in the top quarter of his or her high school class or have a minimum cumulative grade-point average of 3.0 on a four-point scale in an eligible institution;</para><para>(b) Agree to complete a teacher education program at an eligible institution and to complete the major on which the applicant's eligibility is based; and</para><para>(c) Commit to teach in an accredited or approved public or private school in Nebraska upon (i) successful completion of the teacher education program for which the applicant is applying to the Attracting Excellence to Teaching Program and (ii) becoming certified pursuant to sections 79-806 to 79-815.</para><para>(3) An eligible student may apply on an annual basis for a loan in an amount of not more than three thousand dollars per year, except that an eligible student who is enrolling for a student-teaching semester may apply for an additional loan of up to three thousand dollars for the student-teaching semester and receive up to a total of six thousand dollars for the year. Loans awarded to individual students shall not exceed a cumulative period exceeding five consecutive years. Loans shall only be awarded through an eligible institution. Loans shall be funded pursuant to section 85-3112.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1399, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 685, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB547, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2014), &#167; 79-8,135; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1284, &#167; 19. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>