<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id243"><amendatorysection chaptername="State University, State Colleges, and Postsecondary Education" statutenumber="85-3102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>85-3102</statuteno><catchline>Transfer of powers, duties, and functions to Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education; financial obligations; contracts; documents; funds; appropriations; suit, action, or other proceeding; records; transfer; effect.</catchline><para>(1) On and after July 1, 2024, all powers, duties, and functions that the State Department of Education had pursuant to the Excellence in Teaching Act prior to such date are transferred to the Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education.</para><para>(2) Any financial obligations of the State Department of Education relating to the Excellence in Teaching Act that remain unpaid as of July 1, 2024, and that are subsequently certified as valid encumbrances to the accounting division of the Department of Administrative Services pursuant to sections 81-138.01 to 81-138.04, shall be paid by the commission from any unexpended balance in the Excellence in Teaching Cash Fund.</para><para>(3) On and after July 1, 2024, whenever the State Department of Education is referred to or designated by any contract or other document in connection with any duties and functions under the Excellence in Teaching Act, such reference or designation shall apply to the commission. All contracts entered into by the State Department of Education prior to July 1, 2024, in connection with any duties and functions under the Excellence in Teaching Act are hereby recognized, with the commission succeeding to all rights and obligations under such contracts. Any cash funds, custodial funds, gifts, trusts, and grants and any appropriations of funds from prior fiscal years available to satisfy obligations incurred under such contracts shall be transferred and appropriated to the commission for the payment of such obligations. All documents and records transferred, or copies of the same, may be authenticated or certified by the commission for all legal purposes.</para><para>(4) No suit, action, or other proceeding, judicial or administrative, lawfully commenced prior to July 1, 2024, or which could have been commenced prior to such date, by or against the State Department of Education, the Commissioner of Education, or any employee of the State Department of Education, in relation to the discharge of duties under the Excellence in Teaching Act, shall abate by reason of the transfer of duties and functions under the Excellence in Teaching Act from the State Department of Education to the commission.</para><para>(5) On July 1, 2024, all documents and records of the State Department of Education pertaining to duties and functions under the Excellence in Teaching Act shall be transferred to the commission and shall become the property of the commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB705, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>