<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds And Oaths, Official" statutenumber="11-112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>11-112</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; terms.</catchline><para>All official bonds shall obligate the principal and sureties for the faithful discharge of all duties required by law of such principal, and shall inure to the benefit of any persons injured by a breach of the conditions of such bonds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 13, &#167; 12, p. 97; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5718; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5048; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 12-112; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 11-112. </para></source><annotation><para>Sheriff and surety on his official bond are required to respond in damages to any person for a breach of duty imposed by law. O'Dell v. Goodsell, 149 Neb. 261, 30 N.W.2d 906 (1948).</para><para>Statute, by construction, constitutes part of bond, and the scope of statutory obligation cannot validly be limited by any other provision in the instrument. Village of Hampton v. Gausman, 136 Neb. 550, 286 N.W. 757 (1939).</para><para>County judge is liable on his official bond for trust funds lost by reason of insolvency of bank in which he deposited them though he acted in good faith and without negligence in selecting depository. Ericsson v. Streitz, 132 Neb. 692, 273 N.W. 17 (1937).</para><para>Recovery authorized thereon by person injured by negligent acts committed by policeman in exercise of municipal authority, although bond runs to city as obligee. Curnyn v. Kinney, 119 Neb. 478, 229 N.W. 894 (1930).</para><para>A bond given for the faithful discharge of the duties of one legally entrusted with state and county funds is an official bond, and the statutory provisions relative thereto enter and become a part of the contract. United States Fidelity &amp; Guaranty Co. v. McLaughlin, 76 Neb. 307, 107 N.W. 577 (1906).</para><para>This section requires of a principal, who is a custodian of public money, the absolute accounting for and payment over of money coming into his official position. Adams v. Weisberger, 62 Neb. 326, 87 N.W. 16 (1901).</para><para>Money paid to the clerk of district court by referee in partition proceeding, in obedience to court order directing money to be brought into court, is received by the clerk in his official capacity. Dirks v. Juel, 59 Neb. 353, 80 N.W. 1045 (1899).</para><para>Counties may recover on official bonds of their officers for all damages caused by their neglect of duty. Toncray v. Dodge County, 33 Neb. 802, 51 N.W. 235 (1892).</para><para>Liability on bond is original and primary, and action may be brought against both principal and sureties without suit having first been brought against the officer for the tort. Kane v. Union Pacific Railroad, 5 Neb. 105 (1876).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>