<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<sectno id="id5">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Bonds and Oaths, Official" id="id6" statutenumber="11-119"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">11-119</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Bonds; officers;
penal sums.</catchline><para>The following named officers shall
execute a bond with penalties of the following amounts:</para>
<para>(1) The Governor, one hundred thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(2) The Lieutenant Governor, one hundred thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(3) The Auditor of Public Accounts, one hundred thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(4) The Secretary of State, one hundred thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(5) The Attorney General, one hundred thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(6) The State Treasurer, not less than one million dollars
and not more than double the amount of money that may come into his or her
hands, to be fixed by the Governor;</para>
<para>(7) Each county attorney, a sum not less than one thousand
dollars to be fixed by the county board;</para>
<para>(8) Each clerk of the district court, not less than five thousand
dollars or more than one hundred thousand dollars to be determined by the
county board;</para>
<para>(9) Each county clerk, not less than one thousand dollars
or more than one hundred thousand dollars to be determined by the county board,
except that when a county clerk also has the duties of other county offices
the minimum bond shall be two thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(10) Each county treasurer, not less than ten thousand dollars
and not more than the amount of money that may come into his or her hands,
to be determined by the county board;</para>
<para>(11) Each sheriff, in counties of not more than twenty thousand
inhabitants, five thousand dollars, and in counties over twenty thousand inhabitants,
ten thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(12) Each district superintendent of public instruction, one
thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(13) Each county surveyor, five hundred dollars;</para>
<para>(14) Each county commissioner or supervisor, in counties of
not more than twenty thousand inhabitants, one thousand dollars, in counties
over twenty thousand and not more than thirty thousand inhabitants, two thousand
dollars, in counties over thirty thousand and not more than fifty thousand
inhabitants, three thousand dollars, and in counties over fifty thousand inhabitants,
five thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(15) Each register of deeds in counties having a population
of more than sixteen thousand five hundred inhabitants, not less than two
thousand dollars or more than one hundred thousand dollars to be determined
by the county board;</para>
<para>(16) Each township clerk, two hundred fifty dollars;</para>
<para>(17) Each township treasurer, two thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(18) Each county assessor, not more than five thousand dollars
and not less than two thousand dollars;</para>
<para>(19) Each school district treasurer, not less than five hundred
dollars or more than double the amount of money that may come into his or
her hands, the amount to be fixed by the president and secretary of the district;</para>
<para>(20) Each road overseer, two hundred fifty dollars;</para>
<para>(21) Each member of a county weed district board and the manager
thereof, such amount as may be determined by the county board of commissioners
or supervisors of each county with the same amount to apply to each member
of any particular board;</para>
<para>(22) In any county, in lieu of the individual bonds required
to be furnished by county officers, a schedule, position, or blanket bond
or undertaking may be given by county officers, or a single corporate surety
fidelity, schedule, position, or blanket bond or undertaking covering all
the officers, including officers required by law to furnish an individual
bond or undertaking, may be furnished. The county may pay the premium for
the bond. The bond shall be, at a minimum, an aggregate of the amounts fixed
by law or by the person or board authorized by law to fix the amounts, and
with such terms and conditions as may be required by sections 11-101 to 11-130; and</para>
<para>(23) Each learning
community coordinating council treasurer, not less than five hundred dollars
or more than double the amount of money that may come into his or her hands,
the amount to be fixed by the learning community coordinating council.</para>
<para>All other state officers, department heads, and employees
shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1881, c. 13, &#167; 19, p. 98; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 11, &#167; 1, p. 63; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 12, &#167; 1, p. 66; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5725; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 110, &#167; 1, p. 282; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5055; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 156, &#167; 1, p. 417; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 12-119; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 115, &#167; 1, p. 460; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 105; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 12-119; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 11-119; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 16, &#167; 4, p. 97; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 14, &#167; 1, p. 89; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 206; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 538, &#167; 31, p. 1716; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 160; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 52, &#167; 1, p. 350; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 298, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 226, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 7, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 103, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 369, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1030, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 179, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 272, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Elected county officials are required to give individual official bonds. Blanket bond is not sufficient. Foote v. County of Adams, 163 Neb. 406, 80 N.W.2d 179 (1956).</para><para>Deputy attorney general is required to give bond while assistant attorney general is not. Carlsen v. State, 127 Neb. 11, 254 N.W. 744 (1934).</para><para>Approval of bond in double amount required for particular office will not be compelled by mandamus. State ex rel. Baird v. Slattery, 108 Neb. 415, 187 N.W. 899 (1922).</para><para>The amendment of 1901 to this section was unconstitutional because broader than title. Prowett v. Nance County, 82 Neb. 400, 117 N.W. 996 (1908); Knight v. Lancaster County, 74 Neb. 82, 103 N.W. 1064 (1905).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>