<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Bonds And Oaths, Official" statutenumber="11-123"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>11-123</statuteno><catchline>Bonds; guaranty companies; eligibility; approval.</catchline><para>Whenever any recognizance, stipulation, bond or undertaking, conditioned for the faithful performance of any duty or for doing or refraining from doing anything in such recognizance, stipulation, bond or undertaking specified, is, by the laws of this state, required or permitted to be given with one surety or with two or more sureties, the execution of the same, or the guaranteeing of the performance of the conditions thereof, shall be sufficient when executed or guaranteed solely by a corporation duly organized and existing under the laws of this state, or of any state of the United States, having a paid-up capital of not less than one hundred thousand dollars and having power under its charter to guarantee or insure the fidelity of persons holding places of public and private trust, to become surety on bonds and obligations of persons and corporations, and to become surety on any bond, recognizance or other writing in the nature of a bond, in the same manner that natural persons may, subject to all the rights and liabilities of such persons; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> such corporation is approved as surety upon such recognizance, stipulation, bond or undertaking by the head of the department, court, judge, officer, board or body executive, legislative or judicial, required or authorized to approve or accept the same.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 122; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5728; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5058; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 12-122; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 98, &#167; 3, p. 327; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 12-122; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 11-123. </para></source><annotation><para>This section as originally enacted in 1895 was unconstitutional. Fidelity &amp; Deposit Co. of Maryland v. Libby, 72 Neb. 850, 101 N.W. 994 (1904).</para><para>Surety company must be empowered to transact business in Nebraska before mandamus will lie to compel approval of bond. Woodward v. State ex rel. Thomssen, 58 Neb. 598, 79 N.W. 164 (1899).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>