<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Money and Financing" statutenumber="58-270"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>58-270</statuteno><catchline>Authority; reports; contents; audit; issuance of bonds; notices.</catchline><para>(1) The authority shall, following the close of each fiscal year, submit a report of its activities for the preceding year to the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature of this state. Each member of the Legislature shall receive a copy of such report by making a request for it to the chairperson of the authority. Each report shall set forth a complete operating and financial statement for the authority during the fiscal year it covers. An independent certified public accountant shall at least once in each year audit the books and accounts of the authority.</para><para>(2) At least fourteen days prior to taking any final action to authorize the issuance of bonds to provide financing for projects, the beneficiaries or borrowers of which are not specifically identified, the authority shall notify the Governor, the Clerk of the Legislature, and any news media requesting notification of such proposed issuance of bonds. Such notice shall include:</para><para>(a) The public purposes to be effectuated and the needs to be addressed through the issuance of the bonds;</para><para>(b) The manner in which such need was identified;</para><para>(c) The anticipated principal amount of the bond issue and the anticipated date of issuance of the bonds;</para><para>(d) The anticipated size of any reserve funds; and</para><para>(e) The professionals involved in connection with the issuance of the bonds.</para><para>(3) Within thirty days following the issuance of bonds subject to subsection (2) of this section, the authority shall notify the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature of:</para><para>(a) The final principal amount of the bonds;</para><para>(b) The net interest cost of the bonds;</para><para>(c) The costs of issuance paid and to whom paid;</para><para>(d) The total amount of any reserve funds;</para><para>(e) The net interest cost to the beneficiaries or borrowers; and</para><para>(f) The amount of funds available for loans.</para><para>(4) With respect to bonds subject to subsection (2) of this section, until ninety-five percent of the proceeds of such bonds to be made available for loans are so used or a corresponding amount of such bonds are redeemed, the authority shall, no less often than quarterly after the issuance of such bonds, report to the Governor and the Clerk of the Legislature the status of the use of the proceeds of such issue of bonds.</para><para>Once the notice required pursuant to subsection (2) of this section is filed, nothing in this section shall require the authority to amend or supplement the notice prior to the issuance of the bonds.</para><para>(5) The notice and reporting requirements contained in this section shall be deemed satisfied upon good faith compliance by the authority. The failure to comply with any part of this section shall not affect the validity of any bonds issued by the authority.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 626, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 372, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 253, &#167; 67. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 