<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Money And Financing" id="id423" statutenumber="58-855"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>58-855</statuteno><catchline id="id426">Act; supplemental to other laws.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Educational, Health, Cultural, and Social Services Finance Authority Act shall be deemed to provide a complete, additional, and alternative method for doing the things authorized in the act and shall be regarded as supplemental and additional to powers conferred by other laws. The issuance of bonds and refunding bonds under the act need not comply with the requirements of any other law applicable to the issuance of bonds, and the acquisition, construction, improvement, equipment, and renovation of a project pursuant to the act by the authority need not comply with the requirements of any competitive bidding law or other restriction imposed on the procedure for award of contracts for the acquisition, construction, improvement, equipment, and renovation of a project or the lease, sale, or disposition of property of the authority, except that if the prospective lessee so requests in writing, the authority shall call for construction bids in such manner as shall be determined by the authority with the approval of such lessee. Except as otherwise expressly provided in the act, none of the powers granted to the authority under the act shall be subject to the supervision of or regulation by or require the approval or consent of any municipality, commission, board, body, bureau, official, or other political subdivision or agency of the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 321, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 465, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2952; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 5, &#167; 52; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 85-1752; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB170, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB224, &#167; 33. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>