<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id45">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Money and Financing" id="id47" statutenumber="58-702"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>58-702</statuteno><catchline id="id50">Legislative findings.</catchline>
<para>The Legislature finds that current economic conditions, lack
of available affordable housing, federal housing policies that have placed
an increasing burden on the state, and declining resources at all levels of
government adversely affect the ability of Nebraska's citizens to obtain safe,
decent, and affordable housing. Lack of affordable housing also affects the
ability of communities to maintain and develop viable and stable economies.</para>
<para>Furthermore, the Legislature finds that impediments exist
to the construction and rehabilitation of affordable housing. Local codes
and state statutes have an important effect on housing's affordability by
placing increased costs on developers. Financing affordable housing, especially
in rural areas and smaller communities, is becoming increasingly difficult. In addition, existing dilapidated housing
stock and industrial buildings are detrimental to new affordable housing development
and the general health and safety of people living and working in or around
such places. An affordable housing trust fund would assist all
Nebraska communities in financing affordable housing projects and other projects which make the community safer for residents.</para>
<para>To enhance the economic development of the state and to provide
for the general prosperity of all of Nebraska's citizens, it is in the public
interest to assist in the provision of safe, decent, and affordable housing
in all areas of the state. The establishment of the Nebraska Affordable Housing
Act will assist in creating conditions favorable to meeting the affordable
housing needs of the state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1322, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB388, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
