<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id856"><amendatorysection chaptername="Money and Financing" statutenumber="58-274"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>58-274</statuteno><catchline>Authority; administration of grant or loan program; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, public funds has the same meaning as in section 81-11,106.</para><para>(2) If the authority administers any grant or loan program involving public funds pursuant to an agreement with a state agency, the following requirements shall apply:</para><para>(a) The authority shall provide information regarding such grant or loan program and the public funds involved in such program to such state agency, upon such agency's request, in order to allow the state agency to comply with its responsibilities under section 81-1113;</para><para>(b) The authority shall record information regarding such grant or loan program and the public funds involved in such program in an accounting system. The information to be recorded in the accounting system shall include:</para><para>(i) All revenue and fund balances relating to such public funds;</para><para>(ii) All expenditures of such public funds, including the amount of all grant and loan awards; and</para><para>(iii) All schedules of uses of funds, including all invoices and other supporting documentation, that are submitted by grant or loan recipients under such grant or loan program, except that the requirement to include such schedules and documentation shall apply only to the extent such information is in the possession of the authority; and</para><para>(c) The authority shall allow such state agency, the Legislative Fiscal Analyst, and the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services to have access to the accounting system described in subdivision (2)(b) of this section, upon request.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB768, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>