<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Money And Financing" statutenumber="58-704"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>58-704</statuteno><catchline>Housing advisory committee; created; members; duties; meetings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that the development of operational rules and regulations and an appropriate source of funding is critical to the success of the Affordable Housing Trust Fund. A housing advisory committee is created to address issues related to the operation of the fund and to recommend a plan to coordinate low-income housing efforts throughout the state. On or before December 15, 1996, the committee shall recommend to the Legislature and the Governor the most viable revenue source or sources for the funding of the fund. The committee shall also recommend for public review proposals for rules and regulations to carry out the fund, including time limitations for the use of financial assistance and limitations on the administrative costs of proposed projects. For administrative purposes, the committee shall be located in the Department of Economic Development.</para><para>(2) The committee shall consist of fifteen members who represent a wide range of interests associated with the development and sales of housing. The Governor shall appoint the members and a chairperson and vice-chairperson from the members. The committee may be a committee or council previously created by statute or executive order of the Governor. The Governor shall attempt to have the nonprofit and for-profit communities equally represented on the advisory committee.</para><para>(3) The committee shall meet at the call of the chairperson or a majority of the members. The chairperson shall call such meetings as he or she determines necessary to fulfill the duties of the committee. A quorum shall be one-half of the members.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1322, &#167; 14. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 