<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id100">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Money And Financing" id="id102" statutenumber="58-814"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>58-814</statuteno><catchline id="id105">Authority; members; qualifications; appointment; terms; removal.</catchline><para>(1) The
authority shall consist of seven members, to be appointed by the Governor,
who shall be residents of the state, not more than four of whom shall be members
of the same political party.</para>
<para>(2) Of the
seven members:</para><para>(a) At
least one shall
be a trustee, director, officer, or employee of one or more private institutions
of higher education in the state;</para>
<para>(b) At least one shall be
a person having a favorable reputation for skill, knowledge, and experience
in the field of finance;</para>
<para>(c) At least one shall be
a person experienced in and having a favorable reputation for skill, knowledge,
and experience in the educational building construction field;</para>
<para>(d) At least one shall be
a person experienced in and having a favorable reputation in the field of
public accounting;</para>
<para>(e) After
the initial appointment provided for in subdivision (3)(a) of this section
is made, at least one shall be a trustee, director, officer, or employee of
one or more private health care institutions in the state; and</para>
<para>(f) After
the initial appointment provided for in subdivision (3)(b) of this section
is made, at least one shall be a trustee, director, officer, or employee of
one or more private social services institutions in the state.</para>
<para>(3) The initial
appointments of the members described in subdivisions (2)(e) and (2)(f) of
this section shall be made as follows:</para><para>(a) For the first member whose term expires
after September 6, 2013, and who is not the sole member described in subdivision
(2)(a), (2)(b), (2)(c), or (2)(d) of this section, the Governor shall appoint
a successor who meets the qualifications described in subdivision (2)(e) of
this section; and</para><para>(b) For the second member whose term expires after September 6,
2013, and who is not the sole member described in subdivision (2)(a), (2)(b),
(2)(c), or (2)(d) of this section, the Governor shall appoint a successor
who meets the qualifications described in subdivision (2)(f) of this section.</para>
<para>(4) The members of the authority
first appointed shall serve for terms expiring as follows: One on December
31, 1982; two on December 31, 1983; two on December 31, 1984; and two on December
31, 1985, respectively, the term of each such member to be designated by the
Governor. Upon the expiration of the term of any member, his or her successor
shall be appointed for a term of four years and until a successor has been
appointed and qualified. The Governor shall fill any vacancy for the remainder
of the unexpired term. Any member of the authority may be removed by the Governor
for misfeasance, malfeasance, or willful neglect of duty or other cause after
notice and a public hearing unless such notice and hearing shall be expressly
waived in writing by the accused member. Each member shall be eligible for
reappointment to a successive term but shall be declared ineligible for three
consecutive full terms.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 321, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 644, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2911; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 5, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 85-1711; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB170, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>