<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id341">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Money And Financing" id="id343" statutenumber="58-845"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>58-845 </statuteno><catchline id="id346">Bonds issued to acquire federally guaranteed securities; provisions
applicable.</catchline><para>Notwithstanding any other provision
of the Nebraska Educational,
Health, and Social Services Finance Authority Act to the contrary,
the authority may finance the cost of a project or program, refund outstanding
indebtedness, or reimburse advances from any endowment or any similar fund
of an eligible institution as authorized
by the act, by issuing its bonds pursuant to a plan of financing involving
the acquisition of any federally guaranteed security or securities or the
acquisition or entering into of commitments to acquire any federally guaranteed
security or securities. For purposes of this section, federally guaranteed
security means any direct obligation
of or obligation the principal of and interest on which are fully guaranteed
or insured by the United States of America or any obligation issued by or
the principal of and interest on which are fully guaranteed or insured by
any agency or instrumentality of the United States of America, including without
limitation any such obligation that is issued pursuant to the National Housing
Act, or any successor provision of law, each as amended from time to time.</para>
<para>In furtherance of the powers granted in this section, the
authority may acquire or enter into commitments to acquire any federally guaranteed
security and pledge or otherwise use any such federally guaranteed security
in such manner as the authority deems in its best interest to secure or otherwise
provide a source of repayment of any of its bonds issued to finance or refinance
a project or program or may enter into any appropriate agreement with any eligible institution whereby the authority may
make a loan to any such eligible institution for the
purpose of acquiring or entering into commitments to acquire any federally
guaranteed security.</para>
<para>Any agreement entered into pursuant to this section may contain
such provisions as are deemed necessary or desirable by the authority for
the security or protection of the authority or the holders of such bonds,
except that the authority, prior to making any such acquisition, commitment,
or loan, shall first determine and enter into an agreement with any such eligible institution or any other appropriate
institution or corporation to require that the proceeds derived from the acquisition
of any such federally guaranteed security will be used, directly or indirectly,
for the purpose of financing or refinancing a project or program.</para>
<para>Any bonds issued pursuant to this section shall not exceed
in principal amount the cost of financing or refinancing such project or program
as determined by the participating eligible institution and approved
by the authority, except that such costs may include, without limitation,
all costs and expenses necessary or incidental to the acquisition of or commitment
to acquire any federally guaranteed security and to the issuance and obtaining
of any insurance or guarantee of any obligation issued or incurred in connection
with any federally guaranteed security. In other respects any such bonds shall
be subject to the Nebraska Educational, Health, and Social
Services Finance Authority Act, including sections 58-841 and 58-842, and the
trust indenture securing such bonds
may contain such of the provisions set forth in section 58-843 as
the authority may deem appropriate.</para>
<para>If a project is financed or refinanced pursuant to this section,
the title to such project shall remain in the participating eligible institution owning
the project, subject to the lien
of any mortgage or security interest securing, directly or indirectly, the
federally guaranteed securities then being purchased or to be purchased, and
there shall be no lease of such facility between the authority and such eligible institution.</para>
<para>Section 58-840 shall not apply to
any project financed pursuant to this section, but the authority shall return
the securities purchased through the issuance of bonds pursuant to this section
to the issuer of such securities when such securities have been fully paid,
when such bonds have been fully paid and retired, or when adequate provision,
not involving the application of such securities, has been made to pay and
retire such bonds fully, all other conditions of the trust indenture securing such
bonds have been satisfied, and the lien on such bonds has been released in
accordance with the Nebraska Educational, Health, and Social
Services Finance Authority Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 321, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 465, &#167; 22; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1994), &#167; 79-2942; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 5, &#167; 42; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2008), &#167; 85-1742; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB170, &#167; 45.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>