<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Money and Financing" statutenumber="58-708"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>58-708</statuteno><catchline>Department of Economic Development; selection of projects to receive assistance; duties.</catchline><para>(1) During each calendar year in which funds are available from the Affordable Housing Trust Fund for use by the Department of Economic Development, the department shall allocate a specific amount of funds, not less than twenty-five percent, to each congressional district. Entitlement area funds allocated under this section that are not awarded to an eligible project from within the entitlement area within one year shall be made available for distribution to eligible projects elsewhere in the state. The department shall announce a grant and loan application period of at least ninety days duration for all nonentitlement areas. In selecting projects to receive trust fund assistance, the department shall develop a qualified allocation plan and give first priority to financially viable projects that serve the lowest income occupants for the longest period of time. The qualified allocation plan shall:</para><para>(a) Set forth selection criteria to be used to determine housing priorities of the housing trust fund which are appropriate to local conditions, including the community's immediate need for affordable housing, proposed increases in home ownership, private dollars leveraged, level of local government support and participation, and repayment, in part or in whole, of financial assistance awarded by the fund; and</para><para>(b) Give first priority in allocating trust fund assistance among selected projects to those projects which serve the lowest income occupant and are obligated to serve qualified occupants for the longest period of time.</para><para>(2) The department shall fund in order of priority as many applications as will utilize available funds less actual administrative costs of the department in administering the program. In administering the program the department may contract for services or directly provide funds to other governmental entities or instrumentalities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1322, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 40, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>