<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,234"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,234</statuteno><catchline>Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates; design requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The department, in consultation with the Commission on Indian Affairs, shall design license plates to be known as Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates. The design shall reflect the unique culture and history of Native American tribes historically and currently located in Nebraska. The design shall be selected on the basis of limiting the manufacturing cost of each plate to an amount less than or equal to the amount charged for license plates pursuant to section 60-3,102. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section and section 60-3,235.</para><para>(2) One type of Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates shall be alphanumeric plates. The department shall:</para><para>(a) Assign a designation up to five characters; and</para><para>(b) Not use a county designation.</para><para>(3) One type of Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates shall be personalized message plates. Such plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for personalized message license plates in section 60-3,118, except that a maximum of five characters may be used.</para><para>(4) The department shall cease to issue Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates beginning with the next license plate issuance cycle after the license plate issuance cycle that begins in 2023 pursuant to section 60-3,101 if the total number of registered vehicles that obtained such plates is less than five hundred per year within any prior consecutive two-year period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB356, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 33. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>