<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id5" statutenumber="60-6,209"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,209</statuteno><catchline id="id8">License revocation;
reinstatement; conditions; department; Board of Pardons; duties; fee.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any person whose operator's license has been revoked pursuant
to a conviction for a violation of sections 60-6,196, 60-6,197, and 60-6,199
to 60-6,204 for a third or subsequent time for a period of fifteen years may
apply to the Department of Motor Vehicles not
more often than once per calendar year, on forms prescribed by
the department, requesting the department to make a recommendation to the
Board of Pardons for reinstatement of his or her eligibility for an operator's
license. Upon receipt of the application and
a nonrefundable application fee of one hundred dollars, the Director
of Motor Vehicles shall review the application and
make a recommendation for reinstatement or for denial of reinstatement. The
department may recommend reinstatement if such person shows the following:</para>
<para>(a) Such person has completed a state-certified substance
abuse program and is recovering or such person has substantially recovered
from the dependency on or tendency to abuse alcohol or drugs;</para>
<para>(b) Such person has not been convicted, since the date of
the revocation order, of any subsequent violations of section 60-6,196 or
60-6,197 or any comparable city or village ordinance and the applicant has
not, since the date of the revocation order, submitted to a chemical test
under section 60-6,197 that indicated an alcohol concentration in violation
of section 60-6,196 or refused to submit to a chemical test under section
60-6,197;</para>
<para>(c) Such person has not been convicted, since the date of
the revocation order, of driving while under suspension, revocation, or impoundment
under section 60-4,109;</para>
<para>(d) Such person has abstained from the consumption of alcoholic
beverages and the consumption of drugs except at the direction of a licensed
physician or pursuant to a valid prescription;</para>
<para>(e) Such person's operator's license is not currently subject
to suspension or revocation for any other reason; and</para>
<para>(f) Such person
has agreed that, if the Board of Pardons reinstates such person's eligibility
to apply for an ignition interlock permit, such person must provide proof,
to the satisfaction of the department, that an ignition interlock device has
been installed and is maintained on one or more motor vehicles such person
operates for the duration of the original fifteen-year revocation period and
such person must operate only motor vehicles so equipped for the duration
of the original fifteen-year revocation period.</para><para>(2)
In addition, the department may require other evidence from such person to
show that restoring such person's privilege to drive will not present a danger
to the health and safety of other persons using the highways.</para>
<para>(3) Upon review of the application, the director shall make
the recommendation to the Board of Pardons in writing and shall briefly state
the reasons for the recommendations. The recommendation shall include the
original application and other evidence submitted by such person. The recommendation
shall also include any record of any other applications such person has previously
filed under this section.</para>
<para>(4) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to govern the procedures for making a recommendation to the Board of Pardons.
Such rules and regulations shall include the requirement that the treatment
programs and counselors who provide information about such person to the department
must be certified or licensed by the state.</para>
<para>(5) If the Board of Pardons reinstates such person's eligibility
for an operator's license or
an ignition interlock permit or orders a reprieve of such person's
motor vehicle operator's license revocation, such reinstatement or reprieve
may be conditioned for the duration of the original revocation period on such
person's continued recovery and,
if such person is a holder of an ignition interlock permit, shall be conditioned
for the duration of the original revocation period on such person's operation
of only motor vehicles equipped with an ignition interlock device.
If such person is convicted of any subsequent violation of section 60-6,196
or 60-6,197, the reinstatement of the person's eligibility for an operator's
license shall be withdrawn and such person's operator's license will be revoked
by the Department of Motor Vehicles for the time remaining under the original
revocation, independent of any sentence imposed by the court, after thirty
days' written notice to the person by first-class mail at his or her last-known
mailing address as shown by the records of the department.</para>
<para>(6) If the Board of Pardons reinstates a person's eligibility
for an operator's license or
an ignition interlock permit or orders a reprieve of such person's
motor vehicle operator's license revocation, the board shall notify the Department
of Motor Vehicles of the reinstatement or reprieve. Such person may apply
for an operator's license upon payment of a fee of one hundred twenty-five
dollars and the filing of proof of financial responsibility. The fees paid
pursuant to this section shall be collected by the department and remitted
to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit seventy-five dollars
of each fee to the General Fund and fifty dollars of each fee to the Department
of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 291,
&#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-669.19; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 304; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB998, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>This section (60-6,209
(Reissue 1993)) clearly defines the 15-year revocation as serving as a punishment
and is unconstitutional because it permits a judicial commutation of a sentence
of punishment. Because this section permits the judicial branch to exercise
the power of commutation, a power that clearly belongs to the executive branch,
this section is unconstitutional as a violation of the separation of powers
clause of the Nebraska Constitution. State v. Bainbridge, 249 Neb. 260, 543
N.W.2d 154 (1996).</para><para>The law does not grant an absolute right to
defendant to a reduction of a term of revocation, but provides that the period
of revocation "may" be reduced if the provisions of the statute are shown
by the applicant to be satisfied by the preponderance of the evidence. State
v. Packett, 246 Neb. 888, 523 N.W.2d 695 (1994).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>