
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id220" statutenumber="60-6,289"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,289</statuteno><catchline id="id223">Vehicles;
height; limit; height of structure; damages.</catchline><para>(1) No vehicle
unladen or with load shall exceed a height of fourteen feet, six inches, except:</para>
<para>(a) Combines or vehicles used in transporting combines, to be engaged
in harvesting within or without the state, moving into or through the state
during daylight hours when the overall height does not exceed fifteen feet,
six inches;</para>
<para>(b) Livestock forage vehicles with or without load that comply with
subsection (2) of section 60-6,305;</para>
<para>(c) Farm equipment or implements of husbandry being driven, picked up,
or delivered during daylight hours by farm equipment dealers or their representatives as authorized under section 60-6,382 shall
not exceed fifteen feet, six inches;</para>
<para>(d) Self-propelled specialized mobile equipment with a fixed load when
the requirements of subdivision (2)(i) of section 60-6,288 are met;</para>
<para>(e) Vehicles which have been issued a permit pursuant to section 60-6,299;
or</para>
<para>(f) Vehicles with a baled livestock forage load that comply with subsection
(4) of section 60-6,305 when the overall height does not exceed fifteen feet,
six inches.</para>
<para>(2) No person shall be required to raise, alter, construct, or reconstruct
any underpass, bridge, wire, or other structure to permit the passage of any
vehicle having a height, unladen or with load, in excess of twelve feet, six
inches. The owners, lessees, and operators, jointly and severally, of vehicles
exceeding twelve feet, six inches, in height shall assume the risk of loss
to the vehicle or its load and shall be liable for any damages that result
to overhead obstructions from operation of a vehicle exceeding twelve feet,
six inches, in height.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 105, &#167; 2, p. 425; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-1033; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 133, &#167; 1, p. 446; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-720; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 117, &#167; 1, p. 526; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 156, &#167; 2, p. 563; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 308, &#167; 3, p. 1102; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 491, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 39-720; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 593, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 211, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 750, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 284, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 553, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,178; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 385; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB820, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1039, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>