<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id163"  statutenumber="60-6,381"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,381</statuteno><catchline>Golf car vehicles; city, village, or county; operation authorized; restrictions; liability insurance.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A city or village may adopt an ordinance authorizing the operation of golf car vehicles within the corporate limits of the city or village if the operation is on streets adjacent and contiguous to a golf course.</para><para>(b) A county board may adopt an ordinance pursuant to section 23-187 authorizing the operation of golf car vehicles within the county if the operation is on roads adjacent and contiguous to a golf course.</para><para>(c) Any person operating a golf car vehicle as authorized under this subsection shall have a valid Class O operator's license, and the owner of the golf car vehicle shall have liability insurance coverage for the golf car vehicle. The person operating the golf car vehicle shall provide proof of such insurance coverage to any peace officer requesting such proof within five days after such a request.</para><para>(d) The restrictions of subsection (2) of this section do not apply to ordinances adopted under this subsection.</para><para>(2)(a) A city or village may adopt an ordinance authorizing the operation of golf car vehicles on streets within the corporate limits of the city or village if the operation is (i) between sunrise and sunset and (ii) on streets with a posted speed limit of thirty-five miles per hour or less. When operating a golf car vehicle as authorized under this subsection, the operator shall not operate such vehicle at a speed in excess of twenty miles per hour. A golf car vehicle shall not be operated at any time on any state or federal highway but may be operated upon such a highway in order to cross a portion of the highway system which intersects a street as directed in subsection (3) of this section. A city or village may, as part of such ordinance, implement standards for operation of golf car vehicles that are more stringent than the restrictions of this subsection for the safety of the operator and the public.</para><para>(b) A county board may adopt an ordinance pursuant to section 23-187 authorizing the operation of golf car vehicles on roads within the county if the operation is (i) between sunrise and sunset and (ii) on roads with a posted speed limit of thirty-five miles per hour or less. When operating a golf car vehicle as authorized under this subsection, the operator shall not operate such vehicle at a speed in excess of twenty miles per hour. A golf car vehicle shall not be operated at any time on any state or federal highway but may be operated upon such highway in order to cross a portion of the highway system which intersects a road as directed in subsection (3) of this section. A county may, as part of such ordinance, implement standards for operation of golf car vehicles that are more stringent than the restrictions of this subsection for the safety of the operator and the public.</para><para>(c) Any person operating a golf car vehicle as authorized under this subsection shall have a valid Class O operator's license, and the owner of the golf car vehicle shall have liability insurance coverage for the golf car vehicle. The person operating the golf car vehicle shall provide proof of such insurance coverage to any peace officer requesting such proof within five days after such a request. The liability insurance coverage shall be subject to limits, exclusive of interest and costs, as follows: Twenty-five thousand dollars because of bodily injury to or death of one person in any one accident and, subject to such limit for one person, fifty thousand dollars because of bodily injury to or death of two or more persons in any one accident, and twenty-five thousand dollars because of injury to or destruction of property of others in any one accident.</para><para>(3) The crossing of a highway shall be permitted by a golf car vehicle only if:</para><para>(a) The crossing is made at an angle of approximately ninety degrees to the direction of the highway and at a place where no obstruction prevents a quick and safe crossing;</para><para>(b) The golf car vehicle is brought to a complete stop before crossing the shoulder or roadway of the highway;</para><para>(c) The operator yields the right-of-way to all oncoming traffic that constitutes an immediate potential hazard; and</para><para>(d) In crossing a divided highway, the crossing is made only at an intersection of such highway with a street or road, as applicable.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Road means a public way for the purposes of vehicular travel, including the entire area within the right-of-way; and</para><para>(b) Street means a public way for the purposes of vehicular travel in a city or village and includes the entire area within the right-of-way.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1155, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB570, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>