<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,213"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,213</statuteno><catchline>Reckless driving, defined.</catchline><para>Any person who drives any motor vehicle in such a manner as to indicate an indifferent or wanton disregard for the safety of persons or property shall be guilty of reckless driving.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 134, &#167; 3, p. 485; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-11,100; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 99, &#167; 1, p. 339; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,107; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 148, &#167; 3(1), p. 410; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,107; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-669.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 309. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Applicability of statute to private property,</emphasis> see section 60-6,108.</para><para><emphasis>Motor vehicle homicide,</emphasis> penalty, see section 28-306.</para><para><emphasis>Operator's license,</emphasis> assessment of points and revocation, see sections 60-497.01, 60-498, and 60-4,182 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Speed alone does not support a conviction for reckless driving, but it does have a bearing on whether one was driving dangerously under the surroundings and attendant circumstances of the particular case. State v. Howard, 253 Neb. 523, 571 N.W.2d 308 (1997).</para><para>Prosecution for traffic infraction is a criminal action. State v. Knoles, 199 Neb. 211, 256 N.W.2d 873 (1977).</para><para>Improper turn by defendant while overtaking complainant's auto, held to be reckless driving. State v. Kufeldt, 197 Neb. 377, 248 N.W.2d 781 (1977).</para><para>History of statute reviewed in considering municipal ordinance. State v. Green, 182 Neb. 615, 156 N.W.2d 724 (1968).</para><para>Upon conviction, suspension of driver's license is authorized. Kroger v. State, 158 Neb. 73, 62 N.W.2d 312 (1954).</para><para>Reckless driving occurs when any person drives a motor vehicle in such a manner as to indicate an indifferent or wanton disregard of the safety of persons or property. State v. Malone, 26 Neb. App. 121, 917 N.W.2d 164 (2018).</para><para>Recklessness, for purposes of this section, has been defined as the disregard for or indifference to the safety of another or for the consequences of one's act. State v. Malone, 26 Neb. App. 121, 917 N.W.2d 164 (2018).</para><para>One cannot commit the greater offense of willful reckless driving without simultaneously committing the lesser offense of reckless driving; the only distinction between these offenses is intent. State v. Scherbarth, 24 Neb. App. 897, 900 N.W.2d 213 (2017).</para><para>Under certain circumstances, careless driving under section 60-6,212 should be instructed as a lesser-included offense of reckless driving. State v. Howard, 5 Neb. App. 596, 560 N.W.2d 516 (1997).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>