<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,304</statuteno><catchline>Load; contents; requirements; vehicle that contained livestock; spill
prohibited; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)(a)
Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section for a vehicle that contained
livestock, but still contains the manure or urine of such livestock, no vehicle
shall be driven or moved on any highway unless the vehicle is so constructed
or loaded as to prevent its contents from dropping, sifting, leaking, or otherwise
escaping from the vehicle.</para>
<para>(b) Except as provided in subsection (2)
of this section for a vehicle that contained livestock, but still contains
the manure or urine of such livestock, no person shall transport
any sand, gravel, rock less than two inches in diameter, or refuse in any
vehicle on any hard-surfaced state highway if such material protrudes above
the sides of that part of the vehicle in which it is being transported unless
such material is enclosed or completely covered with canvas or similar covering.</para>
<para>(c) No person shall drive
or move a motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer upon any highway unless the
cargo or contents carried by the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer are
properly distributed and adequately secured to prevent the falling of cargo
or contents from the vehicle. The tailgate, doors, tarpaulins, and any other
equipment used in the operation of the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer
or in the distributing or securing of the cargo or contents carried by the
motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer shall be secured to prevent cargo or
contents falling from the vehicle. The means of securement to the motor vehicle,
trailer, or semitrailer must be either tiedowns and tiedown assemblies of
adequate strength or sides, sideboards, or stakes and a rear endgate, endboard,
or stakes strong enough and high enough to assure that cargo or contents will
not fall from the vehicle.</para>
<para>(d) Any person who violates
any provision of this subsection
is guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(2)(a) No person operating
any vehicle that contained livestock, but still contains the manure or urine
of livestock, on any highway located within the corporate limits of a city
of the metropolitan class, shall spill manure or urine from the vehicle.</para>
<para>(b) Any person who violates
this subsection is guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor and shall be assessed
a minimum fine of at least two hundred fifty dollars.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 304, &#167; 1, p. 1095; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1972, &#167; 39-735.02; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 593, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,129; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 400; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 463; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB147, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB174, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>