<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id449" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-6,179.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,179.01</statuteno><catchline id="id452">Use of handheld wireless
communication device; prohibited acts; enforcement; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) This section does not apply to an operator of a commercial motor
vehicle if section 60-6,179.02 applies.</para>
<para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this section,
no person shall use a handheld wireless communication device to read a written
communication, manually type a written communication, or send a written communication
while operating a motor vehicle which is in motion.</para>
<para>(3) The prohibition in subsection (2) of this section does not apply
to:</para>
<para>(a) A person performing his or her official duties as a law enforcement
officer, a firefighter, an ambulance driver, or an emergency medical technician;
or</para>
<para>(b) A person operating a motor vehicle in an emergency situation.</para>
<para>(4) Enforcement of this section by state or local law enforcement agencies
shall be accomplished only as a secondary action when a driver of a motor
vehicle has been cited or charged with a traffic violation or some other offense.</para>
<para>(5) Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of a traffic
infraction. Any person who is found guilty of a traffic infraction under this
section shall be assessed points on his or her motor vehicle operator's license
pursuant to section 60-4,182 and shall be fined:</para>
<para>(a) Two hundred dollars for the first offense;</para>
<para>(b) Three hundred dollars for a second offense; and</para>
<para>(c) Five hundred dollars for a third and subsequent offense.</para>
<para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Commercial motor
vehicle has the same meaning as in section 75-362;</para><para>(b)(i) Handheld wireless communication device
means any device that provides for written communication between two or more
parties and is capable of receiving, displaying, or transmitting written communication.</para>
<para>(ii) Handheld wireless communication device includes, but is not limited
to, a mobile or cellular telephone, a text messaging device, a personal digital
assistant, a pager, or a laptop computer.</para>
<para>(iii) Handheld wireless communication device does not include an electronic
device that is part of the motor vehicle or permanently attached to the motor
vehicle or a handsfree wireless communication device; and</para>
<para>(c) Written communication
includes, but is not limited to, a text message, an instant message, electronic
mail, and Internet web sites.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB945, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 55.</para><operativedate>March 29, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>