<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,144"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,144</statuteno><catchline>Commercial drivers' licenses; applications; contents;
application; demonstration of knowledge and skills; information and documentation
required.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for any original or renewal
commercial driver's license or an applicant for a change of class of commercial
motor vehicle, endorsement, or restriction shall demonstrate his or her knowledge
and skills for operating a commercial motor vehicle as prescribed in the Motor
Vehicle Operator's License Act. An applicant for a commercial driver's license
shall provide the information and documentation required by this section and sections 60-484 and 60-4,144.01 and also, beginning on an implementation
date designated by the director on or before January 1, 2014, the information
and documentation required by section 60-484.04. Such information
and documentation shall include
any additional information required by 49 C.F.R. parts 383 and 391 and also include:</para>
<para>(a) Certification that the commercial motor vehicle in which the applicant
takes any driving skills examination is representative of the class of commercial
motor vehicle that the applicant operates or expects to operate; and</para>
<para>(b) The names of all states
where the applicant has been licensed to operate any type of motor vehicle
in the ten years prior to the date of application.</para>
<para>(2) Any person applying
for any commercial driver's license on or before December 31, 2011, must present
the certification required pursuant to section 60-4,145 or 60-4,146.</para>
<para>(3) Any person applying
for any commercial driver's license on or after January 1, 2012, must make
one of the certifications in section 60-4,144.01 and provide such certification
to the department in order to be issued a commercial driver's license.</para>
<para>(4) On or after January
1, 2012, but no later than January 30, 2014, every person who holds any commercial
driver's license must provide to the department medical certification as required
by section 60-4,144.01. The department may provide notice and prescribe medical
certification compliance requirements for all holders of commercial driver's
licenses. Holders of commercial driver's licenses who fail to meet the prescribed
medical certification compliance requirements may be subject to downgrade.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1989, LB 285, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1178, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 575; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 635, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 147, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1317, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 228, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 559, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
