<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,256"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,256</statuteno><catchline>Objects placed or hung to obstruct
or interfere with view of operator; unlawful; enforcement; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for
any person to operate a motor vehicle with any object placed or hung in or
upon the motor vehicle, except
required or permitted equipment of the motor vehicle,
in such a manner as to significantly
and materially obstruct or interfere with the view of the operator
through the windshield or to prevent the operator from having a clear and
full view of the road and condition of traffic behind the
motor vehicle. Any sticker or identification authorized or required
by the federal government or any agency thereof or the State of Nebraska or
any political subdivision thereof may be placed upon the windshield of the motor vehicle without
violating this
section.</para>
<para>(2) Enforcement of this
section by state or local law enforcement agencies shall be accomplished only
as a secondary action when a driver of a motor vehicle has been cited or charged
with a traffic violation or some other offense.</para><para>(3) Any person who violates this
section is guilty of a traffic infraction. Any person who is found guilty
of a traffic infraction under this section shall be assessed points on his
or her motor vehicle operator's license pursuant to section 60-4,182 and shall
be fined:</para><para>(a)
Fifty dollars for the first offense;</para><para>(b) One hundred dollars for a second offense; and</para>
<para>(c) One hundred fifty
dollars for a third and subsequent offense.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 173, &#167; 1, p. 624; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,123.04; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 30; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,170; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 352; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB500, &#167; 2.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interference with view of driver by passengers or load prohibited,</emphasis> see section 60-6,179.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
