<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id103"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,144.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,144.05</statuteno><catchline>Drug or alcohol violation; effect; erroneous notification; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning November 18, 2024, in compliance with 49 C.F.R. part 382, within sixty calendar days of receiving notification from the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration that a driver is prohibited from operating a commercial motor vehicle due to a drug or alcohol violation, the department shall:</para><para>(a) Update the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record to include the information provided in the notification;</para><para>(b) Notify the holder of the commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit of such holder's prohibited status and that the commercial driver's license privilege or CLP-commercial learner's permit privilege will be removed from such license or permit; and</para><para>(c) Downgrade such license and cancel the permit for holders of a CLP-commercial learner's permit pursuant to established procedures of the department and, if applicable, update the driver's record maintained by the department.</para><para>(2) Beginning November 18, 2024, in compliance with 49 C.F.R. part 382, within ten calendar days of receiving notification from the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration that a driver was erroneously identified as prohibited on the federal Drug and Alcohol Clearinghouse, the department shall:</para><para>(a) Restore the commercial driving privilege as it existed before the erroneous notification;</para><para>(b) Notify the holder of the commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit of:</para><para>(i) Such holder's updated status; and</para><para>(ii) Procedures the driver shall follow to reinstate such driver's license or permit; and</para><para>(c) Expunge the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record or motor vehicle record of any reference to the erroneous prohibited status.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1200, &#167; 40. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>