<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,211.08" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,211.08</statuteno><catchline>Open alcoholic beverage container; consumption of alcoholic beverages; prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Alcoholic beverage means (i) beer, ale porter, stout, and other similar fermented beverages, including sake or similar products, of any name or description containing one-half of one percent or more of alcohol by volume, brewed or produced from malt, wholly or in part, or from any substitute therefor, (ii) wine of not less than one-half of one percent of alcohol by volume, or (iii) distilled spirits which is that substance known as ethyl alcohol, ethanol, or spirits of wine in any form, including all dilutions and mixtures thereof from whatever source or by whatever process produced. Alcoholic beverage does not include trace amounts not readily consumable as a beverage;</para><para>(b) Highway means a road or street including the entire area within the right-of-way;</para><para>(c) Open alcoholic beverage container, except as provided in subsection (3) of section 53-123.04 and subdivision (1)(c) of section 53-123.11, means any bottle, can, or other receptacle:</para><para>(i) That contains any amount of alcoholic beverage; and</para><para>(ii)(A) That is open or has a broken seal or (B) the contents of which are partially removed; and</para><para>(d) Passenger area means the area designed to seat the driver and passengers while the motor vehicle is in operation and any area that is readily accessible to the driver or a passenger while in their seating positions, including any compartments in such area. Passenger area does not include the area behind the last upright seat of such motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk.</para><para>(2) It is unlawful for any person in the passenger area of a motor vehicle to possess an open alcoholic beverage container while the motor vehicle is located in a public parking area or on any highway in this state.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in section 53-186, it is unlawful for any person to consume an alcoholic beverage (a) in a public parking area or on any highway in this state or (b) inside a motor vehicle while in a public parking area or on any highway in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 585, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 562, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>