<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id116" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="60-3,113.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,113.04</statuteno><catchline id="id119">Handicapped or disabled person; parking permit; contents; issuance; duplicate permit.</catchline><para>(1) A handicapped or disabled parking permit shall be of a design, size, configuration, color, and construction and contain such information as specified in the regulations adopted by the United States Department of Transportation in 23 C.F.R. part 1235, UNIFORM SYSTEM FOR PARKING FOR PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2015.</para><para>(2) No handicapped or disabled parking permit shall be issued to any person or for any motor vehicle if any permit has been issued to such person or for such motor vehicle and such permit has been suspended pursuant to section 18-1741.02. At the expiration of such suspension, a permit may be renewed in the manner provided for renewal in sections 60-3,113.02, 60-3,113.03, and 60-3,113.05.</para><para>(3) A duplicate handicapped or disabled parking permit may be provided up to two times during any single permit period if a permit is destroyed, lost, or stolen. Such duplicate permit shall be issued as provided in section 60-3,113.02 or 60-3,113.03, whichever is applicable, except that a new certification by a physician, a physician assistant, or an advanced practice registered nurse need not be provided. A duplicate permit shall be valid for the remainder of the period for which the original permit was issued. If a person has been issued two duplicate permits under this subsection and needs another permit, such person shall reapply for a new permit under section 60-3,113.02 or 60-3,113.03, whichever is applicable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB35, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB657, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB776, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB313, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>