<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id208">
<sectno id="id209" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 23.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id210" statutenumber="60-339">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id212">60-339</statuteno><catchline id="id213">Motor vehicle,
defined.</catchline><para>Motor vehicle means any vehicle propelled
by any power other than muscular power.
Motor vehicle does not include (1)
mopeds, (2) farm tractors, (3) self-propelled equipment designed and used
exclusively to carry and apply fertilizer, chemicals, or related products
to agricultural soil and crops, agricultural floater-spreader implements,
and other implements of husbandry designed for and used primarily for tilling
the soil and harvesting crops or feeding livestock, (4) power unit hay grinders
or a combination which includes a power unit and a hay grinder when operated
without cargo, (5) vehicles which run only on rails or tracks, (6) off-road
designed vehicles, including, but not limited to, golf carts, go-carts, riding
lawnmowers, garden tractors, all-terrain vehicles, utility-type vehicles, snowmobiles registered
or exempt from registration under sections 60-3,207 to 60-3,219, and minibikes,
(7) road and general-purpose construction and maintenance machinery not designed
or used primarily for the transportation of persons or property, including,
but not limited to, ditchdigging apparatus, asphalt spreaders, bucket loaders,
leveling graders, earthmoving carryalls, power shovels, earthmoving equipment,
and crawler tractors, (8) self-propelled chairs used by persons who are disabled,
(9) electric personal assistive mobility devices, and (10) low-speed vehicles.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 23.</para></source><annotation><para>Licensed automobile dealer is required to note mortgage lien on certificate of title. Bank of Keystone v. Kayton, 155 Neb. 79, 50 N.W.2d 511 (1951).</para><para>Legislative definition of motor vehicle for purposes of classification for licensing or taxing does not change the common meaning of words with relation to other matters. Moffitt v. State Automobile Ins. Assn., 140 Neb. 578, 300 N.W. 837 (1941), vacating on rehearing, 139 Neb. 512, 297 N.W. 918 (1941).</para><para>Failure of supposed owner to register automobile as required by law is suspicious circumstance, putting purchaser on inquiry. Wallich v. Sandlovich, 111 Neb. 318, 196 N.W. 317 (1923).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>