<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id167" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-3,130.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,130.04</statuteno><catchline id="id170">Historical vehicle; model-year license plates; authorized.</catchline><para>(1) An owner of a historical vehicle eligible for registration under section 60-3,130 may use a license plate or plates designed by this state in the year corresponding to the model year when the vehicle was manufactured in lieu of the plates designed pursuant to section 60-3,130.03 subject to the approval of the department. The department shall inspect the plate or plates and may approve the plate or plates if it is determined that the model-year license plate or plates are legible and serviceable and that the license plate numbers do not conflict with or duplicate other numbers assigned and in use. An original-issued license plate or plates that have been restored to original condition may be used when approved by the department.</para><para>(2) The department may consult with a recognized car club in determining whether the year of the license plate or plates to be used corresponds to the model year when the vehicle was manufactured.</para><para>(3) If only one license plate is used on the vehicle, the license plate shall be placed on the rear of the vehicle. The owner of a historical vehicle may use only one plate on the vehicle even for years in which two license plates were issued for vehicles in general.</para><para>(4) License plates used pursuant to this section corresponding to the year of manufacture of the vehicle shall not be personalized message license plates, Pearl Harbor license plates, prisoner-of-war license plates, disabled veteran license plates, Purple Heart license plates, amateur radio station license plates, Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates, handicapped or disabled person license plates, specialty license plates, special interest motor vehicle license plates, Military Honor Plates, Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates, Breast Cancer Awareness Plates, or Mountain Lion Conservation Plates.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB110, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB32, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB383, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB220, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB474, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB977, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>