<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id146" statutenumber="60-3,128"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,128</statuteno><catchline id="id149">Nebraska Cornhusker
Spirit Plates; application; fee; transfer; credit allowed.</catchline><para>(1)
A person may apply to the department for Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates
in lieu of regular license plates on an application prescribed and provided
by the department for any motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin trailer,
except for motor vehicles or trailers registered under section 60-3,198. An
applicant receiving a spirit plate for a farm truck with a gross weight of
over sixteen tons or for a commercial motor vehicle registered for a gross
weight of five tons or over shall affix the appropriate tonnage decal to the
spirit plate. The department shall make forms available for such applications
through the county treasurers. Each
application for initial issuance or renewal of spirit plates shall be accompanied
by a fee of seventy dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall
be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit forty-three
percent of the fees for initial issuance and renewal of spirit plates to the
Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund. The State Treasurer shall credit fifty-seven
percent of the fees to the Spirit Plate Proceeds Fund until the fund has been
credited five million dollars from such fees and thereafter to the Highway
Trust Fund.</para>
<para>(2) When the department receives an application for spirit plates, it
shall deliver the plates to the county treasurer of the county
in which the motor vehicle or cabin trailer is registered. The county treasurer shall
issue spirit plates in lieu of regular license plates when the applicant complies
with the other provisions of law for registration of the motor vehicle or
cabin trailer. If spirit plates are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the licensee
shall be issued replacement license plates pursuant to section 60-3,157.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The owner of a motor vehicle or cabin trailer bearing spirit
plates may make application to the county treasurer to have such spirit
plates transferred to a motor vehicle or cabin trailer other than the motor
vehicle or cabin trailer for which such plates were originally purchased if
such motor vehicle or cabin trailer is owned by the owner of the spirit plates.</para>
<para>(b) The owner may have the unused portion of the spirit plate fee credited
to the other motor vehicle or cabin trailer which will bear the spirit plate
at the rate of eight and one-third percent per month for each full month left
in the registration period.</para>
<para>(c) Application for such transfer shall be accompanied by a fee of three
dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the
State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 128; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB110, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 76.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>