
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id6"  statutenumber="60-4,144.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,144.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Commercial drivers' licenses; certification required; medical examiner's certificate.</catchline><para>Certification shall be made as follows:</para><para>(1) A person must certify that he or she operates or expects to operate a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce, is both subject to and meets the qualification requirements under 49 C.F.R. part 391, and is required to obtain a medical examiner's certificate by 49 C.F.R. 391.45. The medical examination required in order to obtain a medical examiner's certificate shall be conducted by a medical examiner who is listed on the National Registry of Certified Medical Examiners. Any nonexcepted holder of a commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license who certifies that he or she will operate a commercial motor vehicle in nonexcepted, interstate commerce must maintain a current medical examiner's certificate and provide a copy of it to the department in order to maintain his or her medical certification status;</para><para>(2) A person must certify that he or she operates or expects to operate a commercial motor vehicle in interstate commerce, but engages exclusively in transportation or operations excepted under 49 C.F.R. 390.3(f), 391.2, 391.68, or 398.3 from all or part of the qualification requirements of 49 C.F.R. part 391, and is therefor not required to obtain a medical examiner's certificate by 49 C.F.R. 391.45;</para><para>(3) A person must certify that he or she operates a commercial motor vehicle only in intrastate commerce and therefor is subject to state driver qualification requirements as provided in section 75-363; or</para><para>(4) A person must certify that he or she operates a commercial motor vehicle in intrastate commerce, but engages exclusively in transportation or operations excepted from all or parts of the state driver qualification requirements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB666, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>