  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,216"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,216</statuteno><catchline>Willful reckless driving; first offense; penalty.</catchline><para>Every person convicted of willful reckless driving shall, upon a first conviction, be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor, and the court shall, as part of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to drive any motor vehicle for any purpose for a period of not less than thirty days nor more than one year from the date ordered by the court and shall order that the operator's license of such person be revoked for a like period. The revocation shall be administered upon sentencing, upon final judgment of any appeal or review, or upon the date that any probation is revoked.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 134, &#167; 3, p. 485; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-11,100; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 99, &#167; 1, p. 339; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,107; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 148, &#167; 3(4), p. 410; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 214, &#167; 3, p. 757; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,107.03; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-669.04; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 312; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 57. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Applicability of statute to private property,</emphasis> see section 60-6,108.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Evidence that a motorist ran at least one stop sign, exceeded the speed limit, and crossed over the road median during a chase by a police officer, was sufficient to sustain his conviction for willful reckless driving even though no property damage was done to other cars and no injuries were sustained. Goodloe v. Parratt, 453 F.Supp. 1380 (D. Neb. 1978).</para><para>The imposition of concurrent terms of ten years imposed upon a defendant who was convicted of willful reckless driving and operating a motor vehicle to avoid arrest, and who had been adjudged to be an habitual criminal, does not constitute cruel and unusual punishment. Goodloe v. Parratt, 453 F.Supp. 1380 (D. Neb. 1978).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 