<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,122.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,122.02</statuteno><catchline>Gold Star Family plates; fee; delivery.</catchline><para>(1) A person may apply to the department for Gold Star Family plates in lieu of regular license plates on an application prescribed and provided by the department for any motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer, except for a motor vehicle or trailer registered under section 60-3,198. An applicant receiving a Gold Star Family plate for a farm truck with a gross weight of over sixteen tons shall affix the appropriate tonnage decal to the plate. The department shall make forms available for such applications through the county treasurers. The license plates shall be issued upon payment of the license fee described in subsection (2) of this section and furnishing proof satisfactory to the department that the applicant is a surviving spouse, whether remarried or not, or an ancestor, including a stepparent, a descendant, including a stepchild, a foster parent or a person in loco parentis, or a sibling of a person who died while in good standing on active duty in the military service of the United States.</para><para>(2)(a) Each application for initial issuance of consecutively numbered Gold Star Family plates shall be accompanied by a fee of five dollars. An application for renewal of such plates shall be accompanied by a fee of five dollars. County treasurers collecting fees for renewals pursuant to this subdivision shall remit them to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit five dollars of the fee for initial issuance and renewal of such plates to the Nebraska Veteran Cemetery System Operation Fund.</para><para>(b) Each application for initial issuance of personalized message Gold Star Family plates shall be accompanied by a fee of forty dollars. An application for renewal of such plates shall be accompanied by a fee of forty dollars. County treasurers collecting fees for renewals pursuant to this subdivision shall remit them to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit twenty-five percent of the fee for initial issuance and renewal of such plates to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and seventy-five percent of the fee to the Nebraska Veteran Cemetery System Operation Fund.</para><para>(3) Until January 1, 2019, when the department receives an application for Gold Star Family plates, the department shall deliver the plates to the county treasurer of the county in which the motor vehicle or trailer is registered. Beginning January 1, 2019, when the department receives an application for Gold Star Family plates, the department may deliver the plates and registration certificate to the applicant by United States mail or to the county treasurer of the county in which the motor vehicle or trailer is registered and the delivery of the plates and registration certificate shall be made through a secure process and system. The county treasurer or the department shall issue Gold Star Family plates in lieu of regular license plates when the applicant complies with the other provisions of the Motor Vehicle Registration Act for registration of the motor vehicle or trailer. If Gold Star Family plates are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the licensee shall be issued replacement license plates upon request and without charge.</para><para>(4) The owner of a motor vehicle or trailer bearing Gold Star Family plates may apply to the county treasurer to have such plates transferred to a motor vehicle other than the vehicle for which such plates were originally purchased if such vehicle is owned by the owner of the plates. The owner may have the unused portion of the fee for the plates credited to the other vehicle which will bear the plates at the rate of eight and one-third percent per month for each full month left in the registration period. Application for such transfer shall be accompanied by a fee of three dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) If the cost of manufacturing Gold Star Family plates at any time exceeds the amount charged for license plates pursuant to section 60-3,102, any money to be credited to the Nebraska Veteran Cemetery System Operation Fund shall instead be credited first to the Highway Trust Fund in an amount equal to the difference between the manufacturing costs of Gold Star Family plates and the amount charged pursuant to section 60-3,102 with respect to such plates and the remainder shall be credited to the Nebraska Veteran Cemetery System Operation Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB570, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB110, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB331, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 43. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>