<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-529"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-529</statuteno><catchline>Proof of financial responsibility; certificate of insurance; contents.</catchline><para>Proof of financial responsibility may be furnished by (1) filing with the department the written certificate of any insurance carrier, duly authorized to do business in this state, or (2) electronic transmission of a certificate by an insurance carrier, duly authorized to do business in this state, certifying that there is in effect a motor vehicle liability policy for the benefit of the person required to furnish proof of financial responsibility, also known as an SR-22 certificate. Such certificate shall give the effective date of the certificate and designate, by explicit description or by appropriate reference, all motor vehicles covered thereby unless the policy is issued to a person who is not the owner of a motor vehicle. A certificate of insurance for fleet vehicles may include, as an appropriate reference, a designation that the insurance coverage is applicable to all vehicles owned by the named insured, or wording of similar effect, in lieu of an explicit description.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 178, &#167; 29, p. 494; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 911, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>An endorsement which is not misleading, ambiguous, or conflicting, which amends an omnibus clause in an uncertified automobile liability insurance policy by limiting the application of the omnibus clause to use of the automobile by a person over the age of twenty-five years, except for the insured or any resident of his household, is not proscribed by statute, nor is it against public policy. Equity Mut. Ins. Co. v. Allstate Ins. Co., 190 Neb. 515, 209 N.W.2d 592 (1973).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 