<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id14" statutenumber="60-4,110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,110</statuteno><catchline id="id17">Operating motor
vehicle during period of suspension, revocation, or impoundment; impounding
of motor vehicle; release, when authorized; restitution authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) Every motor vehicle, regardless of the registered owner
of the motor vehicle, being operated by a person whose operator's license
has been suspended, revoked, or impounded pursuant to a conviction or convictions
for violation of section 60-6,196, 60-6,197, 60-6,211.01, or 60-6,211.02 or
by an order of any court or an administrative order of the director is hereby
declared a public nuisance. The motor vehicle may be seized upon the arrest
of the operator of the motor vehicle and impounded at the expense of the owner
of the motor vehicle. If such operator's license is suspended, revoked, or
impounded pursuant to subdivision
(1)(c) of section 60-4,108 or section 60-498.01, 60-498.02, 60-6,196,
60-6,197, 60-6,211.01, or 60-6,211.02, the motor vehicle shall be impounded
for not less than ten days nor more than thirty days. No motor vehicle impounded
under this section shall be impounded for a period of time exceeding thirty
days except as provided in subsection (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(2) Any motor vehicle impounded shall be released:</para>
<para>(a) To the holder of a bona fide lien on the motor vehicle
executed prior to such impoundment when possession of the motor vehicle is
requested as provided by law by such lienholder for purposes of foreclosing
and satisfying his or her lien on the motor vehicle;</para>
<para>(b) To the titled owner of the motor vehicle when the titled
owner is a lessor. Upon learning the address or telephone number of the rental
or leasing company which owns the motor vehicle, the impounding law enforcement
agency shall immediately contact the company and inform it that the motor
vehicle is available for the company to take possession; or</para>
<para>(c) To the registered owner, a registered co-owner, or a spouse
of the owner upon good cause shown by an affidavit or otherwise to the court
before which the complaint is pending against the operator that the impounded
motor vehicle is essential to the livelihood of the owner, co-owner, or spouse
or the dependents of such owner, co-owner, or spouse.</para>
<para>(3) Any person who, at the direction of a peace officer, tows
and stores a motor vehicle pursuant to this section shall have a lien upon
such motor vehicle while in his or her possession for reasonable towing and
storage charges and shall have a right to retain such motor vehicle until
such charges are paid.</para>
<para>(4) If the registered owner of a motor vehicle was not the
operator of the motor vehicle whose actions caused the motor vehicle to be
impounded, the registered owner of the motor vehicle may recover civilly from
the operator of the motor vehicle all expenses incurred by reason of the impoundment.
In the case of a criminal action, the court may order such operator of the
motor vehicle to pay restitution to the registered owner in an amount equal
to any expenses incurred with respect to impoundment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 321, &#167; 1, p. 1024; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 322, &#167; 1, p. 1025; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-430.06; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1155, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>