<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-484.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-484.05</statuteno><catchline>Operators' licenses; state identification cards; temporary; when issued; period valid; special notation; renewal; return of license or card, when.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall only issue an operator's license or a state identification card that is temporary to any applicant who presents documentation under sections 60-484 and 60-484.04 that shows his or her authorized stay in the United States is temporary. An operator's license or a state identification card that is temporary shall be valid only during the period of time of the applicant's authorized stay in the United States or, if there is no definite end to the period of authorized stay, a period of one year.</para><para>(2) An operator's license or state identification card that is temporary shall clearly indicate that it is temporary with a special notation on the front of the license or card and shall state the date on which it expires.</para><para>(3) An operator's license or state identification card that is temporary may be renewed only upon presentation of valid documentary evidence that the status by which the applicant qualified for the operator's license or state identification card that is temporary has been extended by the United States Department of Homeland Security.</para><para>(4) If an individual has an operator's license or a state identification card issued based on approved lawful status granted under section 202(c)(2)(B)(i) through (x) of the federal REAL ID Act of 2005, Public Law 109-13, and the basis for the approved lawful status is terminated, the individual shall return the operator's license or state identification card to the Department of Motor Vehicles.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB623, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 54. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>