<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"  statutenumber="60-3,186"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,186</statuteno><catchline>Motor vehicle tax; notice; taxes and fees; payment; proceeds; disposition.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall annually determine the motor vehicle tax on each motor vehicle registered pursuant to section 60-3,187 and shall cause a notice of the amount to be delivered to the registrant. The notice may be delivered to the registrant at the address shown upon his or her registration certificate or the registrant's most recent address according to information received by the department from the National Change of Address program of the United States Postal Service or delivered electronically to the registrant if the registrant has provided electronic contact information to the department. The notice shall be provided on or before the first day of the last month of the registration period.</para><para>(2)(a) The motor vehicle tax, motor vehicle fee, registration fee, sales tax, and any other applicable taxes and fees shall be paid to the county treasurer prior to the registration of the motor vehicle for the following registration period. If the motor vehicle being registered has been transferred as a gift or for a nominal amount, any sales tax owed by the transferor on the purchase of the motor vehicle shall have been paid or be paid to the county treasurer prior to the registration of the motor vehicle for the following registration period.</para><para>(b) After retaining one percent of the motor vehicle tax proceeds collected for costs incurred by the county treasurer, and after transferring one percent of the motor vehicle tax proceeds collected to the State Treasurer for credit to the Vehicle Title and Registration System Replacement and Maintenance Cash Fund, the remaining motor vehicle tax proceeds shall be allocated to each county, local school system, school district, city, and village in the tax district in which the motor vehicle has situs.</para><para>(c)(i) Twenty-two percent of the remaining motor vehicle tax proceeds shall be allocated to the county, (ii) sixty percent shall be allocated to the local school system or school district, and (iii) eighteen percent shall be allocated to the city or village, except that (A) if the tax district is not in a city or village, forty percent shall be allocated to the county, and (B) in counties containing a city of the metropolitan class, eighteen percent shall be allocated to the county and twenty-two percent shall be allocated to the city or village.</para><para>(d) The amount allocated to a local school system shall be distributed to school districts in the same manner as property taxes.</para><para>(3) Proceeds from the motor vehicle tax shall be treated as property tax revenue for purposes of expenditure limitations, matching of state or federal funds, and other purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 186; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 248, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB207, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB977, &#167; 11. </para></source><annotation><para>This section provides for disposition and remittance of highway fund after it has been collected. Wayne County v. Steele, 121 Neb. 438, 237 N.W. 288 (1931).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>