
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id107" statutenumber="60-4,113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,113</statuteno><catchline id="id110">Examining personnel; appointment; duties; examinations; issuance of certificate or receipt; license; state identification card; county treasurer; duties; delivery of license or card.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall appoint as his or her agents one or more department personnel who shall examine all applicants for a state identification card or an operator's license as provided in section 60-4,114, except as otherwise provided in subsection (8) of section 60-4,122. The same department personnel may be assigned to one or more counties by the director. In counties in which the county treasurer collects the fees and issues receipts, the county shall furnish office space for the administration of the operator's license examination. Department personnel shall conduct the examination of applicants and deliver to each successful applicant an issuance certificate or receipt. The certificate may be presented to the county treasurer within ninety days after issuance, and the county treasurer shall collect the fee and surcharge as provided in section 60-4,115 and issue a receipt which is valid for up to thirty days. If an operator's license is being issued, the receipt shall also authorize driving privileges for such thirty-day period. If department personnel refuse to issue an issuance certificate or receipt, the department personnel shall state such cause in writing and deliver such written cause to the applicant.</para><para>(2) The department may provide for the central production and issuance of operators' licenses and state identification cards. Production shall take place at a secure production facility designated by the director. The licenses and cards shall be of such a design and produced in such a way as to discourage, to the maximum extent possible, fraud in applicant enrollment, identity theft, and the forgery and counterfeiting of such licenses and cards. Delivery of an operator's license or state identification card shall be to the mailing address provided by the applicant at the time of application and may be provided by secure electronic delivery to specified contact information at the request of the applicant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 148, &#167; 2, p. 513; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-402; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 12, p. 511; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-404; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 141, &#167; 2, p. 447; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 142, &#167; 1, p. 454; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 366, &#167; 36, p. 1270; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 307, &#167; 4, p. 972; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 315, &#167; 3, p. 999; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 316, &#167; 3, p. 1009; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 317, &#167; 1, p. 1016; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 389, &#167; 1, p. 1212; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 329, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 90, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-404; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 57. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>