<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,146.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,146.01</statuteno><catchline>Restricted commercial driver's license; seasonal permit; application or examiner's certificate; operation permitted; term; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any resident of this state who is a seasonal commercial motor vehicle operator for a farm-related or ranch-related service industry may apply for a restricted commercial driver's license. If the applicant is an individual, the application or examiner's certificate shall include the applicant's social security number. A restricted commercial driver's license shall authorize the holder to operate any Class B Heavy Straight Vehicle commercial motor vehicle or any Class B Heavy Straight Vehicle or Class C Small Vehicle commercial motor vehicle required to be placarded pursuant to section 75-364 when the hazardous material being transported is (a) diesel fuel in quantities of one thousand gallons or less, (b) liquid fertilizers in vehicles or implements of husbandry with total capacities of three thousand gallons or less, or (c) solid fertilizers that are not transported or mixed with any organic substance within one hundred fifty miles of the employer's place of business or the farm or ranch being served.</para><para>(2) Any applicant for a restricted commercial driver's license or seasonal permit shall be eighteen years of age or older, shall have possessed a valid operator's license during the twelve-month period immediately preceding application, and shall demonstrate, in a manner to be prescribed by the director, that:</para><para>(a) If the applicant has possessed a valid operator's license for two or more years, that in the two-year period immediately preceding application the applicant:</para><para>(i) Has not possessed more than one operator's license at one time;</para><para>(ii) Has not been subject to any order of suspension, revocation, or cancellation of any type;</para><para>(iii) Has no convictions involving any type or classification of motor vehicle of the disqualification offenses enumerated in sections 60-4,168 and 60-4,168.01; and</para><para>(iv) Has no convictions for traffic law violations that are accident-connected and no record of at-fault accidents; and</para><para>(b) If the applicant has possessed a valid operator's license for more than one but less than two years, the applicant shall demonstrate that he or she meets the requirements prescribed in subdivision (a) of this subsection for the entire period of his or her driving record history.</para><para>(3)(a) Until January 1, 2022, the commercial motor vehicle operating privilege as conferred by the restricted commercial driver's license shall be valid for five years if annually revalidated by the seasonal permit which shall be valid for no more than one hundred eighty consecutive days in any twelve-month period. To revalidate the restricted commercial driver's license, the applicant shall meet the requirements of subsection (2) of this section and shall designate a time period he or she desires the commercial motor vehicle operating privilege to be valid. The time period designated by the applicant shall appear and be clearly indicated on the seasonal permit. A seasonal permit shall not be issued to any person more than once in any twelve-month period. The holder of a restricted commercial driver's license shall operate commercial motor vehicles in the course or scope of his or her employment within one hundred fifty miles of the employer's place of business or the farm or ranch currently being served.</para><para>(b) Beginning January 1, 2022, the restricted commercial driver's license shall be valid for five years and shall clearly indicate the commercial motor vehicle operating privilege for the seasonal period of validity on the back of the restricted commercial driver's license. The seasonal period of validity shall be valid for no more than one hundred eighty consecutive days in any twelve-month period. The applicant shall designate the seasonal period of validity when making application for the restricted commercial driver's license. The holder of the restricted commercial driver's license may change the seasonal period of validity by renewing or obtaining a replacement of the restricted commercial driver's license. The holder of a restricted commercial driver's license shall operate commercial motor vehicles in the course or scope of his or her employment within one hundred fifty miles of the employer's place of business or the farm or ranch currently being served. The department shall annually revalidate the restricted commercial driver's license to confirm that the holder of the restricted commercial driver's license meets the requirements of subsection (2) of this section. If the holder of the restricted commercial driver's license does not meet the requirements of subsection (2) of this section upon revalidation, the department shall provide notice to the holder that the restricted commercial driver's license is canceled and the holder must apply for a Class O operator's license within thirty calendar days after the date notice was sent.</para><para>(4) Any person who violates any provision of this section shall, upon conviction, be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor. In addition to any penalty imposed by the court, the director shall also revoke such person's restricted commercial driver's license and shall disqualify such person from operating any commercial motor vehicle in Nebraska for a period of five years.</para><para>(5) The Department of Motor Vehicles may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out the requirements of this section.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Agricultural chemical business means any business that transports agricultural chemicals predominately to or from a farm or ranch;</para><para>(b) Farm-related or ranch-related service industry means any custom harvester, retail agricultural outlet or supplier, agricultural chemical business, or livestock feeder which operates commercial motor vehicles for the purpose of transporting agricultural products, livestock, farm machinery and equipment, or farm supplies to or from a farm or ranch;</para><para>(c) Retail agricultural outlet or supplier means any retail outlet or supplier that transports either agricultural products, farm machinery, farm supplies, or both, predominately to or from a farm or ranch; and</para><para>(d) Seasonal commercial motor vehicle operator means any person who, exclusively on a seasonal basis, operates a commercial motor vehicle for a farm-related or ranch-related service industry.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 420, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 323, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 142; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB270, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB113, &#167; 29. </para><operativedate>August 28, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>