<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,144"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,144</statuteno><catchline>Buses; registration fees.</catchline>
<para>(1) For buses used exclusively to carry children to and from school,
and other school activities, the registration fee shall be ten dollars.</para>
<para>(2) For buses equipped to carry more than ten persons for hire, the
fee shall be based on the weight of such bus. To ascertain the weight, the
unladen weight in pounds shall be used. There shall be added to such weight
in pounds the number of persons such bus is equipped to carry times two hundred,
the sum thereof being the weight of such bus for license purposes. The unladen
weight shall be ascertained by scale weighing of the bus fully equipped and
as used upon the highways under the supervision of a member of the Nebraska
State Patrol or a carrier enforcement officer and certified by such patrol
member or carrier enforcement officer to the department or county treasurer. The fee therefor
shall be as follows:</para>
<para>(a) If such bus weighs thirty-two thousand pounds and less than thirty-four
thousand pounds, it shall be licensed as a twelve-ton truck as provided in
section 60-3,147 and pay the same fee as therein provided;</para>
<para>(b) If such bus weighs thirty thousand pounds and less than thirty-two
thousand pounds, it shall be licensed as an eleven-ton truck as provided in
section 60-3,147 and pay the same fee as therein provided;</para>
<para>(c) If such bus weighs twenty-eight thousand pounds and less than thirty
thousand pounds, it shall be licensed as a ten-ton truck as provided in section
60-3,147 and pay the same fee as therein provided;</para>
<para>(d) If such bus weighs twenty-two thousand pounds and less than twenty-eight
thousand pounds, it shall be licensed as a nine-ton truck as provided in section
60-3,147 and pay the same fee as therein provided;</para>
<para>(e) If such bus weighs sixteen thousand pounds and less than twenty-two
thousand pounds, it shall be licensed as an eight-ton truck as provided in
section 60-3,147 and pay the same fee as therein provided; and</para>
<para>(f) If such bus weighs less than sixteen thousand pounds, it shall be
licensed as a five-ton truck as provided in section 60-3,147 and pay the same
fee as therein provided, except that upon registration of buses equipped to
carry ten passengers or more and engaged entirely in the transportation of
passengers for hire within municipalities or in and within a radius of five
miles thereof the fee shall be seventy-five dollars, and for buses equipped
to carry more than ten passengers and not for hire the registration fee shall
be thirty dollars.</para>
<para>(3) License plates issued under this section shall be the same size
and of the same basic design as regular license plates issued under section
60-3,100.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 144; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 80.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>