<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-6,270"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,270</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Occupant protection system; three-point safety belt system; use required; when; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) or (3) of this section, no driver shall operate a motor vehicle upon a highway or street in this state unless the driver and each front-seat occupant in the vehicle are wearing occupant protection systems and all occupant protection systems worn are properly adjusted and fastened.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) of this section, no driver shall operate an autocycle upon a highway or street of this state unless the driver is wearing a three-point safety belt system and it is properly adjusted and fastened.</para><para>(3) The following persons shall not be required to wear an occupant protection system or a three-point safety belt system:</para><para>(a) A person who possesses written verification from a physician that the person is unable to wear an occupant protection system or a three-point safety belt system for medical reasons;</para><para>(b) A rural letter carrier of the United States Postal Service while performing his or her duties as a rural letter carrier between the first and last delivery points; and</para><para>(c) A member of an emergency medical service while involved in patient care.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, motor vehicle means a vehicle required by section 60-6,266 to be equipped with an occupant protection system or a three-point safety belt system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 496, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 958, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-6,103.07; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 366; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 138, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB231, &#167; 36. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>