<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id227">
<sectno id="id228" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 31.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id229" statutenumber="60-4,126">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id231">60-4,126</statuteno><catchline id="id232">Farm permit;
issuance; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>Any person who
is younger than sixteen years of age but is over thirteen years of age and
resides upon a farm in this state or is fourteen years of age or older and
is employed for compensation upon a farm in this state may obtain a farm permit
authorizing the operation of farm tractors,
minitrucks, and other motorized implements of farm husbandry upon
the highways of this state if the applicant for such farm permit furnishes
satisfactory proof of age and satisfactorily demonstrates that he or she has
knowledge of the operation of such equipment and of the rules of the road
and laws respecting the operation of motor vehicles upon the highways of this
state. Any person under sixteen years of age but not less than thirteen years
of age may obtain a temporary permit to operate such equipment for a six-month
period after presentation to the department of a request for the temporary
permit signed by the person's parent or guardian and payment of the fee and
surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115. After the expiration of the six-month
period, it shall be unlawful for such person to operate such equipment upon
the highways of this state unless he or she has been issued a farm permit
under this section. The fee for an original, renewal, or duplicate farm permit
shall be the fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115. All farm permits
shall be subject to revocation under the terms of section 60-496. Any person
who violates the terms of a farm permit shall be guilty of an infraction and
shall not be eligible for another school, farm, LPD-learner's, or LPE-learner's
permit until he or she has attained the age of sixteen years.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167;  19; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>