<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id53" statutenumber="60-4,111.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,111.01</statuteno><catchline id="id56">Storage or compilation of information; retailer; seller; authorized acts; sign posted; use of stored information; approval of negotiable instrument or certain payments; authorized acts; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Motor Vehicles, the courts, or law enforcement agencies may store or compile information acquired from an operator's license or a state identification card for their statutorily authorized purposes.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (3) or (4) of this section, no person having use of or access to machine-readable information encoded on an operator's license or a state identification card shall compile, store, preserve, trade, sell, or share such information. Any person who trades, sells, or shares such information shall be guilty of a Class IV felony. Any person who compiles, stores, or preserves such information except as authorized in subsection (3) or (4) of this section shall be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para><para>(3)(a) For purposes of compliance with and enforcement of restrictions on the purchase of alcohol, lottery tickets, and tobacco products, a retailer who sells any of such items pursuant to a license issued or a contract under the applicable statutory provision may scan machine-readable information encoded on an operator's license or a state identification card presented for the purpose of such a sale. The retailer may store only the following information obtained from the license or card: Age and license or card identification number. The retailer shall post a sign at the point of sale of any of such items stating that the license or card will be scanned and that the age and identification number will be stored. The stored information may only be used by a law enforcement agency for purposes of enforcement of the restrictions on the purchase of alcohol, lottery tickets, and tobacco products and may not be shared with any other person or entity.</para><para>(b) For purposes of compliance with the provisions of sections 28-458 to 28-462, a seller who sells methamphetamine precursors pursuant to such sections may scan machine-readable information encoded on an operator's license or a state identification card presented for the purpose of such a sale. The seller may store only the following information obtained from the license or card: Name, age, address, type of identification presented by the customer, the governmental entity that issued the identification, and the number on the identification. The seller shall post a sign at the point of sale stating that the license or card will be scanned and stating what information will be stored. The stored information may only be used by law enforcement agencies, regulatory agencies, and the exchange for purposes of enforcement of the restrictions on the sale or purchase of methamphetamine precursors pursuant to sections 28-458 to 28-462 and may not be shared with any other person or entity. For purposes of this subsection, the terms exchange, methamphetamine precursor, and seller have the same meanings as in section 28-458.</para><para>(c) The retailer or seller shall utilize software that stores only the information allowed by this subsection. A programmer for computer software designed to store such information shall certify to the retailer that the software stores only the information allowed by this subsection. Intentional or grossly negligent programming by the programmer which allows for the storage of more than the age and identification number or wrongfully certifying the software shall be a Class IV felony.</para><para>(d) A retailer or seller who knowingly stores more information than authorized under this subsection from the operator's license or state identification card shall be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para><para>(e) Information scanned, compiled, stored, or preserved pursuant to subdivision (a) of this subsection may not be retained longer than eighteen months unless required by state or federal law.</para><para>(4) In order to approve a negotiable instrument, an electronic funds transfer, or a similar method of payment, a person having use of or access to machine-readable information encoded on an operator's license or a state identification card may:</para><para>(a) Scan, compile, store, or preserve such information in order to provide the information to a check services company subject to and in compliance with the federal Fair Credit Reporting Act, 15 U.S.C. 1681 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2023, for the purpose of effecting, administering, or enforcing a transaction requested by the holder of the license or card or preventing fraud or other criminal activity; or</para><para>(b) Scan and store such information only as necessary to protect against or prevent actual or potential fraud, unauthorized transactions, claims, or other liability or to resolve a dispute or inquiry by the holder of the license or card.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in subdivision (4)(a) of this section, information scanned, compiled, stored, or preserved pursuant to this section may not be traded or sold to or shared with a third party; used for any marketing or sales purpose by any person, including the retailer who obtained the information; or, unless pursuant to a court order, reported to or shared with any third party. A person who violates this subsection shall be guilty of a Class IV felony.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB261, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB20, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB79, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB149, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB750, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB138, &#167; 21. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>