<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"  statutenumber="60-6,211.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,211.08</statuteno><catchline>Open alcoholic beverage container;
consumption of alcoholic beverages; prohibited acts; applicability of section to certain passengers of limousine
or bus.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Alcoholic beverage means (i) beer, ale, porter, stout, and other
similar fermented beverages, including sake or similar products, of any name
or description containing one-half of one percent or more of alcohol by volume,
brewed or produced from malt, wholly or in part, or from any substitute therefor,
(ii) wine of not less than one-half of one percent of alcohol by volume, or
(iii) distilled spirits which is that substance known as ethyl alcohol, ethanol,
or spirits of wine in any form, including all dilutions and mixtures thereof
from whatever source or by whatever process produced. Alcoholic beverage does
not include trace amounts not readily consumable as a beverage;</para>
<para>(b) Highway means a road or street including the entire area within
the right-of-way;</para>
<para>(c) Limousine means a
luxury vehicle used to provide prearranged passenger transportation on a dedicated
basis at a premium fare that has a seating capacity of at least five and no
more than fourteen persons behind the driver with a physical partition separating
the driver seat from the passenger compartment. Limousine does not include
taxicabs, hotel or airport buses or shuttles, or buses;</para>
<para>(d) Open alcoholic beverage
container, except as provided in subsection (3) of section 53-123.04 and subdivision
(1)(c) of section 53-123.11, means any bottle, can, or other receptacle:</para>
<para>(i) That contains any amount of alcoholic beverage; and</para>
<para>(ii)(A) That is open or has a broken seal or (B) the contents of which
are partially removed; and</para>
<para>(e) Passenger area means the
area designed to seat the driver and passengers while the motor vehicle is
in operation and any area that is readily accessible to the driver or a passenger
while in their seating positions, including any compartments in such area.
Passenger area does not include the area behind the last upright seat of such
motor vehicle if the area is not normally occupied by the driver or a passenger
and the motor vehicle is not equipped with a trunk.</para>
<para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this section,
it is unlawful for any person in the passenger area of a motor
vehicle to possess an open alcoholic beverage container while the motor vehicle
is located in a public parking area or on any highway in this state.</para>
<para>(3) Except as provided in section 53-186 or subsection (4) of this section, it is unlawful
for any person to consume an alcoholic beverage (a) in a public parking area
or on any highway in this state or (b) inside a motor vehicle while in a public
parking area or on any highway in this state.</para>
<para>(4) This section does
not apply to persons who are passengers of, but not drivers of, a limousine
or bus being used in a charter or special party service as defined by rules
and regulations adopted and promulgated by the Public Service Commission and
subject to Chapter 75, article 3. Such passengers may possess open alcoholic
beverage containers and may consume alcoholic beverages while such limousine
or bus is in a public parking area or on any highway in this state if (a)
the driver of the limousine or bus is prohibited from consuming alcoholic
liquor and (b) alcoholic liquor is not present in any area that is readily
accessible to the driver while in the driver's seat, including any compartments
in such area.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 585, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 562, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB281, &#167; 3.</para></source>
<annotation><para>Conviction for possessing an open container of alcohol in a vehicle was invalid when police officers found defendant intoxicated in a vehicle that was parked on a residential driveway and overhanging a public sidewalk. State v. McCave, 282 Neb. 500, 805 N.W.2d 290 (2011).</para></annotation>
  </law>
</legaldoc>