<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,376" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,376</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Electric personal assistive mobility device; operation; violation; penalty.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Any person who operates an electric personal assistive mobility device on a highway shall have all of the rights and shall be subject to all of the duties applicable to the operator of a vehicle under the Nebraska Rules of the Road except (a) as provided in special electric personal assistive mobility device regulations adopted pursuant to the Nebraska Rules of the Road, (b) any provisions of the Nebraska Rules of the Road which by their nature can have no application, and (c) as provided in section 60-6,142 with respect to operating an electric personal assistive mobility device on a shoulder of a highway.</para><para id="id00">(2) An electric personal assistive mobility device may be operated on any highway, alley, sidewalk, bike trail, path, or any other area where persons travel, except as provided by the Department of Transportation or local authority. Regulations applicable to an electric personal assistive mobility device shall apply whenever an electric personal assistive mobility device is so operated.</para><para id="id00">(3) An operator of an electric personal assistive mobility device shall yield to pedestrian traffic and any human-powered or animal-powered vehicle at all times. An operator of an electric personal assistive mobility device shall give an audible signal before overtaking and passing any pedestrian or human-powered or animal-powered vehicle. A person violating this subsection shall be fined ten dollars for the first offense. A person violating this subsection shall have his or her electric personal assistive mobility device impounded for up to thirty days for each subsequent offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 460; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 230. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>