<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id274"  statutenumber="60-4,142"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,142</statuteno><catchline id="id277">CLP-commercial learner's permit issuance; renewal.</catchline><para>Any resident or nondomiciled applicant may obtain a CLP-commercial learner's permit from the department by making application to licensing staff of the department. An applicant shall present proof to licensing staff that he or she holds a valid Class O license or commercial driver's license or a foreign nondomiciled applicant shall successfully complete the requirements for the Class O license before a CLP-commercial learner's permit is issued. An applicant shall also successfully complete the commercial driver's license general knowledge examination under section 60-4,155 and examinations for all previously issued endorsements as provided in 49 C.F.R. 383.25(a)(3) and 49 C.F.R. 383.153(b)(2)(vii). Upon application, the examination may be waived if the applicant presents a Nebraska commercial driver's license which is valid or has been expired for less than one year, presents a valid commercial driver's license from another state, or is renewing a CLP-commercial learner's permit. The CLP-commercial learner's permit shall be valid for a period of one hundred eighty days. The CLP-commercial learner's permit holder may renew the CLP-commercial learner's permit for an additional one hundred eighty days without retaking the general and endorsement knowledge tests. The successful applicant shall pay the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115 for the issuance or renewal of a CLP-commercial learner's permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 108, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 853, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>