<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id60"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-705"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-705</statuteno><catchline>24/7 sobriety program permit; issuance; requirements; revocation; grounds; court order.</catchline><para>(1) If an individual has been arrested for a violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197 or a city or village ordinance enacted in conformance with such sections and is participating in a 24/7 sobriety program, such individual may petition the court for an order allowing the individual to apply for a 24/7 sobriety program permit as set forth in section 60-706. A 24/7 sobriety program permit shall only be issued if the individual's operator's license has been revoked pursuant to section 60-498.01 for the pending offense.</para><para>(2) The court shall only issue an order under subsection (1) of this section if the court has sufficient proof the individual is enrolled in a 24/7 sobriety program and has gone at least thirty consecutive days without any sanctions being imposed.</para><para>(3) If, after the issuance of an order allowing an individual to apply for a 24/7 sobriety program permit, the individual withdraws or is terminated from the 24/7 sobriety program, the court shall immediately issue an order revoking the 24/7 sobriety program permit and cause a copy of the order to be sent to the director.</para><para>(4) The holder of a commercial driver's license under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act is not eligible for a 24/7 sobriety program permit.</para><para>(5) A person shall be eligible to be issued a 24/7 sobriety program permit allowing operation of a motor vehicle if he or she is not subject to any other suspension, cancellation, required no-driving period, or period of revocation and has successfully completed the application for a 24/7 sobriety program permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB271, &#167; 5. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act,</emphasis> see section 60-462.</para> </crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>