<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id207" statutenumber="60-4,100"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,100</statuteno><catchline id="id210">Suspension; when authorized; citation; lack of financial ability to pay; hearing; determination; court or magistrate; powers; order; operate as release.</catchline><para>(1) Any resident of this state who has violated a promise to comply with the terms of a traffic citation issued by a law enforcement officer for a moving violation in any jurisdiction outside this state pursuant to the Nonresident Violator Compact of 1977 or in any jurisdiction inside this state shall be subject to having his or her operator's license suspended pursuant to this section.</para><para>(2) The court having jurisdiction over the offense for which the citation has been issued shall notify the director of a resident's violation of a promise to comply with the terms of the citation after thirty working days have elapsed from the date of the failure to comply, unless within such thirty working days the resident appears before the clerk of the county court having jurisdiction over the offense to request a hearing pursuant to subsection (3) of this section to establish that such resident lacks the financial ability to pay the citation.</para><para>(3) A hearing requested under subsection (2) of this section shall be set before the court or magistrate on the first regularly scheduled court date following the request. At the hearing, the resident shall have the opportunity to present information as to his or her income, assets, debts, or other matters affecting his or her financial ability to pay the citation. Following the hearing, the court or magistrate shall determine the resident's financial ability to pay the citation, including his or her financial ability to pay in installments.</para><para>(4)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (4)(c) of this section, if the court or magistrate determines under subsection (3) of this section that the resident is financially able to pay the citation and the resident refuses to pay, the court or magistrate shall either:</para><para>(i) Notify the director of the resident's violation of a promise to comply with the terms of the citation; or</para><para>(ii) Postpone the hearing for a period of no more than one month during which period the court or magistrate may order the resident to complete such hours of community service as the court or magistrate deems appropriate, subject to a total limit of twenty hours. At the end of such period, if the resident has completed such community service to the satisfaction of the court or magistrate, the court or magistrate shall enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the resident of the obligation to pay such citation and shall notify the director. If the resident has not completed such community service to the satisfaction of the court or magistrate, the court or magistrate shall notify the director of the resident's violation of a promise to comply with the terms of the citation. A hearing may only be postponed once under this subdivision.</para><para>(b) If the court or magistrate determines under subsection (3) of this section that the resident is financially unable to pay the citation, the court or magistrate shall either:</para><para>(i) Enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the resident of the obligation to pay such citation;</para><para>(ii) Postpone the hearing for a period of no more than one month during which period the court or magistrate may order the resident to complete such hours of community service as the court or magistrate deems appropriate, subject to a total limit of twenty hours. At the end of such period, if the resident has completed such community service to the satisfaction of the court or magistrate, the court or magistrate shall enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the resident of the obligation to pay such citation and shall notify the director. If the resident has not completed such community service to the satisfaction of the court or magistrate, the court or magistrate shall notify the director of the resident's violation of a promise to comply with the terms of the citation. A hearing may only be postponed once under this subdivision.</para><para>(c) If the court or magistrate determines under subsection (3) of this section that the resident is financially able to pay in installments and the resident agrees to make such payments, the court or magistrate shall make arrangements suitable to the court or magistrate and to the resident by which the resident may pay in installments. The court or magistrate shall enter an order specifying the terms of such arrangements and the dates on which payments are to be made. If the resident fails to pay an installment, the court or magistrate shall notify the director of the resident's violation of a promise to comply with the terms of the citation unless the resident requests a hearing from the clerk of the county court on or before ten working days after such installment was due. At the hearing, the resident shall show good cause for such failure, including financial inability to pay. If, following such hearing, the court or magistrate finds:</para><para>(i) That the resident has not demonstrated good cause for such failure, the court or magistrate shall either notify the director of the resident's violation of a promise to comply with the terms of the citation or postpone the hearing and order community service pursuant to subdivision (4)(a)(ii) of this section;</para><para>(ii) That the resident remains financially able to pay but has demonstrated good cause for such missed installment, the court or magistrate shall make any necessary modifications to the order specifying the terms of the installment payments; or</para><para>(iii) That the resident has become financially unable to pay, the court or magistrate shall enter an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section discharging the resident of the obligation to pay such citation and shall notify the director.</para><para>(5) An order discharging the resident of the obligation to pay a traffic citation shall be set forth in or accompanied by a judgment entry. Such order shall operate as a complete release of such payment obligation.</para><para>(6) Upon notice to the director that a resident has violated a promise to comply with the terms of a traffic citation as provided in this section, the director shall send written notice to such resident by regular United States mail to the resident's last-known mailing address or, if such address is unknown, to the last-known residence address of such resident as shown by the records of the department. Such notice shall state that such resident has twenty working days after the date of the notice to show the director that the resident has complied with the terms of such traffic citation. If the resident fails to show the director that he or she has complied with the terms of such traffic citation on or before twenty working days after the date of the notice, the director shall summarily suspend the operator's license and issue an order. The order shall be sent by regular United States mail to the resident's last-known mailing address as shown by the records of the department. The suspension shall continue until the resident has furnished the director with satisfactory evidence of compliance with the terms of the citation.</para><para>(7) The reinstatement fee required under section 60-4,100.01 shall be waived if five years have passed since issuance of the license suspension order under this section.</para><para>(8) The performance or completion of an order to complete community service under this section may be supervised or confirmed by a community correctional facility or program or another similar entity as ordered by the court or magistrate.</para><para>(9) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Agency means any public or governmental unit, institution, division, or agency or any private nonprofit organization which provides services intended to enhance the social welfare or general well-being of the community, which agrees to accept community service from residents under this section and to supervise and report the progress of such community service to the court or magistrate;</para><para>(b) Community correctional facility or program has the same meaning as in section 47-621; and</para><para>(c) Community service means uncompensated labor for an agency to be performed by a resident when the resident is not working or attending school.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 23, p. 518; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 124, &#167; 4, p. 472; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-428; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-426; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 344, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 153, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-426; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 420, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 10, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB259, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nonresident Violator Compact of 1977,</emphasis> see section 1-119, Vol. 2A, Appendix.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>