<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,353"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,353</statuteno><catchline>Operation; rules and regulations; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>Any department, board, or commission of the State of Nebraska with jurisdiction over state parks and state recreation areas as defined in section 37-338 and state wayside areas as described in section 81-711, in which motor vehicles of any type are permitted, may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations permitting and controlling the operation of minibikes and designating the place, time, and manner of such operation in the public recreation area under its control. In designating the manner of such operation within a specific location and during a specific time, the department, board, or commission may establish speed limits and restrictions on the age of the operator, noise emission levels, and number of minibikes permitted to be operated within a specific area at the same time. The other provisions of the Nebraska Rules of the Road not inconsistent with sections 60-678 and 60-6,347 to 60-6,353 shall apply to the public area.</para><para>Such department, board, or commission may further authorize the supervising official of any area under its ownership or control to prohibit operation of any minibike in emergency situations by personal or posted notice.</para><para>Any person operating a minibike in a place, at a time, or in a manner not permitted by the department, board, or commission having control over the area shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para><para>Any political subdivision of the State of Nebraska with jurisdiction over highways may adopt and promulgate rules, regulations, ordinances, or resolutions in conformity with such sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1196, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 135; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 60-2108; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 449; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 922, &#167; 406. </para></source></law></legaldoc>