<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id5" statutenumber="60-4,141.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">60-4,141.01</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Operation of
commercial motor vehicle; restrictions;
prohibited acts; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall operate a commercial motor vehicle upon the highways
of this state while his or her commercial driver's license or privilege to
operate a commercial motor vehicle is suspended, revoked, or canceled, while subject to a disqualification or an
out-of-service order, or while
there is an out-of-service order in effect for the commercial motor vehicle
being operated or for the motor carrier operation.</para>
<para>(2) No person
shall operate a commercial motor vehicle transporting hazardous materials
upon the highways of this state while his or her commercial driver's license
or privilege to operate a commercial motor vehicle is suspended, revoked,
or canceled, while subject to a disqualification or an out-of-service order,
or while there is an out-of-service order in effect for the commercial motor
vehicle being operated or for the motor carrier operation.</para>
<para>(3) No person
shall operate a commercial motor vehicle transporting sixteen or more passengers
including the driver upon the highways of this state while his or her commercial
driver's license or privilege to operate a commercial motor vehicle is suspended,
revoked, or canceled, while subject to a disqualification or an out-of-service
order, or while there is an out-of-service order in effect for the commercial
motor vehicle being operated or for the motor carrier operation.</para>
<para>(4) No person shall operate
a commercial motor vehicle upon the highways of this state while he or she
is disqualified under section 60-4,168.</para>
<para>(5) Any person
operating a commercial motor vehicle in violation of subsection (1), (2),
(3), or (4) of this section shall (a) for a first such offense, be guilty
of a Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part of the judgment
of conviction, order such person not to operate any commercial motor vehicle
for any purpose for a period of one year from the date ordered by the court
and also order the commercial driver's license of such person to be revoked
for a like period and (b) for each subsequent such offense, be guilty of a
Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part of the judgment of conviction,
order such person not to operate any commercial motor vehicle for any purpose
for a period of two years from the date ordered by the court and also order
the commercial driver's license of such person to be revoked for a like period.
Such orders of the court shall be administered upon sentencing, upon final
judgment of any appeal or review, or upon the date that any probation is revoked,
whichever is later.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section, out-of-service order has the same
meaning as in section 75-362.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB204, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>