<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-399"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-399</statuteno><catchline>Display of plates; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise specifically provided, no person shall operate or park or cause to be operated or parked a motor vehicle or tow or park or cause to be towed or parked a trailer on the highways unless such motor vehicle or trailer has displayed the proper number of plates as required in the Motor Vehicle Registration Act.</para><para>In each registration period in which new license plates are not issued, previously issued license plates shall have affixed thereto the validation decals issued pursuant to section 60-3,101. In all cases such license plates shall be securely fastened in an upright position to the motor vehicle or trailer so as to prevent such plates from swinging and at a minimum distance of twelve inches from the ground to the bottom of the license plate. No person shall attach to or display on such motor vehicle or trailer any (a) license plate or registration certificate other than as assigned to it for the current registration period, (b) fictitious or altered license plates or registration certificate, (c) license plates or registration certificate that has been canceled by the department, or (d) license plates lacking current validation decals.</para><para>(2) All letters, numbers, printing, writing, and other identification marks upon such plates and certificate shall be kept clear and distinct and free from grease, dust, or other blurring matter, so that they shall be plainly visible at all times during daylight and under artificial light in the nighttime.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 99. </para></source><annotation><para>"Display" of license plates as described in this section logically implies a display of the license plate which is visible. State v. Reiter, 3 Neb. App. 153, 524 N.W.2d 575 (1994).</para><para>Officer properly stopped vehicle bearing both Missouri license plates and in transit sticker, and when driver failed to produce identification, and upon noticing scratches around vehicle identification number checked to determine whether vehicle was stolen, upon learning it was, was justified in making arrest. United States v. Harris, 528 F.2d 1327 (8th Cir. 1975).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>