<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id16">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id18" statutenumber="60-498.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-498.01</statuteno><catchline id="id21">Driving under
influence of alcohol; operator's license; confiscation and revocation; application
for ignition interlock permit; procedures; appeal; restrictions relating to
ignition interlock permit; prohibited acts relating to ignition interlock
devices; additional revocation period.</catchline><para>(1) Because
persons who drive while under the influence of alcohol present a hazard to
the health and safety of all persons using the highways, a procedure is needed
for the swift and certain revocation of the operator's license of any person
who has shown himself or herself to be a health and safety hazard (a) by driving
with an excessive concentration of alcohol in his or her body or (b) by driving
while under the influence of alcohol.</para>
<para>(2) If a person arrested as described in subsection (2) of
section 60-6,197 refuses to submit to the chemical test of blood, breath,
or urine required by section 60-6,197, the test shall not be given except
as provided in section 60-6,210 for the purpose of medical treatment and the
arresting peace officer, as agent for the director, shall verbally serve notice
to the arrested person of the intention to immediately confiscate and revoke
the operator's license of such person and that the revocation will be automatic
fifteen days after the date of arrest. The arresting peace officer shall within
ten days forward to the director a sworn report stating (a) that the person
was arrested as described in subsection (2) of section 60-6,197 and the reasons
for such arrest, (b) that the person was requested to submit to the required
test, and (c) that the person refused to submit to the required test. The
director may accept a sworn report submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(3) If a person arrested as described in subsection (2) of
section 60-6,197 submits to the chemical test of blood or breath required
by section 60-6,197, the test discloses the presence of alcohol in any of
the concentrations specified in section 60-6,196, and the test results are
available to the arresting peace officer while the arrested person is still
in custody, the arresting peace officer, as agent for the director, shall
verbally serve notice to the arrested person of the intention to immediately
confiscate and revoke the operator's license of such person and that the revocation
will be automatic fifteen days after the date of arrest. The arresting peace
officer shall within ten days forward to the director a sworn report stating
(a) that the person was arrested as described in subsection (2) of section
60-6,197 and the reasons for such arrest, (b) that the person was requested
to submit to the required test, and (c) that the person submitted to a test,
the type of test to which he or she submitted, and that such test revealed
the presence of alcohol in a concentration specified in section 60-6,196.
The director may accept a sworn report submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(4) On behalf of the director, the arresting peace officer
submitting a sworn report under subsection (2) or (3) of this section shall
serve notice of the revocation on the arrested person, and the revocation
shall be effective fifteen days after the date of arrest. The notice of revocation
shall contain a statement explaining the operation of the administrative license
revocation procedure. The peace officer shall also provide to the arrested
person information prepared and approved by the director describing how to
request an administrative license revocation hearing or apply for an ignition
interlock permit from the department. A petition for an administrative license
revocation hearing must be completed and delivered to the department or postmarked
within ten days after the person's arrest or the person's right to an administrative
license revocation hearing to contest the revocation will be foreclosed. The
director shall prepare and approve the information form, the application for
an ignition interlock permit, and
the notice of revocation and shall provide them to law enforcement agencies.</para>
<para>If the person has an operator's license, the arresting peace
officer shall take possession of the license and issue a temporary operator's
license valid for fifteen days. The arresting peace officer shall forward
the operator's license to the department along with the sworn report made
under subsection (2) or (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(5)(a) If the results of a chemical test indicate the presence
of alcohol in a concentration specified in section 60-6,196, the results are
not available to the arresting peace officer while the arrested person is
in custody, and the notice of revocation has not been served as required by
subsection (4) of this section, the peace officer shall forward to the director
a sworn report containing the information prescribed by subsection (3) of
this section within ten days after receipt of the results of the chemical
test. If the sworn report is not received within ten days, the revocation
shall not take effect. The director may accept a sworn report submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(b) Upon receipt of the report, the director shall serve the
notice of revocation on the arrested person by mail to the address appearing
on the records of the director. If the address on the director's records differs
from the address on the arresting peace officer's report, the notice shall
be sent to both addresses. The notice of revocation shall contain a statement
explaining the operation of the administrative license revocation procedure.
The director shall also provide to the arrested person information prepared
and approved by the director describing how to request an administrative license
revocation hearing and an application for an ignition interlock permit. A
petition for an administrative license revocation hearing must be completed
and delivered to the department or postmarked within ten days after the mailing
of the notice of revocation or the person's right to an administrative license
revocation hearing to contest the revocation will be foreclosed. The director
shall prepare and approve the ignition interlock permit application and the
notice of revocation. The revocation shall be effective fifteen days after
the date of mailing.</para>
<para>(c) If the records of the director indicate that the arrested
person possesses an operator's license, the director shall include with the
notice of revocation a temporary operator's license which expires fifteen
days after the date of mailing. Any arrested person who desires an administrative
license revocation hearing and has been served a notice of revocation pursuant
to this subsection shall return his or her operator's license with the petition
requesting the hearing. If the operator's license is not included with the
petition requesting the hearing, the director shall deny the petition.</para>
<para>(6)(a) An arrested person's operator's license confiscated
pursuant to subsection (4) of this section shall be automatically revoked
upon the expiration of fifteen days after the date of arrest, and the petition
requesting the hearing shall be completed and delivered to the department
or postmarked within ten days after the person's arrest. An arrested person's
operator's license confiscated pursuant to subsection (5) of this section
shall be automatically revoked upon the expiration of fifteen days after the
date of mailing of the notice of revocation by the director, and the arrested
person shall postmark or return to the director a petition within ten days
after the mailing of the notice of revocation if the arrested person desires
an administrative license revocation hearing. The petition shall be in writing
and shall state the grounds on which the person is relying to prevent the
revocation from becoming effective. The hearing and any prehearing conference
may be conducted in person or by telephone, television, or other electronic
means at the discretion of the director, and all parties may participate by
such means at the discretion of the director.</para>
<para>(b) The director shall conduct the hearing within twenty days
after a petition is received by the director. Upon receipt of a petition,
the director shall notify the petitioner of the date and location for the
hearing by mail postmarked at least seven days prior to the hearing date.
The filing of the petition shall not prevent the automatic revocation of the
petitioner's operator's license at the expiration of the fifteen-day period.
A continuance of the hearing to a date beyond the expiration of the temporary
operator's license shall stay the expiration of the temporary license when
the request for continuance is made by the director.</para>
<para>(c) At hearing the issues under dispute shall be limited to:</para>
<para>(i) In the case of a refusal to submit to a chemical test
of blood, breath, or urine:</para>
<para>(A) Did the peace officer have probable cause to believe the
person was operating or in the actual physical control of a motor vehicle
in violation of section 60-6,196 or a city or village ordinance enacted in
conformance with such section; and</para>
<para>(B) Did the person refuse to submit to or fail to complete
a chemical test after being requested to do so by the peace officer; or</para>
<para>(ii) If the chemical test discloses the presence of alcohol
in a concentration specified in section 60-6,196:</para>
<para>(A) Did the peace officer have probable cause to believe the
person was operating or in the actual physical control of a motor vehicle
in violation of section 60-6,196 or a city or village ordinance enacted in
conformance with such section; and</para>
<para>(B) Was the person operating or in the actual physical control
of a motor vehicle while having an alcohol concentration in violation of subsection
(1) of section 60-6,196.</para>
<para>(7)(a) Any arrested person who submits an application for
an ignition interlock permit in lieu of a petition for an administrative license
revocation hearing regarding the revocation of his or her operator's license
pursuant to this section shall complete the application for an ignition interlock
permit in which such person acknowledges that he or she understands that he
or she will have his or her license administratively revoked pursuant to this
section, that he or she waives his or her right to a hearing to contest the
revocation, and that he or she understands that he or she is required to have
an ignition interlock permit in order to operate a motor vehicle for the period
of the revocation and shall include sufficient evidence that an ignition interlock
device is installed on one or more vehicles that will be operated by the arrested
person. Upon the arrested person's completion of the ignition interlock permit
application process, the department shall issue the person an ignition interlock
permit, subject to any applicable requirements and any applicable no-drive
period if the person is otherwise eligible.</para>
<para>(b) An arrested person who is issued an ignition interlock
permit pursuant to this section shall receive day-for-day credit for the period
he or she has a valid ignition interlock permit against the license revocation
period imposed by the court arising from the same incident.</para>
<para>(c) If a person files a completed application for an ignition
interlock permit, the person waives his or her right to contest the revocation
of his or her operator's license.</para>
<para>(8) Any person who has not petitioned for an administrative
license revocation hearing and is subject to an administrative license revocation
may immediately apply for an ignition interlock permit to use during the applicable
period of revocation set forth in section 60-498.02, subject to the following
additional restrictions:</para>
<para>(a) If such person submitted to a chemical test which disclosed
the presence of a concentration of alcohol in violation of section 60-6,196
and has no prior administrative license revocations on which final orders
have been issued during the immediately preceding fifteen-year period at the
time the order of revocation is issued, the ignition interlock permit will
be immediately available fifteen days after the date of arrest or the date
notice of revocation was provided to the arrested person, as long as he or
she is otherwise eligible for an ignition interlock permit, upon completion
of an application process for an ignition interlock permit;</para>
<para>(b) If such person submitted to a chemical test which disclosed
the presence of a concentration of alcohol in violation of section 60-6,196
and has one or more prior administrative license revocations on which final
orders have been issued during the immediately preceding fifteen-year period
at the time the order of revocation is issued, the ignition interlock permit
will be available beginning fifteen days after the date of arrest or the date
notice of revocation was provided to the arrested person plus forty-five additional
days of no driving, as long as he or she is otherwise eligible for an ignition
interlock permit, upon completion of an application process for an ignition
interlock permit;</para>
<para>(c) If such person refused to submit to a chemical test of
blood, breath, or urine as required by section 60-6,197, the ignition interlock
permit will be available beginning fifteen days after the date of arrest plus
ninety additional days of no driving, as long as he or she is otherwise eligible
for an ignition interlock permit, upon completion of an application process
for an ignition interlock permit; and</para>
<para>(d) Any person who petitions for an administrative license
revocation hearing shall not be eligible for an ignition interlock permit
unless ordered by the court at the time of sentencing for the related criminal
proceeding.</para>
<para>(9) The director shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to govern the conduct of the administrative license revocation hearing and
insure that the hearing will proceed in an orderly manner. The director may
appoint a hearing officer to preside at the hearing, administer oaths, examine
witnesses, take testimony, and report to the director. Any motion for discovery
filed by the petitioner shall entitle the prosecutor to receive full statutory
discovery from the petitioner upon a prosecutor's request to the relevant
court pursuant to section 29-1912 in any criminal proceeding arising from
the same arrest. A copy of the motion for discovery shall be filed with the
department and a copy provided to the prosecutor in the jurisdiction in which
the petitioner was arrested. Incomplete discovery shall not stay the hearing
unless the petitioner requests a continuance. All proceedings before the hearing
officer shall be recorded. Upon receipt of the arresting peace officer's sworn
report, the director's order of revocation has prima facie validity and it
becomes the petitioner's burden to establish by a preponderance of the evidence
grounds upon which the operator's license revocation should not take effect.
The director shall make a determination of the issue within seven days after
the conclusion of the hearing. A person whose operator's license is revoked
following a hearing requested pursuant to this section may appeal the order
of revocation as provided in section 60-498.04.</para>
<para>(10) Any person who tampers with or circumvents an ignition
interlock device installed pursuant to sections 60-498.01 to 60-498.04 or
who operates a motor vehicle not equipped with a functioning ignition interlock
device required pursuant to such sections or otherwise is in violation of
the purposes for operation indicated on the ignition interlock permit under
such sections shall, in addition to any possible criminal charges, have his
or her revocation period and ignition interlock permit extended for six months
beyond the end of the original revocation period.</para>
<para>(11) A person
under the age of eighteen years who holds any license or permit issued under
the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act and has violated subdivision (3)(b)
or (c) of section 28-306, subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-394, or
section 28-1254, 60-6,196, 60-6,197, or 60-6,197.06 shall not be eligible
for an ignition interlock permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1095, &#167; 5; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1972, &#167; 39-727.16; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 872, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 291, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-669.15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 300; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 939, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 51; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 60-6,205; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 20.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Constitutionality</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Refusal to submit to test</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Rules and regulations</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Venue</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Prima facie case</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>6. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Constitutionality</emphasis></para><para>The administrative license revocation provisions pertaining to motorists who refuse to submit to chemical testing do not violate the due process or equal protection rights of those motorists by treating them differently than motorists who submit to, but fail, such testing. Betterman v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 273 Neb. 178, 728 N.W.2d 570 (2007).</para><para>The due process rights of a motorist who refuses to submit to chemical testing are not violated by this section even though the statutory scheme does not operate to reinstate the motorist's administratively revoked driver's license if he or she is acquitted of the criminal refusal charge. Kenley v. Neth, 271 Neb. 402, 712 N.W.2d 251 (2006).</para><para>This section does not violate the Equal Protection Clauses of the federal and state Constitutions by treating motorists who refuse to submit to chemical testing differently than motorists who submit to, but fail, such testing. Kenley v. Neth, 271 Neb. 402, 712 N.W.2d 251 (2006).</para><para>Although this section does not allow a motorist to challenge the validity of the initial traffic stop, it does not violate due process because the Fourth Amendment exclusionary rule is not applicable in civil license revocation proceedings. Chase v. Neth, 269 Neb. 882, 697 N.W.2d 675 (2005).</para><para>This section does not create an unconstitutional classification between those who submit to urine tests and those who submit to blood and breath tests pursuant to this section. Kalisek v. Abramson, 257 Neb. 517, 599 N.W.2d 834 (1999).</para><para>Administrative license revocation statutes are reviewed using the rational relationship standard of review. The administrative license revocation statutes do not violate equal protection, nor do they constitute cruel and unusual punishment. Schindler v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 256 Neb. 782, 593 N.W.2d 295 (1999).</para><para>The Legislature intended administrative license revocation to be a civil sanction, and the sanction is not so punitive in purpose or effect as to negate the Legislature's intent; therefore, administrative license revocation for failure to submit to a chemical test does not violate double jeopardy. State v. Howell, 254 Neb. 247, 575 N.W.2d 861 (1998).</para><para>The purpose of administrative license revocation is to protect the public from the health and safety hazards of driving and to deter drunk driving. Criminal prosecution and punishment following a hearing under this section do not violate the Double Jeopardy Clause of the U.S. Constitution. State v. Young, 249 Neb. 539, 544 N.W.2d 808 (1996).</para><para><emphasis>2. Refusal to submit to test</emphasis></para><para>The sworn report of the arresting officer must indicate (1) that the person was arrested as described in section 60-6,197(2) and the reasons for the arrest, (2) that the person was requested to submit to the required test, and (3) that the person refused to submit to the required test. Nothnagel v. Neth, 276 Neb. 95, 752 N.W.2d 149 (2008).</para><para>Failure to produce an adequate breath sample constitutes a refusal to submit to breath test. Porter v. Jensen, 223 Neb. 438, 390 N.W.2d 511 (1986).</para><para>A motorist's subsequent offer to take a blood alcohol test previously refused does not nullify or cure such driver's initial refusal to take the test requested by the arresting officer. Hoyle v. Peterson, 216 Neb. 253, 343 N.W.2d 730 (1984).</para><para>Adoption of this section did not change rule that refusal to submit to test may be shown in prosecution for driving while under influence of intoxicating liquor. State v. Meints, 189 Neb. 264, 202 N.W.2d 202 (1972).</para><para><emphasis>3. Rules and regulations</emphasis></para><para>When the applicable rules and regulations are not strictly complied with, the Department of Motor Vehicles cannot obtain the benefit of a presumption that all facts recited in the sworn report are true. Morrissey v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 264 Neb. 456, 647 N.W.2d 644 (2002).</para><para>Due process is denied where the rules and regulations governing the administrative license revocation procedure were not on file with the Secretary of State for at least 5 days at the time of the arrest. Dannehl v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 3 Neb. App. 492, 529 N.W.2d 100 (1995).</para><para><emphasis>4. Venue</emphasis></para><para>For purposes of subsection (6)(a) of this section, an administrative license revocation hearing is held at the location of the hearing officer. Gracey v. Zwonechek, 263 Neb. 796, 643 N.W.2d 381 (2002).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (6)(a) of this section, generalized objections directed to the method by which a license revocation hearing was being held are not objections to venue. Davis v. Wimes, 263 Neb. 504, 641 N.W.2d 37 (2002).</para><para>Subsection (6)(a) of this section is a venue statute. Reiter v. Wimes, 263 Neb. 277, 640 N.W.2d 19 (2002).</para><para>Subsection (6)(a) of this section, establishing the location for administrative license revocation hearings, is a venue statute. A telephonic hearing under the Administrative Procedure Act pertaining to license revocation is subject to the terms of subsection (6)(a) of this section. Muir v. Nebraska Dept. of Motor Vehicles, 260 Neb. 450, 618 N.W.2d 444 (2000).</para><para><emphasis>5. Prima facie case</emphasis></para><para>An arresting officer's sworn report triggers the administrative license revocation process by establishing a prima facie basis for revocation. The sworn report must, at a minimum, contain the information specified in this section in order to confer jurisdiction. Murray v. Neth, 279 Neb. 947, 783 N.W.2d 424 (2010).</para><para>The arresting officer's sworn report triggers the administrative license revocation process by establishing a prima facie basis for revocation. Nothnagel v. Neth, 276 Neb. 95, 752 N.W.2d 149 (2008).</para><para>A sworn statement containing the recitations required by this section establishes a prima facie case under the provisions of the administrative license revocation statutes. McPherrin v. Conrad, 248 Neb. 561, 537 N.W.2d 498 (1995).</para><para>The burden is upon the state to make a prima facie case for revocation before the director. Mackey v. Director of Motor Vehicles, 194 Neb. 707, 235 N.W.2d 394 (1975).</para><para>Once the arresting officer's sworn report is received, the case for revocation has prima facie validity and it becomes the petitioner's burden to establish by a preponderance of the evidence grounds upon which the operator's license revocation should not take effect. Scott v. State, 13 Neb. App. 867, 703 N.W.2d 266 (2005).</para><para><emphasis>6. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The Department of Motor Vehicles has the power, in an administrative license revocation proceeding, to evaluate the jurisdictional averments in a sworn report and, if necessary, solicit a sworn addendum to that report if necessary to establish jurisdiction to proceed. Murray v. Neth, 279 Neb. 947, 783 N.W.2d 424 (2010).</para><para>An acknowledgment on a sworn report which does not set forth the name of the individual making the acknowledgment, i.e., the arresting officer, does not substantially comply with the requirements of Nebraska law. Johnson v. Neth, 276 Neb. 886, 758 N.W.2d 395 (2008).</para><para>Sworn reports in administrative license revocation proceedings are, by definition, affidavits. Johnson v. Neth, 276 Neb. 886, 758 N.W.2d 395 (2008).</para><para>Although this section limits the issues under dispute, it does not prohibit evidence pertinent to the issue of enhancement after those issues have been resolved. Stenger v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 274 Neb. 819, 743 N.W.2d 758 (2008).</para><para>In an administrative license revocation proceeding, the sworn report of the arresting officer must, at a minimum, contain the information specified in subsection (3) of this section in order to confer jurisdiction. Snyder v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 274 Neb. 168, 736 N.W.2d 731 (2007).</para><para>In an administrative license revocation proceeding, the sworn report of the arresting officer must, at a minimum, contain the information specified in the applicable statute in order to confer jurisdiction. Betterman v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 273 Neb. 178, 728 N.W.2d 570 (2007).</para><para>The failure to hold a hearing within the time provided in subsection (6)(b) of this section does not invalidate the administrative license revocation proceeding unless the motorist can show that he or she was prejudiced by the delay. Betterman v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 273 Neb. 178, 728 N.W.2d 570 (2007).</para><para>A report that does not contain the affirmation of an "arresting peace officer" that the facts recited in the report are true is not a proper "sworn report" as required by this section. Arndt v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 270 Neb. 172, 699 N.W.2d 39 (2005).</para><para>An arresting officer's sworn report must, at a minimum, contain the information specified in this section in order to confer jurisdiction upon the Department of Motor Vehicles to revoke an operator's license. Hahn v. Neth, 270 Neb. 164, 699 N.W.2d 32 (2005).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the administrative license revocation process must be based on a valid arrest, because the sworn report which triggers the administrative license revocation must be prepared by an "arresting peace officer" who has "validly arrested" a driver. Young v. Neth, 263 Neb. 20, 637 N.W.2d 884 (2002).</para><para>Under subsection (6)(c)(i)(A) of this section, a peace officer must have probable cause prior to revoking a driver's license for refusal to submit to a chemical test. State v. Howell, 254 Neb. 247, 575 N.W.2d 861 (1998).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, after January 1, 1993, a person who agrees to submit to a chemical test and fails it is subject to automatic administrative license revocation. Smith v. State, 248 Neb. 360, 535 N.W.2d 694 (1995).</para><para>The oath to an affidavit is not required to be administered with any particular ceremony, but the affiant must perform some corporal act whereby he consciously takes upon himself the obligation of an oath. Moore v. Peterson, 218 Neb. 615, 358 N.W.2d 193 (1984).</para><para>This section simply forstalls a forcible taking of a specimen. Wiseman v. Sullivan, 190 Neb. 724, 211 N.W.2d 906 (1973).</para><para>This section is pari materia with section 39-727.03 (transferred to section 60-6,197), and other sections mentioned in opinion. Stevenson v. Sullivan, 190 Neb. 295, 207 N.W.2d 680 (1973).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the failure of the notary to include the expiration date of his or her commission on the sworn report does not render such sworn report invalid because the presence of a notarial seal and the notary's signature serves as presumptive evidence of the performance of the notary's duty. Valeriano-Cruz v. Neth, 14 Neb. App. 855, 716 N.W.2d 765 (2006).</para><para>Although this section requires the "sworn report" required by subsection (2) of this section to include the "reasons for [the] arrest," an arresting officer need not specifically delineate on the sworn report all of the information contained on an attached probable cause form, so long as the sworn report provides adequate notice that one is being accused of driving under the influence and/or failure of a chemical test. Taylor v. Wimes, 10 Neb. App. 432, 632 N.W.2d 366 (2001).</para><para>When an arrested driver is released before the results of blood alcohol content testing are known to the arresting officer, then under subsection (5)(a) of this section (60-6,205 (Reissue 1993)) the arresting officer is "unable to serve" notice, and the statutory provision allowing service by certified mail by the Department of Motor Vehicles becomes operative. Kuebler v. Abramson, 4 Neb. App. 420, 544 N.W.2d 513 (1996).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>