<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id94">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id96" statutenumber="60-180"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-180</statuteno><catchline id="id99">Violations; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) A person who operates in this state a vehicle for which
a certificate of title is required without having such certificate in accordance
with the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act or upon which the certificate
of title has been canceled is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(2) A person who is a dealer or acting on behalf of a dealer
and who acquires, purchases, holds, or displays for sale a new vehicle without
having obtained a manufacturer's or importer's certificate or a certificate
of title therefor as provided for in the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title
Act is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(3) A person who fails to surrender any certificate of title
or any certificate of registration or license plates or tags upon cancellation
of the same by the department and notice thereof as prescribed in the Motor
Vehicle Certificate of Title Act is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(4) A person who fails to surrender the certificate of title
to the county treasurer
or department as provided in section 60-169 in case of the destruction
or dismantling or change of a vehicle in such respect that it is not the vehicle
described in the certificate of title is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(5) A person who purports to sell or transfer a vehicle without
delivering to the purchaser or transferee thereof a certificate of title or
a manufacturer's or importer's certificate thereto duly assigned to such purchaser
as provided in the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act is guilty of a Class
III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(6) A person who knowingly alters or defaces a certificate
of title or manufacturer's or importer's certificate is guilty of a Class
III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(7) Except as otherwise provided in section 60-179, a person
who violates any of the other provisions of the Motor Vehicle Certificate
of Title Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant
to the act is guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 49.</para></source><annotation><para>Legislature contemplated that form provided must be fully and properly executed. Loyal's Auto Exchange, Inc. v. Munch, 153 Neb. 628, 45 N.W.2d 913 (1951).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>