 <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-490" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-490</statuteno><catchline>Operators' licenses; state identification cards; expiration; renewal.</catchline><para>(1) Operators' licenses issued to persons required to use bioptic or telescopic lenses as provided in section 60-4,118 shall expire annually on the licensee's birthday for all such licenses issued prior to January 1, 2007, and on the licensee's birthday in the second year after issuance, unless specifically restricted to a shorter renewal period as determined under section 60-4,118, for all such licenses issued on or after January 1, 2007.</para><para>(2) Except for state identification cards issued to persons less than twenty-one years of age, all state identification cards expire on the cardholder's birthday in the fifth year after issuance. A state identification card issued to a person who is less than twenty-one years of age expires on his or her twenty-first birthday or on his or her birthday in the fifth year after issuance, whichever comes first.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (1) of this section and section 60-4,147.05 and except for operators' licenses issued to persons less than twenty-one years of age, operators' licenses issued pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act expire on the licensee's birthday in the fifth year after issuance. An operator's license issued to a person less than twenty-one years of age expires on his or her twenty-first birthday. Except as otherwise provided in section 60-4,147.05, the Department of Motor Vehicles shall mail out a renewal notice for each operator's license at least thirty days before the expiration of the operator's license.</para><para>(4)(a) The expiration date shall be stated on each operator's license or state identification card.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in section 60-4,147.05, licenses and state identification cards issued to persons who are twenty-one years of age or older which expire under this section may be renewed within a ninety-day period before the expiration date. Any person who is twenty-one years of age or older and who is the holder of a valid operator's license or state identification card may renew his or her license or card prior to the ninety-day period before the expiration date on such license or card if such applicant furnishes proof that he or she will be absent from the state during the ninety-day period prior to such expiration date.</para><para>(c) A person who is twenty years of age may apply for an operator's license or a state identification card within sixty days prior to his or her twenty-first birthday. The operator's license or state identification card may be issued within ten days prior to such birthday.</para><para>(d) A person who is under twenty years of age and who holds a state identification card may apply for renewal within a ninety-day period prior to the expiration date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 742, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 7, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 1, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1008, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>