<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,224"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,224</statuteno><catchline>Headlights; glare; duty of operator; penalty.</catchline><para>Notwithstanding any other provision of the Nebraska Rules of the Road:</para><para>(1) Whenever any person operating a motor vehicle on any highway in this state meets another person operating a motor vehicle, proceeding in the opposite direction and equipped with headlights constructed and adjusted to project glaring or dazzling light to persons in front of such headlights, upon signal of either person, the other shall dim the headlights of his or her motor vehicle or tilt the beams of glaring or dazzling light projecting therefrom downward so as not to blind or confuse the vision of the operator in front of such headlights; and</para><para>(2) Whenever any person operating a motor vehicle on any highway in this state follows another vehicle within two hundred feet to the rear, he or she shall dim the headlights of his or her motor vehicle or tilt the beams of glaring or dazzling light projecting therefrom downward.</para><para>Any person who violates any provision of this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1931, c. 106, &#167; 1, p. 279; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-1121; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-733; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 231, &#167; 1, p. 720; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-733; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 593, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-628.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 320. </para></source>
<annotation><para>The specific duty of a driver to dim a vehicle's lights in response to a signal from an oncoming driver is set forth in this section. State v. Carnicle, 18 Neb. App. 761, 792 N.W.2d 893 (2010).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc> 