  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,130"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,130</statuteno><catchline>Employment driving permit; application; contents; driver improvement course; violations; penalty; loss of eligibility; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) Application for an employment driving permit shall be made to the Department of Motor Vehicles on forms furnished for that purpose by the department. The application form shall contain such information as deemed necessary by the director to carry out this section and section 60-4,129. If the department has a digital image and digital signature of the applicant preserved in the digital system implemented under section 60-484.01, the employment driving permit, if issued, may contain such image and signature. The application form shall also include a voter registration portion pursuant to section 32-308 and the following specific question: Do you wish to register to vote as part of this application process? To be eligible for an employment driving permit, the applicant shall furnish, along with the application to the director, the following:</para><para>(a) An affidavit from the applicant's employer stating that such applicant is required to operate a motor vehicle from his or her residence to his or her place of employment and return;</para><para>(b) If such applicant requires the use of a motor vehicle during the normal course of employment, an affidavit from the applicant's employer setting forth the facts establishing such requirement;</para><para>(c) An affidavit stating that there exists no other reasonable alternative means of transportation to and from work available to the applicant; and</para><para>(d) If the applicant is self-employed, an affidavit to the department setting forth the provisions of his or her employment.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, upon making application for such permit, the applicant shall certify that he or she will attend and complete, within sixty days, a driver improvement course presented by the department or show successful completion of the driver education and training course as provided in section 60-4,183. If such course is not completed, the employment driving permit shall be surrendered to the department. If any person fails to return to the department the permit as provided in this subsection, the department shall direct any peace officer or authorized representative of the department to secure possession of the permit and to return the permit to the department. An applicant whose operator's license has been suspended pursuant to section 43-3318 is not required to fulfill such driver improvement or education and training course requirements. All applicants shall file and maintain proof of financial responsibility as required by the Motor Vehicle Safety Responsibility Act.</para><para>(3) Any person who fails to surrender a permit, as required by this section, shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>(4) The fee prescribed in section 60-4,115 shall be submitted to the department along with the application for an employment driving permit.</para><para>(5) When the holder of an employment driving permit is convicted, on or after the date of issuance of the employment driving permit, of any traffic violation or of operating a motor vehicle for a purpose other than specified by such permit, the person shall not be eligible to receive another employment driving permit during that particular period of revocation. This subsection does not apply to a holder of an employment driving permit if the reason for his or her license revocation or suspension only involved a suspension under section 43-3318 and not a revocation under any other section.</para><para>(6) Any person who feels himself or herself aggrieved because of the refusal of the director to issue the employment driving permit may appeal in the manner set forth in section 60-4,105.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 259, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 38; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-669.35; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 80; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 573; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 141; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 21. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Safety Responsibility Act,</emphasis> see section 60-569.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 