<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id998"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,144.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,144.02</statuteno><catchline>Commercial drivers' licenses; CLP-commercial learner's permit; medical examiner's certificate; variance; department; duties; failure of driver to comply; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For each operator of a commercial motor vehicle required to have a commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit, the department, in compliance with 49 C.F.R. 383.73 and 49 C.F.R. 384.225, shall:</para><para>(a) Post the driver's self-certification of type of driving under section 60-4,144.01 to the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record;</para><para>(b) Retain the medical examiner's certificate of any driver required to provide documentation of physical qualification for three years beyond the date the certificate was issued;</para><para>(c) Post the information from the medical examiner's certificate received from the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration to the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record, including:</para><para>(i) The medical examiner's name;</para><para>(ii) The medical examiner's telephone number;</para><para>(iii) The date of the medical examiner's certificate issuance;</para><para>(iv) The medical examiner's license number and the state that issued it;</para><para>(v) The medical examiner's National Registry identification number;</para><para>(vi) The indicator of the medical certification status, either "certified" or "not-certified";</para><para>(vii) The expiration date of the medical examiner's certificate;</para><para>(viii) The existence of any medical variance on the medical certificate, such as an exemption letter, Skill Performance Evaluation certification, or grandfather provisions;</para><para>(ix) Any restrictions, for example, corrective lenses, hearing aid, or required to have possession of an exemption letter or Skill Performance Evaluation certificate while on duty; and</para><para>(x) The date the medical examiner's certificate information was posted to the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record;</para><para>(d) Before June 23, 2025, post the medical variance information received from the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration within ten business days to the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record, including the:</para><para>(i) Date of medical variance issuance or renewal; and</para><para>(ii) Expiration date of medical variance; and</para><para>(e) Beginning on an implementation date designated by the director, but not later than June 23, 2025, post the medical variance information electronically received from the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration within one business day to the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record, including the:</para><para>(i) Date of medical variance issuance or renewal; and</para><para>(ii) Expiration date of medical variance.</para><para>(2)(a) If a driver's medical certification or medical variance expires, or the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration notifies the department that a medical variance was removed or rescinded, the department shall:</para><para>(i) Notify the holder of the commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit of his or her "not-certified" medical certification status and that the CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license privilege will be removed from the driver's license or permit unless the driver submits a current medical certificate or medical variance or changes his or her self-certification to driving only in excepted commerce, if permitted by the department;</para><para>(ii) Initiate established department procedures for downgrading the license. The commercial driver's license downgrade shall be completed and recorded within sixty days of the driver's medical certification status becoming "not-certified" to operate a commercial motor vehicle; and</para><para>(iii)(A) Before June 23, 2025, update the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record as "not-certified" within ten calendar days; and</para><para>(B) Beginning on an implementation date designated by the director, but not later than June 23, 2025, update the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record as "not-certified" within one business day.</para><para>(b)(i) Before June 23, 2025, if a driver fails to provide the department with the certification contained in 49 C.F.R. 383.71(b)(1)(i), or a current medical examiner's certificate if the driver self-certifies according to 49 C.F.R. 383.71(b)(1)(i) that he or she is operating in nonexcepted interstate commerce as required by 49 C.F.R. 383.71(h), the department shall mark that Commercial Driver License Information System driver record as "not-certified" and initiate a commercial driver's license downgrade following department procedures in accordance with subdivision (2)(a)(ii) of this section. The CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license shall be canceled and marked as "not-certified".</para><para>(ii) Beginning on an implementation date designated by the director, but not later than June 23, 2025, for any driver who fails to maintain the certification required by 49 C.F.R. 383.71(b)(1) or for any driver who self-certifies pursuant to 49 C.F.R. 383.71(b)(1)(i) that the driver is operating in nonexcepted interstate commerce pursuant to 49 C.F.R. 383.71(h), the department shall:</para><para>(A) Update the Commercial Driver License Information System driver record for such driver as "not-certified";</para><para>(B) Initiate a downgrade for such driver following department procedures in accordance with subdivision (2)(a) of this section;</para><para>(C) Cancel the CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license for such driver; and</para><para>(D) Mark the CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license for such driver as "not-certified".</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB666, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB398, &#167; 46. </para><operativedate>June 5, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>