<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section><?Pub Caret?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-487"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-487</statuteno><catchline>Cancellation of operator's license
or commercial driver's license; when.</catchline><para>(1) If any magistrate
or judge finds in his or her judgment of conviction that the application or issuance certificate pursuant to which the director
has issued an operator's license under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License
Act contains any false or fraudulent statement deliberately and knowingly
made to any officer as to any matter material to the issuance of such license
or does not contain required or correct information or that the person to
whom the license was issued was not eligible to receive such license, then
the license shall be absolutely void from the date of issue and such motor
vehicle operator shall be deemed to be not licensed to operate a motor vehicle.
Such license shall be at once canceled of record in his or her office by the
director upon receipt of a copy of such judgment of conviction. The director
may, upon his or her own motion, summarily cancel any license for any of the
reasons set forth in this section if such reason or reasons affirmatively
appear on his or her official records.</para>
<para>(2) If the director determines, in a check of an applicant's license
status and record prior to issuing a commercial driver's license, or at any
time after the commercial driver's license is issued, that the applicant falsified
information contained in the application, the director may summarily cancel
the person's commercial driver's license or his or her pending application
as provided in subsection (1) of this section and disqualify the person from
operating a commercial motor vehicle for sixty days.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 148, &#167; 10, p. 517; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-410; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 20, p. 517; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 124, &#167; 1, p. 469; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-410; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-416; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-416; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 420, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 10.</para><effectivedate>March 11, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>