<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-107"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>60-107</statuteno><catchline>Cabin trailer, defined.</catchline><para>Cabin trailer means a trailer or a semitrailer, which is designed, constructed, and equipped as a dwelling place, living abode, or sleeping place, whether used for such purposes or instead permanently or temporarily for the advertising, sale, display, or promotion of merchandise or services or for any other commercial purpose except transportation of property for hire or transportation of property for distribution by a private carrier. Cabin trailer does not mean a trailer or semitrailer which is permanently attached to real estate. There are four classes of cabin trailers:</para><para>(1) Camping trailer which includes cabin trailers one hundred two inches or less in width and forty feet or less in length and adjusted mechanically smaller for towing;</para><para>(2) Mobile home which includes cabin trailers more than one hundred two inches in width or more than forty feet in length;</para><para>(3) Travel trailer which includes cabin trailers not more than one hundred two inches in width nor more than forty feet in length from front hitch to rear bumper, except as provided in subdivision (2)(k) of section 60-6,288; and</para><para>(4) Manufactured home means a structure, transportable in one or more sections, which in the traveling mode is eight body feet or more in width or forty body feet or more in length or when erected on site is three hundred twenty or more square feet and which is built on a permanent frame and designed to be used as a dwelling with or without a permanent foundation when connected to the required utilities and includes the plumbing, heating, air conditioning, and electrical systems contained in the structure, except that manufactured home includes any structure that meets all of the requirements of this subdivision other than the size requirements and with respect to which the manufacturer voluntarily files a certification required by the United States Secretary of Housing and Urban Development and complies with the standards established under the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974, as such act existed on January 1, 2019, 42 U.S.C. 5401 et seq.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB79, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>