<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id5" statutenumber="60-6,232"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,232</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Rotating or flashing
amber light; when permitted.</catchline><para>A rotating or flashing
amber light or lights shall be displayed on the roof of any motor vehicle
being operated by any rural mail carrier outside the corporate limits of any
municipality in this state on or near any highway in the process of delivering
mail.</para>
<para>A rotating or flashing amber light or lights may be displayed
on (1) any vehicle of the Military Department while on any state emergency
mission, (2) any motor vehicle being operated by any public utility, vehicle
service, or towing service or any publicly or privately owned construction
or maintenance vehicle while performing its duties on or near any highway,
(3) any motor vehicle being operated by any member of the Civil Air Patrol,
(4) any pilot vehicle escorting an overdimensional load, (5) any vehicle while
actually engaged in the moving of houses, buildings, or other objects of extraordinary
bulk, including unbaled livestock forage as authorized by subdivision (2)(f)
of section 60-6,288, (6)
any motor vehicle owned by or operated on behalf of a railroad carrier that
is stopped to load or unload passengers,
or (7) any motor vehicle operated by or for an emergency management worker
as defined in section 81-829.39 or a storm spotter as defined in section 81-829.67
who is activated by a local emergency management organization.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 327, &#167; 4, p. 1171; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 365, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1972, &#167; 39-788.03; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 427, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,150; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 328; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 59, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 471, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB573, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
