<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id34">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id36"  statutenumber="60-465.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-465.02</statuteno><catchline>Covered farm vehicle, defined.</catchline>
<para>(1) Covered
farm vehicle means a motor vehicle, including an articulated motor vehicle:</para>
<para>(a) That:</para>
<para>(i) Is traveling
in the state in which the vehicle is registered or another state;</para>
<para>(ii) Is operated
by:</para><para>(A) A farm owner or operator;</para><para>(B) A ranch owner or operator; or</para>
<para>(C) An employee
or family member of an individual specified in subdivision (1)(a)(ii)(A) or
(1)(a)(ii)(B) of this section;</para><para>(iii) Is transporting to or from a farm
or ranch:</para><para>(A) Agricultural commodities;</para><para>(B) Livestock; or</para><para>(C) Machinery or supplies;</para>
<para>(iv) Except
as provided in subsection (2) of this section, is not used in the operations
of a for-hire motor carrier; and</para><para>(v) Is equipped with a special license plate
or other designation by the state in which the vehicle is registered to allow
for identification of the vehicle as a farm vehicle by law enforcement personnel;
and</para><para>(b) That has a gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight,
whichever is greater, that is:</para><para>(i) Less than twenty-six thousand one pounds;
or</para><para>(ii) Twenty-six thousand one pounds or more and is traveling within
the state or within one hundred fifty air miles of the farm or ranch with
respect to which the vehicle is being operated.</para><para>(2) Covered farm vehicle
includes a motor vehicle that meets the requirements of subsection (1) of
this section, except for subdivision (1)(a)(iv) of this section, and:</para>
<para>(a) Is operated
pursuant to a crop share farm lease agreement;</para><para>(b) Is owned by a tenant
with respect to that agreement; and</para><para>(c) Is transporting the landlord's portion
of the crops under that agreement.</para><para>(3) Covered farm vehicle does not include:</para>
<para>(a) A combination
of truck-tractor and semitrailer which is operated by a person under eighteen
years of age; or</para><para>(b) A combination of truck-tractor and semitrailer which is used
in the transportation of materials found to be hazardous for the purposes
of the federal Hazardous Materials Transportation Act and which require the
combination to be placarded under 49 C.F.R. part 172, subpart F.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>