<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,136" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,136</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Motor vehicle insurance data base; created; powers and duties; Motor Vehicle Insurance Data Base Task Force; created.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The motor vehicle insurance data base is created. The department shall develop and administer the motor vehicle insurance data base which shall include the information provided by insurance companies as required by the department pursuant to sections 60-3,136 to 60-3,139. The motor vehicle insurance data base shall be used to facilitate registration of motor vehicles in this state by the department and its agents. The director may contract with a designated agent for the purpose of establishing and operating the motor vehicle insurance data base and monitoring compliance with the financial responsibility requirements of such sections.</para><para>(b) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out sections 60-3,136 to 60-3,139. The rules and regulations shall include specifications for the information to be transmitted by the insurance companies to the department for inclusion in the motor vehicle insurance data base, and specifications for the form and manner of transmission of data for inclusion in the motor vehicle insurance data base, as recommended by the Motor Vehicle Insurance Data Base Task Force created in subsection (2) of this section in its report to the department.</para><para>(2)(a) The Motor Vehicle Insurance Data Base Task Force is created. The Motor Vehicle Insurance Data Base Task Force shall investigate the best practices of the industry and recommend specifications for the information to be transmitted by the insurance companies to the department for inclusion in the motor vehicle insurance data base and specifications for the form and manner of transmission of data for inclusion in the motor vehicle insurance data base.</para><para>(b) The Motor Vehicle Insurance Data Base Task Force shall consist of:</para><para>(i) The Director of Motor Vehicles or his or her designee;</para><para>(ii) The Director of Insurance or his or her designee;</para><para>(iii) The following members who shall be selected by the Director of Insurance:</para><para>(A) One representative of a domestic automobile insurance company or domestic automobile insurance companies;</para><para>(B) One representative of an admitted foreign automobile insurance company or admitted foreign automobile insurance companies; and</para><para>(C) One representative of insurance producers licensed under the laws of this state; and</para><para>(iv) Four members to be selected by the Director of Motor Vehicles.</para><para>(c) The requirements of this subsection shall expire on July 1, 2004, except that the director may reconvene the task force at any time thereafter if he or she deems it necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB666, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>