<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="60-484.04">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-484.04</statuteno><catchline>Operators' licenses; state identification
cards; applicant present evidence of lawful status.</catchline><para>(1) Except
as provided in section 60-4,144 with respect to operators of commercial motor
vehicles, before being issued any other type of operator's license or a state
identification card under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act, the department
shall require an applicant to present valid documentary evidence that he or
she has lawful status in the United States. Lawful status may be shown by:</para>
<para>(a) A valid, unexpired United States passport;</para>
<para>(b) A certified copy of a birth certificate filed with a state office
of vital statistics or equivalent agency in the individual's state of birth;</para>
<para>(c) A Consular Report of Birth Abroad (CRBA) issued by the United States
Department of State, Form FS-240, DS-1350, or FS-545;</para>
<para>(d) A valid, unexpired Permanent Resident Card (Form I-551) issued by
the United States Department of Homeland Security or United States Citizenship and Immigration
Services;</para>
<para>(e) An unexpired employment authorization document (EAD) issued by the
United States Department of Homeland Security, Form I-766 or Form I-688B;</para>
<para>(f) An unexpired foreign passport with a valid, unexpired United States
visa affixed accompanied by the approved I-94 form documenting the applicant's
most recent admittance into the United States;</para>
<para>(g) A Certificate of Naturalization issued by the United States Department
of Homeland Security, Form N-550 or Form N-570;</para>
<para>(h) A Certificate of Citizenship, Form N-560 or Form N-561, issued by
the United States Department of Homeland Security;</para>
<para>(i) A driver's license or identification card issued in compliance with
the standards established by the REAL ID Act of 2005, Public Law 109-13, division
B, section 1, 119 Stat. 302; or</para>
<para>(j) Such other documents as the director may approve.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If an applicant presents
one of the documents listed under subdivision (1)(a), (b),
(c), (d), (g), or (h) of this section, the verification of the applicant's
identity in the manner prescribed in section 60-484 will also provide satisfactory
evidence of lawful status.</para>
<para>(b) If the applicant presents one of the identity documents listed under
subdivision (1)(e), (f), or (i) of this
section, the verification of the identity documents does not provide satisfactory
evidence of lawful status. The applicant must also present a second document
from subsection (1) of this section or documentation
issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security or other federal
agencies demonstrating lawful status as determined by the United States Citizenship and Immigration
Services.</para>
<para>(3) An applicant may present
other documents as designated by the director as proof of lawful status. Any
documents accepted shall be recorded according to a written exceptions process
established by the director.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 12.</para><operativedate>July 8, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>