<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,141</statuteno><catchline>Agents of department; fees; collection.</catchline><para>(1) The various county treasurers shall act as agents for the department in the collection of all motor vehicle taxes, motor vehicle fees, and registration fees. An approved licensed dealer participating in the electronic dealer services system pursuant to section 60-1507 may collect all such taxes and fees as agent for the appropriate county treasurer and the department in a manner provided by such system.</para><para>(2) While acting as agents pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the county treasurers or any approved licensed dealers participating in the electronic dealer services system shall in addition to the taxes and registration fees collect one dollar and fifty cents for each registration of a motor vehicle or trailer of a resident of the State of Nebraska and four dollars and fifty cents for each registration of a motor vehicle or trailer of a nonresident. The county treasurer shall credit such additional fees collected by the county treasurer or any approved licensed dealer participating in the electronic dealer services system to the county general fund in a manner provided by such system.</para><para>(3) The county treasurers shall transmit all motor vehicle fees and registration fees collected pursuant to this section to the State Treasurer on or before the twentieth day of each month and at such other times as the State Treasurer requires for credit to the Motor Vehicle Fee Fund and the Highway Trust Fund, respectively, except as provided in section 60-3,156. Any county treasurer who fails to transfer to the State Treasurer the amount due the state at the times required in this section shall pay interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.02, as such rate may be adjusted from time to time, from the time the motor vehicle fees and registration fees become due until paid.</para><para>(4) If a registrant requests delivery of license plates, registration certificates, or validation decals by mail, the county treasurer may charge a postage and handling fee in an amount not more than necessary to recover the cost of postage and handling for the specific items mailed to the registrant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 141; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 78; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB207, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 52. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>