
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id5" statutenumber="60-682.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id7">60-682.01</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Speed limit violations;
fines.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who operates a vehicle in
violation of any maximum speed limit established for any highway or freeway
is guilty of a traffic infraction and upon conviction shall be fined:</para>
<para>(a) Ten dollars for traveling one to five miles per hour over
the authorized speed limit;</para>
<para>(b) Twenty-five dollars for traveling over five miles per
hour but not over ten miles per hour over the authorized speed limit;</para>
<para>(c) Seventy-five dollars for traveling over ten miles per
hour but not over fifteen miles per hour over the authorized speed limit;</para>
<para>(d) One hundred twenty-five dollars for traveling over fifteen
miles per hour but not over twenty miles per hour over the authorized speed
limit;</para>
<para>(e) Two hundred dollars for traveling over twenty miles per
hour but not over thirty-five miles per hour over the authorized speed limit;
and</para>
<para>(f) Three hundred dollars for traveling over thirty-five miles
per hour over the authorized speed limit.</para>
<para>(2) The fines prescribed in subsection (1) of this section
shall be doubled if the violation occurs within a maintenance, repair, or
construction zone established pursuant to section 60-6,188. For purposes of
this subsection, maintenance, repair, or construction zone means (a)(i) the portion of a highway identified by
posted or moving signs as being under maintenance, repair, or construction
or (ii) the portion of a highway
identified by maintenance, repair, or construction zone speed limit signs
displayed pursuant to section 60-6,188 and
(b) within such portion of a highway where road construction workers are present.
The maintenance, repair, or construction zone starts at the location of the
first sign identifying the maintenance, repair, or construction zone and continues
until a posted or moving sign indicates that the maintenance, repair, or construction
zone has ended.</para>
<para>(3) The fines prescribed in subsection (1) of this section
shall be doubled if the violation occurs within a school crossing zone as
defined in section 60-658.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 901, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 91, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB621, &#167;  2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB111, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>