<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id470"  statutenumber="60-6,179.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,179.02</statuteno><catchline>Operator of commercial motor
vehicle; operator of certain
passenger motor vehicle; operator of school bus; texting while
driving prohibited; exception; use
of handheld mobile telephone while driving prohibited; exception; violation;
penalty.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (1)(b) of this
section, no operator of a commercial motor vehicle or a motor vehicle designed or used to transport between
nine and fifteen passengers, including the driver, not for direct compensation,
if the vehicle does not otherwise meet the definition of a commercial motor
vehicle, shall engage in texting while driving such vehicle.</para>
<para>(b) Texting while driving
is permissible by an operator of a commercial motor vehicle or a motor vehicle designed or used to transport between
nine and fifteen passengers, including the driver, not for direct compensation,
if the vehicle does not otherwise meet the definition of a commercial motor
vehicle, when necessary to communicate with law enforcement officials
or other emergency services.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except as otherwise
provided in subdivision (2)(b) of this section, no operator of a commercial
motor vehicle or a motor vehicle designed or used to transport between nine
and fifteen passengers, including the driver, not for direct compensation,
if the vehicle does not otherwise meet the definition of a commercial motor
vehicle, shall use a handheld mobile telephone while driving and no motor
carrier shall allow or require its operators to use a handheld mobile telephone
while driving such vehicle.</para><para>(b) Using a handheld mobile telephone is permissible
by an operator of a commercial motor vehicle or a motor vehicle designed or
used to transport between nine and fifteen passengers, including the driver,
not for direct compensation, if the vehicle does not otherwise meet the definition
of a commercial motor vehicle, when necessary to communicate with law enforcement
officials or other emergency services.</para><para>(3)(a) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision
(3)(b) of this section, no operator of a school bus shall engage in texting
during school bus operations.</para><para>(b) Texting while driving is permissible by an operator
of a school bus during school bus operations when necessary to communicate
with law enforcement officials or other emergency services.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Except as otherwise
provided in subdivision (4)(b) of this section, no operator of a school bus
shall use a handheld mobile telephone during school bus operations.</para>
<para>(b) Using a handheld
mobile telephone is permissible by an operator of a school bus during school
bus operations when necessary to communicate with law enforcement officials
or other emergency services.</para><para>(5) Any
person who violates this section shall be guilty of a traffic infraction.
Any person who is found guilty of a traffic infraction under this section
shall be subject to disqualification as provided in section 60-4,168, shall
be assessed points on his or her motor vehicle operator's license pursuant
to section 60-4,182, and shall be fined:</para>
<para>(a) Two hundred dollars for the first offense;</para>
<para>(b) Three hundred dollars for a second offense; and</para>
<para>(c) Five hundred dollars for a third and subsequent offense.</para>
<para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Commercial motor
vehicle has the same meaning as in section 75-362;</para><para>(b) Driving means operating a commercial motor
vehicle, including
while temporarily stationary because of traffic, a traffic control device,
or other momentary delays. Driving does not include operating a commercial
motor vehicle when the operator moves the vehicle to the side
of, or off, a highway and halts in a location where the vehicle can safely
remain stationary;</para>
<para>(c) Electronic device includes,
but is not limited to, a cellular telephone; a personal digital assistant;
a pager; a computer; or any other device used to input, write, send, receive,
or read text;</para>
<para>(d) Mobile telephone
means a mobile communication device that falls under or uses any commercial
mobile radio service as defined in regulations of the Federal Communications
Commission, 47 C.F.R. 20.3. Mobile telephone does not include two-way or citizens
band radio services;</para><para>(e)
School bus operations means the use of a school bus to transport school children
or school personnel;</para><para>(f)(i) Texting
means manually entering alphanumeric text into, or reading text from, an electronic
device. This action includes, but
is not limited to, short message service, emailing, instant messaging, a command
or request to access an Internet web page, pressing more than a single button
to initiate or terminate a voice communication using a mobile telephone, or
engaging in any other form of electronic text retrieval or entry for present or future
communication.</para>
<para>(ii) Texting does not include:</para>
<para>(A) Inputting, selecting, or reading information on a global positioning
system or navigation system;</para>
<para>(B) Pressing a single button to initiate or terminate a voice communication
using a mobile telephone; or</para>
<para>(C) Using a device capable of performing multiple functions, including,
but not limited to, fleet management systems, dispatching devices, smartphones,
citizens band radios, and music players, for a purpose other than texting; and</para>
<para>(g) Use a handheld mobile
telephone means:</para><para>(i)
Using at least one hand to hold a mobile telephone to conduct a voice communication;</para>
<para>(ii) Dialing or answering
a mobile telephone by pressing more than a single button; or</para>
<para>(iii) Reaching for a
mobile telephone in a manner that requires a driver to maneuver so that he
or she is no longer in a seated driving position and restrained by a seat
belt that is installed in accordance with 49 C.F.R. 393.93 and adjusted in
accordance with the vehicle manufacturer's instructions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 56.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>