<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,202"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,202</statuteno><catchline>Registration fees; collection and distribution; procedure; Highway Tax Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Before July 1, 2024, registration fees credited to the Motor Carrier Services Division Distributive Fund pursuant to section 60-3,198 and remaining in such fund at the close of each calendar month shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit as follows: (i) Twenty-seven percent of such amount shall be credited to the Highway Tax Fund; (ii) sixty-four percent of such amount shall be credited to the Highway Trust Fund; and (iii) nine percent of such amount shall be credited to the Motor Carrier Services System Replacement and Maintenance Fund.</para><para>(b) Beginning July 1, 2024, registration fees credited to the Motor Carrier Services Division Distributive Fund pursuant to section 60-3,198 and remaining in such fund at the close of each calendar month shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit as follows: (i) Twenty-eight percent of such amount shall be credited to the Highway Tax Fund; (ii) sixty-seven percent of such amount shall be credited to the Highway Trust Fund; and (iii) five percent of such amount shall be credited to the Motor Carrier Services System Replacement and Maintenance Fund.</para><para>(2) On or before the last day of each quarter of the calendar year, the State Treasurer shall distribute all funds in the Highway Tax Fund to the county treasurer of each county in the same proportion as the number of original motor vehicle registrations in each county bears to the total of all original registrations within the state in the registration year immediately preceding.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of motor vehicle tax funds from the State Treasurer pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the county treasurer shall distribute such funds to taxing agencies within the county in the same proportion that the levy of each such taxing agency bears to the total of such levies of all taxing agencies in the county.</para><para>(4) In the event any taxing district has been annexed, merged, dissolved, or in any way absorbed into another taxing district, any apportionment of motor vehicle tax funds under subsection (3) of this section to which such taxing district would have been entitled shall be apportioned to the successor taxing district which has assumed the functions of the annexed, merged, dissolved, or absorbed taxing district.</para><para>(5) On or before March 1 of each year, the department shall furnish to the State Treasurer a tabulation showing the total number of original motor vehicle registrations in each county for the immediately preceding calendar year, which shall be the basis for computing the distribution of motor vehicle tax funds as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(6) The Highway Tax Fund is created. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 202; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB977, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB79, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB113, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB509, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1200, &#167; 21. </para><operativedate>April 16, 2024</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>