<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-390"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-390</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of registration; contents.</catchline><para>The certificate of registration shall contain upon the face thereof the name of the registered owner of the motor vehicle or trailer, his or her residential mailing address, a description of the motor vehicle or trailer as set forth in the application for registration, and whether alternative fuel was used to propel the motor vehicle and, if so, the type of fuel. The certificate of registration shall have and contain the identical registration number denoted on the license plate in connection with which such certificate of registration is issued and shall be valid only for the registration period for which it is issued. On the back of the certificate, the certificate of registration shall include a statement in boldface print that an automobile liability policy or proof of financial responsibility is required in Nebraska. By paying the required registration fees, every person whose name appears on the registration of the motor vehicle or trailer certifies that a current and effective automobile liability policy or proof of financial responsibility will be maintained for the motor vehicle or trailer at the time of registration and while the motor vehicle or trailer is operated on a highway of this state and that he or she will also provide a current and effective automobile liability policy, evidence of insurance, or proof of financial responsibility for the motor vehicle or trailer upon demand.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 90. </para></source><annotation><para>Failure of supposed owner to register automobile as required by law, or to comply with requirements as to transfer, was a suspicious circumstance, sufficient to put purchaser on inquiry. Wallich v. Sandlovich, 111 Neb. 318, 196 N.W. 317 (1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>