<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id195"  statutenumber="60-3,113.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,113.03</statuteno><catchline>Handicapped or disabled person; parking permit; permit for specific motor vehicle; application; issuance; procedure; renewal; notice; identification card.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall take an application from any person for a handicapped or disabled parking permit that is issued for a specific motor vehicle and entitles the holder thereof or a person driving the motor vehicle for the purpose of transporting handicapped or disabled persons or temporarily handicapped or disabled persons to park in those spaces or access aisles provided for by sections 18-1736 and 18-1737 if the motor vehicle is used primarily for the transportation of handicapped or disabled persons or temporarily handicapped or disabled persons. Such permit shall be used only when the motor vehicle for which it was issued is being used for the transportation of a handicapped or disabled person or temporarily handicapped or disabled person and such person will enter or exit the motor vehicle while it is parked in such designated spaces or access aisles.</para><para>(2) A person applying for a handicapped or disabled parking permit or for the renewal of a permit pursuant to this section shall apply for a permit for each motor vehicle used for the transportation of handicapped or disabled persons or temporarily handicapped or disabled persons and shall include such information as is required by the department, including a demonstration to the department that each such motor vehicle is used primarily for the transportation of handicapped or disabled persons or temporarily handicapped or disabled persons. An application for the renewal of a permit under this section may be submitted within one hundred eighty days prior to the expiration of the permit.</para><para>(3) The department, upon receipt of a completed application, shall verify that the applicant qualifies for a handicapped or disabled parking permit under this section and, if so, shall deliver the permit to the applicant. In issuing renewed permits, the department shall deliver each individual renewal to the applicant as provided in section 60-3,113.02. The renewed permit shall not be issued sooner than ten days prior to the date of expiration, and the existing permit shall be invalid upon receipt of the renewed permit. No more than one such permit shall be issued for each motor vehicle under this section.</para><para>(4) In issuing any handicapped or disabled parking permit under this section, the department shall include a notice and an identification card to the registered owner of the motor vehicle or the applicant. The notice shall contain information listing the legal uses of the permit and that the permit is not transferable, is to be used for the motor vehicle for which it is issued, is not to be altered or reproduced, and is to be used only when a handicapped or disabled person or a temporarily handicapped or disabled person will enter or exit the motor vehicle while it is parked in a designated parking space or access aisle. The notice shall also indicate that those convicted of handicapped parking infractions shall be subject to suspension of the permit for six months. The identification card shall identify the motor vehicle for which the permit is issued as is necessary to the enforcement of sections 18-1736 to 18-1741.07 as determined by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB657, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 61. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>