<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id187"  statutenumber="60-3,113.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,113.02</statuteno><catchline>Handicapped or disabled person; parking permit; issuance; procedure; renewal; notice; identification card.</catchline><para>(1) A handicapped or disabled person or temporarily handicapped or disabled person or his or her parent, legal guardian, foster parent, or certifying health care provider may apply for a handicapped or disabled parking permit to the department or through a health care provider using a secure online process developed by the department which will entitle the holder of a permit or a person driving a motor vehicle for the purpose of transporting such holder to park in those spaces or access aisles provided for by sections 18-1736 and 18-1737 when the holder of the permit will enter or exit the motor vehicle while it is parked in such spaces or access aisles. For purposes of this section, (a) the handicapped or disabled person or temporarily handicapped or disabled person is considered the holder of the permit and (b) certifying health care provider means the physician, physician assistant, or advanced practice registered nurse who makes the certification required in subsection (2) of this section or his or her designee.</para><para>(2) The application process for a handicapped or disabled parking permit or for the renewal of a permit under this section shall include presentation of proof of identity by the handicapped or disabled person or temporarily handicapped or disabled person and certification by a physician, a physician assistant, or an advanced practice registered nurse practicing under and in accordance with his or her certification act that the person who will be the holder meets the statutory criteria for qualification. An application for the renewal of a permit under this section may be submitted within one hundred eighty days prior to the expiration of the permit. No applicant shall be required to provide his or her social security number. In the case of a temporarily handicapped or disabled person, the certifying physician, physician assistant, or advanced practice registered nurse shall recommend that the permit for the temporarily handicapped or disabled person be issued for either a three-month period or a six-month period, with such recommendation to be based on the estimated date of recovery.</para><para>(3) The department, upon receipt of a completed application for a handicapped or disabled parking permit under this section, shall verify that the applicant qualifies for such permit and, if so, shall deliver the permit to the applicant. In issuing a renewal of a permit, the department shall deliver a new expiration sticker to the applicant to be affixed to the existing permit. Such renewal sticker shall not be issued sooner than ten days prior to the date of expiration of the existing permit. A person may hold up to two permits under this section. If a person holds a permit under this section, such person may not hold a permit under section 60-3,113.03.</para><para>(4) In issuing any handicapped or disabled parking permit under this section, the department shall include a notice and an identification card. The notice shall contain information listing the legal uses of the permit and that the permit is not transferable, is to be used by the party to whom issued, is not to be altered or reproduced, and is to be used only when a handicapped or disabled person or a temporarily handicapped or disabled person will enter or exit the motor vehicle while it is parked in a designated parking space or access aisle. The notice shall also indicate that those convicted of handicapped parking infractions shall be subject to suspension of the permit for six months. The identification card shall show the expiration date of the permit and such identifying information with regard to the handicapped or disabled person or temporarily handicapped or disabled person to whom the permit is issued as is necessary to the enforcement of sections 18-1736 to 18-1741.07 as determined by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB31, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB657, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 60. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>