<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id281" statutenumber="60-4,144"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,144</statuteno><catchline id="id284">Commercial driver's license; CLP-commercial learner's permit; applications; contents; parolee immigration status; effect; application; demonstration of knowledge and skills; information and documentation required; verification.</catchline><para>(1) An applicant for issuance of any original or renewal commercial driver's license or an applicant for a change of class of commercial motor vehicle, endorsement, or restriction shall demonstrate his or her knowledge and skills for operating a commercial motor vehicle as prescribed in the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act. An applicant for a commercial driver's license shall provide the information and documentation required by this section and section 60-4,144.01. Such information and documentation shall include any additional information required by 49 C.F.R. parts 383 and 391 and also include:</para><para>(a) Certification that the commercial motor vehicle in which the applicant takes any driving skills examination is representative of the class of commercial motor vehicle that the applicant operates or expects to operate; and</para><para>(b) The names of all states where the applicant has been licensed to operate any type of motor vehicle in the ten years prior to the date of application.</para><para>(2)(a) Before being issued a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license, the applicant shall provide (i) his or her full legal name, date of birth, mailing address, gender, race or ethnicity, and social security number, (ii) two forms of proof of address of his or her principal residence unless the applicant is a program participant under the Address Confidentiality Act, except that a nondomiciled applicant for a CLP-commercial learner's permit or nondomiciled commercial driver's license holder does not have to provide proof of residence in Nebraska, (iii) evidence of identity as required by this section, and (iv) a brief physical description of himself or herself.</para><para>(b) The applicant's social security number shall not be printed on the CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license and shall be used only (i) to furnish information to the United States Selective Service System under section 60-483, (ii) with the permission of the director in connection with the certification of the status of an individual's driving record in this state or any other state, (iii) for purposes of child support enforcement pursuant to section 42-358.08 or 43-512.06, (iv) to furnish information regarding an applicant for or holder of a commercial driver's license with a hazardous materials endorsement to the Transportation Security Administration of the United States Department of Homeland Security or its agent, (v) to furnish information to the Department of Revenue under section 77-362.02, (vi) to furnish information to the Secretary of State for purposes of the Election Act, or (vii) to query the federal Drug and Alcohol Clearinghouse.</para><para>(c) No person shall be a holder of a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license and a state identification card at the same time.</para><para>(3) Before being issued a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license, an applicant, except a nondomiciled applicant, shall provide proof that this state is his or her state of residence. Acceptable proof of residence is a document with the person's name and residential address within this state.</para><para>(4)(a) Before being issued a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license, an applicant shall provide proof of identity.</para><para>(b) The following are acceptable as proof of identity:</para><para>(i) A valid, unexpired United States passport;</para><para>(ii) A certified copy of a birth certificate filed with a state office of vital statistics or equivalent agency in the individual's state of birth;</para><para>(iii) A Consular Report of Birth Abroad issued by the United States Department of State;</para><para>(iv) A valid, unexpired permanent resident card issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security or United States Citizenship and Immigration Services;</para><para>(v) An unexpired employment authorization document issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security;</para><para>(vi) An unexpired foreign passport with a valid, unexpired United States visa affixed accompanied by the approved form documenting the applicant's most recent admittance into the United States;</para><para>(vii) A Certificate of Naturalization issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security;</para><para>(viii) A Certificate of Citizenship issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security;</para><para>(ix) A driver's license or identification card issued in compliance with the standards established by the federal REAL ID Act of 2005, Public Law 109-13, division B, section 1, 119 Stat. 302; or</para><para>(x) Such other documents as the director may approve.</para><para>(c) If an applicant presents one of the documents listed under subdivision (b)(i), (ii), (iii), (iv), (vii), or (viii) of this subsection, the verification of the applicant's identity will also provide satisfactory evidence of lawful status.</para><para>(d) If the applicant presents one of the identity documents listed under subdivision (b)(v), (vi), or (ix) of this subsection, the verification of the identity documents does not provide satisfactory evidence of lawful status. The applicant shall also present a second document from subdivision (4)(b) of this section, a document from subsection (5) of this section, or documentation issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security or other federal agencies demonstrating lawful status as determined by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services.</para><para>(e) An applicant may present other documents as designated by the director as proof of identity. Any documents accepted shall be recorded according to a written exceptions process established by the director.</para><para>(f)(i) Any person assigned a parolee immigration status by the United States Department of Homeland Security may apply for and be issued a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license that is not in compliance with the federal REAL ID Act of 2005, Public Law 109-13, if the person:</para><para>(A) Possessed an unexpired foreign passport issued to such person at the time of such person's entry into the United States of America; and</para><para>(B) Fulfills the requirements of subdivision (2)(a) of this section and such requirements are verified pursuant to section 60-484.06.</para><para>(ii) Any CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license issued under this subsection is otherwise subject to all laws relating to CLP-commercial learner's permits or commercial driver's licenses.</para><para>(5)(a) Whenever a person, as a nondomiciled individual to this state, is renewing, replacing, upgrading, transferring, or applying for a commercial driver's license, or replacing, upgrading, transferring, or applying for a CLP-commercial learner's permit, the Department of Motor Vehicles shall verify the citizenship in the United States of the person or the lawful status in the United States of the person.</para><para>(b) The following are acceptable as proof of citizenship or lawful status:</para><para>(i) A valid, unexpired United States passport;</para><para>(ii) A certified copy of a birth certificate filed with a state office of vital statistics or equivalent agency in the individual's state of birth, Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, or the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands;</para><para>(iii) A Consular Report of Birth Abroad issued by the United States Department of State;</para><para>(iv) A Certificate of Naturalization issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security;</para><para>(v) A Certificate of Citizenship issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security; or</para><para>(vi) A valid, unexpired Permanent Resident Card issued by the United States Department of Homeland Security or United States Citizenship and Immigration Services.</para><para>(6) An applicant may present other documents as designated by the director as proof of lawful status. Any documents accepted shall be recorded according to a written exceptions process established by the director.</para><para>(7)(a) An applicant shall obtain a nondomiciled CLP-commercial driver's license or nondomiciled CLP-commercial learner's permit:</para><para>(i) If the applicant is domiciled in a foreign jurisdiction and the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administrator has not determined that the commercial motor vehicle operator testing and licensing standards of that jurisdiction meet the standards contained in subparts G and H of 49 C.F.R. part 383; or</para><para>(ii) If the applicant is domiciled in a state that is prohibited from issuing commercial learners' permits and commercial drivers' licenses in accordance with 49 C.F.R. 384.405. Such person is eligible to obtain a nondomiciled CLP-commercial learner's permit or nondomiciled commercial driver's license from Nebraska that complies with the testing and licensing standards contained in subparts F, G, and H of 49 C.F.R. part 383.</para><para>(b) An applicant for a nondomiciled CLP-commercial learner's permit and nondomiciled commercial driver's license shall do the following:</para><para>(i) Complete the requirements to obtain a CLP-commercial learner's permit or a commercial driver's license under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act, except that an applicant domiciled in a foreign jurisdiction shall provide an unexpired employment authorization document issued by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services or an unexpired foreign passport accompanied by an approved I-94 form documenting the applicant's most recent admittance into the United States. No proof of domicile is required;</para><para>(ii) After receipt of the nondomiciled CLP-commercial learner's permit or nondomiciled commercial driver's license and, for as long as the permit or license is valid, notify the Department of Motor Vehicles of any adverse action taken by any jurisdiction or governmental agency, foreign or domestic, against his or her driving privileges. Such adverse actions include, but are not limited to, license disqualification or disqualification from operating a commercial motor vehicle for the convictions described in 49 C.F.R. 383.51. Notifications shall be made within the time periods specified in 49 C.F.R. 383.33; and</para><para>(iii) Provide a mailing address to the Department of Motor Vehicles. If the applicant is applying for a foreign nondomiciled CLP-commercial learner's permit or foreign nondomiciled commercial driver's license, he or she shall provide a Nebraska mailing address and his or her employer's mailing address to the Department of Motor Vehicles.</para><para>(c) An applicant for a nondomiciled CLP-commercial learner's permit or nondomiciled commercial driver's license who holds a foreign operator's license is not required to surrender his or her foreign operator's license.</para><para>(8) Any person applying for a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license may answer the following:</para><para>(a) Do you wish to register to vote as part of this application process?</para><para>(b) Do you wish to have a veteran designation displayed on the front of your operator's license to show that you served in the armed forces of the United States? (To be eligible you shall register with the Nebraska Department of Veterans' Affairs registry.)</para><para>(c) Do you wish to include your name in the Donor Registry of Nebraska and donate your organs and tissues at the time of your death?</para><para>(d) Do you wish to receive any additional specific information regarding organ and tissue donation and the Donor Registry of Nebraska?</para><para>(e) Do you wish to donate $1 to promote the Organ and Tissue Donor Awareness and Education Fund?</para><para>(9) Application for a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license shall include a signed oath, affirmation, or declaration of the applicant that the information provided on the application for the permit or license is true and correct.</para><para>(10) Any person applying for a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license shall make one of the certifications in section 60-4,144.01 and any certification required under section 60-4,146 and shall provide such certifications to the Department of Motor Vehicles in order to be issued a CLP-commercial learner's permit or a commercial driver's license.</para><para>(11) Every person who holds any commercial driver's license shall provide to the department medical certification as required by section 60-4,144.01. The department may provide notice and prescribe medical certification compliance requirements for all holders of commercial drivers' licenses. Holders of commercial drivers' licenses who fail to meet the prescribed medical certification compliance requirements may be subject to downgrade.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 94; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1178, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 575; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 635, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 147, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1317, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 228, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 559, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB47, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB192, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB138, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1200, &#167; 38. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Address Confidentiality Act,</emphasis> see section 42-1201.</para><para><emphasis>Donor Registry of Nebraska,</emphasis> see section 71-4822.</para><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Department of Veterans' Affairs registry,</emphasis> see section 80-414.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>