<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,224"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,224</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates; application; form; fee; delivery; fee; transfer; procedure; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Beginning October 1, 2015, and ending December 31, 2022, a person may apply to the department for Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates in lieu of regular license plates on an application prescribed and provided by the department for any motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer, except for a motor vehicle or trailer registered under section 60-3,198. An applicant receiving a plate under this section for a farm truck with a gross weight of over sixteen tons shall affix the appropriate tonnage decal to the plate. The department shall make forms available for such applications through the county treasurers.</para><para>(2) Each application for initial issuance or renewal of Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates shall be accompanied by a fee of seventy dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit fifteen percent of the fee for initial issuance and renewal of plates under subsection (3) of section 60-3,223 to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and eighty-five percent of such fee to the Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plate Proceeds Fund. The State Treasurer shall credit forty-three percent of the fee for initial issuance and renewal of plates under subsection (4) of section 60-3,223 to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and fifty-seven percent of such fee to the Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plate Proceeds Fund.</para><para>(3)(a) When the department receives an application for Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates, the department may deliver the plates and registration certificate to the applicant by United States mail or to the county treasurer of the county in which the motor vehicle or trailer is registered and the delivery of the plates and registration certificate shall be made through a secure process and system. Beginning on an implementation date designated by the director on or before January 1, 2022, if delivery of the plates and registration certificate is made by the department to the applicant, the department may charge a postage and handling fee in an amount not more than necessary to recover the cost of postage and handling for the specific items mailed to the registrant. The department shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund. The county treasurer or the department shall issue plates under this section in lieu of regular license plates when the applicant complies with the other provisions of the Motor Vehicle Registration Act for registration of the motor vehicle or trailer. If plates are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the licensee shall be issued replacement license plates pursuant to section 60-3,157.</para><para>(b) The county treasurer or the department may issue temporary license stickers to the applicant under this section for the applicant to lawfully operate the vehicle pending receipt of the license plates. No charge in addition to the registration fee shall be made for the issuance of a temporary license sticker under this subdivision. The department shall furnish temporary license stickers for issuance by the county treasurer at no cost to the counties. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations regarding the design and issuance of temporary license stickers.</para><para>(4) The owner of a motor vehicle or trailer bearing Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates may apply to the county treasurer to have such plates transferred to a motor vehicle or trailer other than the motor vehicle or trailer for which such plates were originally purchased if such motor vehicle or trailer is owned by the owner of the plates. The owner may have the unused portion of the fee for the plates credited to the other motor vehicle or trailer which will bear the plates at the rate of eight and one-third percent per month for each full month left in the registration period. Application for such transfer shall be accompanied by a fee of three dollars. The State Treasurer shall credit fees collected pursuant to this subsection to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) Nebraska 150 Sesquicentennial Plates shall not be issued or renewed beginning on January 1, 2023.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB220, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB270, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB113, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>