<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,187"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,187</statuteno><catchline>Special speed limitations; motor vehicle towing a mobile home; motor-driven cycle.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall operate any motor vehicle when towing a mobile home at a rate of speed in excess of fifty miles per hour.</para><para>(2)(a) A person may operate any motor-driven cycle at a speed in excess of thirty-five miles per hour upon a roadway at nighttime if such motor-driven cycle is equipped with a headlight or headlights capable of revealing a person or vehicle in such roadway at least three hundred feet ahead and with a taillight on the rear exhibiting a red light visible, under normal atmospheric conditions, from a distance of at least five hundred feet to the rear of such motor-driven cycle.</para><para>(b) A person may operate any motor-driven cycle at a speed in excess of twenty-five miles per hour, but not more than thirty-five miles per hour, upon a roadway at nighttime if such motor-driven cycle is equipped with a headlight or headlights capable of revealing a person or vehicle in such roadway at least one hundred feet ahead, but less than three hundred feet ahead, and with a taillight on the rear exhibiting a red light visible, under normal atmospheric conditions, from a distance of at least five hundred feet to the rear of such motor-driven cycle.</para><para>(c) A person shall not operate any motor-driven cycle upon a roadway at nighttime if the headlight or headlights do not reveal a person or vehicle in such roadway at least one hundred feet ahead, or the taillight is not visible, under normal atmospheric conditions, from a distance of at least five hundred feet to the rear of such motor-driven cycle.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 873, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 381, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 256, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 23, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 430, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 504, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 369, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-666; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 283; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 901, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 80, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Livestock forage vehicles,</emphasis> speed limits, see section 60-6,305.</para><para><emphasis>Mopeds,</emphasis> maximum speed, see section 60-6,313.</para><para><emphasis>Operator's license,</emphasis> assessment of points for speeding, see section 60-4,182 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Unreasonable classification of persons is not created hereby. State ex rel. Douglas v. Gradwohl, 194 Neb. 745, 235 N.W.2d 854 (1975).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>