<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,130.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,130.01</statuteno><catchline>Medical hardship driving permit; issuance; conditions; violations; penalty; revocation.</catchline><para>(1) Any person whose license or privilege to operate a motor vehicle in this state is revoked under sections 60-4,183 and 60-4,186 shall be eligible to operate any motor vehicle, except a commercial motor vehicle, in this state under a medical hardship driving permit, valid for a period of ninety days. Upon expiration of the permit, a person may reapply for a medical hardship driving permit in the same manner as the original application.</para><para>(2) Any person whose license or privilege to operate a motor vehicle in this state has been suspended or revoked pursuant to any law of this state, except sections 60-4,183 and 60-4,186, shall not be eligible to receive a medical hardship driving permit during the period of such suspension or revocation.</para><para>(3) An individual who is issued a medical hardship driving permit may operate any motor vehicle, except a commercial motor vehicle, from his or her residence or place of employment to a hospital, clinic, doctor's office, or similar location and return. Such permit shall indicate for which purposes the permit may be used. All permits issued pursuant to this section shall indicate that the permit is not valid for the operation of any commercial motor vehicle.</para><para>(4) The operation of a motor vehicle by the holder of a medical hardship driving permit, except as provided in this section, shall be unlawful. Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para><para>(5) The director shall revoke the medical hardship driving permit for an individual upon receipt of an abstract of conviction, other than a conviction which is based upon actions which resulted in the application for such medical hardship driving permit, indicating that the individual committed an offense for which points are assessed pursuant to section 60-4,182. If the permit is revoked in this manner, the individual shall not be eligible to receive a medical hardship driving permit for the remainder of the period of suspension or revocation of his or her operator's license or privilege to operate a motor vehicle.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 105, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc>