<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,210" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,210</statuteno><catchline>Blood sample; results of chemical test; admissible in criminal prosecution; disclosure required.</catchline><para>(1) If the driver of a motor vehicle involved in an accident is transported to a hospital within or outside of Nebraska and a sample of the driver's blood is withdrawn by a physician, registered nurse, qualified technician, or hospital for the purpose of medical treatment, the results of a chemical test of the sample shall be admissible in a criminal prosecution for a violation punishable under subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-306 or a violation of section 28-305, 60-6,196, or 60-6,198 to show the alcoholic content of or the presence of drugs or both in the blood at the time of the accident regardless of whether (a) a peace officer requested the driver to submit to a test as provided in section 60-6,197 or (b) the driver had refused a chemical test.</para><para>(2) Any physician, registered nurse, qualified technician, or hospital in this state performing a chemical test to determine the alcoholic content of or the presence of drugs in such blood for the purpose of medical treatment of the driver of a vehicle involved in a motor vehicle accident shall disclose the results of the test (a) to a prosecuting attorney who requests the results for use in a criminal prosecution under subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-306 or section 28-305, 60-6,196, or 60-6,198 and (b) to any prosecuting attorney in another state who requests the results for use in a criminal prosecution for driving while intoxicated, driving under the influence, or motor vehicle homicide under the laws of the other state if the other state requires a similar disclosure by any hospital or person in such state to any prosecuting attorney in Nebraska who requests the results for use in such a criminal prosecution under the laws of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 872, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-669.20; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 305; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 925, &#167; 15. </para></source><annotation><para>Admission of evidence of blood test results in a criminal prosecution for manslaughter under section 28-305 is not authorized under this section. State v. Brouillette, 265 Neb. 214, 655 N.W.2d 876 (2003).</para><para>Unlike subsection (1) of this section, section 60-6,201(1) does not limit the use of chemical test results to prosecution under a specific statute; rather, it authorizes the use of results of the specified chemical test as competent evidence in "any" prosecution "under" a state statute "involving" operation of a motor vehicle while under the influence of alcoholic liquor or "involving" such operation with an excessive level of alcohol. State v. Guzman-Gomez, 13 Neb. App. 235, 690 N.W.2d 804 (2005).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>