<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,123"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,123</statuteno><catchline>Traffic control signals; meaning;
turns on red signal; when;
signal not in service; effect.</catchline><para>Whenever traffic
is controlled by traffic control signals exhibiting different colored lights
or colored lighted arrows, successively one at a time or in combination, only
the colors green, red, and yellow shall be used, except for special pedestrian
signals carrying a word legend,
number, or symbol, and such lights shall indicate and apply to
drivers of vehicles and pedestrians as follows:</para>
<para>(1)(a) Vehicular traffic facing a circular green indication may proceed
straight through or turn right or left unless a sign at such place prohibits
either such turn, but vehicular traffic, including vehicles turning right
or left, shall yield the right-of-way to other vehicles and to pedestrians
lawfully within the intersection or an adjacent crosswalk at the time such
indication is exhibited;</para>
<para>(b) Vehicular traffic facing a green arrow indication, shown alone or
in combination with another indication, may cautiously enter the intersection
only to make the movement indicated by such arrow or such other movement as
is permitted by other indications shown at the same time, and such vehicular
traffic shall yield the right-of-way to pedestrians lawfully within an adjacent
crosswalk and to other traffic lawfully using the intersection; and</para>
<para>(c) Unless otherwise directed by a pedestrian-control signal, pedestrians
facing any green indication, except when the sole green indication is a turn
arrow, may proceed across the roadway within any marked or unmarked crosswalk;</para>
<para>(2)(a) Vehicular traffic facing a steady yellow indication is thereby
warned that the related green movement is being terminated or that a red indication
will be exhibited immediately thereafter when vehicular traffic shall not
enter the intersection, and upon display of a steady yellow indication, vehicular
traffic shall stop before entering the nearest crosswalk at the intersection,
but if such stop cannot be made in safety, a vehicle may be driven cautiously
through the intersection; and</para>
<para>(b) Pedestrians facing a steady yellow indication, unless otherwise
directed by a pedestrian-control signal, are thereby advised that there is
insufficient time to cross the roadway before a red indication is shown and
no pedestrian shall then start to cross the roadway;</para>
<para>(3)(a) Vehicular traffic facing a steady red indication alone shall
stop at a clearly marked stop line or shall stop, if there is no such line,
before entering the crosswalk on the near side of the intersection or, if
there is no crosswalk, before entering the intersection. The traffic shall
remain standing until an indication to proceed is shown except as provided
in subdivisions (3)(b) and (3)(c) of this section;</para>
<para>(b) Except where a traffic control device is in place prohibiting a
turn, vehicular traffic facing a steady red indication may cautiously enter
the intersection to make a right turn after stopping as required by subdivision
(3)(a) of this section. Such vehicular traffic shall yield the right-of-way
to pedestrians lawfully within an adjacent crosswalk and to other traffic
lawfully using the intersection;</para>
<para>(c) Except where a traffic control device is in place prohibiting a
turn, vehicular traffic facing a steady red indication at the intersection
of two one-way streets may cautiously enter the intersection to make a left
turn after stopping as required by subdivision (3)(a) of this section. Such
vehicular traffic shall yield the right-of-way to pedestrians lawfully within
an adjacent crosswalk and to other traffic lawfully using the intersection;
and</para>
<para>(d) Unless otherwise directed by a pedestrian-control signal, pedestrians
facing a steady red indication alone shall not enter the roadway;</para>
<para>(4) If a traffic control signal is erected and maintained at a place
other than an intersection, the provisions of this section shall be applicable
except as to those provisions which by their nature can have no application.
Any stop required shall be made at a sign or marking on the pavement indicating
where the stop shall be made, but in the absence of any such sign or marking,
the stop shall be made at the signal;
and</para>
<para>(5)(a) If a traffic control
signal at an intersection is not operating because of a power failure or other
cause and no peace officer, flagperson, or other traffic control device is
providing direction for traffic at the intersection, the intersection shall
be treated as a multi-way stop; and</para><para>(b) If a traffic control signal is not in service
and the signal heads are turned away from traffic or covered with opaque material,
subdivision (a) of this subdivision shall not apply.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 821, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 135, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-614; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 219; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>In the case of a collision involving two vehicles approaching an intersection from opposite directions with a green light for both vehicles, a determination of which vehicle was "lawfully" in the intersection first, thereby possessing a superior right-of-way for purposes of this section, was a question of fact for the jury. Nguyen v. Rezac, 256 Neb. 458, 590 N.W.2d 375 (1999).</para><para>Speeding up to cross an intersection on a yellow light in violation of subdivision (2)(a) of this section provides sufficient cause for a police officer observing the violation to make an investigatory stop. State v. LaMere, 230 Neb. 629, 432 N.W.2d 822 (1988).</para><para>A pedestrian crossing at a regular crosswalk with the right-of-way has a right, until he has notice or knowledge to the contrary, to assume that others will respect his right-of-way. Even though a statute grants the right-of-way to a pedestrian crossing a street in the crosswalk, it does not excuse contributory negligence on his part. Holly v. Mitchell, 213 Neb. 203, 328 N.W.2d 750 (1982).</para><para>A city ordinance regulating funeral processions was a reasonable and valid exercise of the city's police power under section 39-697(1)(c) (transferred to section 60-680) and does not conflict with Nebraska's present right-of-way statutes, section 39-609(1) (transferred to section 60-6,119) and this section. Herman v. Lee, 210 Neb. 563, 316 N.W.2d 56 (1982).</para><para>Directed verdict was improperly granted to a motorist where a factual issue existed as to whether the motorist or a bicyclist was in the favored position to proceed into the intersection. Luellman v. Ambroz, 2 Neb. App. 855, 516 N.W.2d 627 (1993).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>