<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,236"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,236</statuteno><catchline>Vehicles required to have clearance lights; flares; reflectors; when required as equipment.</catchline><para>Any vehicle required by section 60-6,235 to have clearance lights, while operating on the highways during the period from sunset to sunrise, shall at all times be equipped with at least three portable flares, or red emergency reflectors referred to in section 60-6,237, which may be plainly visible for a distance of five hundred feet.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 129, &#167; 1, p. 460; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-11,112; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,118; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 121, &#167; 1(1), p. 318; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 193, &#167; 1, p. 591; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,118; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,162; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 332; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 33. </para></source><annotation><para>Where truck was left on highway after dark without flares, there was evidence of negligence. Plumb v. Burnham, 151 Neb. 129, 36 N.W.2d 612 (1949).</para><para>Violation of this section may constitute manslaughter. Vaca v. State, 150 Neb. 516, 34 N.W.2d 873 (1948).</para><para>Passenger car, with trailer attached, does not come within class of vehicles required to be equipped with flares. Anderson v. Robbins Incubator Co., 143 Neb. 40, 8 N.W.2d 446 (1943).</para><para>Charges of negligence of bus company in blocking highway should have been submitted to jury, together with question of whether under such circumstances agent was negligent in the manner of giving signals. McClelland v. Interstate Transit Lines, 142 Neb. 439, 6 N.W.2d 384 (1942).</para><para>Evidence of failure to set up flares, together with other acts of negligence, was sufficient to make case for jury. Grantham v. Watson Bros. Transp. Co., 142 Neb. 362, 6 N.W.2d 372 (1942).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 