<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id99" statutenumber="60-3,161"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,161</statuteno><catchline id="id102">Registration;
records; copy or extract provided; electronic access; fee.</catchline><para>(1)
The department shall keep a record of each motor vehicle and trailer registered,
alphabetically by name of the owner, with cross reference in each instance
to the registration number assigned to such motor vehicle and trailer. The
record may be destroyed by any public officer having custody of it after three
years from the date of its issuance.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall issue a copy of the record of a registered
or titled motor vehicle or trailer to any person after receiving from the
person the name on the registration, the license plate number, the vehicle
identification number, or the title number of a motor vehicle or trailer,
if the person provides to the department verification of identity and purpose
pursuant to section 60-2906 or 60-2907. A fee of one dollar shall be charged
for the copy. An extract of the entire file of motor vehicles and trailers
registered or titled in the state or updates to the entire file may be provided
to a person upon payment of a fee of eighteen dollars per thousand records.
Any fee received by the department pursuant to this subsection shall be deposited
into the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para>
<para>(3) The record of each motor vehicle or trailer registration or title
maintained by the department pursuant to this section may be made available
electronically through the portal established
under section 84-1204 so long as the Uniform Motor Vehicle Records Disclosure
Act is not violated. There shall be a fee of one dollar per record for individual
records. For batch requests for multiple motor vehicle or trailer title and
registration records selected on the basis of criteria of the individual making
the request, there shall be a fee of fifty dollars for every request under
two thousand records and a fee of eighteen dollars per one thousand records
for any number of records over two thousand, plus a reasonable programming
fee not to exceed five hundred twenty dollars. All fees collected pursuant
to this subsection for electronic access to records through the portal shall be deposited in the Records Management
Cash Fund and shall be distributed as provided in any agreements between the
State Records Board and the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
2005, LB 274, &#167; 161; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform
Motor Vehicle Records Disclosure Act,</emphasis> see section 60-2901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>