<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-491"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-491</statuteno><catchline>Prohibited acts.</catchline><para>It shall be unlawful for any person:</para><para>(1) To display or cause or permit to be displayed or have in his or her possession any canceled, revoked, suspended, impounded, fictitious, or fraudulently altered operator's license or state identification card issued by the State of Nebraska or any other state;</para><para>(2) To lend his or her operator's license or state identification card to any person or knowingly permit the use thereof by another;</para><para>(3) To display or represent as one's own any operator's license or state identification card not issued to him or her by the State of Nebraska or any other state;</para><para>(4) To fail or refuse to surrender to the director upon his or her lawful demand any operator's license or state identification card which has been suspended, revoked, or canceled;</para><para>(5) To use a false or fictitious name in applying for an operator's license or state identification card or knowingly to make a false statement or knowingly to conceal a material fact or otherwise commit a fraud in applying for an operator's license or state identification card;</para><para>(6) To permit any unlawful use of an operator's license or state identification card issued to him or her by the State of Nebraska or any other state;</para><para>(7) To do any act forbidden or fail to perform any act required by the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act;</para><para>(8) To make any false affidavit or knowingly to swear or affirm falsely to any matter or thing required by the terms of the act to be sworn to or affirmed. Such person shall be guilty of perjury and, upon conviction thereof, shall be punished as other persons committing perjury are punishable;</para><para>(9) To cause or knowingly permit his or her child or ward under the age of sixteen years to drive a motor vehicle upon any highway when such minor is not authorized under the act or is in violation of any of the provisions of the act;</para><para>(10) To authorize or knowingly permit a motor vehicle owned by him or her or under his or her control to be driven upon any highway by any person who is not authorized under the act or is in violation of any of the provisions of the act; or</para><para>(11) To manufacture any fraudulent state identification card whether of the State of Nebraska or any other state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 26, p. 521; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 124, &#167; 6, p. 474; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-431; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-417; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-417; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 284, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 335, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 15. </para></source><annotation><para>A person who violates subsection (10) of this section is guilty of negligence and liable for damages proximately resulting from the negligent operation of the motor vehicle. DeWester v. Watkins, 275 Neb. 173, 745 N.W.2d 330 (2008).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 