<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,186"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,186</statuteno><catchline>Operation after revocation; violation; penalty; employment driving permit or medical hardship driving permit excepted; proof of financial responsibility.</catchline><para>It shall be unlawful to operate a motor vehicle on the public highways after revocation of an operator's license under sections 60-4,182 to 60-4,186, except that a motor vehicle other than a commercial motor vehicle may be operated under an employment driving permit as provided by section 60-4,129 or a medical hardship driving permit as provided in section 60-4,130.01. Any person who violates the provisions of this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para><para>Any operator's license revoked under sections 60-4,182 to 60-4,186 shall remain revoked for six months, and at the expiration of the six-month period, such person shall give and maintain for three years proof of financial responsibility as required by section 60-524. Any person whose operator's license has been revoked pursuant to sections 60-4,182 to 60-4,186 a second time within five years shall have his or her operator's license revoked for three years, and at the expiration of the three-year period, such person shall give and maintain for three years proof of financial responsibility as required by section 60-524.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 219, &#167; 6, p. 771; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 158, &#167; 1, p. 461; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 174, &#167; 4, p. 628; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 213, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 39-7,133; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 259, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-669.30; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 105, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 84. </para></source><annotation><para>The gravamen of or the misconduct prohibited by section 60-418 (transferred to section 60-4,107) and this section is operation of a motor vehicle after judicial or administrative deprivation of the operator's privilege or license to operate a motor vehicle on the public highways of the State of Nebraska. Although the terms suspension and revocation were used interchangeably in this case, such misuse did not arise to the stature of sufficient prejudice to warrant reversal of judgment. State v. Jost, 219 Neb. 162, 361 N.W.2d 526 (1985).</para><para>At expiration of period of revocation or suspension of license, operator of motor vehicle must give and maintain proof of financial responsibility. State v. Smith, 181 Neb. 846, 152 N.W.2d 16 (1967).</para><para>This section sets forth the penalty under the point system act. State v. Ruggiere, 180 Neb. 869, 146 N.W.2d 373 (1966).</para><para>Revocation of license for points accumulated before amendment of statute was not ex post facto application of statute. Durfee v. Ress, 163 Neb. 768, 81 N.W.2d 148 (1957).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 