<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,147.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,147.05</statuteno><catchline>Hazardous materials endorsement; expiration; when.</catchline><para>(1) A commercial driver's license with a hazardous materials endorsement expires five years after the date of issuance of a determination of no security threat.</para><para>(2) When adding a hazardous materials endorsement to an existing Nebraska commercial driver's license before the expiration date of the existing license, the expiration date of the new commercial driver's license with the hazardous materials endorsement added shall be five years from the date of the determination of threat assessment. The license shall be issued upon payment of the appropriate prorated fee prescribed in section 60-4,115 for any additional time period added. If the date of the threat assessment plus five years is earlier than the expiration date of the commercial driver's license before the hazardous materials endorsement was added, the fee for a change of class, endorsement, or restriction shall apply.</para><para>(3) The Department of Motor Vehicles shall mail out a renewal notice for each such license at least sixty days before the expiration of the license. An applicant for renewal may initiate the renewal process after receiving such notice, but the renewal process shall be initiated at least thirty days before the expiration date in order to allow time to process the security threat assessment. The department may extend the expiration date of the endorsement for ninety days if the Transportation Security Administration of the United States Department of Homeland Security or its agent has not provided a determination of threat assessment before the expiration date. Any additional extension must be approved in advance by the designee of the Transportation Security Administration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>