<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id214">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id216" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="60-3,113.06"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo>
<statuteno>60-3,113.06</statuteno><catchline>Handicapped or disabled persons;
parking permit; use; display; prohibited acts; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) This section
applies beginning on the implementation date designated by the director under
section 60-3,113.01.</para>
<para>(2) A handicapped
or disabled parking permit shall not be transferable and shall be used only
by the party to whom issued or for the motor vehicle for which issued and
only for the purpose for which the permit is issued. A handicapped or disabled
parking permit shall be displayed by hanging the permit from the motor vehicle's
rearview mirror so as to be clearly visible through the front windshield.
A handicapped or disabled parking permit shall be displayed on the dashboard
only when there is no rearview mirror. No person shall alter or reproduce
in any manner a handicapped or disabled parking permit. No person shall knowingly
hold more than the allowed number of handicapped or disabled parking permits.
No person shall display a handicapped or disabled parking permit issued under
section 60-3,113.02 and park in a space or access aisle designated for the
exclusive use of a handicapped or disabled person unless the holder of the
permit will enter or exit the motor vehicle while it is parked in a designated
space or access aisle. No person shall display a handicapped or disabled parking
permit issued under section 60-3,113.03 and park in a space or access aisle
designated for the exclusive use of a handicapped or disabled person unless
the person displaying the permit is driving the motor vehicle for which the
permit was issued and a handicapped or disabled person will enter or exit
the motor vehicle while it is parked in a designated space or access aisle.
Any violation of this subsection shall constitute a handicapped parking infraction
as defined in section 18-1741.01 and shall be subject to the penalties and
procedures set forth in sections 18-1741.01 to 18-1741.07.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>