<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-479.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>60-479.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Fraudulent document recognition training; criminal history record information check; lawful status check; cost.</catchline><para>(1) All persons handling source documents or engaged in the issuance of new, renewed, or reissued operators' licenses or state identification cards shall have periodic fraudulent document recognition training.</para><para>(2) All persons and agents of the department involved in the recording of verified application information or verified operator's license and state identification card information, involved in the manufacture or production of licenses or cards, or who have the ability to affect information on such licenses or cards shall be subject to a criminal history record information check, including a check of prior employment references, and a lawful status check as required by 6 C.F.R. part 37, as such part existed on January 1, 2017. Such persons and agents shall provide fingerprints which shall be submitted to the Federal Bureau of Investigation. The bureau shall use its records for the criminal history record information check.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of a request pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the Nebraska State Patrol shall undertake a search for criminal history record information relating to such applicant, including transmittal of the applicant's fingerprints to the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history record information check. The criminal history record information check shall include information concerning the applicant from federal repositories of such information and repositories of such information in other states, if authorized by federal law. The Nebraska State Patrol shall issue a report to the employing public agency that shall include the criminal history record information concerning the applicant. The cost of any background check shall be borne by the employer of the person or agent.</para><para>(4) Any person convicted of any disqualifying offense as provided in 6 C.F.R. part 37, as such part existed on January 1, 2017, shall not be involved in the recording of verified application information or verified operator's license and state identification card information, involved in the manufacture or production of licenses or cards, or involved in any capacity in which such person would have the ability to affect information on such licenses or cards. Any employee or prospective employee of the department shall be provided notice that he or she will undergo such criminal history record information check prior to employment or prior to any involvement with the issuance of operators' licenses or state identification cards.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB35, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB776, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB313, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB929, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 63. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>