<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,141"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,141</statuteno><catchline>Operation outside classification of license; restrictions; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsections (2) and (3) of this section, no person shall operate any class of commercial motor vehicle upon the highways of this state unless such person possesses a valid commercial driver's license authorizing the operation of the class of commercial motor vehicle being operated, except that (a) any person possessing a valid commercial driver's license authorizing the operation of a Class A commercial motor vehicle may lawfully operate any Class B or C commercial motor vehicle and (b) any person possessing a valid commercial driver's license authorizing the operation of a Class B commercial motor vehicle may lawfully operate a Class C commercial motor vehicle. No person shall operate upon the highways of this state any commercial motor vehicle which requires a specific endorsement unless such person possesses a valid commercial driver's license with such endorsement. No person possessing a restricted commercial driver's license shall operate upon the highways of this state any commercial motor vehicle to which such restriction is applicable.</para><para>(2) Any person holding an LPC-learner's permit may operate a commercial motor vehicle for learning purposes upon the highways of this state if accompanied by a person who is twenty-one years of age or older, who holds a commercial driver's license valid for the class of commercial motor vehicle being operated, and who occupies the seat beside the person for the purpose of giving instruction in the operation of the commercial motor vehicle. Any person holding an LPC-learner's permit may operate a commercial motor vehicle upon the highways of this state for purposes of taking a driving skills examination if accompanied by an examiner who is designated by the director under section 60-4,149 or employed by a third-party tester certified pursuant to section 60-4,158 and who occupies the seat beside the person for the purpose of giving the examination. A person holding an LPC-learner's permit shall not operate a commercial motor vehicle transporting hazardous materials.</para><para>(3) The provisions of subsection (1) of this section shall not apply to any nonresident until the state of residence of such nonresident begins the issuance of commercial drivers' licenses in conformance with the requirements of the Commercial Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 1986, 49 U.S.C. 31100 et seq., and the Motor Carrier Safety Improvement Act of 1999, 49 U.S.C. 31301 et seq., and section 1012 of the federal Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism Act of 2001, USA PATRIOT Act, 49 U.S.C. 5103a, and such nonresident is required by his or her state of residence to possess a commercial driver's license to operate a commercial motor vehicle. Any nonresident who is in this state for a period of thirty consecutive days or more shall apply for a Nebraska-issued commercial driver's license and shall surrender to the Department of Motor Vehicles any operator's license issued to such nonresident by any other state.</para><para>(4) Any person who operates a commercial motor vehicle upon the highways of this state in violation of this section shall, upon conviction, be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 91; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 7, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>