<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-170"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-170</statuteno><catchline>Nontransferable certificate of title;
when issued; procedure; surrender for certificate of title; procedure.</catchline>
<para>(1) When an insurance company authorized to do business in Nebraska
acquires a vehicle which has been properly titled and registered in a state
other than Nebraska through payment of a total loss settlement on account
of theft and the vehicle has not become unusable for transportation through
damage and has not sustained any malfunction beyond reasonable maintenance
and repair, the company shall obtain the certificate of title from the owner
and may make application for a nontransferable certificate of title by surrendering
the certificate of title to the county treasurer. A
nontransferable certificate of title shall be issued in the same manner and
for the same fee or fees as provided for a certificate of title in sections
60-154 to 60-160 and shall be on a form prescribed by the department.</para>
<para>(2) A vehicle which has a nontransferable certificate of title shall
not be sold or otherwise transferred or disposed of without first obtaining
a certificate of title under the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act.</para>
<para>(3) When a nontransferable certificate of title is surrendered for a
certificate of title, the application shall be accompanied by a statement
from the insurance company stating that to the best of its knowledge the vehicle
has not become unusable for transportation through damage and has not sustained
any malfunction beyond reasonable maintenance and repair. The statement shall
not constitute or imply a warranty of condition to any subsequent purchaser
or operator of the vehicle.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 45.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>