<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,233" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,233</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Rotating or flashing red light or red and blue lights; when permitted; application; permit; expiration.</catchline><para id="id00">(1)(a) A rotating or flashing red light or lights or such light or lights in combination with a blue light or lights may be displayed on any motor vehicle operated by any volunteer firefighter, peace officer, or physician medical director anywhere in this state while actually en route to the scene of a fire or other emergency requiring his or her services as a volunteer firefighter, peace officer, or physician medical director, but only after its use has been authorized in writing by the county sheriff and, with respect to a physician medical director, such person has successfully completed an emergency vehicle operator course.</para><para id="id00">(b) Application for a permit to display such light shall be made in writing to the sheriff on forms to be prescribed and furnished by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety. The application shall be accompanied by a statement that the applicant is a volunteer firefighter, peace officer, or physician medical director and is requesting issuance of the permit. The statement shall be signed by the applicant's superior.</para><para id="id00">(c) The permit shall be carried at all times in the vehicle named in the permit. Each such permit shall expire on December 31 of each year and shall be renewed in the same manner as it was originally issued.</para><para id="id00">(d) The sheriff may at any time revoke such permit upon a showing of abuse thereof or upon receipt of notice from the applicant's superior that the holder thereof is no longer an active volunteer firefighter, peace officer, or physician medical director. Any person whose permit has been so revoked shall upon demand surrender it to the sheriff or his or her authorized agent.</para><para id="id00">(2) A rotating or flashing red light or lights or such light or lights in combination with a blue light or lights may be displayed on any motor vehicle being used by rescue squads actually en route to, at, or returning from any emergency requiring their services, or by any privately owned wrecker when engaged in emergency services at the scene of an accident, or at a disabled vehicle, located outside the city limits of a city of the metropolitan or primary class, but only after its use has been authorized in writing by the county sheriff. Applications shall be made and may be revoked in the same manner as for volunteer firefighters as provided in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, physician medical director has the same meaning as in section 38-1210.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 327, &#167; 5, p. 1171; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 365, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1972, &#167; 39-788.04; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 64, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 416, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-6,151; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 329; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB8, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>