<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,225"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,225</statuteno><catchline>Spotlights; auxiliary driving lights; signal lights; other devices; intensity and direction.</catchline><para>(1) Any motor vehicle may be equipped with spotlights as specified in section 60-6,219, and every lighted spotlight shall be so aimed and used upon approaching another vehicle that no part of the beam will be directed to the left of the center of the highway nor more than one hundred feet ahead of the vehicle.</para><para>(2) Any motor vehicle may be equipped with not to exceed two auxiliary driving lights mounted on the front at a height not less than twelve inches nor more than forty-two inches above the level surface on which the vehicle stands, and every such auxiliary driving light shall meet the requirements and limitations set forth in section 60-6,221. The restrictions on mounting height provided in this subsection shall not apply to any motor vehicle equipped with a blade, plow, or any other device designed for the movement of snow. Auxiliary driving lights shall be turned off at the same time the motor vehicle's headlights are required to be dimmed when approaching another vehicle from either the front or the rear.</para><para>(3) Whenever a motor vehicle is equipped with a signal light, the signal light shall be so constructed and located on the vehicle as to give a signal which shall be plainly visible in normal sunlight from a distance of one hundred feet to the rear of the vehicle but shall not project a glaring or dazzling light.</para><para>(4) Any device, other than headlights, spotlights, or auxiliary driving lights, which projects a beam of light of an intensity greater than twenty-five candlepower shall be so directed that no part of the beam will strike the level of the surface on which the vehicle stands at a distance of more than fifty feet from the vehicle.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1931, c. 110, &#167; 44, p. 319; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-1175; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-779; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 366, &#167; 7, p. 1251; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 192, &#167; 1, p. 589; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-779; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 816, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 544, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 224, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,139; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 321; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 59, &#167; 3. </para></source>
<annotation>
<para>Auxiliary driving lights are defined by subsection (2) of this section, and under that subsection, if they do not meet the criteria for headlights set forth in section 60-6,221, it is a Class III misdemeanor under section 60-6,222. State v. Carnicle, 18 Neb. App. 761, 792 N.W.2d 893 (2010).</para>
<para>If fog lamps are contemplated under subsection (4) of this section as any device, other than headlights, spotlights, or auxiliary driving lights, which projects a beam of light of an intensity greater than 25 candlepower, then such fog lamps must be so directed that no part of the beam will strike the level of the surface on which the vehicle stands at a distance of more than 50 feet from the vehicle. State v. Carnicle, 18 Neb. App. 761, 792 N.W.2d 893 (2010).</para>
<para>The terms of subsection (2) of this section require reference to section 60-6,221, which provides that headlights shall produce a driving light sufficient to render clearly discernible a person 200 feet ahead, but the headlights shall not project a glaring or dazzling light to persons in front of such headlights. State v. Carnicle, 18 Neb. App. 761, 792 N.W.2d 893 (2010).</para>
</annotation>
</law></legaldoc>