<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id18">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id20" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-465"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-465</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Commercial motor
vehicle, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Commercial motor vehicle
means a motor vehicle or combination of motor vehicles used in commerce to
transport passengers or property if the motor vehicle:</para>
<para>(a) Has a gross combination weight rating or gross combination weight of eleven thousand
seven hundred ninety-four kilograms or more (twenty-six thousand one pounds
or more) inclusive of a towed unit with a gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight of
more than four thousand five hundred thirty-six kilograms (ten thousand pounds);</para>
<para>(b) Has a gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight of eleven thousand seven
hundred ninety-four or more kilograms (twenty-six thousand one pounds or more);</para>
<para>(c) Is designed to transport sixteen or more passengers, including
the driver; or</para>
<para>(d) Is of any size and is used in the transportation of materials
found to be hazardous for the purposes of the federal Hazardous Materials
Transportation Act and which require the motor vehicle to be placarded under
49 C.F.R. part 172, subpart F.</para>
<para>(2) Commercial motor vehicle does not include:</para>
<para>(a) A covered farm vehicle;</para>
<para>(b) Any recreational vehicle as defined in section
60-347 or motor vehicle towing a cabin trailer as defined in sections 60-314
and 60-339;</para>
<para>(c) Any emergency vehicle necessary to the preservation of life or property or the
execution of emergency governmental functions which is equipped with audible
and visual signals and operated by a public or volunteer fire
department; or</para>
<para>(d) Any motor vehicle owned or operated by the United
States Department of Defense or Nebraska National Guard when such motor vehicle
is driven by persons identified in section 60-4,131.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 235; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 853, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 6.</para><operativedate>March 29, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>