<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id213">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id215" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="60-4,189"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,189</statuteno><catchline>Operator's license; state identification
card; notation of word "veteran"; Department of Motor Vehicles; duties; replacement
license or card.</catchline><para>(1) An operator's license or a state identification card
shall include a notation of the word "veteran" on the front of the license
or card as directed by the department if the individual applying for such
license or card is eligible for the license or card and (a) has served on
active duty in the armed forces of the United States, other than active duty
for training, and was discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization
of honorable or general (under honorable conditions) from such service, (b)
registers with the Department of Veterans' Affairs pursuant to section 80-414
as verification of such service, and (c) indicates on the application under
section 60-484 his or her wish to include such notation on his or her license
or card.</para>
<para>(2) The Department
of Motor Vehicles shall consult the registry established pursuant to section
80-414 before placing the notation of the word "veteran" on the operator's
license or state identification card issued to the applicant. Such notation
shall not be authorized unless the registry verifies the applicant's eligibility.
If the Director of Motor Vehicles discovers evidence of fraud in an application
under this section, the director may summarily cancel the license or state
identification card and send notice of the cancellation to the licensee or
cardholder. If the Department of Motor Vehicles has information that an individual
is no longer eligible for the notation, the department may summarily cancel
the license and send notice of the cancellation to the licensee or cardholder.
The notation shall not be restored until the Department of Motor Vehicles
subsequently verifies the applicant's eligibility by consulting the registry
of the Department of Veterans' Affairs.</para><para>(3) The notation authorized in subsection
(1) of this section shall continue to be included on the license or card upon
renewal of such license or card if the licensee or cardholder, at the time
of renewal, indicates the desire to include the notation.</para>
<para>(4) An individual
may obtain a replacement operator's license or state identification card to
add or remove the notation authorized in subsection (1) of this section by
applying to the Department of Motor Vehicles for such replacement license
or card and, if adding the notation, by meeting the requirements of subsection
(1) of this section. The fee for such replacement license or card shall be
the fee provided in section 60-4,115.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB93, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>