<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id86" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-144"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-144</statuteno><catchline id="id89">Certificate of title; issuance;
filing; application; form.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as provided in subdivisions
(b), (c), and (d) of this subsection, the county treasurer shall be responsible
for issuing and filing certificates of title for vehicles, and each county
shall issue and file such certificates of title using the vehicle titling
and registration computer system prescribed by the department. Application
for a certificate of title shall be made upon a form prescribed by the department.
All applications shall be accompanied by the appropriate fee or fees.</para>
<para>(b) The department shall issue and file certificates of title for Nebraska-based
fleet vehicles. Application for a certificate of title shall be made upon
a form prescribed by the department. All applications shall be accompanied
by the appropriate fee or fees.</para>
<para>(c) The department shall issue and file certificates of title for state-owned
vehicles. Application for a certificate of title shall be made upon a form
prescribed by the department. All applications shall be accompanied by the
appropriate fee or fees.</para>
<para>(d) The department shall issue certificates of title pursuant to section
60-142.06. Application for a certificate of title shall be made upon a form
prescribed by the department. All applications shall be accompanied by the
appropriate fee or fees.</para>
<para>(2) If the owner of an all-terrain vehicle, a utility-type vehicle,
or a minibike resides in Nebraska, the application shall be filed with the
county treasurer of
the county in which the owner resides.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection,
if a vehicle, other than an all-terrain vehicle, a utility-type vehicle, or
a minibike, has situs in Nebraska, the application shall be filed with the
county treasurer of
the county in which the vehicle has situs.</para>
<para>(b) If a motor vehicle dealer licensed under the Motor Vehicle Industry
Regulation Act, applies for a certificate of title for a vehicle, the application
may be filed with the county treasurer of
any county.</para>
<para>(4) If the owner of a vehicle is a nonresident, the application shall
be filed in the county in which the transaction is consummated.</para>
<para>(5) The application shall be filed within thirty days after the delivery
of the vehicle.</para>
<para>(6) All applicants registering a vehicle pursuant to section 60-3,198
shall file the application for a certificate of title with the Division of
Motor Carrier Services of the department. The division shall deliver the certificate
to the applicant if there are no liens on the vehicle. If there are one or
more liens on the vehicle, the certificate of title shall be handled as provided
in section 60-164. All certificates of title issued by the division shall
be issued in the manner prescribed for the county treasurer in section 60-152.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 765, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB212, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 29.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 60-1401.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>There is no legal requirement that a lien be noted on a certificate of title purportedly covering property not subject to the Certificate of Title Act, even though a certificate of title for such property has been issued. Cushman Sales &amp; Service of Nebraska, Inc. v. Muirhead, 201 Neb. 495, 268 N.W.2d 440 (1978).</para><para>Under the Nebraska Certificate of Title Act, a certificate of title is the exclusive method provided by statute for the transfer of title to an automobile, but it is not conclusive of ownership. First Nat. Bank &amp; Trust Co. v. Ohio Cas. Ins. Co., 196 Neb. 595, 244 N.W.2d 209 (1976).</para><para>In the absence of even an assignment of certificate of title, title to motor vehicle remained in person named in certificate of title. Turpin v. Standard Reliance Ins. Co., 169 Neb. 233, 99 N.W.2d 26 (1959).</para><para>If applicant is a nonresident, application for certificate must be filed in county in which transaction is consummated. Universal C.I.T. Credit Corp. v. Vogt, 165 Neb. 611, 86 N.W.2d 771 (1957).</para><para>Legislature contemplated that form provided must be fully and properly executed. Loyal's Auto Exchange, Inc. v. Munch, 153 Neb. 628, 45 N.W.2d 913 (1951).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>