<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-166"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-166</statuteno><catchline>New certificate of title; issued when;
proof required; processing of application.</catchline><para>(1) In the event
of (a) the transfer of ownership of a vehicle by operation of law as upon
inheritance, devise, or bequest, order in bankruptcy, insolvency, replevin,
or execution sale or as provided in sections 30-24,125, 52-601.01 to 52-605,
60-1901 to 60-1911, and 60-2401 to 60-2411, (b) the engine of a vehicle being
replaced by another engine, (c) a vehicle being sold to satisfy storage or
repair charges, or (d) repossession being had upon default in performance
of the terms of a chattel mortgage, trust receipt, conditional sales contract,
or other like agreement, the county treasurer of
any county or the department, upon
the surrender of the prior certificate of title or the manufacturer's or importer's
certificate, or when that is not possible, upon presentation of satisfactory
proof of ownership and right of possession to such vehicle, and upon payment
of the appropriate fee and the presentation of an application for certificate
of title, may issue to the applicant a certificate of title thereto. If the
prior certificate of title issued for such vehicle provided for joint ownership
with right of survivorship, a new certificate of title shall be issued to
a subsequent purchaser upon the assignment of the prior certificate of title
by the surviving owner and presentation of satisfactory proof of death of
the deceased owner. Only an affidavit by the person or agent of the person
to whom possession of such vehicle has so passed, setting forth facts entitling
him or her to such possession and ownership, together with a copy of the journal
entry, court order, or instrument upon which such claim of possession and
ownership is founded, shall be considered satisfactory proof of ownership
and right of possession, except that if the applicant cannot produce such
proof of ownership, he or she may submit to the department such evidence as
he or she may have, and the department may thereupon, if it finds the evidence
sufficient, issue the certificate of title or authorize any county treasurer to issue a certificate
of title, as the case may be.</para>
<para>(2) If from the records of the county treasurer or
the department there appear to be any liens on such vehicle, such certificate
of title shall comply with section 60-164 or 60-165 regarding such liens unless
the application is accompanied by proper evidence of their satisfaction or
extinction.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 41.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB751, section 8, with LB801, section 41, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB801 became effective July 19, 2012. Changes made by LB751 became operative July 19, 2012.</note></source><annotation><para>There is no legal requirement that a lien be noted on a certificate of title purportedly covering property not subject to the Certificate of Title Act, even though a certificate of title for such property has been issued. Cushman Sales &amp; Service of Nebraska, Inc. v. Muirhead, 201 Neb. 495, 268 N.W.2d 440 (1978).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>