<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,244"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,244</statuteno><catchline>Support Our Troops Plates; application; form; fee; delivery; fee; transfer; procedure; fee.</catchline><para>(1) A person may apply to the department for Support Our Troops Plates in lieu of regular license plates on an application prescribed and provided by the department for any motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer, except for a motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer registered under section 60-3,198. An applicant receiving a Support Our Troops Plate for a farm truck with a gross weight of over sixteen tons shall affix the appropriate tonnage decal to the plate. The department shall make forms available for such applications through the county treasurers. The license plates shall be issued upon payment of the license fee described in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2)(a) In addition to all other fees required for registration under the Motor Vehicle Registration Act, each application for initial issuance of alphanumeric Support Our Troops Plates shall be accompanied by a fee of five dollars. An application for renewal of such plates shall be accompanied by a fee of five dollars. County treasurers collecting fees pursuant to this subdivision shall remit such fees to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit five dollars of the fee to the Veterans Employment Program Fund.</para><para>(b) In addition to all other fees required for registration under the Motor Vehicle Registration Act, each application for initial issuance or renewal of personalized message Support Our Troops Plates shall be accompanied by a fee of seventy dollars. County treasurers collecting fees pursuant to this subdivision shall remit such fees to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit twenty-five percent of the fee for initial issuance and renewal of such plates to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and seventy-five percent of the fee to the Veterans Employment Program Fund.</para><para>(3) When the department receives an application for Support Our Troops Plates, the department may deliver the plates and registration certificate to the applicant by United States mail or to the county treasurer of the county in which the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is registered and the delivery of the plates and registration certificate shall be made through a secure process and system. Beginning on an implementation date designated by the director on or before January 1, 2022, if delivery of the plates and registration certificate is made by the department to the applicant, the department may charge a postage and handling fee in an amount not more than necessary to recover the cost of postage and handling for the specific items mailed to the registrant. The department shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund. The county treasurer or the department shall issue Support Our Troops Plates in lieu of regular license plates when the applicant complies with the other provisions of the Motor Vehicle Registration Act for registration of the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer. If Support Our Troops Plates are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the licensee shall be issued replacement license plates upon request pursuant to section 60-3,157.</para><para>(4) The owner of a motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer bearing Support Our Troops Plates may apply to the county treasurer to have such plates transferred to a motor vehicle other than the vehicle for which such plates were originally purchased if such vehicle is owned by the owner of the plates. The owner may have the unused portion of the fee for the plates credited to the other vehicle which will bear the plates at the rate of eight and one-third percent per month for each full month left in the registration period. Application for such transfer shall be accompanied by a fee of three dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) If the cost of manufacturing Support Our Troops Plates at any time exceeds the amount charged for license plates pursuant to section 60-3,102, any money to be credited to the Veterans Employment Program Fund shall instead be credited first to the Highway Trust Fund in an amount equal to the difference between the manufacturing costs of Support Our Troops Plates and the amount charged pursuant to section 60-3,102 with respect to such plates and the remainder shall be credited to the Veterans Employment Program Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB138, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB113, &#167; 20. </para><operativedate>August 28, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>