<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id322" statutenumber="60-4,167"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,167</statuteno><catchline id="id325">Alcoholic liquor; officer's
report; notice of disqualification; hearing before director; procedure.</catchline>
<para>Upon receipt of a law enforcement officer's sworn report provided for
in section 60-4,164, the director shall serve the notice of disqualification
to the person who is the subject of the report by regular United States mail
to the person's last-known address appearing on the records of the director.
If the address on the director's records differs from the address on the arresting
officer's report, the notice of disqualification shall be sent to both addresses.
The notice of disqualification shall contain a statement explaining the operation
of the disqualification procedure and the rights of the person. The director
shall also provide to the person a self-addressed envelope and a petition
form which the person may use to request a hearing before the director to
contest the disqualification. The petition form shall clearly state on its
face that the petition must be completed and delivered to the department or
postmarked within ten days after receipt or the person's right to a hearing
to contest the disqualification will be foreclosed. The director shall prescribe
and approve the form for the petition, the self-addressed envelope, and the
notice of disqualification. If not contested, the disqualification shall automatically
take effect thirty days after the date of mailing of the notice of disqualification
by the director. Any chemical test or tests made under section 60-4,164, if
made in conformity with the requirements of section 60-6,201, shall be competent
evidence of the alcoholic content of such person's blood or breath. The commercial
driver's license or commercial
learner's permit of the person who is the subject of the report
shall be automatically disqualified upon the expiration of thirty days after
the date of the mailing of the notice of disqualification by the director.
The director shall conduct the hearing in the county in which the violation
occurred or in any county agreed to by the parties. Upon receipt of a petition,
the director shall notify the petitioner of the date and location for the
hearing by regular United States mail postmarked at least seven days prior
to the hearing date.</para>
<para>After granting the petitioner an opportunity to be heard on such issue,
if it is not shown to the director that the petitioner's refusal to submit
to such chemical test or tests was reasonable or unless it is shown to the
director that the petitioner was not operating or in the actual physical control
of a commercial motor vehicle with an alcoholic concentration in his or her
blood or breath equal to or in excess of that specified in subsection (5)
of section 60-4,164, the director shall enter an order pursuant to section
60-4,169 revoking the petitioner's commercial driver's license or commercial learner's permit and the petitioner's privilege
to operate a commercial motor vehicle in this state and disqualifying the
person from operating a commercial motor vehicle for the period specified
by section 60-4,168.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 117; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 191, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 323, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 48.</para><operativedate>July 8, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>