<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id78" statutenumber="60-4,125"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,125</statuteno><catchline id="id81">LPD-learner's permit; LPE-learner's permit; violations; impoundment or revocation of permit; effect on eligibility for operator's license; not eligible for ignition interlock permit.</catchline><para>(1) For any minor convicted or adjudicated of violating the terms of an LPD-learner's permit issued pursuant to section 60-4,123 or an LPE-learner's permit issued pursuant to section 60-4,124, the court shall, in addition to any other penalty or disposition, order the impoundment or revocation of such learner's permit and order that such minor shall not be eligible for another operator's license or school, farm, LPD-learner's, or LPE-learner's permit until he or she has attained the age of sixteen years.</para><para>(2) Any person who holds an LPD-learner's permit issued pursuant to section 60-4,123 and has violated subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-306, subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-394, or section 28-1254, 60-6,196, 60-6,197, 60-6,197.06, or 60-6,198 shall not be eligible for an ignition interlock permit.</para><para>(3) A copy of the court's abstract or adjudication shall be transmitted to the director who shall place in an impound status or revoke the LPD-learner's or LPE-learner's permit of such minor in accordance with the order of the court and not again issue another operator's license or school, farm, LPD-learner's, or LPE-learner's permit to such minor until such minor has attained the age of sixteen years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 359, &#167; 7, p. 1153; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-409.05; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 420, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 353, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB269, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>