<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-366"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-366</statuteno><catchline>Nonresident owner; registration; when; reciprocity.</catchline><para>(1) Any nonresident owner who desires to register a motor vehicle or trailer in this state shall register in the county where the motor vehicle or trailer is domiciled or where the owner conducts a bona fide business.</para><para>(2) A nonresident owner, except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, owning any motor vehicle or trailer which has been properly registered in the state, country, or other place of which the owner is a resident, and which at all times, when operated or towed in this state, has displayed upon it the license plate or plates issued for such motor vehicle or trailer in the place of residence of such owner, may operate or permit the operation or tow or permit the towing of such motor vehicle or trailer within the state without registering such motor vehicle or trailer or paying any fees to this state.</para><para>(3) Any nonresident owner gainfully employed or present in this state, operating a motor vehicle or towing a trailer in this state, shall register such motor vehicle or trailer in the same manner as a Nebraska resident, after thirty days of continuous employment or presence in this state, unless the state of his or her legal residence grants immunity from such requirements to residents of this state operating a motor vehicle or towing a trailer in that state. Any nonresident owner who operates a motor vehicle or tows a trailer in this state for thirty or more continuous days shall register such motor vehicle or trailer in the same manner as a Nebraska resident unless the state of his or her legal residence grants immunity from such requirements to residents of this state operating a motor vehicle or towing a trailer in that state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 66. </para></source><annotation><para>Right of nonresident owner of motor vehicle to operate under license issued by another state is recognized. Universal C.I.T. Credit Corp. v. Vogt, 165 Neb. 611, 86 N.W.2d 771 (1957).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>