<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id415">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id417" statutenumber="60-4,184"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,184</statuteno><catchline id="id420">Revocation
of license; notice; failure to return license; procedure; penalty; appeal;
effect.</catchline><para>Within ten days after the revocation provided
for by section 60-4,183, the director shall notify in writing the person whose
operator's license has been revoked that such license has been revoked. Such
notice shall:</para>
<para>(1) Contain a list of the convictions for violations upon
which the director relies as his or her authority for the revocation, with
the dates of such violations upon which convictions were had and the dates
of such convictions, the trial courts in which such judgments of conviction
were rendered, and the points charged for each conviction;</para>
<para>(2) State the term of such revocation;</para>
<para>(3) Include a demand that the license be returned to the
director immediately; and</para>
<para>(4) Be served by mailing it to such person by regular United States mail
to the last-known residence of such person or, if such address is unknown,
to the last-known business address of such person.</para>
<para>If any person fails to return his or her license to the director
as demanded, the director shall immediately direct any peace officer or authorized
representative of the director to secure possession of such license and return
the license to the director. A refusal to surrender an operator's license
on demand shall be unlawful, and any person failing to surrender his or her
license as required by this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
<para>Any person who feels aggrieved because of such revocation
may appeal from such revocation in the manner set forth in section 60-4,105.
Such appeal shall not suspend the order of revocation of such license unless
a stay of such order is allowed by a judge of such court pending a final determination
of the review. The license of any person claiming to be aggrieved shall not
be restored to such person, in the event the final judgment of a court finds
against such person, until the full time of revocation, as fixed by the Department
of Motor Vehicles, has elapsed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 219, &#167; 3, p. 770; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 157, &#167; 1, p. 460; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 242, &#167; 32, p. 845; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 366, &#167; 28, p. 1263; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 174, &#167; 3, p. 627; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,130; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 263, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-669.28; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 41.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>