<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,172"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,172</statuteno><catchline>Nonresident licensee or permit holder; conviction within state;
director; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Within ten days after receiving an
abstract of conviction of any nonresident who holds
a commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license for
any violation of state law or local ordinance related to motor vehicle traffic
control, other than parking violations, committed in a commercial motor vehicle
operated in this state, the director shall notify the driver licensing authority
which licensed the nonresident who
holds a commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license and
the Commercial Driver License Information System of such conviction.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Within ten
days after disqualifying a nonresident who
holds a commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license
or canceling, revoking, or suspending the
commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license held by a nonresident, for
a period of at least sixty days, the department shall
notify the driver licensing authority which licensed the nonresident and the
Commercial Driver License Information System of such action.</para>
<para>(b) The notification shall include both the disqualification and the
violation that resulted in the disqualification, cancellation, revocation,
or suspension. The notification and the information it provides shall be recorded
on the driver's record.</para>
<para>(3) Within ten
days after receiving an abstract of conviction of any nonresident who holds a commercial learner's permit or commercial
driver's license for any violation of state law or local ordinance related
to motor vehicle traffic control, other than parking violations, committed
in any type of motor vehicle operated in this state, the director shall notify
the driver licensing authority which licensed the nonresident and the Commercial
Driver License Information System of such conviction.</para>
<para>(4) Within ten
days after receiving an abstract of conviction of any nonresident who holds a driver's license for any violation
of state law or local ordinance related to motor vehicle traffic control,
other than parking violations, committed in a commercial motor vehicle operated
in this state, the director shall notify the driver licensing authority which
licensed the nonresident.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 53.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>