<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-6,317"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,317</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Bicycles on roadways and bicycle paths; general rules; regulation by local authority.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any person who operates a bicycle upon a roadway at less than the normal speed of traffic at the time and place and under conditions then existing shall ride as near to the right-hand curb or right-hand edge of the roadway as practicable except when:</para><para>(i) Overtaking and passing another bicycle or vehicle proceeding in the same direction;</para><para>(ii) Preparing for a left turn onto a private road or driveway or at an intersection;</para><para>(iii) Reasonably necessary to avoid conditions that make it unsafe to continue along the right-hand curb or right-hand edge of the roadway, including fixed or moving objects, stopped or moving vehicles, bicycles, pedestrians, animals, or surface hazards;</para><para>(iv) Riding upon a lane of substandard width which is too narrow for a bicycle and a vehicle to travel safely side by side within the lane; or</para><para>(v) Lawfully operating a bicycle on the paved shoulders of a highway included in the state highway system as provided in section 60-6,142.</para><para>(b) Any person who operates a bicycle upon a roadway with a posted speed limit of thirty-five miles per hour or less on which traffic is restricted to one direction of movement and which has two or more marked traffic lanes may ride as near to the left-hand curb or left-hand edge of the roadway as practicable.</para><para>(c) Whenever a person operating a bicycle leaves the roadway to ride on the paved shoulder or leaves the paved shoulder to enter the roadway, the person shall clearly signal his or her intention and yield the right-of-way to all other vehicles.</para><para>(2) No bicyclist shall suddenly leave a curb or other place of safety and walk or ride into the path of a vehicle which is so close that it is impossible for the driver to stop.</para><para>(3) Any person who operates a bicycle upon a highway shall not ride more than single file except on paths or parts of highways set aside for the exclusive use of bicycles.</para><para>(4) A bicyclist riding a bicycle on a sidewalk or across a roadway or shoulder in a crosswalk shall have all the rights and duties applicable to a pedestrian under the same circumstances but shall yield the right-of-way to pedestrians. Nothing in this subsection relieves the bicyclist or the driver of a vehicle from the duty to exercise care.</para><para>(5) A local authority may by ordinance further regulate the operation of bicycles and may provide for the registration and inspection of bicycles.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 90; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-690; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 413; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB716, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>