<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"  statutenumber="60-142.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-142.03</statuteno><catchline>Recognized car club; qualified
car club representative; department; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of this section, car club means an organization that has members
with knowledge of and expertise pertaining to authentic vehicles and that
has members with knowledge of and expertise pertaining to the restoration
and preservation of specific makes and models of vehicles using replacement
parts that are essentially the same in design and material to that originally
supplied by the manufacturer for a specific year, make, and model of vehicle.</para>
<para>(2) To become a recognized car club, a car club shall apply to the department.
For a car club to become recognized, it must be a nonprofit organization with
established bylaws and at least twenty members. The applicant shall provide
a copy of the bylaws and a membership list to the department. The department
shall determine if a car club qualifies as a recognized car club. The determination
of the department shall be final and nonappealable.</para>
<para>(3) A member of a recognized car club may apply to the department to
become a qualified car club representative. Each qualified car club representative
shall be designated by the president or director of the local chapter of the
recognized car club of which he or she is a member. The department shall identify
and maintain a list of qualified car club representatives. A qualified car
club representative may apply to be placed on the list of qualified car club
representatives by providing the department with his or her name, address,
and telephone number, the name, address, and telephone number of the recognized
car club he or she represents, a copy of the designation of the representative
by the president or director of the local chapter of the recognized car club,
and such other information as may be required by the department. The department
may place a qualified car club representative on the list upon receipt of
a completed application and may provide each representative with information
for inspection of vehicles and parts. The determination of the department
regarding designation of an individual as a qualified car club representative
and placement on the list of qualified car club representatives shall be final
and nonappealable. The department shall distribute the list to county treasurers.</para>
<para>(4) When a qualified car club representative inspects vehicles and replacement
parts, he or she shall determine whether all major component parts used in
the assembly of a vehicle are original or essentially the same in design and
material to that originally supplied by the manufacturer for the specific
year, make, and model of vehicle, including the appropriate engine, body material,
body shape, and other requirements as prescribed by the department. After
such inspection, the representative shall provide the owner with a statement
in the form prescribed by the department which includes the findings of the
inspection. No qualified car club representative shall charge any fee for
the inspection or the statement. No qualified car club representative shall
provide a statement for any vehicle owned by such representative or any member
of his or her immediate family.</para>
<para>(5) The director may summarily remove a person from the list of qualified
car club representatives upon written notice. Such person may reapply for
inclusion on the list upon presentation of suitable evidence satisfying the
director that the cause for removal from the list has been corrected, eliminated,
no longer exists, or will not affect or interfere with the person's judgment
or qualifications for inspection of vehicles to determine whether or not any
replacement parts are essentially the same in design and material to that
originally supplied by the original manufacturer for the specific year, make,
and model of vehicle.</para>
<para>(6) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to
carry out this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>