<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles"  statutenumber="60-3,222"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,222</statuteno><catchline>Payment of fee or tax; check, draft,
or financial transaction returned or not honored; county treasurer; powers;
notice; return of registration and license plates required; sheriff; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) If a fee required
under the Motor Vehicle Registration Act or a tax required to be paid on any
motor vehicle or trailer has been paid by check, draft, or other financial
transaction, including an electronic financial transaction, and the check,
draft, or financial transaction has been returned or not honored because of
insufficient funds, no account, a stop-payment order, or any other reason,
a county treasurer may cancel or refuse to issue or renew registration under
the act.</para>
<para>(2) The county
treasurer may take the action described in subsection (1) of this section
no sooner than seven days after the notice required in subsection (3) of this
section has been mailed.</para><para>(3) Prior to taking action described in subsection
(1) of this section, the county treasurer shall notify the applicant or registrant
of the proposed action and the reasons for such action in writing, by first-class,
registered, or certified mail, mailed to the applicant's or registrant's last-known
address as shown on the application for registration or renewal.</para>
<para>(4) If the county
treasurer takes action pursuant to this section, the county treasurer shall
reinstate the registration without delay upon the payment of certified funds
by the applicant or registrant for any fees and taxes due and reasonable administrative
costs, not to exceed twenty-five dollars, incurred in taking such action.</para>
<para>(5) Any person
who is sent a notice from the county treasurer pursuant to subsection (1)
of this section shall, within ten business days after mailing of the notice,
return to the county treasurer the motor vehicle registration and license
plates of the vehicle or trailer regarding which the action has been taken.
If the person fails to return the registration and license plates to the county
treasurer, the county treasurer shall notify the sheriff of the county in
which the person resides that the person is in violation of this section.
The sheriff may recover the registration and license plates and return them
to the county treasurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB129, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>