<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-480"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-480</statuteno><catchline>Operators' licenses; classification.</catchline>
<para>Operators' licenses issued by the department pursuant
to the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act shall be classified as follows:</para>
<para>(1) Class O license. The operator's license which authorizes the person
to whom it is issued to operate on highways any motor vehicle except a commercial
motor vehicle or motorcycle;</para>
<para>(2) Class M license. The operator's license or endorsement on a Class
O license, provisional operator's permit, learner's permit, school permit,
or commercial driver's license which authorizes the person to whom it is issued
to operate a motorcycle on highways;</para>
<para>(3) CDL-commercial driver's license. The operator's license which authorizes
the person to whom it is issued to operate a class of commercial motor vehicle or any motor vehicle, except a motorcycle,
on highways;</para>
<para>(4) CLP-commercial learner's
permit. A permit which when carried with a Class O license authorizes an individual
to operate a class of commercial motor vehicle when accompanied by a holder
of a valid commercial driver's license for purposes of behind-the-wheel training.
When issued to a commercial driver's license holder, a CLP-commercial learner's
permit serves as authorization for accompanied behind-the-wheel training in
a commercial motor vehicle for which the holder's current commercial driver's
license is not valid;</para><para>(5) RCDL-restricted
commercial driver's license. The class of commercial driver's license which,
when held with an annual seasonal permit, authorizes a seasonal commercial
motor vehicle operator as defined in section 60-4,146.01 to operate any Class
B Heavy Straight Vehicle or Class C Small Vehicle commercial motor vehicle
for purposes of a farm-related or ranch-related service industry as defined
in such section within one hundred fifty miles of the employer's place of
business or the farm or ranch currently being served as provided in such section
or any other motor vehicle, except a motorcycle, on highways;</para>
<para>(6) POP-provisional operator's
permit. A motor vehicle operating permit with restrictions issued pursuant
to section 60-4,120.01 to a person who is at least sixteen years of age but
less than eighteen years of age which authorizes the person to operate any
motor vehicle except a commercial motor vehicle or motorcycle;</para>
<para>(7) SCP-school permit. A permit
issued to a student between fourteen years and two months of age and sixteen
years of age for the purpose of driving in accordance with the requirements
of section 60-4,124;</para>
<para>(8) FMP-farm permit. A permit
issued to a person for purposes of operating farm tractors and other motorized
implements of farm husbandry on highways in accordance with the requirements
of section 60-4,126;</para>
<para>(9) LPD-learner's permit. A permit issued
in accordance with the requirements of section 60-4,123 to a person at least
fifteen years of age which authorizes the person to operate a motor vehicle,
except a commercial motor vehicle, for learning purposes when accompanied
by a licensed operator who is at least twenty-one years of age and who possesses
a valid operator's license issued by this state or another state;</para>
<para>(10) LPE-learner's permit. A permit issued to a person at least fourteen
years of age which authorizes the person to operate a motor vehicle, except
a commercial motor vehicle, while learning to drive in preparation for application
for a school permit;</para>
<para>(11) EDP-employment driving permit. A permit issued to a person which
authorizes the person to operate a motor vehicle, except a commercial motor
vehicle, pursuant to the requirements of sections 60-4,129 and 60-4,130;</para>
<para>(12) IIP-ignition interlock permit. A permit issued to a person which
authorizes the person to operate a motor vehicle, except a commercial motor
vehicle, which is equipped with an ignition interlock device;</para>
<para>(13) SEP-seasonal permit. A permit issued to a person who holds a restricted
commercial driver's license authorizing the person to operate a commercial
motor vehicle, as prescribed by section 60-4,146.01, for no more than one
hundred eighty consecutive days in any twelve-month period. The seasonal permit
shall be valid and run from the date of original issuance of the permit for
one hundred eighty days and from the date of annual revalidation of the permit;
and</para>
<para>(14) MHP-medical hardship driving permit. A permit issued to a person
which authorizes the person to operate a motor vehicle, except a commercial
motor vehicle, pursuant to the requirements of sections 60-4,130.01 and 60-4,130.02.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1989, LB 285, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 105, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 420, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 387, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 675, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 9.</para><operativedate>July 8, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>