
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id6"  statutenumber="60-6,197.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,197.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Driving while
license has been revoked; driving under influence of alcoholic liquor or drug;
second and subsequent violations; restrictions on motor vehicles; additional
restrictions authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Upon conviction for
a violation described in section 60-6,197.06 or a second or subsequent violation
of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197, the court shall impose either of the following
restrictions:</para>
<para>(a)(i) The court shall order all motor vehicles owned by the
person so convicted immobilized at the owner's expense for a period of time
not less than five days and not more than eight months and shall notify the
Department of Motor Vehicles of the period of immobilization. Any immobilized
motor vehicle shall be released to the holder of a bona fide lien on the motor
vehicle executed prior to such immobilization when possession of the motor
vehicle is requested as provided by law by such lienholder for purposes of
foreclosing and satisfying such lien. If a person tows and stores a motor
vehicle pursuant to this subdivision at the direction of a peace officer or
the court and has a lien upon such motor vehicle while it is in his or her
possession for reasonable towing and storage charges, the person towing the
vehicle has the right to retain such motor vehicle until such lien is paid.
For purposes of this subdivision, immobilized or immobilization means revocation
or suspension, at the discretion of the court, of the registration of such
motor vehicle or motor vehicles, including the license plates; and</para>
<para>(ii)(A) Any immobilized motor vehicle shall be released by
the court without any legal or physical restraints to any registered owner
who is not the registered owner convicted of a second or subsequent violation
of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197 if an affidavit is submitted to the court
by such registered owner stating that the affiant is employed, that the motor
vehicle subject to immobilization is necessary to continue that employment,
that such employment is necessary for the well-being of the affiant's dependent
children or parents, that the affiant will not authorize the use of the motor
vehicle by any person known by the affiant to have been convicted of a second
or subsequent violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197, that affiant will
immediately report to a local law enforcement agency any unauthorized use
of the motor vehicle by any person known by the affiant to have been convicted
of a second or subsequent conviction of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197, and
that failure to release the motor vehicle would cause undue hardship to the
affiant.</para>
<para>(B) A registered owner who executes an affidavit pursuant
to subdivision (1)(a)(ii)(A) of this section which is acted upon by the court
and who fails to immediately report an unauthorized use of the motor vehicle
which is the subject of the affidavit is guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor
and may not file any additional affidavits pursuant to subdivision (1)(a)(ii)(A)
of this section.</para>
<para>(C) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to implement the provisions of subdivision (1)(a) of this section; or</para>
<para>(b) As an alternative to subdivision (1)(a) of this section,
the court shall order the convicted person, in order to operate a motor vehicle,
to obtain an ignition interlock permit and install an ignition interlock device
on each motor vehicle owned or operated by the convicted person if he or she
was sentenced to an operator's license revocation of at least one year. If
the person's operator's license has been revoked for at least a one-year period,
after a minimum of a forty-five-day no driving period, the person may operate
a motor vehicle with an ignition interlock permit and an ignition interlock
device pursuant to this subdivision and shall retain the ignition interlock
permit and ignition interlock device for not less than a one-year period or the period of revocation ordered
by the court, whichever is longer. No ignition interlock permit may be issued
until sufficient evidence is presented to the department that an ignition
interlock device is installed on each vehicle and that the applicant is eligible
for use of an ignition interlock device. If
the person has an ignition interlock device installed as required under this
subdivision, the person shall not be eligible for reinstatement of his or
her operator's license until he or she has had the ignition interlock device
installed for the period ordered by the court.</para>
<para>(2) In addition to the restrictions required by subdivision
(1)(b) of this section, the court may require a person convicted of a second
or subsequent violation of section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197 to use a continuous
alcohol monitoring device and abstain from alcohol use for a period of time
not to exceed the maximum term of license revocation ordered by the court.
A continuous alcohol monitoring device shall not be ordered for a person convicted
of a second or subsequent violation unless the installation of an ignition
interlock device is also required.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 585, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 925, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB497, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB924, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB158, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>