<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,158"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,158</statuteno><catchline>Third-party testers; applicant; criminal history record check;
fingerprints; rules and regulations; fees; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) The director shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing
the certification of third-party testers by the department. Such rules and regulations shall
substantially comply with the requirements of 49 C.F.R. 383.75. A third-party skills test examiner employed
by a certified third-party tester is not required to hold a commercial driver's
license to administer a driving skills examination and occupy the seat beside
an applicant for a commercial driver's license.</para>
<para>(2)(a) An applicant to
be certified as a third-party skills test examiner shall provide fingerprints
to the Nebraska State Patrol. The Nebraska State Patrol shall undertake a
search for criminal history record information relating to such applicant,
including transmittal of the applicant's fingerprints to the Federal Bureau
of Investigation for a national criminal history record information check.
The criminal history record information shall include information concerning
the applicant from federal repositories of such information and repositories
of such information in other states if authorized by federal law. The Nebraska
State Patrol shall issue a report to the department that includes the criminal
history record information concerning the applicant. The applicant shall pay
the actual cost of the fingerprinting and criminal background check.</para>
<para>(b) A third-party skills
test examiner shall be subject to a national criminal history record information
check.</para><para>(c)
The department shall maintain a record of the results of the criminal background
check and third-party skills test examiner test training and certification
of all third-party skills test examiners.</para><para>(d) The department shall rescind the certification
to administer commercial driver's license tests of all third-party skills
test examiners who:</para><para>(i)
Do not successfully complete the required refresher training every four years;
or</para><para>(ii)
Do not pass a national criminal history record information check. Criteria
for not passing the criminal background check must include at least the following:</para>
<para>(A) Any felony conviction
within the last ten years; or</para><para>(B) Any conviction involving fraudulent activities.</para>
<para>(3) A certification to conduct
third-party testing shall be valid for two years, and the department shall
charge a fee of one hundred dollars to issue or renew the certification of
any third-party tester. The department shall remit the fees collected to the
State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund.</para>
<para>(4) Any third-party tester
who violates any of the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant
to this section shall be subject to having his or her certification revoked
by the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 108; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 44.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>