<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id184" statutenumber="60-3,100"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,100</statuteno><catchline id="id187">License plates; issuance; delivery; display; requirements; fees.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall issue to every person whose motor vehicle or trailer is registered one or two fully reflectorized license plates upon which shall be displayed (a) the registration number consisting of letters and numerals assigned to such motor vehicle or trailer in figures not less than two and one-half inches nor more than three inches in height and (b) also the word Nebraska suitably lettered so as to be attractive. The license plates shall be of a color designated by the director. The color of the plates shall be changed each time the license plates are changed. Each time the license plates are changed, the director shall secure competitive bids for materials pursuant to the State Procurement Act. Autocycle, motorcycle, minitruck, low-speed vehicle, and trailer license plate letters and numerals may be one-half the size of those required in this section.</para><para>(2)(a) This subsection applies on and before December 31, 2028.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, two license plates shall be issued for every motor vehicle.</para><para>(c) One license plate shall be issued for (i) apportionable vehicles, (ii) buses, (iii) dealers, (iv) minitrucks, (v) motorcycles, other than autocycles, (vi) special interest motor vehicles that use the special interest motor vehicle license plate authorized by and issued under section 60-3,135.01, (vii) trailers, and (viii) truck-tractors.</para><para>(d)(i) One license plate shall be issued, upon request and compliance with this subdivision, for any passenger car which is not manufactured to be equipped with a bracket on the front of the vehicle to display a license plate. A license decal shall be issued with the license plate as provided in subdivision (ii) of this subdivision and shall be displayed on the driver's side of the windshield. In order to request a single license plate and license decal, there shall be an additional annual nonrefundable registration fee of fifty dollars plus the cost of the decal paid to the county treasurer at the time of registration. All fees collected under this subdivision shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Highway Trust Fund.</para><para>(ii) The department shall design, procure, and furnish to the county treasurers a license decal which shall be displayed as evidence that a license plate has been obtained under this subdivision. Each county treasurer shall furnish a license decal to the person obtaining the plate.</para><para>(e) When two license plates are issued, one shall be prominently displayed at all times on the front and one on the rear of the registered motor vehicle or trailer. When only one plate is issued, it shall be prominently displayed on the rear of the registered motor vehicle or trailer. When only one plate is issued for motor vehicles registered pursuant to section 60-3,198 and truck-tractors, it shall be prominently displayed on the front of the apportionable vehicle.</para><para>(3)(a) This subsection applies on and after January 1, 2029.</para><para>(b) One license plate shall be issued for every registered motor vehicle or trailer.</para><para>(c) Except as otherwise provided in this subsection, the license plate for a registered motor vehicle or trailer shall be prominently displayed on the rear of the registered motor vehicle or trailer.</para><para>(d) When a license plate is issued for motor vehicles registered pursuant to section 60-3,198 and truck-tractors, such license plate shall be prominently displayed on the front of the apportionable vehicle or truck-tractor.</para><para>(4)(a) The director shall designate an implementation date for this subsection that is on or before January 1, 2029. Beginning on such implementation date, the department may deliver any license plate or registration certificate to the applicant or to the county treasurer of the county in which the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is registered by United States mail or through an alternative shipping service. The delivery of such license plate or registration certificate shall be made through a secure process.</para><para>(b) If delivery of any license plate or registration certificate is made by the department to the applicant, the department may charge a postage and handling fee in an amount not more than necessary to recover the cost of postage and handling for the specific items mailed to the applicant. The department shall remit the fee to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(5) Any person who presents proof of registration shall be permitted to operate the registered motor vehicle or tow the registered trailer for a period of thirty days without a mailed license plate displayed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB289, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB216, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB231, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB53, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB356, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB461, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB97, &#167; 20. </para><operativedate>September 03, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Procurement Act,</emphasis> see section 73-801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Where the front license plate was placed in the front window of the defendant's vehicle, displayed so that a law enforcement officer was unable to ascertain the numbers or see the plate clearly, a traffic violation occurred, giving the officer probable cause to stop the defendant's vehicle. State v. Richardson, 17 Neb. App. 388, 763 N.W.2d 420 (2008).</para><para>"Display" of license plates as described in this section logically implies a display of the license plate which is visible. State v. Reiter, 3 Neb. App. 153, 524 N.W.2d 575 (1994).</para><para>Officer properly stopped vehicle bearing both Missouri license plates and in transit sticker, and when driver failed to produce identification, and upon noticing scratches around vehicle identification number checked to determine whether vehicle was stolen, upon learning it was, was justified in making arrest. United States v. Harris, 528 F.2d 1327 (8th Cir. 1975).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>