<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id111"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-378"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>60-378</statuteno><catchline>Transporter license plates; display; fee; records.</catchline><para>(1) Any transporter that is registered with the Secretary of State and authorized to transact business in this state may, in lieu of registering each motor vehicle or trailer which such transporter is transporting, upon payment of a fee of ten dollars, apply to the department for a transporter's certificate and one transporter license plate. Additional pairs of transporter certificates and transporter license plates may be procured for a fee of ten dollars each.</para><para>(2) Transporter license plates shall be displayed upon:</para><para>(a) The motor vehicle or trailer being transported; or</para><para>(b) A properly registered truck or truck-tractor that is a work or service vehicle in the process of towing a trailer that is itself being delivered by the transporter.</para><para>(3) The applicant for a transporter license plate shall keep for three years a record of each motor vehicle or trailer transported by the applicant under this section. Such record shall be available to the department for inspection.</para><para>(4) Each applicant shall file with the department proof of his or her status as a bona fide transporter.</para><para>(5) Transporter license plates:</para><para>(a) May be the same size as license plates issued for motorcycles other than autocycles;</para><para>(b) Shall bear a mark to distinguish them as transporter license plates; and</para><para>(c) Shall be serially numbered so as to distinguish them from each other.</para><para>(6) Transporter license plates shall only be displayed upon the:</para><para>(a) Front of a driven motor vehicle of a lawful combination;</para><para>(b) Front of a motor vehicle driven singly;</para><para>(c) Rear of a trailer being towed; or</para><para>(d) Front of a registered truck or truck-tractor that is described in subdivision (2)(b) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 78; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB699, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB972, &#167; 42. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>