<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-4,118.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,118.03</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Mental, medical, or vision problems; records and reports; examinations; reports; appeal; immunity.</catchline><para id="id00">Whenever the director reviews the denial or cancellation of an operator's license because of mental, medical, or vision problems that may affect the person's ability to safely operate a motor vehicle as provided in sections 60-4,114 and 60-4,118, the director may consider records and reports from a qualified physician. The applicant or licensee may cause a written report to be forwarded to the director by a physician of his or her choice pursuant to an immediate appeal to the director under section 60-4,114. The director shall grant reasonable time for the applicant or licensee to submit such records. The director shall give due consideration to any such report.</para><para id="id00">Reports received by the director for the purpose of assisting the director in determining whether a person is qualified to be licensed shall be for the confidential use of the director and any designees of the director and may not be divulged to any person other than the applicant or licensee or used in evidence in any legal proceeding, except that a report may be admitted in an appeal of an order of the director based on the report. Any person aggrieved by a decision of the director made pursuant to this section may appeal the decision as provided in section 60-4,105.</para><para id="id00">No person examining any applicant or licensee shall be liable in tort or otherwise for any opinion, recommendation, or report presented to the director if such action was taken in good faith and without malice.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 211, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB644, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>