<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-6,154"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,154</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Crossing at other than crosswalks; yield right-of-way.</catchline><para>(1) Every pedestrian who crosses a roadway at any point other than within a marked crosswalk, or within an unmarked crosswalk at an intersection, shall yield the right-of-way to all vehicles upon the roadway.</para><para>(2) Any pedestrian who crosses a roadway at a point where a pedestrian tunnel or overhead pedestrian crossing has been provided shall yield the right-of-way to all vehicles upon the roadway.</para><para>(3) Between adjacent intersections at which traffic control signals are in operation, pedestrians shall not cross at any place except in a marked crosswalk.</para><para>(4) Where a path designated for bicycles and pedestrians crosses a highway, a pedestrian who is in the crossing in accordance with the traffic control device shall have the right-of-way within the crossing with respect to vehicles and bicycles.</para><para>(5) No pedestrian shall cross a roadway intersection diagonally unless authorized by traffic control devices, and when authorized to cross diagonally, pedestrians shall cross only in accordance with the traffic control devices pertaining to such crossing movements.</para><para>(6) Local authorities and the Department of Transportation, by erecting appropriate official traffic control devices, may, within their respective jurisdictions, prohibit pedestrians from crossing any roadway in a business district or any designated highway except in a crosswalk.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 43; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-643; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 250; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB716, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 204. </para></source><annotation><para>Violation of this provision is not determinative of the degree of a pedestrian's negligence, if any. Hennings v. Schufeldt, 222 Neb. 416, 384 N.W.2d 274 (1986).</para><para>Pedestrians may cross intersection diagonally when authorized by official traffic-control devices, but only in accordance with devices pertaining to such movements. Therkildsen v. Gottsch, 194 Neb. 729, 235 N.W.2d 622 (1975).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, a pedestrian who stepped from the curb into traffic failed to prove causation to withstand a directed verdict because the evidence showed that the driver could not have avoided hitting the pedestrian even if the driver had seen the pedestrian step from the curb. Fidler v. Koster, 8 Neb. App. 884, 603 N.W.2d 165 (1999).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>