<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id206"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,294.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,294.02</statuteno><catchline>Overweight raw-milk vehicle; prohibited acts; map of bridge structures; Department of Transportation; powers and duties; liability of owner.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(a) Raw milk needs to be promptly processed;</para><para>(b) Lawful truck weight requirements can lead to an inability to haul all available raw milk produced at a dairy farm, which results in some raw milk being wasted;</para><para>(c) There has been a reduction in the availability of raw milk processing facilities in this state; and</para><para>(d) The opportunity and need for overweight raw-milk vehicle permits to operate overweight raw-milk vehicles to carry only raw milk from a dairy farm to a milk processing facility for such raw milk is needed due to 23 U.S.C. 127(a)(13), as such section existed on January 1, 2025, concerning the carrying of fluid milk products.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Bridge map means the map described in subsection (4) of this section;</para><para>(b) Department means the Department of Transportation;</para><para>(c) Overweight raw-milk vehicle means a vehicle that has been issued and currently holds an overweight raw-milk vehicle permit;</para><para>(d) Overweight raw-milk vehicle permit means a valid special, continuing, or continuous overweight raw-milk vehicle permit issued under section 60-6,298 to carry raw milk from a dairy farm to a processing facility for such raw milk; and</para><para>(e) Prohibited bridge structure means a bridge structure identified as prohibited on the bridge map.</para><para>(3) An overweight raw-milk vehicle shall:</para><para>(a) Not exceed a gross weight of one hundred seven thousand five hundred pounds;</para><para>(b) For each single axle and each group of axles on the truck-tractor and the hauling tanker trailer, not exceed the weight limits calculated using the federal bridge formula identified in 23 U.S.C. 127, as such section existed on January 1, 2025;</para><para>(c) Carry a physical or digital copy of the bridge map;</para><para>(d) Not enter any prohibited bridge structure; and</para><para>(e) Not travel on the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways, unless authorized by the department on the overweight raw-milk vehicle permit pursuant to written approval from the Federal Highway Administration for such authorization.</para><para>(4)(a) Prior to January 1, 2026, the department shall create a map of bridge structures in this state onto which an overweight raw-milk vehicle shall not enter.</para><para>(b) The department shall review the bridge map at least once each year and make any necessary updates to the bridge map.</para><para>(c) The department shall publish the most recent version of the bridge map on the public website provided by the department.</para><para>(5)(a) The department may revoke the overweight raw-milk vehicle permit for any overweight raw-milk vehicle that violates subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(b) Any such revocation shall not become effective until the holder of any such revoked permit has been provided written notice by the department of such revocation. Any such notice provided by United States mail is not effective until received by the holder of the revoked permit.</para><para>(c) Any such revocation may be appealed by the holder of the revoked permit. The appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para><para>(6) If the department determines that overweight raw-milk vehicle permits put this state at risk of losing federal aid funding, the department shall revoke all such permits.</para><para>(7) For any overweight raw-milk vehicle that enters a prohibited bridge structure and is the proximate cause of damage to the prohibited bridge structure, the owner of the overweight raw-milk vehicle shall be liable for all costs associated with repairing such damage. The department may bring an action to recover such costs associated with repairing such damage in the district court of the county where the prohibited bridge structure is located or in the district court of Lancaster County. Any money recovered in such action shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Roads Operations Cash Fund.</para><para>(8) The department may grant an exception to section 60-6,290 regarding the length of a vehicle if such length is reasonable and is needed for an overweight raw-milk vehicle to comply with all weight limits for single axles and groups of axles.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB561, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>May 16, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>