<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,135"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,135</statuteno><catchline>Undercover license plates; issuance;
confidential.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Undercover license plates may be issued
to federal, state,
county, city, or village law enforcement agencies and shall be used only for
legitimate criminal investigatory purposes. Undercover license plates may
also be issued to the Nebraska State Patrol, the Game and Parks Commission,
deputy state sheriffs employed by the Nebraska Brand Committee and State Fire
Marshal for state law enforcement purposes, persons employed by the Tax Commissioner
for state revenue enforcement purposes, the Department of Health and Human
Services for the purposes of communicable disease control, the prevention
and control of those communicable diseases which endanger the public health,
the enforcement of drug control laws, or other investigation purposes, the
Department of Agriculture for special investigative purposes, and the Insurance
Fraud Prevention Division of the Department of Insurance for investigative
purposes. Undercover license plates shall not be used on personally owned
vehicles or for personal use of government-owned vehicles.</para>
<para>(b) The director shall prescribe a form for agencies to apply for undercover
license plates. The form shall include a space for the name and signature
of the contact person for the requesting agency, a statement that the undercover
license plates are to be used only for legitimate criminal investigatory purposes,
and a statement that undercover license plates are not to be used on personally
owned vehicles or for personal use of government-owned vehicles.</para>
<para>(2) The agency shall include the name and signature of the contact person
for the agency on the form and pay the fee prescribed in section 60-3,102.
If the undercover license plates will be used for the investigation of a specific
event rather than for ongoing investigations, the agency shall designate on
the form an estimate of the length of time the undercover license plates will
be needed. The contact person in the agency shall sign the form and verify
the information contained in the form.</para>
<para>(3) Upon receipt of a completed form, the director shall determine whether
the undercover license plates will be used by an approved agency for a legitimate
purpose pursuant to subsection (1) of this section. If the director determines
that the undercover license plates will be used for such a purpose, he or
she may issue the undercover license plates in the form and under the conditions
he or she determines to be necessary. The decision of the director regarding
issuance of undercover license plates is final.</para>
<para>(4) The department shall keep records pertaining to undercover license
plates confidential, and such records shall not be subject to public disclosure.</para>
<para>(5) The contact person shall return the undercover license plates to
the department if:</para>
<para>(a) The undercover license plates expire and are not renewed;</para>
<para>(b) The purpose for which the undercover license plates were issued
has been completed or terminated; or</para>
<para>(c) The director requests their return.</para>
<para>(6) A state agency, board, or commission that uses motor vehicles from
the transportation services bureau of the Department of Administrative Services
shall notify the bureau immediately after undercover license plates have been
assigned to the motor vehicle and shall provide the equipment and license
plate number and the undercover license plate number to the bureau. The transportation
services bureau shall maintain a list of state-owned motor vehicles which
have been assigned undercover license plates. The list shall be confidential
and not be subject to public disclosure.</para>
<para>(7) The contact person shall be held accountable to keep proper records
of the number of undercover plates possessed by the agency, the particular
license plate numbers for each motor vehicle, and the person who is assigned
to the motor vehicle. This record shall be confidential and not be subject
to public disclosure.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 135; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 227; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB28, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>