<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002-->
<?APT Element gi="legaldoc"?>
<?APT Element gi="law" attrs="type"?>
<?APT Element gi="section"?>
<?APT Element gi="sectno"?>
<?APT Element gi="amendatorysection" attrs="amended chaptername statutenumber"?>
<?APT Element gi="bookinfo"?>
<?APT Element gi="statuteno"?>
<?APT Element gi="catchline"?>
<?APT Element gi="para"?>
<?APT Element gi="source"?>
<?APT Element gi="effectivedate"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection
amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,151"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,151</statuteno><catchline>Commercial
driver's license; restricted commercial driver's license; seasonal permit;
form.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The commercial driver's license shall be conspicuously
marked Nebraska Commercial Driver's License and shall be, to the maximum extent
practicable, tamper and forgery proof.</para><para>(b) This subdivision applies
until the implementation date designated by the director pursuant to section
60-462.02. The commercial driver's license shall include the following information:</para><para>(i)
The name and residential address of the holder;</para><para>(ii) The holder's
color photograph or digital image;</para><para>(iii) A physical description
of the holder, including sex, height, weight, and eye and hair colors;</para><para>(iv)
The holder's date of birth;</para><para>(v) The holder's signature;</para><para>(vi)
The class of commercial motor vehicle or vehicles which the holder is authorized
to operate, including any endorsements or restrictions;</para><para>(vii)
The dates between which the commercial driver's license is valid; and</para><para>(viii)
The organ and tissue donor information specified in section 60-494.</para><para>(c)
This subdivision applies beginning on the implementation date designated by
the director pursuant to section 60-462.02. The form of the commercial driver's
license shall also comply with section 60-4,117.</para><para>(2) The restricted
commercial driver's license shall be conspicuously marked Nebraska Restricted
Commercial Driver's License and shall be, to the maximum extent practicable,
tamper and forgery proof. The restricted commercial driver's license shall
contain such additional information as deemed necessary by the director.</para><para>(3)
The seasonal permit shall contain such information as deemed necessary by
the director but shall include the time period during which the commercial
motor vehicle operating privilege is effective. The seasonal permit shall
be valid only when held in conjunction with a restricted commercial driver's
license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1178, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 420, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 25.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
