<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,162"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,162</statuteno><catchline>Employment as driver; employer;
duties; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Each employer shall require
prospective applicants for employment as a driver of a commercial motor vehicle
to provide the information required by section 60-4,161.</para>
<para>(2) No employer may knowingly
allow, require, permit, or authorize a driver to operate a commercial motor
vehicle in the United States in any of the following circumstances:</para>
<para>(a) During any period
in which the driver does not have a current commercial learner's permit or
commercial driver's license or does not have a commercial learner's permit
or commercial driver's license with the proper class or endorsements. An employer
may not use a driver to operate a commercial motor vehicle who violates any
restriction on the driver's commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's
license;</para><para>(b)
During any period in which the driver has a commercial learner's permit or
commercial driver's license disqualified by a state, has lost the right to
operate a commercial motor vehicle in a state, or has been disqualified from
operating a commercial motor vehicle;</para><para>(c) During any period in which the driver has more
than one commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license;</para>
<para>(d) During any period
in which the driver, the commercial motor vehicle he or she is operating,
or the motor carrier operation is subject to an out-of-service order; or</para>
<para>(e) In violation of a
federal, state, or local law or regulation pertaining to railroad-highway
grade crossings.</para><para>(3) Any employer who violates
this section shall, upon conviction, be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 499, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 47.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>