<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id169">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id171" statutenumber="60-3,113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,113</statuteno><catchline id="id174">Handicapped
or disabled person; plates; department; compile and maintain registry.</catchline>
<para>(1) The department shall, without the payment of any fee
except the taxes and fees required by sections 60-3,102, 60-3,185, 60-3,190, and
60-3,191, issue license plates for one motor vehicle not used
for hire and a license plate for one motorcycle not used for hire to:</para>
<para>(a) Any permanently handicapped or disabled person or
his or her parent, legal guardian, foster parent, or agent upon application
and proof of a permanent handicap or disability; or</para>
<para>(b) A trust which owns the motor vehicle or motorcycle if
a designated beneficiary of the trust qualifies under subdivision (a) of this
subsection.</para>
<para>An application
and proof of disability in the form and with the information required by section
18-1738 or 60-3,113.02 shall
be submitted before license plates
are issued or reissued.</para><?Pub Caret?>
<para>(2) The license plate or plates shall carry the internationally
accepted wheelchair symbol, which symbol is a representation of a person seated
in a wheelchair surrounded by a border six units wide by seven units high,
and such other letters or numbers as the director prescribes. Such license
plate or plates shall be used by such person in lieu of the usual license
plate or plates.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall compile and maintain a registry
of the names, addresses, and license numbers of all persons who obtain special
license plates pursuant to this section and all persons who obtain a handicapped
or disabled parking permit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 113; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB289, &#167; 21.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
