<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id6" statutenumber="60-3,122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,122</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Pearl Harbor plates.</catchline><para>(1) Any person may, in addition to the application required by section 60-385, apply to the department for license plates designed by the department to indicate that he or she is a survivor of the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor if he or she:</para><para>(a) Was a member of the United States Armed Forces on December 7, 1941;</para><para>(b) Was on station on December 7, 1941, during the hours of 7:55 a.m. to 9:45 a.m. Hawaii time at Pearl Harbor, the island of Oahu, or offshore at a distance not to exceed three miles;</para><para>(c) Was discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable from the United States Armed Forces; and</para><para>(d) Holds a current membership in a Nebraska Chapter of the Pearl Harbor Survivors Association.</para><para>(2) The license plates shall be issued upon the applicant paying the regular license fee and furnishing proof satisfactory to the department that the applicant fulfills the requirements provided by subsection (1) of this section. Any number of motor vehicles, trailers, semitrailers, or cabin trailers owned by the applicant may be so licensed at any one time. Motor vehicles and trailers registered under section 60-3,198 shall not be so licensed.</para><para>(3) If the license plates issued pursuant to this section are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the recipient of the plates shall be issued replacement license plates upon request and without charge.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB110, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB705, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB642, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>