
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"  statutenumber="60-139"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-139</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of title; vehicle identification
number; required; when.</catchline><para>Except as provided in section 60-137,
60-138, 60-142, or
60-142.01, no person shall sell or otherwise dispose of a vehicle without
(1) delivering to the purchaser or transferee of such vehicle a certificate
of title with such assignments thereon as are necessary to show title in the
purchaser and (2) having affixed to the vehicle its vehicle identification
number if it is not already affixed. No person shall bring into this state
a vehicle for which a certificate of title is required in Nebraska, except
for temporary use, without complying with the Motor Vehicle Certificate of
Title Act.</para>
<para>No purchaser or transferee shall receive a certificate of title which
does not contain such assignments as are necessary to show title in the purchaser
or transferee. Possession of a certificate of title which does not comply
with this requirement shall be prima facie evidence of a violation of this
section, and such purchaser or transferee, upon conviction, shall be subject
to the penalty provided by section 60-180.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB241, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>There is no legal requirement that a lien be noted on a certificate of title purportedly covering property not subject to the Certificate of Title Act, even though a certificate of title for such property has been issued. Cushman Sales &amp; Service of Nebraska, Inc. v. Muirhead, 201 Neb. 495, 268 N.W.2d 440 (1978).</para><para>Policies of motor vehicle liability insurance were construed in the light of the provisions of this and two succeeding sections. Turpin v. Standard Reliance Ins. Co., 169 Neb. 233, 99 N.W.2d 26 (1959).</para><para>Upon sale of motor vehicle, seller must deliver to purchaser a certificate of title. State Farm Mutual Auto Ins. Co. v. Drawbaugh, 159 Neb. 149, 65 N.W.2d 542 (1954).</para><para>Licensed automobile dealer is required to have mortgage lien noted on certificate of title. Bank of Keystone v. Kayton, 155 Neb. 79, 50 N.W.2d 511 (1951).</para><para>Seller is required to deliver certificate of title to purchaser in order to pass title. Loyal's Auto Exchange, Inc. v. Munch, 153 Neb. 628, 45 N.W.2d 913 (1951).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
