<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id102" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-148"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-148</statuteno><catchline id="id105">Assignment of
distinguishing identification number; when.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever
a person applies for a certificate of title for a vehicle, the department
shall assign a distinguishing identification number to the vehicle if the
vehicle identification number is destroyed, obliterated, or missing. The owner
of such a vehicle to which such number is assigned shall have such number
affixed to such vehicle as provided in subsection (2) of this section and
sign an affidavit on a form prepared by the department that such number has
been attached. Before the certificate of title for an assigned number is released
to the applicant by the county treasurer, the
applicant shall also provide a statement that an inspection has been conducted.</para>
<para>(2) The department shall develop a metallic assigned vehicle identification
number plate which can be permanently secured to a vehicle by rivets or a
permanent sticker or other form of marking or identifying the vehicle with
the distinguishing identification number as determined by the director. All
distinguishing identification numbers shall contain seventeen characters in
conformance with national standards. When the manufacturer's vehicle identification
number is known, it shall be used by the department as the assigned number.
In the case of an assembled all-terrain vehicle, utility-type vehicle, or
minibike or assembled vehicle, the department shall use a distinguishing identification
number. The department shall, upon application by an owner, provide the owner
with a number plate or a permanent sticker or other form of marking or identification
displaying a distinguishing identification number or the manufacturer's number.</para>
<para>(3) Any vehicle to which a distinguishing identification number is assigned
shall be titled under such distinguishing identification number when titling
of the vehicle is required under the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 32.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>