<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-4,138"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,138</statuteno><catchline>Commercial drivers' licenses and
restricted commercial drivers' licenses; classification.</catchline><para>(1)
Commercial drivers' licenses and restricted commercial drivers' licenses shall
be issued by the department
in compliance with 49 C.F.R. parts 383 and 391, shall be classified
as provided in subsection (2) of this section, and shall bear such endorsements
and restrictions as are provided in subsections (3) and (4) of this section.</para>
<para>(2) Commercial motor vehicle classifications for purposes of commercial
drivers' licenses shall be as follows:</para>
<para>(a) Class A Combination Vehicle &#8212; Any combination of motor vehicles
and towed vehicles with a gross vehicle weight rating of more than twenty-six
thousand pounds if the gross vehicle weight rating of the vehicles being towed
are in excess of ten thousand pounds;</para>
<para>(b) Class B Heavy Straight Vehicle &#8212; Any single commercial motor vehicle
with a gross vehicle weight rating of twenty-six thousand one pounds or more
or any such commercial motor vehicle towing a vehicle with a gross vehicle
weight rating not exceeding ten thousand pounds; and</para>
<para>(c) Class C Small Vehicle &#8212; Any single commercial motor vehicle with
a gross vehicle weight rating of less than twenty-six thousand one pounds
or any such commercial motor vehicle towing a vehicle with a gross vehicle
weight rating not exceeding ten thousand pounds comprising:</para>
<para>(i) Motor vehicles designed to transport sixteen or more passengers,
including the driver; and</para>
<para>(ii) Motor vehicles used in the transportation of hazardous materials
and required to be placarded pursuant to section 75-364.</para>
<para>(3) The endorsements to a commercial driver's license shall be as follows:</para>
<para>(a) T &#8212; Double/triple trailers;</para>
<para>(b) P &#8212; Passenger;</para>
<para>(c) N &#8212; Tank vehicle;</para>
<para>(d) H &#8212; Hazardous materials;</para>
<para>(e) X &#8212; Combination tank vehicle and hazardous materials; and</para>
<para>(f) S &#8212; School bus.</para>
<para>(4) The restrictions to a commercial driver's license shall be as follows:</para>
<para>(a) I &#8212; Operation of a commercial motor vehicle only in intrastate commerce
due to an exemption from 49 C.F.R. part 391 pursuant to subsection (4) of
section 75-363;</para>
<para>(b) K &#8212; Operation of a commercial motor vehicle only in intrastate commerce;</para>
<para>(c) L &#8212; Operation of only a commercial motor vehicle which is not equipped
with air brakes;</para>
<para>(d) M &#8212; Operation of a commercial motor vehicle which is not a Class
A bus;</para>
<para>(e) N &#8212; Operation of a commercial motor vehicle which is not a Class
A or Class B bus;</para>
<para>(f) O &#8212; Operation of a commercial motor vehicle which is not a tractor-trailer
combination; and </para>
<para>(g) V &#8212; Operation of
a commercial motor vehicle for drivers with medical variance documentation.
The documentation shall be required to be carried on the driver's person while
operating a commercial motor vehicle.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 420, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 938, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 9.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
