<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-678"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>60-678</statuteno><catchline>Regulations; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The State of Nebraska or any department, board, commission, or governmental subdivision thereof is hereby authorized, in its respective jurisdiction, to enact regulations permitting, prohibiting, and controlling the use of motor vehicles, minibikes, motorcycles, off-road recreation vehicles of any and all types, electric bicycles, other powered vehicles, electric personal assistive mobility devices, and vehicles which are not self-propelled. Any person who operates any of such vehicles without the permission of the appropriate governmental entity or in a place, time, or manner which has been prohibited by such entity shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para><para>(2) Such governmental entity described in subsection (1) of this section may further authorize the supervising official of any area under its ownership or control to permit, control, or prohibit operation of any motor vehicle, minibike, motorcycle, off-road recreational vehicle of any or all types, electric bicycles, other powered vehicle, electric personal assistive mobility device, or vehicle which is not self-propelled on all or any portion of any area under its ownership or control at any time by posting or, in case of an emergency, by personal notice. Any person operating any such vehicle where prohibited, where not permitted, or in a manner so as to endanger the peace and safety of the public or as to harm or destroy the natural features or manmade features of any such area shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 644, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 102; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-2106; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 454; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB138, &#167; 44. </para><operativedate>September 2, 2023</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>