<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id5" statutenumber="60-4,108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,108</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Operating motor
vehicle during period of suspension, revocation, or impoundment; penalties;
juvenile; violation; handled in juvenile court.</catchline><para>(1)
It shall be unlawful for any person to operate a motor vehicle during any
period that he or she is subject to a court order not to operate any motor
vehicle for any purpose or during any period that his or her operator's license
has been revoked or impounded pursuant to conviction or convictions for violation
of any law or laws of this state, by an order of any court, or by an administrative
order of the director. Except as otherwise provided by subsection (3) of this
section or by other law, any person so offending shall (a) for a first such
offense, be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part
of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to operate any motor
vehicle for any purpose for a period of one year from the date ordered by
the court and also order the operator's license of such person to be revoked
for a like period, (b) for a second or third such offense, be guilty of
a Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part of the judgment of
conviction, order such person not to operate any motor vehicle for any purpose
for a period of two years from the date ordered by the court and also order
the operator's license of such person to be revoked for a like period, and (c) for a fourth or subsequent such
offense, be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part
of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to operate any motor
vehicle for any purpose for a period of two years from the date ordered by
the court and also order the operator's license of such person to be revoked
for a like period. Such orders of the court shall be administered
upon sentencing, upon final judgment of any appeal or review, or upon the
date that any probation is revoked, whichever is later.</para>
<para>(2) It shall be unlawful for any person to operate a motor
vehicle (a) during any period that his or her operator's license has been
suspended, (b) after a period of revocation but before issuance of a new license,
or (c) after a period of impoundment but before the return of the license.
Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, any person so offending
shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor, and the court may, as a part of
the judgment of conviction, order such person not to operate any motor vehicle
for any purpose for a period of one year from the date ordered by the court,
except that if the person at the time of sentencing shows proof of reinstatement
of his or her suspended operator's license, proof of issuance of a new license,
or proof of return of the impounded license, the person shall only be fined
in an amount not to exceed one hundred dollars. If the court orders the person
not to operate a motor vehicle for a period of one year from the date ordered
by the court, the court shall also order the operator's license of such person
to be revoked for a like period. Such orders of the court shall be administered
upon sentencing, upon final judgment of any appeal or review, or upon the
date that any probation is revoked, whichever is later.</para>
<para>(3) If a juvenile whose operator's license or permit has been
impounded by a juvenile court operates a motor vehicle during any period that
he or she is subject to the court order not to operate any motor vehicle or
after a period of impoundment but before return of the license or permit,
such violation shall be handled in the juvenile court and not as a violation
of this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 275, &#167; 2, p. 1002; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 293, &#167; 3, p. 1099; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 149, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 356, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 153, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-430.01; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 772, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1155, &#167; 13.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The language "from the date ordered by the court" means "from the date selected by the court." State v. Fuller, 278 Neb. 585, 772 N.W.2d 868 (2009).</para><para>The penalty of 1 or 2 years' suspension found in this section does not constitute cruel and unusual punishment. State v. Green, 236 Neb. 33, 458 N.W.2d 472 (1990).</para><para>Sentence which ordered suspension of driver's license for one year following release from jail upon conviction of second offense driving while under suspension does not conform to sentencing requirements of this statute. State v. Moore, 215 Neb. 229, 337 N.W.2d 782 (1983).</para><para>Not abuse of discretion for court to deny probation and impose mandatory sentence under the statute following conviction. State v. Adams, 198 Neb. 729, 255 N.W.2d 280 (1977).</para><para>This section provides only penalty for driving motor vehicle while driver's license is suspended. Stuckey v. Rohnert, 179 Neb. 727, 140 N.W.2d 9 (1966).</para><para>Penalty for violation of this section is increased upon conviction of second offense. State v. Steemer, 175 Neb. 342, 121 N.W.2d 813 (1963).</para><para>The provisions of this section providing an increased penalty for second offense is not ex post facto as to a first offense committed prior to the enactment thereof. State v. Steemer, 175 Neb. 342, 121 N.W.2d 813 (1963).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>