<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,297"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,297</statuteno><catchline>Disabled vehicles; length, load, width, height limitations; exception; special single trip permit; liability.</catchline><para>(1) Subdivision (1)(b) of section 60-6,290 and subsections (2) and (3) of section 60-6,294 shall not apply to a vehicle or combination of vehicles disabled or wrecked on a highway or right-of-way when the vehicle or combination of vehicles is towed to a place of secure safekeeping by any wrecker or tow truck performing a wrecker or towing service.</para><para>(2) Subdivision (1)(b) of section 60-6,290 and subsections (2) and (3) of section 60-6,294 shall not apply to a single vehicle that is disabled or wrecked when the single vehicle is towed by any wrecker or tow truck to a place for repair or to a point of storage or is being transported by a covered heavy-duty tow and recovery vehicle.</para><para>(3)(a) Section 60-6,288, subsection (1) of section 60-6,289, subdivision (1)(b) of section 60-6,290, and subsections (2) and (3) of section 60-6,294 shall not apply to a vehicle or combination of vehicles permitted by the Department of Transportation for overwidth, overheight, overlength, or overweight operation that is disabled or wrecked on a highway or right-of-way when the vehicle or combination of vehicles is towed if the vehicle or combination of vehicles is towed by any wrecker or tow truck performing a wrecker or towing service to the first or nearest place of secure safekeeping off the traveled portion of the highway that can accommodate the parking of such disabled vehicle or combination of vehicles.</para><para>(b) After the vehicle or combination of vehicles has been towed to a place of secure safekeeping, such vehicle or combination of vehicles shall then be operated in compliance with section 60-6,288, subsection (1) of section 60-6,289, subdivision (1)(b) of section 60-6,290, and subsections (2) and (3) of section 60-6,294, or the vehicle or combination of vehicles shall acquire a special single trip permit from the department for the movement of the overwidth, overheight, overlength, or overweight vehicle or combination of vehicles beyond the first or nearest place of secure safekeeping to its intended destination.</para><para>(4) The owners, lessees, and operators of any wrecker or tow truck exceeding the width, height, length, or weight restrictions while towing a disabled or wrecked vehicle or combination of vehicles shall be jointly and severally liable for any injury or damages that result from the operation of the wrecker or tow truck while exceeding such restrictions.</para><para>(5) If a disabled or wrecked vehicle or combination of vehicles is towed, the wrecker or tow truck shall be connected with the air brakes and brake lights of the towed vehicle or combination of vehicles.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Covered heavy-duty tow and recovery vehicle means a vehicle that (i) is transporting a disabled vehicle on the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways from the place where the vehicle became disabled to the nearest appropriate repair facility, including such segments of highways off the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways that connect the nearest appropriate repair facility to the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways and adjoining portions of the state highway system for reasonable access to terminals and facilities for food, fuel, repairs, and rest, as designated by the Department of Transportation, and (ii) has a gross vehicle weight that is equal to or exceeds the gross vehicle weight of the disabled vehicle being transported;</para><para>(b) Place of secure safekeeping means a location off the traveled portion of the highway that can accommodate the parking of the disabled or wrecked vehicle or combination of vehicles in order for the vehicle or combination of vehicles to be repaired or moved to a point of storage; and</para><para>(c) Wrecker or tow truck means an emergency commercial vehicle equipped, designed, and used to assist or render aid and transport or tow a disabled vehicle or combination of vehicles from a highway or right-of-way to a place of secure safekeeping.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 383, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,180.02; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 393; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 137, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 82, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB35, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 223; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 71. </para><operativedate>November 14, 2020</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>