<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id600"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,191"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,191</statuteno><catchline>Maximum lawful speed; temporary reduction; reasons; display sign; minimum speed, effect; Department of Transportation; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Transportation may temporarily reduce the maximum lawful speed for vehicles on any highway for any of the following reasons:</para><para>(a) Any weather or environmental condition that reduces the visibility of vehicle operators to approximately one-fourth of one mile or less, including, but not limited to, fog, precipitation, smoke, or dust;</para><para>(b) Any condition that could result in reduced vehicle traction to the highway, including rain, water, ice, snow, oil, road surface conditions, or any object on the highway;</para><para>(c) Any emergency situation; or</para><para>(d) Any traffic congestion, reduced traffic mobility, or reduced traffic flow.</para><para>(2) Any reduction of the maximum lawful speed for vehicles on a highway under subsection (1) of this section is only effective if the Department of Transportation prominently displays an electronic or digital sign with the reduced maximum lawful speed for vehicles on such highway.</para><para>(3) When the normal maximum lawful speed limit for a highway has been reduced under this section, the normal maximum lawful speed limit for such highway shall not apply until another electronic, digital, nonelectronic, or nondigital sign indicates a return to the normal maximum lawful speed limit for such highway.</para><para>(4) Any temporarily reduced maximum lawful speed limit under this section shall be changed in increments of five miles per hour.</para><para>(5) When the maximum lawful speed limit is temporarily reduced under this section, there shall be no minimum speed limit for the corresponding area of the temporarily reduced maximum lawful speed limit.</para><para>(6) The Department of Transportation shall:</para><para>(a) Develop and implement a policy for determining:</para><para>(i) When to temporarily reduce maximum lawful speed limits;</para><para>(ii) What such speed limits should be; and</para><para>(iii) The increments, which may exceed the increments specified in section 60-6,190, to be used in reducing and reestablishing the regular maximum lawful speed limit;</para><para>(b) Keep appropriate records that include when any maximum lawful speed limit under this section has been changed, what such maximum lawful speed limit was set at, and the reason for the change; and</para><para>(c) Keep appropriate records that include the maximum lawful speed limit for each highway.</para><para>(7) The Department of Transportation may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB530, &#167; 28. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>