
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id890"><amendatorysection statutenumber="60-4,148.01" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,148.01</statuteno><catchline>Commercial drivers' licenses; CLP-commercial learners' permits; electronic renewal and replacement; department; duties; applicant; requirements; renewal; fee and surcharge; delivery.</catchline><para>(1) The department may develop and offer methods for successful applicants to obtain commercial drivers' licenses electronically and for the electronic renewal and replacement of commercial drivers' licenses and CLP-commercial learners' permits.</para><para>(2)(a) An applicant who has successfully passed the knowledge and skills tests for a commercial driver's license pursuant to section 60-4,149 and who has a digital image and digital signature preserved in the digital system that is not more than ten years old may obtain a commercial driver's license using the preserved digital image and digital signature by electronic means in a manner prescribed by the department pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(b) To be eligible to obtain a license pursuant to this subsection:</para><para>(i) There must have been no changes to the applicant's name since his or her most recent application for a CLP-commercial learner's permit;</para><para>(ii) The new license must not contain a hazardous materials endorsement;</para><para>(iii) The applicant must meet the requirements of section 60-4,144 and submit the information and documentation and make the certifications required under section 60-4,144; and</para><para>(iv) The applicant must satisfy any other eligibility criteria that the department may prescribe pursuant to subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(c) The successful applicant shall pay the fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115. Upon receipt of such fee and surcharge and an application it deems satisfactory, the department shall deliver the license by mail.</para><para>(3)(a) An applicant whose commercial driver’s license or CLP-commercial learner's permit expires prior to his or her seventy-second birthday and who has a digital image and digital signature preserved in the digital system may, once every ten years, renew such license or permit using the preserved digital image and digital signature by electronic means in a manner prescribed by the department pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(b) To be eligible for renewal under this subsection:</para><para>(i) The renewal must be prior to or within one year after expiration of such license or permit;</para><para>(ii) The driving record abstract maintained in the department's computerized records must show that such license or permit is not suspended, revoked, canceled, or disqualified;</para><para>(iii) There must be no changes to the applicant’s name or to the class, endorsements, or restrictions on such license or permit;</para><para>(iv) The applicant must not hold a hazardous materials endorsement or must relinquish such endorsement;</para><para>(v) The applicant must meet the requirements of section 60-4,144 and submit the information and documentation and make the certifications required under section 60-4,144; and</para><para>(vi) The applicant must satisfy any other eligibility criteria that the department may prescribe pursuant to subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(c) Every applicant seeking renewal of his or her commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit must apply for renewal in person at least once every ten years and have a new digital image and digital signature captured.</para><para>(d) An applicant seeking renewal under this subsection (3) shall pay the fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115. Upon receipt of such fee and surcharge and an application it deems satisfactory, the department shall deliver the renewal license or permit by mail.</para><para>(4)(a) Any person holding a commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit who has a digital image and digital signature not more than ten years old preserved in the digital system and who loses his or her license or permit, who requires issuance of a replacement license or permit because of a change of address, or whose license or permit is mutilated or unreadable may obtain a replacement commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit using the preserved digital image and digital signature by electronic means in a manner prescribed by the department pursuant to this subsection.</para><para>(b) To be eligible to obtain a replacement license or permit pursuant to this subsection:</para><para>(i) There must be no changes to the applicant’s name and no changes to the class, endorsements, or restrictions on such license or permit;</para><para>(ii) The applicant must meet the requirements of section 60-4,144 and submit the information and documentation and make the certifications required under section 60-4,144; and</para><para>(iii) The applicant must satisfy any other eligibility criteria that the department may prescribe pursuant to subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(c) An application for a replacement license or permit because of a change of address shall be made within sixty days after the change of address.</para><para>(d) An applicant seeking replacement under this subsection (4) shall pay the fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115. Upon receipt of such fee and surcharge and an application it deems satisfactory, the department shall deliver the replacement license or permit by mail. The replacement license or permit shall be subject to the provisions of subsection (4) of section 60-4,150.</para><para>(5) An application to obtain a commercial driver's license or to renew or replace a commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit because of a change of name may not be made electronically pursuant to this section and shall be made in person at a licensing station within sixty days after the change of name.</para><para>(6) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing eligibility for the use of electronic methods for successful applicants to obtain commercial drivers' licenses and for the renewal and replacement of commercial drivers' licenses and CLP-commercial learners' permits, taking into consideration medical and vision requirements, safety concerns, and any other factors consistent with the purposes of the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act that the director deems relevant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB977, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>