<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,237"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,237</statuteno><catchline>Vehicles required to have clearance lights; flares; reflectors; how and when displayed.</catchline><para>The operator of any vehicle required by section 60-6,235 to have clearance lights shall, immediately upon bringing his or her vehicle to a stop upon or immediately adjacent to the traveled portion of the highway at any time during the period from sunset to sunrise, (1) place one lighted flare or one red emergency reflector at the side of such vehicle just inside the white line marking the center of paved highways and near the center of dirt or gravel highways, (2) place one lighted flare or one red emergency reflector approximately one hundred feet to the rear of such vehicle, and (3) place one lighted flare or one red emergency reflector approximately one hundred feet to the front of such vehicle. The operator shall maintain such lighted flares or red emergency reflectors in such positions during the time such vehicle remains parked, except that motor vehicles transporting flammables shall be required to use two flares or two red emergency reflectors to be placed as described in this section to the front and rear but shall not be permitted to place open flame flares adjacent to such vehicles.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 129, &#167; 1, p. 460; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-11,112; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,118; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 121, &#167; 1(2), p. 319; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 366, &#167; 23, p. 1259; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 189, &#167; 4, p. 581; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 193, &#167; 2, p. 592; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 181, &#167; 5, p. 538; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,118.01; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 224, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,163; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 333; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 34. </para></source><annotation><para>The term immediately, as used in this section, means with reasonable and prompt diligence, under all of the facts and circumstances shown. Gleason v. Baack, 137 Neb. 272, 289 N.W. 349 (1939).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 