<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id301" statutenumber="60-493"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-493</statuteno><catchline id="id304">Organ and tissue donation; county treasurer or licensing staff; distribute brochure; additional information; department; duty.</catchline><para>(1) When a person applies for an operator's license or state identification card, the county treasurer or licensing staff of the Department of Motor Vehicles shall distribute a brochure provided by an organ and tissue procurement organization and approved by the Department of Health and Human Services containing a description and explanation of the Revised Uniform Anatomical Gift Act to each person applying for a new or renewal license or card.</para><para>(2) If an individual desires to receive additional specific information regarding organ and tissue donation and the Donor Registry of Nebraska as indicated on an application and retained by the department under section 60-484, 60-4,144, or 60-4,181, the department shall notify a representative of the federally designated organ procurement organization for Nebraska within five working days of the name and address of such individual.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 115, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-406.01; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1178, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 280; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 559, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 229; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1036, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Revised Uniform Anatomical Gift Act,</emphasis> see section 71-4824.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>