<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,228"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,228</statuteno><catchline>Metropolitan utilities district license plates; public power district license plates; application; issuance.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This subsection applies until January 1, 2023.</para><para>(b) Upon application and payment of the fees required pursuant to this section and section 60-3,229, each motor vehicle and trailer operated by a public power district shall be issued permanent public power district license plates. The public power district license plates shall be issued by the county in which the public power district is headquartered.</para><para>(c) Public power district vehicles shall display a distinctive license plate provided by the department pursuant to this section.</para><para>(d) Any license plate issued pursuant to this section shall remain affixed to the front and rear of the motor vehicle and to the rear of the trailer as long as the public power district vehicle is registered pursuant to this section by the owner or lessor making the original application pursuant to subdivision (1)(b) of this section.</para><para>(2)(a) This subsection applies beginning on January 1, 2023.</para><para>(b) Upon application and payment of the fees required pursuant to this section and section 60-3,229, each motor vehicle and trailer operated by a metropolitan utilities district or a public power district shall be issued permanent metropolitan utilities district or public power district license plates. The metropolitan utilities district or public power district license plates shall be issued by the county in which the metropolitan utilities district or public power district is headquartered.</para><para>(c) Metropolitan utilities district vehicles or public power district vehicles shall display a distinctive license plate provided by the department pursuant to this section.</para><para>(d) Any license plate issued pursuant to this section shall remain affixed to the front and rear of the motor vehicle and to the rear of the trailer as long as the metropolitan utilities district vehicle or public power district vehicle is registered pursuant to this section by the owner or lessor making the original application pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB783, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 71. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>