<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,180"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,180</statuteno><catchline>Nonresident vehicles; reciprocal agreements authorized; terms and conditions; revision; absence of agreement; effect.</catchline><para>(1) In order to effect the purposes of sections 60-3,178, 60-3,179, and 60-3,198, the director shall have the power, duty, and authority to enter into reciprocal agreements with the duly authorized representatives of other jurisdictions, including states, districts, territories, or possessions of the United States and foreign countries, states, or provinces, granting to trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, or buses or owners of trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, or buses which are properly registered or licensed in such jurisdictions, and for which evidence of compliance is supplied, benefits, privileges, and exemptions from the payment, wholly or partially, of any fees or other charges imposed upon such trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, or buses or owners with respect to the operation or ownership of such trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, or buses under the laws of this state. Such agreements or arrangements shall provide that trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, or buses registered or licensed in this state when operated upon the highways of such other jurisdictions shall receive exemptions, benefits, and privileges of a similar kind or to a similar degree as are extended to trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, or buses from such jurisdictions in this state. Such agreements may be revised or replaced by new agreements from time to time in order to promote greater uniformity among the jurisdictions. The director may withdraw from any agreement when he or she determines that it is for the best interest of the State of Nebraska upon thirty days' notice.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding any provisions of the Nebraska statutes to the contrary or inconsistent herewith, such agreements may provide, with respect to resident or nonresident fleets of apportionable vehicles which are engaged in interjurisdiction and intrajurisdiction commerce, that the registrations of such fleets can be apportioned between this state and other jurisdictions in which such fleets operate in accordance with the method set out in section 60-3,198. A Nebraska-based fleet owner may include trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses in such apportionable fleet by listing them in an application filed pursuant to section 60-3,198, and any trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses so included shall be eligible for permanent license plates issued pursuant to section 60-3,203. The registration procedure required by section 60-3,198 shall be the only such registration required, and when the fees required by such section and section 60-3,203 if applicable have been paid, the trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses listed on the application shall be duly registered as part of such Nebraska-based fleet and shall be considered part of a Nebraska-based fleet for purposes of taxation.</para><para>(3) In the absence of an agreement or arrangement with any jurisdiction, the director is authorized to examine the laws and requirements of such jurisdiction and to declare the extent and nature of exemptions, benefits, and privileges to be extended to trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses registered in such jurisdiction or to the owners or operators of such trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses.</para><para>When no written agreement or arrangement has been entered into with another jurisdiction or declaration issued pertaining thereto, any trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses properly registered in such jurisdiction, and for which evidence of compliance is supplied, may be operated in this state and shall receive the same exemptions, benefits, and privileges granted by such other jurisdiction to trucks, truck-tractors, trailers, and buses registered in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 180. </para></source><annotation><para>Where truck-tractor was licensed in Michigan with whom Nebraska maintained reciprocity, no license fees were required even though trailer was licensed in Iowa. Ashton v. State, 173 Neb. 78, 112 N.W.2d 540 (1961).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>