<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-387"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-387</statuteno><catchline>Proof of financial responsibility required.</catchline><para>An application for registration of a motor vehicle shall be accompanied by proof of financial responsibility or evidence of insurance covering the motor vehicle. Proof of financial responsibility shall be evidenced by a copy of proof of financial responsibility filed pursuant to subdivision (2), (3), or (4) of section 60-528 bearing the seal of the department. Evidence of insurance shall give the effective dates of the automobile liability policy, which dates shall be evidence that the coverage is in effect on and following the date of registration, and shall designate, by explicit description or by appropriate reference, all motor vehicles covered. Evidence of insurance in the form of a certificate of insurance for fleet vehicles may include, as an appropriate reference, a designation that the insurance coverage is applicable to all vehicles owned by the named insured, or wording of similar effect, in lieu of an explicit description. Proof of financial responsibility also may be evidenced by (1) a check by the department or its agents of the motor vehicle insurance database created under section 60-3,136 or (2) any other automated or electronic means as prescribed or developed by the department. For purposes of this section, fleet means a group of at least five vehicles that belong to the same owner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 34.</para></source><annotation><para>Recent legislative enactments to make automobile liability insurance compulsory could not be read retroactively in violation of vested rights under the policy, where the enactments were not in force when the policy was issued or when the loss occurred. Glockel v. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co., 224 Neb. 598, 400 N.W.2d 250 (1987).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>