<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id109">
<sectno id="id110" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 13.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id111" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-149"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id113">60-149</statuteno><catchline id="id114">Application;
documentation required.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If a certificate
of title has previously been issued for a vehicle in this state, the application
for a new certificate of title shall be accompanied by the certificate of
title duly assigned except as otherwise provided in the Motor Vehicle Certificate
of Title Act.</para>
<para>(b) Except for manufactured homes or mobile
homes as provided in subsection (2) of this section, if a certificate
of title has not previously been issued for the vehicle in this state or if
a certificate of title is unavailable pursuant to subsection (4) of section
52-1801, the application shall be accompanied by:</para>
<para>(i) A manufacturer's or importer's certificate except as otherwise provided in subdivision
(vii) of this subdivision; </para>
<para>(ii) A duly certified copy of the manufacturer's or importer's certificate;</para>
<para>(iii) An affidavit by the owner affirming ownership in the
case of an all-terrain vehicle,
a utility-type vehicle, or a minibike;</para>
<para>(iv) A certificate of title from another state;</para>
<para>(v) A court order issued by a court of record, a manufacturer's
certificate of origin, or an assigned registration certificate, if the law
of the state from which the vehicle was brought into this state does not have
a certificate of title law;</para>
<para>(vi) Documentation prescribed in section 60-142.01, 60-142.02,
60-142.04, or 60-142.05; or</para>
<para>(vii) A manufacturer's
or importer's certificate and an affidavit by the owner affirming ownership
in the case of a minitruck.</para><para>(c) If the
application for a certificate of title in this state is accompanied by a valid
certificate of title issued by another state which meets that state's requirements
for transfer of ownership, then the application may be accepted by this state.</para>
<para>(d) If a certificate of title has not previously been issued
for the vehicle in this state and the applicant is unable to provide such
documentation, the applicant may apply for a bonded certificate of title as
prescribed in section 60-167.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If the application
for a certificate of title for a manufactured home or a mobile home is being
made in accordance with subdivision (4)(b) of section 60-137 or if the certificate
of title for a manufactured home or a mobile home is unavailable pursuant
to section 52-1801, the application shall be accompanied by proof of ownership
in the form of:</para><para>(i)
A duly assigned manufacturer's or importer's certificate;</para>
<para>(ii) A certificate of
title from another state;</para><para>(iii)
A court order issued by a court of record;</para><para>(iv) Evidence of ownership as provided for in section
30-24,125, 52-601.01 to 52-605, 60-1901 to 60-1911, or 60-2401 to 60-2411;
or</para><para>(v)
Assessment records for the manufactured home or mobile home from the county
assessor and an affidavit by the owner affirming ownership.</para>
<para>(b) If the applicant
cannot produce proof of ownership described in subdivision (a) of this subsection,
he or she may submit to the department such evidence as he or she may have,
and the department may thereupon, if it finds the evidence sufficient, issue
the certificate of title or authorize the county clerk or designated county
official to issue a certificate of title, as the case may be.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section,
certificate of title includes a salvage certificate, a salvage branded certificate
of title, or any other document of ownership issued by another state or jurisdiction
for a salvage vehicle. Only a salvage branded certificate of title shall be
issued to any vehicle conveyed upon a salvage certificate, a salvage branded
certificate of title, or any other document of ownership issued by another
state or jurisdiction for a salvage vehicle.</para>
<para>(4) The county clerk or designated
county official shall retain the evidence of title presented by the applicant
and on which the certificate of title is issued.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB933, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Certificate of title, based upon a duplicate issued in another state, is not protected. Allstate Ins. Co. v. Enzolera, 164 Neb. 38, 81 N.W.2d 588 (1957).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>