<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,120</statuteno><catchline>Operator's license; state identification card; duplicate or replacement.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section for persons temporarily out of the state, any person duly licensed or holding a valid state identification card issued under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act who loses his or her operator's license or card may obtain a duplicate upon filing with the county treasurer or the Department of Motor Vehicles an application showing such loss and furnishing proof of identification in accordance with section 60-484. If satisfied that the loss is genuine, the issuer shall cause to be issued, upon the payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115, a duplicate license or card. No more than two duplicates of a license or card may be issued in this manner. Upon the issuance of any duplicate or replacement license or card, the license or card from which the duplicate or replacement is issued shall be void.</para><para>(2) If any person changes his or her name because of marriage or divorce or by court order or a common-law name change, he or she shall apply to the county treasurer for a replacement operator's license or state identification card and furnish proof of identification in accordance with section 60-484. If any person changes his or her address, the person shall apply to the county treasurer for a replacement operator's license or state identification card and furnish satisfactory evidence of such change. The application shall be made within sixty days after the change of name or address. The license or card shall be issued upon payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115.</para><para>(3) In the event a mutilated and unreadable operator's license is held by any person duly licensed under the act or a mutilated and unreadable state identification card which was issued under the act is held by a person, such person may obtain a replacement license or card upon showing the original mutilated or unreadable license or card to the county treasurer. A replacement license or card may be issued, without a photograph, to any person who is out of the state at the time of application for the replacement license or card. Such license or card shall state on its face that it shall become invalid thirty days after such person resumes residence in the state. If the county treasurer is satisfied that the license or card is mutilated or unreadable, the county treasurer shall cause to be issued, upon the payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115, a replacement license or card.</para><para>(4) If any person duly licensed under the act loses his or her operator's license or if any holder of a state identification card loses his or her card while temporarily out of the state, he or she may apply for a duplicate operator's license or card without a photograph by filing with the county treasurer an application and affidavit showing such loss. Upon the officer being satisfied that the loss is genuine, the officer shall cause to be issued, upon the payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115, a duplicate operator's license or card without a photograph. Upon the issuance of the duplicate, the original license or card shall be void.</para><para>(5) Any person holding a valid operator's license or state identification card without a photograph shall surrender such license or card to the treasurer of his or her county of residence within thirty days after resuming residency in this state. After the thirty-day period, such license or card shall be considered invalid. Upon the timely surrender of the license or card and payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115, such person shall be issued an operator's license or card with a color photograph or digital image of the licensee included.</para><para>(6) An application form for a replacement or duplicate operator's license or state identification card shall include a voter registration portion pursuant to section 32-308 and the following specific question: Do you wish to register to vote as part of this application process?</para><para>(7) An applicant may obtain a replacement or duplicate operator's license or state identification card pursuant to subsection (1), (3), or (4) of this section by electronic means in a manner prescribed by the department. If the applicant has a digital image and digital signature preserved in the digital system, the replacement or duplicate shall be issued with the preserved digital image and digital signature.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 148, &#167; 9, p. 517; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-409; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 19, p. 517; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 176, &#167; 2, p. 689; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-409; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-415; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 141, &#167; 8, p. 453; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 207, &#167; 4, p. 678; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 315, &#167; 10, p. 1005; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 316, &#167; 10, p. 1015; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 234, &#167; 7, p. 626; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 506, &#167; 2, p. 2083; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 134, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 371, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1296, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 90, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 606, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 46, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 811, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 575, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 284, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-415; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 126, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 201, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 572; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 1, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>