<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id58" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="60-3,104.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,104.01</statuteno><catchline>Specialty license plates; application;
fee; delivery; transfer; credit allowed; fee.</catchline><para>(1) A person may apply for specialty
license plates in lieu of regular license plates on an application prescribed
and provided by the department pursuant to section 60-3,104.02 for any motor
vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin trailer, except for motor vehicles
or trailers registered under section 60-3,198. An applicant receiving a specialty
license plate for a farm truck with a gross weight of over sixteen tons or
for a commercial motor vehicle registered for a gross weight of five tons
or over shall affix the appropriate tonnage decal to the plate. The department
shall make forms available for such applications. Each application for initial
issuance or renewal of specialty license plates shall be accompanied by a
fee of seventy dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall be
remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit fifteen
percent of the fee for initial issuance and renewal of specialty license plates
to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and eighty-five percent of the
fee to the Highway Trust Fund.</para>
<para>(2) When the department receives an application for specialty license
plates, it shall deliver the plates to the county treasurer of the county
in which the motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin trailer is registered.
The county treasurer shall issue specialty license plates in lieu of
regular license plates when the applicant complies with the other provisions
of law for registration of the motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin
trailer. If specialty license plates are lost, stolen, or mutilated, the licensee
shall be issued replacement license plates pursuant to section 60-3,157.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The owner of a motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin
trailer bearing specialty license plates may make application to the county
treasurer to have such specialty license plates transferred to
a motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin trailer other than the motor
vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin trailer for which such plates were
originally purchased if such motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin
trailer is owned by the owner of the specialty license plates.</para>
<para>(b) The owner may have the unused portion of the specialty license plate
fee credited to the other motor vehicle, trailer, semitrailer, or cabin trailer
which will bear the specialty license plates at the rate of eight and one-third
percent per month for each full month left in the registration period.</para>
<para>(c) Application for such transfer shall be accompanied by a fee of three
dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the
State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB110, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 65.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>