<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002-->
<?APT Element gi="legaldoc"?>
<?APT Element gi="law" attrs="type"?>
<?APT Element gi="section" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="sectno" attrs="id opdate"?>
<?APT Element gi="amendatorysection" attrs="amended chaptername id statutenumber"?>
<?APT Element gi="bookinfo"?>
<?APT Element gi="statuteno" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="catchline" attrs="id"?>
<?APT Element gi="para"?>
<?APT Element gi="source"?>
<?APT Element gi="operativedate"?>
<?APT Element gi="annotation"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id16"><sectno id="id17" opdate=" March 20, 2008">Sec.
2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id18"
statutenumber="60-141"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno
id="id20">60-141</statuteno><catchline id="id21">Dealer; inventory; certificates
required; when.</catchline><para>A dealer need not apply for certificates
of title for any vehicles in stock or acquired for stock purposes, but upon
transfer of such vehicle in stock or acquired for stock purposes, the dealer
shall give the transferee a reassignment of the certificate of title on such
vehicle or an assignment of a manufacturer's or importer's certificate. If
all reassignments on the manufacturer's or importer's certificate have been
used, the dealer may attach a dealer assignment form prescribed by the department
prior to any subsequent transfer. If all reassignments on the dealer assignment
form or the certificate of title have been used, the dealer shall obtain title
in the dealer's name prior to any subsequent transfer. No dealer shall execute
a reassignment on or transfer ownership by way of a manufacturer's statement
of origin unless the dealer is franchised by the manufacturer of the vehicle.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>Purchasers,
other than dealers, must acquire certificate of title. State Farm Mutual Auto
Ins. Co. v. Drawbaugh, 159 Neb. 149, 65 N.W.2d 542 (1954).</para><para>Concluding
proviso does not exempt dealer from having mortgage lien noted on certificate
of title. Bank of Keystone v. Kayton, 155 Neb. 79, 50 N.W.2d 511 (1951).</para><para>A
motor vehicle mortgage lien, not shown on certificate of title, is not valid
against subsequent holder of mortgage lien shown on the certificate. Securities
Credit Corp. v. Pindell, 153 Neb. 298, 44 N.W.2d 501 (1950).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
