<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-168"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-168</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of title; loss or mutilation;
duplicate certificate; subsequent purchaser, rights; recovery of original;
duty of owner.</catchline><para>(1) In the event of a lost or mutilated certificate
of title, the owner of the vehicle or the holder of a lien on the vehicle
shall apply, upon a form prescribed by the department, to the department or to any county treasurer for a duplicate
certificate of title and shall pay the fee prescribed by section 60-156. The
application shall be signed and sworn to by the person making the application
or a person authorized to sign under section 60-151. Thereupon the county treasurer, with the approval
of the department, or the department shall issue a duplicate certificate of
title to the person entitled to receive the certificate of title. If the records
of the title have been destroyed pursuant to section 60-152, the county treasurer shall issue a duplicate
certificate of title to the person entitled to receive the same upon such
showing as the county treasurer may
deem sufficient. If the applicant cannot produce such proof of ownership,
he or she may apply directly to the department and submit such evidence as
he or she may have, and the department may, if it finds the evidence sufficient,
authorize the county treasurer to
issue a duplicate certificate of title. A duplicate certificate of title so
issued shall show only those unreleased liens of record. The new purchaser
shall be entitled to receive an original certificate of title upon presentation
of the assigned duplicate copy of the certificate of title, properly assigned
to the new purchaser, to the county treasurer prescribed
in section 60-144.</para>
<para>(2) Any purchaser of a vehicle for which a certificate of title was
lost or mutilated may at the time of purchase require the seller of the same
to indemnify him or her and all subsequent purchasers of the vehicle against
any loss which he, she, or they may suffer by reason of any claim presented
upon the original certificate. In the event of the recovery of the original
certificate of title by the owner, he or she shall forthwith surrender the
same to the county treasurer or
the department for cancellation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 42.</para></source><annotation><para>Issuance of duplicate certificates is authorized, but purchaser is charged with notice of possible impairment of title. Allstate Ins. Co. v. Enzolera, 164 Neb. 38, 81 N.W.2d 588 (1957).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>