<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id33"><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id35" statutenumber="60-6,299"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,299</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Permit to move
building; limitations; application; Department of Roads; rules and regulations;
violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Roads
may issue permits for vehicles moving a building or objects requiring specialized
moving dollies. Such permits shall allow the vehicles transporting buildings
or objects requiring specialized dollies to operate on highways under the
jurisdiction of the department, excluding any portion of the National System
of Interstate and Defense Highways. Such permit shall specify the maximum
allowable width, length, height, and weight of the building to be transported,
the route to be used, and the hours during which such building or object may
be transported. Any vehicle moving a building or object requiring specialized
moving dollies shall be escorted by another vehicle or vehicles in the manner
determined by the department. Such vehicles shall travel at a speed which
is not in excess of five miles per hour when carrying loads which are in excess
of the maximum gross weight specified by law by more than twenty-five percent.
The permit shall not be issued for travel on a state highway containing a
bridge or structure which is structurally inadequate to carry such building
or object as determined by the department. The department may prescribe conditions
of operation of such vehicle when necessary to assure against damage to the
road foundations, surfaces, or structures and require such security as may
be deemed necessary to compensate for any injury to any roadway or road structure.</para>
<para>(2) The application for any such permit shall (a) specifically describe the vehicle, (b) specifically describe the
load to be moved, (c) include
a signed affirmation under oath that, for any load sixteen feet high or higher,
the applicant has contacted any and all electric utilities that have high
voltage conductors and infrastructure that cross over the roadway affected
by the move and made arrangements with such electric utilities for the safe
movement of the load under any high voltage conductors owned by such electric
utilities, and (d) whenever
possible, describe the
particular highways for which the permit is requested. The company or individual
shall maintain a copy of the permit in each vehicle moving a building or object
requiring specialized moving dollies which shall be open to inspection by
any peace officer, carrier enforcement officer, or authorized agent of any
authority granting such permit. The fee for such permit shall be ten dollars.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
governing the issuance of the permits. Such rules and regulations shall include,
but not be limited to, driver qualifications, equipment selection, hours of
operation, weather conditions, road conditions, determination of any damage
caused to highways or bridges, cutting or trimming of trees, removal or relocation
of signs or other property of the state, raising or lowering of electric supply
and communication lines, and such other safety considerations as the department
deems necessary.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who violates the terms of a permit issued pursuant
to this section or otherwise violates this section shall be guilty of a Class
III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 553, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,181.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 395; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB997, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>