<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id62" statutenumber="60-4,124"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,124</statuteno><catchline id="id65">School permit; LPE-learner's permit; issuance; operation restrictions; violations; penalty; not eligible for ignition interlock permit.</catchline><para>(1) A person who is younger than sixteen years and three months of age but is older than fourteen years and two months of age may be issued a school permit if such person either resides outside a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class or attends a school which is outside a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class and if such person has held an LPE-learner's permit for two months. A school permit shall not be issued until such person has demonstrated that he or she is capable of successfully operating a motor vehicle, moped, or motorcycle and has in his or her possession an issuance certificate authorizing the county treasurer to issue a school permit. In order to obtain an issuance certificate, the applicant shall present (a) proof of successful completion of a department-approved driver safety course which includes behind-the-wheel driving specifically emphasizing (i) the effects of the consumption of alcohol on a person operating a motor vehicle, (ii) occupant protection systems, (iii) risk assessment, and (iv) railroad crossing safety and (b)(i) proof of successful completion of a written examination and driving test administered by a driver safety course instructor or (ii) a certificate in a form prescribed by the department, signed by a parent, guardian, or licensed driver at least twenty-one years of age, verifying that the applicant has completed fifty hours of lawful motor vehicle operation, under conditions that reflect department-approved driver safety course curriculum, with a parent, guardian, or adult at least twenty-one years of age, who has a current Nebraska operator's license or who is licensed in another state. The department may waive the written examination if the applicant has been issued an LPE-learner's permit or LPD-learner's permit and if such permit is valid or has expired no more than one year prior to application. The written examination shall not be waived if the permit being applied for contains a class or endorsement which is different from the class or endorsement of the LPE-learner's permit.</para><para>(2) A person holding a school permit may operate a motor vehicle, moped, or motorcycle or an autocycle:</para><para>(a) To and from where he or she attends school, or property used by the school he or she attends for purposes of school events or functions, over the most direct and accessible route by the nearest highway from his or her place of residence to transport such person or any family member who resides with such person to attend duly scheduled courses of instruction and extracurricular or school-related activities at the school he or she attends or on property used by the school he or she attends; or</para><para>(b) Under the personal supervision of a licensed operator. Such licensed operator shall be at least twenty-one years of age and licensed by this state or another state and shall (i) for all motor vehicles other than autocycles, motorcycles, or mopeds, actually occupy the seat beside the permitholder, (ii) in the case of an autocycle, actually occupy the seat beside or behind the permitholder, or (iii) in the case of a motorcycle, other than an autocycle, or a moped, if the permitholder is within visual contact of and under the supervision of, in the case of a motorcycle, a licensed motorcycle operator or, in the case of a moped, a licensed motor vehicle operator.</para><para>(3) The holder of a school permit shall not use any type of interactive wireless communication device while operating a motor vehicle on the highways of this state. Enforcement of this subsection shall be accomplished only as a secondary action when the holder of the school permit has been cited or charged with a violation of some other law.</para><para>(4) A person who is younger than sixteen years of age but is over fourteen years of age may be issued an LPE-learner's permit, which permit shall be valid for a period of three months. An LPE-learner's permit shall not be issued until such person successfully completes a written examination prescribed by the department and demonstrates that he or she has sufficient powers of eyesight to safely operate a motor vehicle, moped, or motorcycle or an autocycle.</para><para>(5)(a) While holding the LPE-learner's permit, the person may operate a motor vehicle on the highways of this state if (i) for all motor vehicles other than autocycles, motorcycles, or mopeds, he or she has seated next to him or her a person who is a licensed operator, (ii) in the case of an autocycle, he or she has seated next to or behind him or her a person who is a licensed operator, or (iii) in the case of a motorcycle, other than an autocycle, or a moped, he or she is within visual contact of and is under the supervision of a person who, in the case of a motorcycle, is a licensed motorcycle operator or, in the case of a moped, is a licensed motor vehicle operator. Such licensed motor vehicle or motorcycle operator shall be at least twenty-one years of age and licensed by this state or another state.</para><para>(b) The holder of an LPE-learner's permit shall not use any type of interactive wireless communication device while operating a motor vehicle on the highways of this state. Enforcement of this subdivision shall be accomplished only as a secondary action when the holder of the LPE-learner's permit has been cited or charged with a violation of some other law.</para><para>(6) Department personnel or the county treasurer shall collect the fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115 from each successful applicant for a school or LPE-learner's permit. All school permits shall be subject to impoundment or revocation under the terms of section 60-496. Any person who violates the terms of a school permit shall be guilty of an infraction and shall not be eligible for another school, farm, LPD-learner's, or LPE-learner's permit until he or she has attained the age of sixteen years.</para><para>(7) Any person who holds a permit issued under this section and has violated subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-306, subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-394, or section 28-1254, 60-6,196, 60-6,197, 60-6,197.06, or 60-6,198 shall not be eligible for an ignition interlock permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 387, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 675, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 853, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB415, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB231, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB814, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB269, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>