<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,172"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,172</statuteno><catchline>Nonresident licensee; conviction within state; director; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Within ten days after receiving an abstract of conviction of any nonresident holder of a commercial driver's license for any violation of state law or local ordinance related to motor vehicle traffic control, other than parking violations, committed in a commercial motor vehicle operated in this state, the director shall notify the driver licensing authority which licensed the nonresident and the Commercial Driver License Information System of such conviction.</para><para>(2)(a) Beginning September 30, 2005, within ten days after disqualifying a nonresident holder of an out-of-state commercial driver's license or canceling, revoking, or suspending a nonresident's out-of-state commercial driver's license, for a period of at least sixty days, the Department of Motor Vehicles shall notify the driver licensing authority which licensed the nonresident and the Commercial Driver License Information System of such action.</para><para>(b) The notification shall include both the disqualification and the violation that resulted in the disqualification, cancellation, revocation, or suspension. The notification and the information it provides shall be recorded on the driver's record.</para><para>(3) Beginning September 30, 2005, within ten days after receiving an abstract of conviction of any nonresident holder of a commercial driver's license for any violation of state law or local ordinance related to motor vehicle traffic control, other than parking violations, committed in any type of motor vehicle operated in this state, the director shall notify the driver licensing authority which licensed the nonresident and the Commercial Driver License Information System of such conviction.</para><para>(4) Beginning September 30, 2005, within ten days after receiving an abstract of conviction of any nonresident holder of a driver's license for any violation of state law or local ordinance related to motor vehicle traffic control, other than parking violations, committed in a commercial motor vehicle operated in this state, the director shall notify the driver licensing authority which licensed the nonresident.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 562, &#167; 19. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 