<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,319"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,319</statuteno><catchline>Bicycles; reflective device or material; retail sale; requirements; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>No commercial dealer shall sell or offer to sell at retail any bicycle unless such bicycle is equipped with pedals which display a white or amber reflective device or material on both the front and rear surfaces of the pedal and such reflective surface is visible during the hours of darkness from four hundred feet when viewed from the front or rear under low beam headlights of a motor vehicle under normal atmospheric conditions.</para><para>All bicycles shall also be equipped with tires bearing a white or silver retroreflective material on each side or a wide-angle reflector mounted on the spokes of each wheel. Such retroreflective material shall be at least three-sixteenths of an inch wide, shall be affixed as an integral part of the tire or wheel, and shall remain effective for the life of the tire or wheel. The spoke-mounted, wide-angle reflector devices shall have a reflective surface of at least two square inches and shall be clear, amber, or red in color. Both the retroreflective tires and wide-angle spoke reflectors shall be visible during the hours of darkness from four hundred feet when viewed under low beam headlights of a motor vehicle under normal atmospheric conditions when the bicycle is traveling at a ninety degree right angle to the direction of travel of the motor vehicle and is directly in front of such motor vehicle. Such reflective devices shall remain visible when the bicycle is turned forty degrees in either direction from such angle and crosses directly in front of such motor vehicle at a distance of four hundred feet.</para><para>No commercial dealer shall sell or offer to sell at retail any bicycle which does not comply with this section. Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 827, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 628, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,138.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 415. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 