<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id918"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,163.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,163.02</statuteno><catchline>Alternate license plates; types; design; fees; designated recipient.</catchline><para>The department shall issue the following types of alternate license plates pursuant to this section and sections 60-3,104, 60-3,163, and 60-3,163.01:</para><para>(1) Arbor Day Plates. The department shall design such license plates in consultation with the Nebraska Statewide Arboretum and a nonprofit organization holding a certificate of exemption under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code with a mission to inspire people to plant, nurture, and celebrate trees. The design of such plates shall represent the history and importance of Arbor Day in Nebraska. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Arbor Day Plates is the Home of Arbor Day Plate Cash Fund. A person may apply for Arbor Day Plates beginning on January 1, 2026;</para><para>(2) Breast Cancer Awareness Plates. The department shall design such license plates to include a pink ribbon and the words "early detection saves lives" along the bottom of the license plate. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Breast Cancer Awareness Plates is the University of Nebraska Medical Center for the breast cancer navigator program;</para><para>(3) Choose Life License Plates. The department shall design such license plates to reflect support for the protection of Nebraska's children. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Choose Life License Plates is the Health and Human Services Cash Fund to supplement federal funds available to the Department of Health and Human Services for the Temporary Assistance for Needy Families program, 42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.;</para><para>(4) Czech Heritage Plates. The department, in consultation with the Czech Honorary Consul of Nebraska, shall design such license plates to reflect Czech heritage in Nebraska. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Czech Heritage Plates is the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund;</para><para>(5) Donate Life Plates. The department shall design such license plates to reflect support for organ and tissue donation, registration as a donor on the Donor Registry of Nebraska, and the federally designated organ procurement organization for Nebraska. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Donate Life Plates is the Organ and Tissue Donor Awareness and Education Fund;</para><para>(6) Down Syndrome Awareness Plates. The department shall design such license plates to include the words "Down syndrome awareness" inside a heart-shaped yellow and blue ribbon. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Down Syndrome Awareness Plates is the University of Nebraska Medical Center for the Down Syndrome Clinic;</para><para>(7) Josh the Otter-Be Safe Around Water Plates. The department shall design such license plates to include a blue background with the head of an otter surfacing above water surrounded by the words "Josh the Otter-Be Safe Around Water". The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Josh the Otter-Be Safe Around Water Plates is the Josh the Otter-Be Safe Around Water Cash Fund;</para><para>(8) Mountain Lion Conservation Plates. The department shall design such license plates to reflect support for the conservation of the mountain lion population. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Mountain Lion Conservation Plates is the Game and Parks Commission Educational Fund;</para><para>(9) Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates. The department, in consultation with the Commission on Indian Affairs, shall design license plates that reflect the unique culture and history of Native American tribes historically and currently located in Nebraska. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Native American Cultural Awareness and History Plates is the Native American Scholarship and Leadership Fund;</para><para>(10)(a) Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates. The department shall design such license plates to (i) include the word "Cornhuskers" or "Huskers" prominently in the design, (ii) use scarlet and cream colors in the design or such other similar colors as the department determines to best represent the official team colors of the University of Nebraska Cornhuskers athletic programs and to provide suitable reflection and contrast, (iii) use cream or a similar color for the background of the design and scarlet or a similar color for the printing, and (iv) create a design reflecting support for the University of Nebraska Cornhuskers athletic programs in consultation with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Athletic Department.</para><para>(b) Alphanumeric Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates shall (i) be consecutively numbered beginning with the number one and use numbers that are a size that maximizes legibility, and (ii) not use a county designation or any characters other than numbers on the spirit plates.</para><para>(c) Personalized message Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for personalized message license plates in subsection (2) of section 60-3,118. The characters used shall consist only of letters, numerals, or a combination of letters and numerals of the same size and design specified in section 60-3,100. A maximum of seven characters may be used.</para><para>(d) Each application for initial issuance or renewal of Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates shall be accompanied by a fee of seventy dollars. Fees collected pursuant to this subdivision shall be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit sixty percent of the fee to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and forty percent of the fee to the designated recipient for alternate license plate fees.</para><para>(e) The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates is the Highway Trust Fund;</para><para>(11) Nebraska History Plates. The department shall design such license plates in consultation with the Nebraska State Historical Society to reflect the importance of historical preservation in Nebraska and the value of our shared Nebraska history. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Nebraska History Plates is the Support Nebraska History Cash Fund;</para><para>(12) Pets for Vets Plates. The department shall design such license plates to support veterans and companion or therapy pet animals. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Pets for Vets Plates is the Pets for Vets Cash Fund;</para><para>(13) Prostate Cancer Awareness Plates. The department shall design such license plates to include a light blue ribbon and the words "early detection saves lives" along the bottom of the license plate. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Prostate Cancer Awareness Plates is the University of Nebraska Medical Center for the Nebraska Prostate Cancer Research Program;</para><para>(14) Sammy's Superheroes license plates for childhood cancer awareness. The department shall design such license plates to include a blue handprint over a yellow ribbon and the words "childhood cancer awareness". The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Sammy's Superheroes license plates for childhood cancer awareness is the University of Nebraska Medical Center for pediatric cancer research;</para><para>(15) Support the Arts Plates. The department shall design such license plates in consultation with the Nebraska Arts Council to reflect support for the arts in Nebraska. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Support the Arts Plates is the Support the Arts Cash Fund;</para><para>(16)(a) Support Our Troops Plates. The department shall design such license plates to reflect support for troops from all branches of the armed forces. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Support Our Troops Plates is the Veterans Employment Program Fund.</para><para>(b)(i) Each application for initial issuance or renewal of alphanumeric Support Our Troops Plates shall be accompanied by a fee of five dollars. The State Treasurer shall credit five dollars of the fee to the designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Support Our Troops Plates.</para><para>(ii) Each application for initial issuance or renewal of personalized message Support Our Troops Plates shall be accompanied by a fee of seventy dollars. Twenty-five percent of such fee shall be credited to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund and seventy-five percent of such fee shall be credited to the designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Support Our Troops Plates;</para><para>(17) The Good Life Is Outside Plates. The department shall design such license plates to reflect the importance of safe walking and biking in Nebraska and the value of our recreational trails. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for The Good Life Is Outside Plates is the Game and Parks State Park Improvement and Maintenance Fund for the purpose of trail improvement and maintenance; and</para><para>(18) Wildlife Conservation Plates. The department shall create no more than three designs for such license plates to reflect support for the conservation of Nebraska wildlife, including sandhill cranes, bighorn sheep, and ornate box turtles. The designated recipient for alternate license plate fees for Wildlife Conservation Plates is the Wildlife Conservation Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB398, &#167; 35. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>