<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,167"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,167</statuteno><catchline>Financial responsibility; owner; requirements; prohibited acts; violation; penalty; dismissal of citation; when.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any owner of a motor vehicle or trailer which is being operated or towed with In Transit stickers pursuant to section 60-376, which is being operated or towed pursuant to section 60-365 or 60-369, or which is required to be registered in this state and which is operated or towed on a public highway of this state to allow the operation or towing of the motor vehicle or trailer on a public highway of this state without having a current and effective automobile liability policy, evidence of insurance, or proof of financial responsibility. The owner shall be presumed to know of the operation or towing of his or her motor vehicle or trailer on a highway of this state in violation of this section when the motor vehicle or trailer is being operated or towed by a person other than the owner. An owner of a motor vehicle or trailer who operates or tows the motor vehicle or trailer or allows the operation or towing of the motor vehicle or trailer in violation of this section shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor and shall be advised by the court that his or her motor vehicle operator's license, motor vehicle certificate of registration, and license plates will be suspended by the department until he or she complies with sections 60-505.02 and 60-528. Upon conviction the owner shall have his or her motor vehicle operator's license, motor vehicle certificate of registration, and license plates suspended by the department until he or she complies with sections 60-505.02 and 60-528. The owner shall also be required to comply with section 60-528 for a continuous period of three years after the violation. This subsection shall not apply to motor vehicles or trailers registered in another state.</para><para>(2) An owner who is unable to produce a current and effective automobile liability policy, evidence of insurance, or proof of financial responsibility upon the request of a law enforcement officer shall be allowed ten days after the date of the request to produce proof to the appropriate prosecutor or county attorney that a current and effective automobile liability policy or proof of financial responsibility was in existence for the motor vehicle or trailer at the time of such request. Upon presentation of such proof, the citation shall be dismissed by the prosecutor or county attorney without cost to the owner and no prosecution for the offense cited shall occur.</para><para>(3) The department shall, for any person convicted for a violation of this section, reinstate such person's operator's license, motor vehicle certificate of registration, and license plates and rescind any order requiring such person to comply with section 60-528 without cost to such person upon presentation to the director that, at the time such person was cited for a violation of this section, a current and effective automobile liability policy or proof of financial responsibility was in existence for the motor vehicle or trailer at the time the citation was issued.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 167. </para></source></law></legaldoc>