<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id379" statutenumber="60-4,170"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,170</statuteno><catchline id="id382">Revocation; notice; failure
to surrender license or permit;
violation; penalty; appeal.</catchline><para>Within ten days after the revocation
provided for by section 60-4,169, the director shall notify in writing the
person whose commercial driver's license,
CLP-commercial learner's permit, or privilege to operate a commercial
motor vehicle has been revoked that such license, permit, or privilege has been revoked. Such
notice shall: (1) Contain a list of the disqualifying convictions or administrative
determinations upon which the director relies as his or her authority for
the revocation, with the dates on which such disqualifying violations occurred
and the dates of such convictions or administrative determinations and the
trial courts or administrative agencies in which such convictions or administrative
determinations were rendered; (2) state the term of revocation; (3) include
a demand that the commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit be returned
to the director immediately; and (4) be served by mailing the notice to such
person by regular United States mail to the address of such person. Any
person refusing or failing to surrender a commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit as
required by this section shall, upon conviction, be guilty of a Class III
misdemeanor.</para>
<para>Any person who feels himself or herself aggrieved because of a revocation
pursuant to section 60-4,169 may appeal from such revocation in the manner
set forth in section 60-4,105. Such appeal shall not suspend the order of
revocation unless a stay of such revocation shall be allowed by the court
pending a final determination of the review. The license of any person claiming
to be aggrieved shall not be restored to such person, in the event of a final
judgment of a court against such person, until the full time of revocation,
as fixed by the director, has elapsed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 120; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 51.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>