<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,162"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,162</statuteno><catchline>Signals given by hand and arm or signal lights; signal lights required; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Any stop signal or turnsignal required by the Nebraska Rules of the Road shall be given either by means of the hand and arm or by signal lights except as otherwise provided in this section.</para><para>(2) With respect to any motor vehicle having four or more wheels manufactured or assembled, whether from a kit or otherwise, after January 1, 1954, designed or used for the purpose of carrying passengers or freight, or any trailer, in use on a highway, any required signal shall be given by the appropriate signal lights when the distance from the center of the top of the steering post to the left outside limit of the body, cab, or load of such motor vehicle or trailer exceeds twenty-four inches. Such measurement shall apply to any single vehicle or trailer and to any combination of vehicles or trailers. This subsection shall not apply during daylight hours to fertilizer trailers as defined in section 60-326 and implements of husbandry designed primarily or exclusively for use in agricultural operations.</para><para>(3) Under any condition when a hand and arm signal would not be visible both to the front and rear of the vehicle of such signaling driver for one hundred feet, the required signals shall be given by such a light or device as required by this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 216, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-653; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 258; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 59, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 238, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 242. </para></source></law></legaldoc>