<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,241"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,241</statuteno><catchline>Vehicles; slow moving; emblem required; when used.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be unlawful for any person to operate on the roadway of any highway any slow-moving vehicle or equipment, any animal-drawn vehicle, or any other machinery, designed for use at speeds less than twenty-five miles per hour, including all road construction or maintenance machinery except when engaged in actual construction or maintenance work either guarded by a flagperson or clearly visible warning signs, which normally travels or is normally used at a speed of less than twenty-five miles per hour unless there is displayed on the rear thereof an emblem as described in and displayed as provided in subsection (2) of this section. The requirement of such emblem shall be in addition to any lighting devices required by law. The emblem shall not be displayed on objects which are customarily stationary in use except while being transported on the roadway of any highway.</para><para>(2) The emblem shall be of substantial construction and shall be a base-down equilateral triangle of fluorescent yellow-orange film with a base of fourteen inches and an altitude of twelve inches. Such triangle shall be bordered with reflective red strips having a minimum width of one and three-fourths inches, with the vertices of the overall triangle truncated such that the remaining altitude shall be a minimum of fourteen inches. The emblem shall comply with the current standards and specifications for slow-moving vehicle emblems of the American Society of Agricultural Engineers. Such emblem shall be mounted on the rear of such vehicle at a height of two to six feet above the roadway and shall be maintained in a clean, reflective condition. This section shall not apply to an electric personal assistive mobility device.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 210, &#167; 1, p. 618; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 230, &#167; 1, p. 607; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-723.10; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 211, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,125; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 337; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 462. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 