<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,301</statuteno><catchline>Vehicles; overload; reduce or shift load; exceptions; permit fee; warning citation; when.</catchline><para>When any motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer is operated upon the highways of this state carrying a load in excess of the maximum weight permitted by section 60-6,294, the load shall be reduced or shifted to within such maximum tolerance before being permitted to operate on any public highway of this state, except that:</para><para>(1) If any motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer exceeds the maximum load on only one axle, only one tandem axle, or only one group of axles when (a) the distance between the first and last axle of such group of axles is twelve feet or less, (b) the excess axle load is no more than five percent in excess of the maximum load for such axle, tandem axle, or group of axles permitted by such section, while the vehicle or combination of vehicles is within the maximum gross load, and (c) the load on such vehicle is such that it can be shifted or the configuration of the vehicle can be changed so that all axles, tandem axle, or groups of axles are within the maximum permissible limit for such axle, tandem axle, or group of axles, such shift or change of configuration may be made without penalty;</para><para>(2) Any motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer carrying only a load of livestock may exceed the maximum load as permitted by such section on only one axle, only one tandem axle, or only one group of axles when the distance between the first and last axle of the group of axles is six feet or less if the excess load on the axle, tandem axle, or group of axles is caused by a shifting of the weight of the livestock by the livestock and if the vehicle or combination of vehicles is within the maximum gross load as permitted by such section;</para><para>(3) With a permit issued by the Department of Transportation or the Nebraska State Patrol, a truck with an enclosed body and a compacting mechanism, designed and used exclusively for the collection and transportation of garbage or refuse, may exceed the maximum load as permitted by such section by no more than twenty percent on only one axle, only one tandem axle, or only one group of axles when the vehicle is laden with garbage or refuse if the vehicle is within the maximum gross load as permitted by such section. There shall be a permit fee of ten dollars per month or one hundred dollars per year. The permit may be issued for one or more months up to one year, and the term of applicability shall be stated on the permit;</para><para>(4) Any motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer carrying any kind of a load, including livestock, which exceeds the legal maximum gross load by five percent or less may proceed on its itinerary and unload the cargo carried thereon to the maximum legal gross weight at the first unloading facility on the itinerary where the cargo can be properly protected. All material so unloaded shall be cared for by the owner or operator of such vehicle at the risk of such owner or operator; and</para><para>(5) Any motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer carrying grain or other seasonally harvested products may operate from the field where such grain or products are harvested to storage, market, or stockpile in the field or from stockpile to market or factory up to seventy miles with a load that exceeds the maximum load permitted by section 60-6,294 by fifteen percent on any tandem axle, group of axles, and gross weight. Any truck with no more than a single rear axle carrying grain or other seasonally harvested products may operate from the field where such grain or products are harvested to storage, market, or stockpile in the field or from stockpile to market or factory up to seventy miles with a load that exceeds the maximum load permitted by section 60-6,294 by fifteen percent on any single axle and gross weight. The owner or a representative of the owner of the agricultural product shall furnish the driver of the loaded vehicle a signed statement of origin and destination.</para><para>Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit to be operated on the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways any vehicle or combination of vehicles which exceeds any of the weight limitations applicable to such system as contained in section 60-6,294.</para><para>If the maximum legal gross weight or axle weight of any vehicle is exceeded by five percent or less and the arresting peace officer or carrier enforcement officer has reason to believe that such excessive weight is caused by snow, ice, or rain, the officer may issue a warning citation to the operator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 134, &#167; 5, p. 420; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 150, &#167; 1, p. 446; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 226, &#167; 3, p. 710; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 318, &#167; 4, p. 1156; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 491, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 39-723.07; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 920, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 823, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 427, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 785, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 726, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 833, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,185; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 397; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB148, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 226. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>