<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id34" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-6,211.05"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,211.05</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Ignition
interlock device; continuous alcohol monitoring device and abstention from
alcohol use; orders authorized; prohibited acts; violation; penalty; costs;
Department of Motor Vehicles Ignition Interlock Fund; created; use; investment;
prohibited acts relating to tampering with device; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) If an order is granted under section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197 and
sections 60-6,197.02 and 60-6,197.03, the court may order that the defendant
install an ignition interlock device of a type approved by the Director of
Motor Vehicles on each motor vehicle operated by the defendant during the
period of revocation. Upon sufficient evidence of installation, the defendant
may apply to the director for an ignition interlock permit pursuant to section
60-4,118.06. The device shall, without tampering or the intervention of another
person, prevent the defendant from operating the motor vehicle when the defendant
has an alcohol concentration greater than three-hundredths of one gram or
more by weight of alcohol per one hundred milliliters of his or her blood
or three-hundredths of one gram or more by weight of alcohol per two hundred
ten liters of his or her breath. The Department of Motor Vehicles shall issue
an ignition interlock permit to the defendant under section 60-4,118.06 only
upon sufficient proof that a defendant has installed an ignition interlock
device on any motor vehicle that the defendant will operate during his or
her release.</para>
<para>(2) If the court orders installation of an ignition interlock
device and issuance of an ignition interlock permit pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section, the court may also order the use of a continuous alcohol
monitoring device and abstention from alcohol use at all times. The device
shall, without tampering or the intervention of another person, test and record
the alcohol consumption level of the defendant on a periodic basis and transmit
such information to probation authorities.</para>
<para>(3) Any order issued by the court pursuant to this section
shall not take effect until the defendant is eligible to operate a motor vehicle
pursuant to subsection (8) of section 60-498.01. A person shall be eligible
to be issued an ignition interlock permit allowing operation of a motor vehicle
equipped with an ignition interlock device if he or she is not subject to
any other suspension, cancellation, required no-driving period, or period
of revocation and has successfully completed the ignition interlock permit
application process. The Department of Motor Vehicles shall review its records
and the driving record abstract of any person who applies for an ignition
interlock permit allowing operation of a motor vehicle equipped with an ignition
interlock device to determine (a) the applicant's eligibility for an ignition
interlock permit, (b) the applicant's previous convictions under section 60-6,196,
60-6,197, or 60-6,197.06 or any previous administrative license revocation,
if any, and (c)
if the applicant is subject to any required no-drive periods before the ignition
interlock permit may be issued. </para>
<para>(4)(a) If the court orders an ignition interlock device or
the Board of Pardons orders an ignition interlock device under section 83-1,127.02,
the court or the Board of Pardons shall order the defendant to apply for an
ignition interlock permit as provided in section 60-4,118.06 which indicates
that the defendant is only allowed to operate a motor vehicle equipped with
an ignition interlock device.</para>
<para>(b) Such court order shall remain in effect for a period of
time as determined by the court not to exceed the maximum term of revocation
which the court could have imposed according to the nature of the violation
and shall allow operation by the defendant of only an ignition-interlock-equipped motor vehicle.</para>
<para>(c) Such Board of Pardons order shall remain in effect for
a period of time not to exceed any period of revocation the applicant is subject
to at the time the application for a reprieve is made.</para>
<para>(5) Any person restricted to operating a motor vehicle equipped
with an ignition interlock device, pursuant to a Board of Pardons order, who
operates upon the highways of this state a motor vehicle without such device
or if the device has been disabled, bypassed, or altered in any way, shall
be punished as provided in subsection (3) of section 83-1,127.02.</para>
<para>(6) If a person ordered to use a continuous alcohol monitoring
device and abstain from alcohol use pursuant to a court order as provided
in subsection (2) of this section violates the provisions of such court order
by removing, tampering with, or otherwise bypassing the continuous alcohol
monitoring device or by consuming alcohol while required to use such device,
he or she shall have his or her ignition interlock permit revoked and be unable
to apply for reinstatement for the duration of the revocation period imposed
by the court.</para>
<para>(7) The director shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
regarding the approval of ignition interlock devices, the means of installing
ignition interlock devices, and the means of administering the ignition interlock
permit program.</para>
<para>(8)(a) The costs incurred in order to comply with the ignition
interlock requirements of this section shall be paid directly to the ignition
interlock provider by the person complying with an order for an ignition interlock
permit and installation of an ignition interlock device.</para>
<para>(b) If the Department of Motor Vehicles has determined the
person to be indigent and incapable of paying for the cost of installation,
removal, or maintenance of the ignition interlock device in accordance with
this section, such costs shall be paid out of the Department of Motor Vehicles
Ignition Interlock Fund if such funds are available, according to rules and
regulations adopted and promulgated by the department. Such costs shall also
be paid out of the Department of Motor Vehicles Ignition Interlock Fund if
such funds are available and if the court or the Board of Pardons, whichever
is applicable, has determined the person to be indigent and incapable of paying
for the cost of installation, removal, or maintenance of the ignition interlock
device in accordance with this section. The Department of Motor Vehicles Ignition
Interlock Fund is created. Money
in the Department of Motor Vehicles Ignition Interlock Fund may be used for
transfers to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any
money in the Department of Motor Vehicles Ignition
Interlock Fund available for investment shall be invested by the
state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and
the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(9)(a)(i) An ignition interlock service facility shall notify
the appropriate district probation office or the appropriate court, as applicable,
of any evidence of tampering with or circumvention of an ignition interlock
device, or any attempts to do so, when the facility becomes aware of such
evidence. Failure of the facility to provide notification as provided in this
subdivision is a Class V misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(ii) An ignition interlock service facility shall notify the
Department of Motor Vehicles, if the ignition interlock permit is issued pursuant
to sections 60-498.01 to 60-498.04, of any evidence of tampering with or circumvention
of an ignition interlock device, or any attempts to do so, when the facility
becomes aware of such evidence. Failure of the facility to provide notification
as provided in this subdivision is a Class V misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(b) If a district probation office receives evidence of tampering
with or circumvention of an ignition interlock device, or any attempts to
do so, from an ignition interlock service facility, the district probation
office shall notify the appropriate court of such violation. The court shall
immediately schedule an evidentiary hearing to be held within fourteen days
after receiving such evidence, either from the district probation office or
an ignition interlock service facility, and the court shall cause notice of
the hearing to be given to the person operating a motor vehicle pursuant to
an order under subsection (1) of this section. If the person who is the subject
of such evidence does not appear at the hearing and show cause why the order
made pursuant to subsection (1) of this section should remain in effect, the
court shall rescind the original order. Nothing in this subsection shall apply
to an order made by the Board of Pardons pursuant to section 83-1,127.02.</para>
<para>(10) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the issuance
of an ignition interlock permit by the Department of Motor Vehicles under
section 60-498.01 or an order for the installation of an ignition interlock
device and ignition interlock permit made pursuant to subsection (1) of this
section as part of a conviction, as well as the administration of such court
order by the Office of Probation Administration for the installation, maintenance,
and removal of such device, as applicable, shall not be construed to create
an order of probation when an order of probation has not been issued.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 564, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 925, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB497, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB924, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB158, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB199, &#167; 27.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB158, section 5, with LB199, section 27, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB199 became effective May 26, 2013. Changes made by LB158 became operative July 1, 2013.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>