<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-6,313"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,313</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Operating mopeds on roadways laned for traffic; prohibited acts.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) A moped shall be entitled to full use of a traffic lane of any highway with an authorized speed limit of forty-five miles per hour or less, and no vehicle shall be operated in such a manner as to deprive any moped of the full use of such lane, except that mopeds and motorcycles may be operated two abreast in a single lane.</para><para id="id00">(2) No person shall operate a moped between lanes of traffic or between adjacent lines or rows of vehicles.</para><para id="id00">(3) Mopeds shall not be operated more than two abreast in a single lane.</para><para id="id00">(4) Any person who operates a moped on a roadway with an authorized speed limit of more than forty-five miles per hour shall ride as near to the right side of the roadway as practicable and shall not ride more than single file.</para><para id="id00">(5) No person who rides upon a moped shall attach himself, herself, or the moped to any other vehicle on a roadway.</para><para id="id00">(6) Mopeds shall not be operated on the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways or on sidewalks.</para><para id="id00">(7) Notwithstanding the maximum speed limits in excess of twenty-five miles per hour established in section 60-6,186, no person shall operate any moped at a speed in excess of thirty miles per hour.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section, motorcycle does not include an autocycle.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 23, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,200; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 409; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 111. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Operator's license,</emphasis> assessment of points for speeding, see section 60-4,182.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>