<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id6" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="60-6,211.11"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,211.11</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Prohibited
acts relating to ignition interlock device; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of
this section, any person ordered by a court or the Department of
Motor Vehicles to operate only motor vehicles equipped with an ignition interlock
device is guilty of a Class I misdemeanor if he or she (a) tampers
with or circumvents and then
operates a motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device
installed under the court order or Department
of Motor Vehicles order while the order is in effect or (b) operates
a motor vehicle which is not equipped with an ignition interlock device in
violation of the court order or Department
of Motor Vehicles order.</para>
<para>(2) Any person
ordered by a court or the Department of Motor Vehicles to operate only motor
vehicles equipped with an ignition interlock device is guilty of a Class IV
felony if he or she (a)(i) tampers with or circumvents and then operates a
motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device installed under the
court order or Department of Motor Vehicles order while the order is in effect
or (ii) operates a motor vehicle which is not equipped with an ignition interlock
device in violation of the court order or Department of Motor Vehicles order
and (b) operates the motor vehicle as described in subdivision (a)(i) or (ii)
of this subsection when he or she has a concentration of two-hundredths of
one gram or more by weight of alcohol per one hundred milliliters of his or
her blood or a concentration of two-hundredths of one gram or more by weight
of alcohol per two hundred ten liters of his or her breath.</para>
<para>(3) Any person who otherwise
operates a motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device in violation
of the requirements of the court order or Department of Motor Vehicles order
under which the device was installed shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB998, &#167; 13.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>