<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-192"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-192</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Odometers; transferor; statement; contents.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The transferor of any motor vehicle described in subsection (2) of this section, which was equipped with an odometer by the manufacturer, shall provide to the transferee a statement, signed by the transferor, setting forth:</para><para id="id00">(a) The mileage on the odometer at the time of transfer; and</para><para id="id00">(b)(i) A statement that, to the transferor's best knowledge, such mileage is that actually driven by the motor vehicle;</para><para id="id00">(ii) A statement that the transferor has knowledge that the mileage shown on the odometer is in excess of the designated mechanical odometer limit; or</para><para id="id00">(iii) A statement that the odometer reading does not reflect the actual mileage and should not be relied upon because the transferor has knowledge that the odometer reading differs from the actual mileage and that the difference is greater than that caused by odometer calibration error.</para><para>(2) Prior to January 1, 2021, this section applies to the transfer of any motor vehicle of an age of less than ten years. Beginning January 1, 2021, this section applies to the transfer of any motor vehicle with a manufacturer's model year designation of 2011 or newer and an age of less than twenty years.</para><para id="id00">(3) If a discrepancy exists between the odometer reading and the actual mileage, a warning notice to alert the transferee shall be included with the statement. The transferor shall retain a true copy of such statement for a period of five years from the date of the transaction.</para><para id="id00">(4) Beginning on the implementation date designated by the director pursuant to subsection (2) of section 60-1508, if motor vehicle ownership has been transferred by operation of law pursuant to repossession under subdivision (2)(b)(iv) of section 60-166, the mileage shall be listed as the odometer reading at the time of the most recent transfer of ownership prior to the repossession of the motor vehicle. The adjustment shall not be deemed a violation of section 60-190.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>