<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id35" statutenumber="60-4,120.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,120.01</statuteno><catchline id="id38">Provisional operator's permit; application; issuance; operation restrictions.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any person who is at least sixteen years of age but less than eighteen years of age may be issued a provisional operator's permit by the Department of Motor Vehicles. The provisional operator's permit shall expire on the applicant's eighteenth birthday. </para><para>(b) No provisional operator's permit shall be issued to any person unless such person:</para><para>(i) Has possessed a valid LPD-learner's permit, LPE-learner's permit, or SCP-school permit for at least a six-month period beginning on the date of issuance of such person's LPD-learner's permit, LPE-learner's permit, or SCP-school permit; and</para><para>(ii) Has not accumulated three or more points pursuant to section 60-4,182 during the six-month period immediately preceding the date of the application for the provisional operator's permit.</para><para>(c) The requirements for the provisional operator's permit prescribed in subdivisions (2)(a) and (b) of this section may be completed prior to the applicant's sixteenth birthday. A person may apply for a provisional operator's permit and take the driving test and the written examination, if required, at any time within sixty days prior to his or her sixteenth birthday upon proof of age in the manner provided in section 60-484.</para><para>(2) In order to obtain a provisional operator's permit, the applicant shall present (a)(i) proof of successful completion of a department-approved driver safety course which includes behind-the-wheel driving specifically emphasizing (A) the effects of the consumption of alcohol on a person operating a motor vehicle, (B) occupant protection systems, (C) risk assessment, and (D) railroad crossing safety and (ii) proof of successful completion of a written examination and driving test administered by a driver safety course instructor or (b) a certificate in a form prescribed by the department, signed by a parent, guardian, or licensed driver at least twenty-one years of age, verifying that the applicant has completed fifty hours of lawful motor vehicle operation including at least ten hours of motor vehicle operation between sunset and sunrise, under conditions that reflect department-approved driver safety course curriculum, with a parent, guardian, or adult at least twenty-one years of age, who has a current Nebraska operator's license or who is licensed in another state. If the applicant presents such a certificate, the applicant shall be required to successfully complete a driving test administered by the department. The written examination shall be waived if the applicant has been issued a Nebraska LPD-learner's permit or has been issued a Nebraska LPE-learner's permit and such permit is valid or has been expired for no more than one year. However, the department shall not waive the written examination if the provisional operator's permit being applied for contains a class or endorsement which is different from the class or endorsement of the LPD-learner's or LPE-learner's permit. Upon presentation by the applicant of a form prescribed by the department showing successful completion of the driver safety course, the written examination and driving test may be waived. Upon presentation of the certificate, the written examination but not the driving test may be waived. Licensing staff shall waive the written examination and the driving test if the applicant has been issued a school permit and such permit is valid or has expired no more than one year prior to application. The written examination shall not be waived if the provisional operator's permit being applied for contains a class or endorsement which is different from the class or endorsement of the school permit.</para><para>(3)(a) The holder of a provisional operator's permit shall only operate a motor vehicle on the highways of this state during the period beginning at 6 a.m. and ending at 12 midnight except when he or she is en route to or from his or her residence to his or her place of employment or a school activity. The holder of a provisional operator's permit may operate a motor vehicle on the highways of this state at any hour of the day or night if accompanied by a parent, guardian, or adult at least twenty-one years of age, who has a current Nebraska operator's license or who is licensed in another state.</para><para>(b) The holder of a provisional operator's permit shall only operate a motor vehicle on the highways of this state during the first six months of holding the permit with no more than one passenger who is not an immediate family member and who is under nineteen years of age.</para><para>(c) The holder of a provisional operator's permit shall not use any type of interactive wireless communication device while operating a motor vehicle on the highways of this state.</para><para>(d) Enforcement of subdivisions (a), (b), and (c) of this subsection shall be accomplished only as a secondary action when the holder of the provisional operator's permit has been cited or charged with a violation of some other law.</para><para>(4) Department personnel or the county treasurer shall collect the fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115 for the issuance of each provisional operator's permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 387, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 1, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 675, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB415, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>