<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id468">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id470" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-6,179.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,179.02</statuteno><catchline>Operator of commercial motor
vehicle; texting while driving prohibited; exception; violation; penalty.</catchline>
<para>(1) Beginning
October 27, 2013, except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) of this section,
no operator of a commercial motor vehicle shall engage in texting while driving.</para>
<para>(2) Texting
while driving is permissible by an operator of a commercial motor vehicle
if such texting is necessary to communicate with law enforcement officials
or other emergency services.</para><para>(3) Any person who violates this section
shall be guilty of a traffic infraction. Any person who is found guilty of
a traffic infraction under this section shall be subject to disqualification
as provided in section 60-4,168, shall be assessed points on his or her motor
vehicle operator's license pursuant to section 60-4,182, and shall be fined:</para>
<para>(a) Two hundred
dollars for the first offense;</para><para>(b) Three hundred dollars for a second
offense; and</para><para>(c) Five hundred dollars for a third and subsequent offense.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes
of this section:</para><para>(a) Driving means operating a commercial motor vehicle, with the
motor running, including while temporarily stationary because of traffic,
a traffic control device, or other momentary delays. Driving does not include
operating a commercial motor vehicle with or without the motor running when
the operator moves the vehicle to the side of, or off, a highway and halts
in a location where the vehicle can safely remain stationary;</para>
<para>(b) Electronic
device includes, but is not limited to, a cellular telephone; a personal digital
assistant; a pager; a computer; or any other device used to input, write,
send, receive, or read text; and</para><para>(c)(i) Texting means manually entering
alphanumeric text into, or reading text from, an electronic device. Texting
includes, but is not limited to, short message service, emailing, instant
messaging, a command or request to access an Internet web page, pressing more
than a single button to initiate or terminate a voice communication using
a mobile telephone, or engaging in any other form of electronic text retrieval
or electronic text entry for present or future communication.</para>
<para>(ii) Texting
does not include:</para><para>(A) Inputting, selecting, or reading information on a global positioning
system or navigation system;</para><para>(B) Pressing a single button to initiate
or terminate a voice communication using a mobile telephone; or</para>
<para>(C) Using a device
capable of performing multiple functions, including, but not limited to, fleet
management systems, dispatching devices, smartphones, citizens band radios,
and music players, for a purpose other than texting.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 45.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>