<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,131"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,131</statuteno><catchline>Driving on right half of roadway required; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Upon all roadways of sufficient width, a vehicle shall be driven upon the right half of the roadway except as follows:</para><para>(a) When overtaking and passing another vehicle proceeding in the same direction under the rules governing such movement;</para><para>(b) When an obstruction exists making it necessary to drive to the left of the center of the highway, except that any person so doing shall yield the right-of-way to all vehicles traveling in the proper direction upon the unobstructed portion of the highway within such distance as to constitute an immediate hazard;</para><para>(c) Upon a roadway divided into three marked lanes for traffic under the rules applicable thereon; or</para><para>(d) Upon a roadway restricted to one-way traffic.</para><para>(2) Upon all roadways, any vehicle proceeding at less than the normal speed of traffic at the time and place and under the conditions then existing shall be driven in the right-hand lane then available for traffic, or as close as practicable to the right-hand curb or edge of the roadway, except when overtaking and passing another vehicle proceeding in the same direction or when preparing for a left turn at an intersection or into a private road or driveway.</para><para>(3) Upon any roadway having four or more lanes for moving traffic and providing for two-way movement of traffic, no vehicle shall be driven to the left of the centerline of the roadway except when authorized by official traffic control devices designating certain lanes to the left side of the center of the roadway for use by traffic not otherwise permitted to use such lanes or except as permitted under subdivision (1)(b) of this section. This subsection shall not be construed to prohibit the crossing of the centerline in making a left turn into or from an alley, private road, or driveway unless such movement is otherwise prohibited by signs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 20; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-620; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 227. </para></source><annotation><para>Violation of this statute is only evidence of negligence and does not constitute negligence per se. Bourke v. Watts, 223 Neb. 511, 391 N.W.2d 552 (1986).</para><para>Violation of a statute is evidence of negligence, but not negligence per se. Clark Bilt, Inc. v. Wells Dairy Co., 200 Neb. 20, 261 N.W.2d 772 (1978).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 