
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id244">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id246" statutenumber="60-4,129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,129</statuteno><catchline id="id249">Employment
driving permit; issuance; conditions; violations; penalty; revocation.</catchline>
<para>(1) Any person whose operator's license
is revoked under section 60-4,183 or 60-4,186 or suspended
under section 43-3318 shall be eligible to operate any motor vehicle, except
a commercial motor vehicle, in this state under an employment driving permit.
An employment driving permit issued due to a revocation under section 60-4,183 or 60-4,186 is valid for
the period of revocation. An employment driving permit issued due to a suspension
of an operator's license under section 43-3318 is valid for no more than three
months and cannot be renewed.</para>
<para>(2) Any person whose operator's license has been suspended
or revoked pursuant to any law of this state, except section 43-3318, 60-4,183, or 60-4,186,
shall not be eligible to receive an employment driving permit during the period
of such suspension or revocation.</para>
<para>(3) A person who is issued an
employment driving permit may operate any motor vehicle, except a commercial
motor vehicle, (a) from his or her residence to his or her place of employment
and return and (b) during the normal course of employment if the use of a
motor vehicle is necessary in the course of such employment. Such permit shall
indicate for which purposes the permit may be used. All permits issued pursuant
to this section shall indicate that the permit is not valid for the operation
of any commercial motor vehicle.</para>
<para>(4) The operation of a motor vehicle by the holder of an
employment driving permit, except as provided in this section, shall be unlawful.
Any person who violates this section shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(5) The director shall revoke a
person's employment driving permit upon receipt of an abstract
of conviction, other than a conviction which is based upon actions which resulted
in the application for such employment driving permit, indicating that the person committed an offense for which points
are assessed pursuant to section 60-4,182. If the permit is revoked in this
manner, the person shall not be eligible
to receive an employment driving permit for the remainder of the period of
suspension or revocation of his or her operator's license.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 259, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 568, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 779, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-669.34; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 291, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 140; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB675, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>Absence of provision to issue occupational driving permits to implied consent violators does not violate the equal protection clause of the fourteenth amendment to the U.S. Constitution. Statute's long-range objective is to reduce carnage caused by intoxicated drivers by getting them off Nebraska roads. Porter v. Jensen, 223 Neb. 438, 390 N.W.2d 511 (1986).</para>
<para>Section 60-498.02, providing that drivers whose operator's licenses had been revoked for a period of 1 year were eligible for an employment driving permit, and this section, providing that drivers whose operator's licenses had been revoked for a period of 90 days were eligible for an employment driving permit after a period of 30 days, are not in conflict or ambiguous. Bazar v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 17 Neb. App. 910, 774 N.W.2d 433 (2009).</para>
</annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>