<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,159"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,159</statuteno><catchline>Licensee; permit holder; convictions; disqualifications;
notification required; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any person
possessing a commercial driver's license or
CLP-commercial learner's permit issued by the department shall, within ten days after the date of conviction, notify the department
of all convictions for violations of state law or local ordinance related
to motor vehicle traffic control, except parking violations, when such convictions
occur in another state.</para>
<para>(2) Any person possessing a commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit issued by
the department who is convicted of violating any state law or local ordinance
related to motor vehicle traffic control in this or any other state, other
than parking violations, shall notify his or her employer in writing of the
conviction within thirty days of the date of conviction.</para>
<para>(3) Any person possessing a commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit issued by
the department whose commercial driver's license or CLP-commercial learner's permit is suspended,
revoked, or canceled by any state, who loses the privilege to operate a
commercial motor vehicle in any state for any period, or who is disqualified
from operating a commercial motor
vehicle for any period shall notify his or her employer of that fact before
the end of the business day following the day the driver received notice of
that fact.</para>
<para>(4) Any person who fails to provide the notifications required in subsection
(1), (2), or (3) of this section shall, upon conviction, be guilty of a Class
III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 45.</para><operativedate>July 8, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>