<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id155">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id157" statutenumber="60-3,129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id159">60-3,129</statuteno><catchline id="id160">Spirit Plate
Proceeds Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The
Spirit Plate Proceeds Fund is created. Any money in the fund available for
investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the
Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) If the cost of manufacturing Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit
Plates at any time exceeds the amount charged for license plates pursuant
to section 60-3,102, any money to be credited to the Spirit Plate Proceeds
Fund shall instead be credited first to the Highway Trust Fund in an amount
equal to the difference between the manufacturing costs of such spirit plates
and the amount charged pursuant to such section with respect to such spirit
plates and the remainder shall be credited to the Spirit Plate Proceeds Fund as provided in section 60-3,128.</para>
<para>(3) The first three million dollars credited to the Spirit
Plate Proceeds Fund and not credited to the Highway Trust Fund shall be appropriated
to the University of Nebraska to establish an endowment fund to provide financial
support to former University of Nebraska athletes to pursue undergraduate
and postgraduate studies at any University of Nebraska campus. Funds appropriated
by the Legislature for such scholarship program shall be held, managed, and
invested as an endowed scholarship fund in such manner as the Board of Regents
of the University of Nebraska shall determine and as authorized by section
72-1246. The income from the endowed scholarship fund shall be expended for
such scholarships. The University of Nebraska shall grant financial support
to former athletes who demonstrate financial need as determined by the Federal
Pell Grant Program or similar need-based qualifications as approved by the
financial aid office of the appropriate campus.</para>
<para>(4) The next two million dollars credited to the Spirit Plate
Proceeds Fund and not credited to the Highway Trust Fund shall be appropriated
to the University of Nebraska to establish an endowment fund to provide financial
support for the academic service units of the athletic departments of the
campuses of the University of Nebraska in support of academic services to
athletes.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 129; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB110, &#167; 12.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>