<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002-->
<?APT Element gi="legaldoc"?>
<?APT Element gi="law" attrs="type"?>
<?APT Element gi="section"?>
<?APT Element gi="sectno"?>
<?APT Element gi="amendatorysection" attrs="amended chaptername statutenumber"?>
<?APT Element gi="bookinfo"?>
<?APT Element gi="statuteno"?>
<?APT Element gi="catchline"?>
<?APT Element gi="para"?>
<?APT Element gi="source"?>
<?APT Element gi="effectivedate"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection
amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,117</statuteno><catchline>Issuance
of license by county treasurer; form; operator's license or state identification
card; delivery; form; county treasurer; duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This
subsection applies until the implementation date designated by the director
pursuant to section 60-462.02. Upon presentation of the certificate for an
operator's license issued by the examining officer to the applicant for such
license, the county treasurer shall issue such license to the applicant. The
license shall be in full force and effect until the expiration date thereon,
until officially revoked, suspended, canceled by an order of the director,
or until ordered revoked or impounded by a court of competent jurisdiction.</para><para>(b)
The operator's license shall be in a form prescribed by the department. The
license may include security features prescribed by the department. The license
shall be conspicuously marked Nebraska Operator's License, shall be, to the
maximum extent practicable, tamper proof, and shall include the following
information:</para><para>(i) The name and residential and post office address
of the holder;</para><para>(ii) The holder's color photograph or digital image;</para><para>(iii)
A physical description of the holder, including sex, height, weight, and eye
and hair colors;</para><para>(iv) The holder's date of birth;</para><para>(v)
The holder's signature;</para><para>(vi) The class of motor vehicle which
the holder is authorized to operate and any endorsements or restrictions;</para><para>(vii)
The dates between which the license is valid;</para><para>(viii) The organ
and tissue donation information specified in section 60-494; and</para><para>(ix)
Such other facts and information as the director may determine.</para><para>(c)
Machine-readable information encoded on an operator's license shall be limited
to the information appearing on the face of the license.</para><para>(2)(a)
This subsection applies beginning on the implementation date designated by
the director pursuant to section 60-462.02. Upon presentation of an issuance
certificate for an operator's license or state identification card issued
by department personnel to the applicant, the county treasurer shall collect
the applicable fee and surcharge as prescribed in section 60-4,115 and issue
a receipt which is valid for up to thirty days. If there is cause for an operator's
license to be issued, the receipt shall also authorize driving privileges
for such thirty-day period. The license or card shall be delivered as provided
in section 60-4,113.</para><para>(b) The operator's license and state identification
card shall be in a form prescribed by the department. The license and card
may include security features prescribed by the department. The license and
card shall be conspicuously marked Nebraska Operator's License or Nebraska
Identification Card, shall be, to the maximum extent practicable, tamper and
forgery proof, and shall include the following information:</para><para>(i)
The full legal name and principal residence address of the holder;</para><para>(ii)
The holder's full facial digital image;</para><para>(iii) A physical description
of the holder, including gender, height, weight, and eye and hair colors;</para><para>(iv)
The holder's date of birth;</para><para>(v) The holder's signature;</para><para>(vi)
The class of motor vehicle which the holder is authorized to operate and any
applicable endorsements or restrictions;</para><para>(vii) The issuance and
expiration date of the license or card;</para><para>(viii) The organ and tissue
donation information specified in section 60-494; and</para><para>(ix) Such
other marks and information as the director may determine.</para><para>(c)
Each operator's license and state identification card shall contain the following
encoded, machine-readable information: The holder's full legal name; date
of birth; gender; race or ethnicity; document issue date; document expiration
date; principal residence address; unique identification number; revision
date; inventory control number; and state of issuance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1929, c. 148, &#167; 4, p. 513; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-404; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 14, p. 512; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-404; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-406; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 286, &#167; 2, p. 1082; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 315, &#167; 4, p. 1000; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 316, &#167; 4, p. 1008; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 90, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-406; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 13.</para></source> </law></legaldoc>
