<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id24" statutenumber="60-4,118.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id26">60-4,118.06</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Ignition
interlock permit; issued; when; operation restrictions; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receipt by the director of (a) a certified copy of a court
order issued pursuant to section 60-6,211.05, a certified copy of an order
for installation of an ignition interlock device and issuance of an ignition
interlock permit pursuant to subdivision (1), (2),  or (3) of section 60-6,197.03,
or a copy of an order from the Board of Pardons pursuant to section 83-1,127.02,
(b) sufficient evidence that the person has surrendered his or her operator's
license to the Department of Motor Vehicles and installed an approved ignition
interlock device in accordance with such order, and (c) payment of the fee
provided in section 60-4,115, such person may apply for an ignition interlock
permit. A person subject to administrative license revocation under section
60-498.02 shall be eligible for an ignition interlock permit as provided in
such section. The director shall issue an ignition interlock permit for the
operation of a motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device. Any
person issued an ignition interlock permit pursuant to a court order shall
only operate the motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device
to and from his or her residence, his or her place of employment, his or her
school, an alcohol treatment program, or an ignition interlock
service facility. The permit shall indicate for which purposes the permit
may be used. All permits issued pursuant to this subsection shall indicate
that the permit is not valid for the operation of any commercial motor vehicle.</para>
<para>(2) Upon expiration of the revocation period or upon expiration of an
order issued by the Board of Pardons pursuant to section 83-1,127.02, a person
may apply to the department in writing for issuance of an operator's license.
Regardless of whether the license surrendered by such person under subsection
(1) of this section has expired, the person shall apply for a new operator's
license pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act.</para>
<para>(3) A person who operates a motor vehicle in violation of the purposes
for operation indicated on the ignition interlock permit shall be guilty of
a Class II misdemeanor, shall have his or her ignition interlock permit revoked,
and shall serve the balance of any revocation period without the privilege
to operate a motor vehicle using an ignition interlock device.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB497, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB924, &#167;  2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>