<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,127</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates; design requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The department, in designing Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates, shall:</para><para>(a) Include the word Cornhuskers or Huskers prominently in the design;</para><para>(b) Use scarlet and cream colors in the design or such other similar colors as the department determines to best represent the official team colors of the University of Nebraska Cornhuskers athletic programs and to provide suitable reflection and contrast;</para><para>(c) Use cream or a similar color for the background of the design and scarlet or a similar color for the printing; and</para><para>(d) Create a design reflecting support for the University of Nebraska Cornhuskers athletic programs in consultation with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Athletic Department. The design shall be selected on the basis of (i) enhancing the marketability of spirit plates to supporters of University of Nebraska Cornhuskers athletic programs and (ii) limiting the manufacturing cost of each spirit plate to an amount less than or equal to the amount charged for license plates pursuant to section 60-3,102.</para><para>(2) One type of Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates shall be consecutively numbered spirit plates. The department shall:</para><para>(a) Number the spirit plates consecutively beginning with the number one, using numerals the size of which maximizes legibility; and</para><para>(b) Not use a county designation or any characters other than numbers on the spirit plates.</para><para>(3) One type of Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates shall be personalized message spirit plates. Such plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for message plates in subsection (2) of section 60-3,118. The characters used shall consist only of letters and numerals of the same size and design and shall comply with the requirements of subdivision (1)(a) of section 60-3,100. A maximum of seven characters may be used.</para><para>(4) The department shall cease to issue Nebraska Cornhusker Spirit Plates beginning with the next license plate issuance cycle after the license plate issuance cycle that begins in 2023 pursuant to section 60-3,101 if the total number of registered vehicles that obtained such plates is less than five hundred per year within any prior consecutive two-year period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 127; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB356, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 22. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>