  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,211.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,211.02</statuteno><catchline>Implied consent to submit to chemical test; when test administered; refusal; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who operates or has in his or her actual physical control a motor vehicle in this state shall be deemed to have given his or her consent to submit to a chemical test or tests of his or her blood or breath for the purpose of determining the concentration of alcohol in such blood or breath.</para><para>(2) Any peace officer who has been duly authorized to make arrests for violations of traffic laws of this state or of ordinances of any city or village may require any person under twenty-one years of age to submit to a chemical test or tests of his or her blood or breath for the purpose of determining the concentration of alcohol in such blood or breath when the officer has probable cause to believe that such person was driving or was in the actual physical control of a motor vehicle in this state in violation of section 60-6,211.01. Such peace officer may require such person to submit to a preliminary breath test. Any person who refuses to submit to such preliminary breath test or whose preliminary breath test results indicate an alcohol concentration in violation of section 60-6,211.01 shall be placed under arrest.</para><para>(3) Any person arrested as provided in this section may, upon the direction of a peace officer, be required to submit to a chemical test or tests of his or her blood or breath for a determination of the concentration of alcohol. If the chemical test discloses the presence of a concentration of alcohol in violation of section 60-6,211.01, the person shall be found guilty of a traffic infraction as defined in section 60-672 and upon conviction shall have his or her operator's license impounded by the court for thirty days for each violation of section 60-6,211.01. Any person who refuses to submit to such test or tests required pursuant to this section shall not have the tests taken but shall be found guilty of a traffic infraction as defined in section 60-672 and upon conviction shall have his or her operator's license impounded by the court for ninety days for refusal to submit to such tests required pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 564, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 