<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id38"  statutenumber="60-154"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-154</statuteno><catchline id="id41">Fees.</catchline><para>(1)(a) For each original certificate of title issued by a county for a motor vehicle or trailer, the fee shall be ten dollars. Three dollars and twenty-five cents shall be retained by the county. Four dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund. Two dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund. Seventy-five cents shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit as follows: Twenty cents to the Motor Vehicle Fraud Cash Fund; forty-five cents to the Nebraska State Patrol Cash Fund; and ten cents to the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Fund.</para><para>(b) For each original certificate of title issued by a county for an all-terrain vehicle, a utility-type vehicle, or a minibike, the fee shall be ten dollars. Three dollars and twenty-five cents shall be retained by the county. Four dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund. Two dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund. Seventy-five cents shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit as follows: Twenty cents to the Motor Vehicle Fraud Cash Fund; and fifty-five cents to the Nebraska State Patrol Cash Fund.</para><para>(2) For each original certificate of title issued by the department for a vehicle except as provided in section 60-159.01, the fee shall be ten dollars. Four dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund. Six dollars shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Motor Carrier Division Cash Fund.</para><para>(3) An approved licensed dealer participating in the electronic dealer services system pursuant to section 60-1507 may collect the fees prescribed by this section and shall remit any such fees to the appropriate county treasurer or the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>