<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-538"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-538</statuteno><catchline>Policy; mandatory provisions.</catchline><para>Every motor vehicle liability policy shall be subject to the following provisions which need not be contained therein: (1) The liability of the insurance carrier with respect to the insurance required by sections 60-501 to 60-569 shall become absolute whenever injury or damage covered by said motor vehicle liability policy occurs; said policy may not be canceled or annulled as to such liability by any agreement between the insurance carrier and the insured after the occurrence of the injury or damage; no statement made by the insured or on his behalf and no violation of said policy shall defeat or void said policy; (2) the satisfaction by the insured of a judgment for such injury or damage shall not be a condition precedent to the right or duty of the insurance carrier to make payment on account of such injury or damage; (3) the insurance carrier shall have the right to settle any claim covered by the policy and, if such settlement is made in good faith, the amount thereof shall be deductible from the limits of liability specified in subsection (2) of section 60-534; and (4) the policy, the written application therefor, if any, and any rider or endorsement which does not conflict with the provisions of sections 60-501 to 60-569 shall constitute the entire contract between the parties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 178, &#167; 38, p. 496. </para></source><annotation><para>Operation of newly acquired automobile without notifying the insurer does not constitute defense against third-party claim. Smith v. Canal Ins. Co., 184 Neb. 866, 173 N.W.2d 36 (1969).</para><para>The first accident is not within the purview of this act. Reserve Ins. Co. v. Aguilera, 181 Neb. 605, 150 N.W.2d 114 (1967).</para><para>Coverage of policy not certified was not limited by lower limits of statute. Universal Underwriters Ins. Co. v. Wagner, 367 F.2d 866 (8th Cir. 1966).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 