<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,117</statuteno><catchline>Operator's license or state identification card; form; county treasurer;
duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Upon
presentation of an issuance certificate for an operator's license or state
identification card issued by department personnel to the applicant, the county
treasurer shall collect the applicable fee and surcharge as prescribed in
section 60-4,115 and issue a receipt which is valid for up to thirty days.
If there is cause for an operator's license to be issued, the receipt shall
also authorize driving privileges for such thirty-day period. The license
or card shall be delivered as provided in section 60-4,113.</para>
<para>(2) The operator's license
and state identification card shall be in a form prescribed by the department.
The license and card may include security features prescribed by the department.
The license and card shall be conspicuously marked Nebraska Operator's License
or Nebraska Identification Card, shall be, to the maximum extent practicable,
tamper and forgery proof, and shall include the following information:</para>
<para>(a) The full legal name and
principal residence address of the holder;</para>
<para>(b) The holder's full facial
digital image;</para>
<para>(c) A physical description
of the holder, including gender, height, weight, and eye and hair colors;</para>
<para>(d) The holder's date of birth;</para>
<para>(e) The holder's signature;</para>
<para>(f) The class of motor vehicle
which the holder is authorized to operate and any applicable endorsements
or restrictions;</para>
<para>(g) The issuance and expiration
date of the license or card;</para>
<para>(h) The organ and tissue donation
information specified in section 60-494; and</para>
<para>(i) Such other marks and information
as the director may determine.</para>
<para>(3) Each operator's license
and state identification card shall contain the following encoded, machine-readable
information: The holder's full legal name; date of birth; gender; race or
ethnicity; document issue date; document expiration date; principal residence
address; unique identification number; revision date; inventory control number;
and state of issuance.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
1929, c. 148, &#167; 4, p. 513; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-404; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 14, p. 512; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-404; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-406; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 286, &#167; 2, p. 1082; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 315, &#167; 4, p. 1000; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 316, &#167; 4, p. 1008; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 90, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-406; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 14.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
