<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,189" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,189</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Driving over bridges; maximum speed; determination by Department of Transportation or local authority; effect.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) No person shall drive a vehicle over any public bridge, causeway, viaduct, or other elevated structure at a speed which is greater than the maximum speed which can be maintained with safety thereon when such structure is posted with signs as provided in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para id="id00">(2) The Department of Transportation or a local authority may conduct an investigation of any bridge or other elevated structure constituting a part of a highway under its jurisdiction, and if it finds that such structure cannot safely withstand vehicles traveling at the speed otherwise permissible, the department or local authority shall determine and declare the maximum speed of vehicles which such structure can safely withstand and shall cause suitable signs stating such maximum speed to be erected and maintained before each end of such structure.</para><para id="id00">(3) Upon the trial of any person charged with a violation of subsection (1) of this section, proof of such determination of the maximum speed by the department or local authority and the existence of such signs shall constitute conclusive evidence of the maximum speed which can be maintained with safety on such bridge or structure.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 285; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 214. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Operator's license,</emphasis> assessment of points for speeding, see section 60-4,182 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Unreasonable classification of persons is not created hereby. State ex rel. Douglas v. Gradwohl, 194 Neb. 745, 235 N.W.2d 854 (1975).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>