<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id40" statutenumber="60-396"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-396</statuteno><catchline id="id43">Credit of fees; vehicle disabled or removed from service.</catchline><para>Whenever the registered owner files an application with the county treasurer showing that a motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is disabled and has been removed from service, the registered owner may, by returning the registration certificate, the license plates, and, when appropriate, the validation decals or, in the case of the unavailability of such registration certificate or certificates, license plates, or validation decals, then by making an affidavit to the county treasurer of such disablement and removal from service, receive a credit for a portion of the registration fee from the fee deposited with the State Treasurer at the time of registration based upon the number of unexpired months remaining in the registration year except as otherwise provided in sections 60-3,121, 60-3,122.02, 60-3,122.04, 60-3,128, 60-3,224, 60-3,227, 60-3,233, 60-3,235, 60-3,238, 60-3,240, 60-3,242, 60-3,244, 60-3,246, 60-3,248, 60-3,250, 60-3,252, and 60-3,254. The owner shall also receive a credit for the unused portion of the motor vehicle tax and fee based upon the number of unexpired months remaining in the registration year. When the owner registers a replacement motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer at the time of filing such affidavit, the credit may be immediately applied against the registration fee and the motor vehicle tax and fee for the replacement motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer. When no such replacement motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is so registered, the county treasurer shall forward the application and affidavit, if any, to the State Treasurer who shall determine the amount, if any, of the allowable credit for the registration fee and issue a credit certificate to the owner. For the motor vehicle tax and fee, the county treasurer shall determine the amount, if any, of the allowable credit and issue a credit certificate to the owner. When such motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is removed from service within the same month in which it was registered, no credits shall be allowed for such month. The credits may be applied against taxes and fees for new or replacement motor vehicles, trailers, or semitrailers incurred within one year after cancellation of registration of the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer for which the credits were allowed. When any such motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is reregistered within the same registration year in which its registration has been canceled, the taxes and fees shall be that portion of the registration fee and the motor vehicle tax and fee for the remainder of the registration year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB570, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB383, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB220, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB474, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB46, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB138, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB356, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>