<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,220"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,220</statuteno><catchline>Lights; vehicle being driven; vehicle parked on freeway.</catchline><para>Whenever a motor vehicle is parked or stopped upon a roadway or shoulder adjacent thereto, whether attended or unattended, during the times mentioned in section 60-6,219, such vehicle shall be equipped with one or more lights which shall exhibit a light in such color as designated by the Department of Motor Vehicles on the roadway side visible from a distance of five hundred feet to the front of such vehicle and a red light visible from a distance of five hundred feet to the rear, except that a local authority may provide by ordinance that no lights need be displayed upon any such vehicle when stopped or parked in accordance with local parking regulations upon a highway where there is sufficient light to reveal any person or obstruction within a distance of five hundred feet upon such highway.</para><para>Any lighted headlights upon a parked vehicle shall be depressed or dimmed and turnsignals shall not be flashed on one side only. On a freeway, the operator of any parked vehicle shall also turn on its interior lights if operable and vehicles equipped with an emergency switch for flashing all directional turnsignals simultaneously shall exhibit such turnsignals.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1935, c. 134, &#167; 9, p. 489; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-11,105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,112; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 184, &#167; 32, p. 564; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 192, &#167; 2, p. 590; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,112; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-670.01; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 316. </para></source><annotation><para>Evidence of violation of this section is evidence of negligence or contributory negligence. Horst v. Johnson, 237 Neb. 155, 465 N.W.2d 461 (1991).</para><para>Instruction on requirements of this section covered parking and lights. Segebart v. Gregory, 160 Neb. 64, 69 N.W.2d 315 (1955).</para><para>Prohibition against parking without lights did not apply to motor vehicle temporarily disabled. Haight v. Nelson, 157 Neb. 341, 59 N.W.2d 576 (1953).</para><para>It is unlawful to park automobile on highway at night without appropriate lights. Segebart v. Gregory, 156 Neb. 261, 55 N.W.2d 678 (1952).</para><para>Violation of this section is not negligence per se but evidence of negligence. Anderson v. Robbins Incubator Co., 143 Neb. 40, 8 N.W.2d 446 (1943).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>