<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id69">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id71"  statutenumber="60-137"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-137</statuteno><catchline id="id74">Act; applicability.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act applies to
all vehicles as defined in the act, except:</para>
<para>(a) Farm trailers;</para>
<para>(b) Well-boring apparatus,
backhoes, bulldozers, and front-end loaders; and</para>
<para>(c) Trucks and buses from
other jurisdictions required to pay registration fees under the Motor Vehicle
Registration Act, except a vehicle registered or eligible to be registered
as part of a fleet of apportionable vehicles under section 60-3,198.</para>
<para>(2)(a) All new all-terrain
vehicles and minibikes sold on or after January 1, 2004, shall be required
to have a certificate of title. An owner of an all-terrain vehicle or minibike
sold prior to such date may apply for a certificate of title for such all-terrain
vehicle or minibike as provided in rules and regulations of the department.</para>
<para>(b) All new
low-speed vehicles sold on or after January 1, 2012, shall be required to
have a certificate of title. An owner of a low-speed vehicle sold prior to
such date may apply for a certificate of title for such low-speed vehicle
as provided in rules and regulations of the department.</para>
<para>(3) An owner of a utility trailer may apply for a certificate
of title upon compliance with the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Every owner of a manufactured home or mobile home shall
obtain a certificate of title for the manufactured home or mobile home prior
to affixing it to real estate.</para>
<para>(b) If a manufactured home or mobile home has been affixed
to real estate and a certificate of title was not issued before it was so
affixed, the owner of such manufactured home or mobile home shall apply for
and be issued a certificate of title at any time for surrender and cancellation
as provided in section 60-169.</para>
<para>(5) All new utility-type vehicles sold on or after January
1, 2011, shall be required to have a certificate of title. An owner of a utility-type
vehicle sold prior to such date may apply for a certificate of title for such
utility-type vehicle as provided in rules and regulations of the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 765, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB953, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB289, &#167; 9.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>There is no legal requirement that a lien be noted on a certificate of title purportedly covering property not subject to the Certificate of Title Act, even though a certificate of title for such property has been issued. Cushman Sales &amp; Service of Nebraska, Inc. v. Muirhead, 201 Neb. 495, 268 N.W.2d 440 (1978).</para><para>Under the Nebraska Certificate of Title Act, a certificate of title is the exclusive method provided by statute for the transfer of title to an automobile, but it is not conclusive of ownership. First Nat. Bank &amp; Trust Co. v. Ohio Cas. Ins. Co., 196 Neb. 595, 244 N.W.2d 209 (1976).</para><para>Certificate of Title Act applies to all motor vehicles required to be licensed with specified exceptions. Bank of Keystone v. Kayton, 155 Neb. 79, 50 N.W.2d 511 (1951).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>