<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id121">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id123" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-3,122.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,122.03</statuteno><catchline>Military Honor Plates.</catchline>
<para>(1)
The department shall design license plates to be known as Military Honor Plates.
The department shall create designs honoring persons who have served or are
serving in the United States Army, United States Navy, United States Marine
Corps, United States Coast Guard, United States Air Force, or National Guard.
There shall be six designs, one for each of such armed forces reflecting its
official emblem, official seal, or other official image. The issuance of plates
for each of such armed forces shall be conditioned on the approval of the
armed forces owning the copyright to the official emblem, official seal, or
other official image. A person may qualify for a Military Honor Plate by registering
with the Department of Veterans' Affairs pursuant to section 80-414. The Department
of Motor Vehicles shall verify the applicant's eligibility for a plate created
pursuant to this section by consulting the registry established by the Department
of Veterans' Affairs.</para>
<para>(2) The design
shall be selected on the basis of limiting the manufacturing cost of each
plate to an amount less than or equal to the amount charged for license plates
pursuant to section 60-3,102. The Department of Motor Vehicles shall make
applications available for each type of plate when it is designed. The department
may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section and
section 60-3,122.04.</para><para>(3) One type of Military Honor Plates shall
be alphanumeric plates. The department shall:</para><para>(a) Assign a designation
up to five characters; and</para><para>(b) Not use a county designation.</para>
<para>(4)
One type of Military Honor Plates shall be personalized message plates. Such
plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for personalized
message license plates in section 60-3,118, except that a maximum of five
characters may be used.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB383, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>