<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id293" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-4,146"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,146</statuteno><catchline id="id296">Application; requirements of federal law; certification.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to certifying himself or herself under this section, an applicant shall also certify himself or herself under section 60-4,144.01.</para><para>(2) Upon making application pursuant to section 60-4,144 or 60-4,148.01, any applicant who operates or expects to operate a commercial motor vehicle in interstate or foreign commerce and who is not subject to 49 C.F.R. part 391 shall certify that he or she is not subject to 49 C.F.R. part 391. Any applicant making certification pursuant to this subsection shall meet the physical and vision requirements established in section 60-4,118 and shall be subject to the provisions of such section.</para><para>(3) Upon making application pursuant to section 60-4,144 or 60-4,148.01, any applicant who operates or expects to operate a commercial motor vehicle solely in intrastate commerce and who is subject to 49 C.F.R. part 391 adopted pursuant to section 75-363 shall certify that the applicant meets the qualification requirements of 49 C.F.R. part 391.</para><para>(4) Upon making application for a CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial driver's license, any applicant who operates or expects to operate a commercial motor vehicle solely in intrastate commerce and who is not subject to 49 C.F.R. part 391 adopted pursuant to section 75-363 shall certify that he or she is not subject to 49 C.F.R. part 391. Any applicant making certification pursuant to this subsection shall meet the physical and vision requirements established in section 60-4,118 and shall be subject to the provisions of such section.</para><para>(5) An applicant who certifies that he or she is not subject to 49 C.F.R. part 391 under subsection (2) or (4) of this section shall answer the following questions on the application:</para><para>(a) Have you within the last three months (e.g. due to diabetes, epilepsy, mental illness, head injury, stroke, heart condition, neurological disease, etc.):</para><para>(i) lost voluntary control or consciousness ... yes ... no</para><para>(ii) experienced vertigo or multiple episodes of dizziness or fainting ... yes ... no</para><para>(iii) experienced disorientation ... yes ... no</para><para>(iv) experienced seizures ... yes ... no</para><para>(v) experienced impairment of memory, memory loss ... yes ... no</para><para>Please explain: .........................................</para><para>(b) Do you experience any condition which affects your ability to operate a motor vehicle? (e.g. due to loss of, or impairment of, foot, leg, hand, arm; neurological or neuromuscular disease, etc.) ... yes ... no</para><para>Please explain: .........................................</para><para>(c) Since the issuance of your last driver's license/permit has your health or medical condition changed or worsened? ... yes ... no</para><para>Please explain, including how the above affects your ability to drive: .................................................</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 211, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 938, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB977, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB644, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>