<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id170">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id172" statutenumber="60-6,355"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,355</statuteno><catchline id="id175">All-terrain
vehicle, defined; utility-type vehicle, defined.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of sections 60-6,355 to 60-6,362:</para>
<para>(a) All-terrain vehicle means any motorized off-highway vehicle
which (i) is fifty inches or less in width, (ii) has a dry weight of nine
hundred pounds or less, (iii) travels on three or more low-pressure tires,
(iv) is designed for operator use only with no passengers or is specifically
designed by the original manufacturer for the operator and one passenger,
(v) has a seat or saddle designed to be straddled by the operator, and (vi)
has handlebars or any other steering assembly for steering control; and</para>
<para>(b)(i) Utility-type vehicle means any motorized off-highway
vehicle which (A) is not less than forty-eight inches nor more than seventy-four
inches in width, (B) is not more than one hundred thirty-five inches, including
the bumper, in length, (C) has a dry weight of not less than nine hundred
pounds nor more than two thousand pounds, (D) travels on four or more low-pressure
tires, and (E) is equipped with a steering wheel and bench or bucket-type
seating designed for at least two people to sit side-by-side.</para>
<para>(ii) Utility-type vehicle does not include golf car vehicles or low-speed vehicles.</para>
<para>(2) All-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles which
have been modified to include additional equipment not required by sections
60-6,357 and 60-6,358 shall not be required to be registered under the Motor
Vehicle Registration Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 80, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-2801; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 451; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 333, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 250; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1155, &#167; 24.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>