<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id202">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id204" statutenumber="60-484.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-484.02</statuteno><catchline id="id207">Digital images
and signatures; use; confidentiality; prohibited
acts; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Each
applicant for an operator's license or state identification card shall have
his or her digital image captured. Digital images shall
be preserved for use as prescribed in sections 60-4,119, 60-4,151, and 60-4,180.
The images shall be used for issuing operators' licenses and state identification
cards. The images may be retrieved only by the Department of Motor Vehicles
for issuing renewal and
replacement operators' licenses and state identification cards and may not
be otherwise released except in accordance with subsection (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(2) Upon application for an operator's license or state identification
card, each applicant shall provide his or her signature in a form prescribed
by the department. Digital signatures shall be preserved for use on original,
renewal, and
replacement operators' licenses and state identification cards and may not
be otherwise released except<?Pub Caret?> in accordance with subsection (4) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) No officer, employee, agent, or contractor of the department
or law enforcement officer shall release a digital image except to a federal,
state, or local law enforcement agency, a certified law enforcement officer
employed in an investigative position by a federal, state, or local agency,
or a driver licensing agency of another state for the purpose of carrying
out the functions of the agency or assisting another agency in carrying out
its functions upon the verification of the identity of the person requesting
the release of the information and the verification of the purpose of the
requester in requesting the release. Any officer, employee, agent, or contractor
of the department or law enforcement officer that knowingly discloses or knowingly
permits disclosure of a digital image or digital signature in violation of
this section shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(4) No officer,
employee, agent, or contractor of the department or law enforcement officer
shall release a digital signature except (a) to a federal, state, or local
law enforcement agency, a certified law enforcement officer employed in an
investigative position by a state or federal agency, or a driver licensing
agency of another state for the purpose of carrying out the functions of the
agency or assisting another agency in carrying out its functions upon the
verification of the identity of the person requesting the release of the information
and the verification of the purpose of the requester in requesting the release
or (b) to the office of the Secretary of State for the purpose of voter registration
as described in section 32-304, 32-308, or 32-309 upon the verification of
the identity of the person requesting the release of the information and the
verification of the purpose of the requester in requesting the release. No
employee or official in the office of the Secretary of State shall release
a digital signature except to a federal, state, or local law enforcement agency,
a certified law enforcement officer employed in an investigative position
by a state or federal agency, or a driver licensing agency of another state
for the purpose of carrying out the functions of the agency or assisting another
agency in carrying out its functions upon the verification of the identity
of the person requesting the release of the information and the verification
of the purpose of the requester in requesting the release. Any officer, employee,
agent, or contractor of the department, law enforcement officer, or employee
or official in the office of the Secretary of State that knowingly discloses
or knowingly permits disclosure of a digital signature in violation of this
section shall be guilty of a Class I misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 560, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 1, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB372, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB805, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB661, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB777, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
