<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,189"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,189</statuteno><catchline>Tax exemption; procedure; appeal.</catchline>
<para>(1) A veteran of the United States Armed Forces who qualifies for an
exemption from the motor vehicle tax under subdivision (2) of section 60-3,185
shall apply for the exemption to the county treasurer not more than
fifteen days before and not later than thirty days after the registration
date for the motor vehicle. A renewal application shall be made annually not
sooner than the first day of the last month of the registration period or
later than the last day of the registration period. The county treasurer shall
approve or deny the application and notify the applicant of his or her decision
within twenty days after the filing of the application. An applicant may appeal
the denial of an application to the county board of equalization within twenty
days after the date the notice was mailed.</para>
<para>(2) An organization which qualifies for an exemption from the motor
vehicle tax under subdivision (6) of section 60-3,185 shall apply for the
exemption to the county treasurer not more than fifteen days before and
not later than thirty days after the registration date for the motor vehicle.
For a newly acquired motor vehicle, an application for exemption must be made
within thirty days after the purchase date. A renewal application shall be
made annually not sooner than the first day of the last month of the registration
period or later than the last day of the registration period. The county treasurer shall
examine the application and recommend either exempt or nonexempt status to
the county board of equalization within twenty days after receipt of the application.
The county board of equalization, after a hearing on ten days' notice to the
applicant and after considering the recommendation of the county treasurer and
any other information it may obtain, shall approve or deny the exemption on
the basis of law and of rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the
Tax Commissioner within thirty days after the hearing. The county board of
equalization shall mail or deliver its final decision to the applicant and
the county treasurer within seven days after the date of decision.
The decision of the county board of equalization may be appealed to the Tax
Equalization and Review Commission in accordance with the Tax Equalization
and Review Commission Act within thirty days after the final decision.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 189; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 90.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Tax Equalization and Review Commission Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5001.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>