<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,237"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,237</statuteno><catchline>Wildlife Conservation Plates; design.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall design license plates to be known as Wildlife Conservation Plates. The department shall create no more than three designs reflecting support for the conservation of Nebraska wildlife, including sandhill cranes, bighorn sheep, and ornate box turtles. Each design shall be selected on the basis of limiting the manufacturing cost of each plate to an amount less than or equal to the amount charged for license plates pursuant to section 60-3,102. The department shall make applications available for this type of plate by January 1, 2021. The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section and section 60-3,238.</para><para>(2) One type of Wildlife Conservation Plates shall be alphanumeric plates. The department shall:</para><para>(a) Assign a designation up to five characters; and</para><para>(b) Not use a county designation.</para><para>(3) One type of Wildlife Conservation Plates shall be personalized message plates. Such plates shall be issued subject to the same conditions specified for personalized message license plates in section 60-3,118, except that a maximum of five characters may be used.</para><para>(4) The department shall cease to issue Wildlife Conservation Plates beginning with the next license plate issuance cycle after the license plate issuance cycle that begins in 2023 pursuant to section 60-3,101 if the total number of registered vehicles that obtained such plates is less than five hundred per year within any prior consecutive two-year period.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB356, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 34. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>