<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id90"><sectno id="id91" opdate="July 18, 2008">Sec.
12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"
id="id92" statutenumber="60-376"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id94">60-376</statuteno><catchline id="id95">Operation
of vehicle without registration; In Transit sticker; records required; proof
of ownership.</catchline><para>Subject to all the provisions of law relating
to motor vehicles and trailers not inconsistent with this section, any motor
vehicle dealer or trailer dealer who is regularly engaged within this state
in the business of buying and selling motor vehicles and trailers, who regularly
maintains within this state an established place of business, and who desires
to effect delivery of any motor vehicle or trailer bought or sold by him or
her from the point where purchased or sold to points within or outside this
state may, solely for the purpose of such delivery by himself or herself,
his or her agent, or a bona fide purchaser, operate such motor vehicle or
tow such trailer on the highways of this state without charge or registration
of such motor vehicle or trailer. A sticker shall be displayed on the front
and rear windows or the rear side windows of such motor vehicle, except a
motorcycle, and displayed on the front and rear of each such trailer. On the
sticker shall be plainly printed in black letters the words In Transit. One
In Transit sticker shall be displayed on a motorcycle, which sticker may be
one-half the size required for other motor vehicles. Such stickers shall include
a registration number, which registration number shall be different for each
sticker or pair of stickers issued, and the contents of such sticker and the
numbering system shall be as prescribed by the department. Each dealer issuing
such stickers shall keep a record of the registration number of each sticker
or pair of stickers on the invoice of such sale. Such sticker shall allow
such owner to operate the motor vehicle or tow such trailer for a period of
thirty days in order to effect proper registration of the new or used motor
vehicle or trailer. When any person, firm, or corporation has had a motor
vehicle or trailer previously registered and license plates assigned to such
person, firm, or corporation, such owner may operate the motor vehicle or
tow such trailer for a period of thirty days in order to effect transfer of
plates to the new or used motor vehicle or trailer. Upon demand of proper
authorities, there shall be presented by the person in charge of such motor
vehicle or trailer, for examination, a duly executed bill of sale therefor
or other satisfactory evidence of the right of possession by such person of
such motor vehicle or trailer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws
2005, LB 274, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>A
vehicle may be operated for 15 days without being registered pursuant to section
60-302, provided that it properly displays "In Transit" decals. State v. Childs,
242 Neb. 426, 495 N.W.2d 475 (1993).</para><para>This section provides for
in-transit tags to be issued by a licensed dealer; it does not allow private
sellers to issue in-transit tags. Thus, such handwritten tags are not entitled
to the presumption of compliance that we have afforded dealer-issued tags.
The law enforcement officer has reasonable suspicion to stop a motor vehicle
when he or she sees such vehicle being operated on the public streets without
license plates and without dealer-issued in-transit tags. Upon demand, the
driver of such vehicle must show documents proving compliance with motor vehicle
registration laws. State v. Kling, 8 Neb. App. 631, 599 N.W.2d 240 (1999).</para><para>
"Display" of in-transit decals as described in this section logically implies
a display of the decal which is visible. State v. Reiter, 3 Neb. App. 153,
524 N.W.2d 575 (1994).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
