<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id21">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id23" statutenumber="60-4,118.06"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,118.06</statuteno><catchline id="id26">Ignition
interlock permit; issued; when; operation restriction; revocation of
permit by director; when.</catchline><para>(1) Upon receipt by the
director of (a) a certified copy of a court order issued pursuant to section
60-6,211.05, a certified copy of an order for installation of an ignition
interlock device and issuance of an ignition interlock permit pursuant to
section 60-6,197.03, or a copy of an order from the Board of Pardons pursuant
to section 83-1,127.02, (b) sufficient evidence that the person has surrendered
his or her operator's license to the department and installed an approved
ignition interlock device in accordance with such order, and (c) payment of
the fee provided in section 60-4,115, such person may apply for an ignition
interlock permit. A person subject to administrative license revocation under
sections 60-498.01 to 60-498.04 shall be eligible for an ignition interlock
permit as provided in such sections. The director shall issue an ignition
interlock permit only for
the operation of a motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device. All
permits issued pursuant to this subsection shall indicate that the permit
is not valid for the operation of any commercial motor vehicle.</para>
<para>(2) Upon expiration of the revocation period or upon expiration
of an order issued by the Board of Pardons pursuant to section 83-1,127.02,
a person may apply to the department in writing for issuance of an operator's
license. Regardless of whether the license surrendered by such person under
subsection (1) of this section has expired, the person shall apply for a new
operator's license pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act.</para>
<para>(3)(a) An ignition interlock permit shall not be issued under
this section or sections 60-498.01 to 60-498.04 to any person except in cases
of a violation of subdivision (3)(b) or (c) of section 28-306, subdivision
(3)(b) or (c) of section 28-394, or section 28-1254, 60-6,196, 60-6,197, or
60-6,197.06.</para>
<para>(b) An ignition interlock permit shall only be available to
a holder of a Class M or O operator's license.</para>
<para>(4) The director shall revoke a person's ignition interlock
permit issued under this section or sections 60-498.01 to 60-498.04 upon receipt
of an (a) abstract of conviction indicating that the person had his or her
operating privileges revoked or canceled or (b) administrative order revoking
or canceling the person's operating privileges, if such conviction or order
resulted from an incident other than the incident which resulted in the application
for the ignition interlock permit.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB497, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB924, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB667, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB158, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>