<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,161"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,161</statuteno><catchline>Turning or moving right or left upon a roadway; required signals; signals prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall turn a vehicle or move right or left upon a roadway unless and until such movement can be made with reasonable safety nor without giving an appropriate signal in the manner provided in sections 60-6,162 and 60-6,163.</para><para>(2) A signal of intention to turn or move right or left when required shall be given continuously during not less than the last one hundred feet traveled by the vehicle before turning.</para><para>(3) No person shall stop or suddenly decrease the speed of a vehicle without first giving an appropriate signal in the manner provided in such sections to the driver of any vehicle immediately to the rear when there is opportunity to give such signal.</para><para>(4) The brake and turnsignal lights required on vehicles by section 60-6,226 shall not be flashed on one side only on a disabled vehicle, flashed as a courtesy or do pass signal to operators of other vehicles approaching from the rear, or flashed on one side only of a parked vehicle except as may be necessary for compliance with this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 52; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-652; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 257. </para></source><annotation><para>The giving of the statutorily required turn signal is not enough; one must exercise reasonable care under all the circumstances. Huntwork v. Voss, 247 Neb. 184, 525 N.W.2d 632 (1995).</para><para>A driver is charged with exercising due diligence to determine whether it is safe to turn left on a roadway. Mitchell v. Kesting, 221 Neb. 506, 378 N.W.2d 188 (1985).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 