<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id253" statutenumber="60-4,120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,120</statuteno><catchline id="id256">Operator's license; state
identification card; replacement.</catchline><para>(1) Any person duly licensed or holding a valid
state identification card issued under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License
Act who loses his or her operator's license or card may make application to
the department for a replacement license or card.</para>
<para>(2) If any person changes his or her name because of marriage or divorce
or by court order or a common-law name change, he or she shall apply to the
department for a replacement operator's license or state identification card
and furnish proof of identification in accordance with section 60-484. If
any person changes his or her address, the person shall apply to the department
for a replacement operator's license or state identification card and furnish
satisfactory evidence of such change. The application shall be made within
sixty days after the change of name or address.</para>
<para>(3) In the event a mutilated or unreadable operator's license
is held by any person duly licensed under the act or a mutilated or unreadable state identification card which
was issued under the act is held by a person, such person may obtain a replacement
license or card. Upon report of the mutilated or unreadable license or card
and application for a replacement license or card, a replacement license or
card may be issued if the department is satisfied that the original license or card is
mutilated or unreadable.</para>
<para>(4) If any person duly licensed under the act loses his or her operator's
license or if any holder of a state identification card loses his or her card
while temporarily out of the state, he or she may make application to the
department for a replacement operator's license
or card by
applying to the department and reporting such loss. Upon receipt of a correctly
completed application, the department shall cause to be issued a replacement operator's license or card.</para>
<para>(5) Any person who holds a valid operator's
license or state identification card without a digital
image shall surrender such license or card to the department within
thirty days after resuming residency in this state. After the thirty-day period,
such license or card shall be considered invalid and no license or card shall be issued until the individual
has made application for replacement or renewal.</para>
<para>(6) Application for a replacement operator's license
or state identification card shall include the information required under sections
60-484 and 60-484.04.</para>
<para>(7) An applicant may obtain a replacement operator's license or state identification
card pursuant to subsection (1) or (3) of this section by electronic means
in a manner prescribed by the department. No replacement license or card shall be
issued unless the applicant has a digital image and digital signature
preserved in the digital system.</para>
<para>(8) Each replacement
operator's license or state identification card shall be issued with the same
expiration date as the license or card for which the replacement is issued.
The replacement license or card shall also state the new issuance date. Upon
issuance of any replacement license or card, the license or card for which
the replacement is issued shall be void.</para><para>(9) A replacement operator's license or state identification
card issued under this section shall be delivered to the applicant as provided
in section 60-4,113 after the county treasurer or department collects the
fee and surcharge prescribed in section 60-4,115 and issues the applicant
a receipt with driving privileges which is valid for up to thirty days.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 148, &#167; 9, p. 517; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-409; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 19, p. 517; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 176, &#167; 2, p. 689; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-409; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-415; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 141, &#167; 8, p. 453; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 207, &#167; 4, p. 678; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 315, &#167; 10, p. 1005; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 316, &#167; 10, p. 1015; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 234, &#167; 7, p. 626; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 506, &#167; 2, p. 2083; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 134, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 371, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1296, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 90, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 606, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 46, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 811, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 575, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 284, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-415; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 126, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 201, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 572; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 1, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB777, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>