<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-505.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-505.02</statuteno><catchline>Reinstatement of license or registration; filing of proof of financial responsibility; payment of fees.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever a license is revoked and the filing of proof of financial responsibility is, by the Motor Vehicle Safety Responsibility Act, made a prerequisite to reinstatement of eligibility for a new license, no license shall be issued unless the licensee, in addition to complying with the other provisions of the act, pays to the Department of Motor Vehicles a reinstatement fee of one hundred twenty-five dollars. The fees paid pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit seventy-five dollars of each fee to the General Fund and fifty dollars of each fee to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(2) Whenever a license is suspended and the filing of proof of financial responsibility is, by the act, made a prerequisite to reinstatement of such license or to the issuance of a new license, no such license shall be reinstated or new license issued unless the licensee, in addition to complying with the other provisions of the act, pays to the department a fee of fifty dollars. The fees paid pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(3) When a registration is suspended and the filing of proof of financial responsibility is, by the act, made a prerequisite to reinstatement of the registration, no such registration shall be reinstated or new registration issued unless the registrant, in addition to complying with the act and the Motor Vehicle Registration Act, pays to the department a fee of fifty dollars. The fees paid pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 298, &#167; 4, p. 1110; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 672, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 236. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>