<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3,201.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3,201.01</statuteno><catchline>Motor carrier services system; build and maintain; Motor Carrier Services System Replacement and Maintenance Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Motor Vehicles shall build and maintain a new motor carrier services system for processing the issuance of vehicle registrations pursuant to section 60-3,198 and the assessment of the motor fuel tax under the International Fuel Tax Agreement Act. The Director of Motor Vehicles shall designate an implementation date for the new system which date is on or before July 1, 2025.</para><para>(2) The Motor Carrier Services System Replacement and Maintenance Fund is created. The fund shall consist of amounts credited under section 60-3,202. The fund shall be used for the building, implementation, and maintenance of a new motor carrier services system for processing the issuance of vehicle registrations pursuant to section 60-3,198 and the assessment of the motor fuel tax under the International Fuel Tax Agreement Act. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund or the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para><para>(3) Any money in the Motor Carrier Services System Replacement and Maintenance Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB113, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 139. </para><operativedate>May 22, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>International Fuel Tax Agreement Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1401.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>