<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id129" statutenumber="60-153"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-153</statuteno><catchline id="id132">Certificate of title; form; contents; secure power-of-attorney form.</catchline><para>(1) A certificate of title shall be printed upon safety security paper to be selected by the department. The certificate of title, manufacturer's statement of origin, and assignment of manufacturer's certificate shall be upon forms prescribed by the department and may include, but shall not be limited to, county of issuance, date of issuance, certificate of title number, previous certificate of title number, vehicle identification number, year, make, model, and body type of the vehicle, name and residential and mailing address of the owner, acquisition date, issuing county treasurer's signature and official seal, and sufficient space for the notation and release of liens, mortgages, or encumbrances, if any. A certificate of title issued on or after September 1, 2007, shall include the words "void if altered". A certificate of title that is altered shall be deemed a mutilated certificate of title. The certificate of title of an all-terrain vehicle, utility-type vehicle, or minibike shall include the words "not to be registered for road use".</para><para>(2) An assignment of certificate of title shall appear on each certificate of title and shall include, but not be limited to, a statement that the owner of the vehicle assigns all his or her right, title, and interest in the vehicle, the name and address of the assignee, the name and address of the lienholder or secured party, if any, and the signature of the owner or the owner's parent, legal guardian, foster parent, or agent in the case of an owner who is a handicapped or disabled person as defined in section 60-331.02.</para><para>(3) A reassignment by a dealer shall appear on each certificate of title and shall include, but not be limited to, a statement that the dealer assigns all his or her right, title, and interest in the vehicle, the name and address of the assignee, the name and address of the lienholder or secured party, if any, and the signature of the dealer or designated representative. Reassignments shall be printed on the reverse side of each certificate of title as many times as convenient.</para><para>(4) The department may prescribe a secure power-of-attorney form and may contract with one or more persons to develop, provide, sell, and distribute secure power-of-attorney forms in the manner authorized or required by the federal Truth in Mileage Act of 1986 and any other federal law or regulation. Any secure power-of-attorney form authorized pursuant to a contract shall conform to the terms of the contract and be in strict compliance with the requirements of the department.</para><para>(5) A certificate of title for a former military vehicle shall include the words "former military vehicle".</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB156, &#167; 5. </para></source><annotation><para>Execution of a certificate of title is the exclusive method of conveying ownership of a motor vehicle, but the certificate is not in itself conclusive evidence of ownership. Weiss v. Union Ins. Co., 202 Neb. 469, 276 N.W.2d 88 (1979).</para><para>There is no legal requirement that a lien be noted on a certificate of title purportedly covering property not subject to the Certificate of Title Act, even though a certificate of title for such property has been issued. Cushman Sales &amp; Service of Nebraska, Inc. v. Muirhead, 201 Neb. 495, 268 N.W.2d 440 (1978).</para><para>Certificate of title may be issued upon a manufacturer's certificate. Turpin v. Standard Reliance Ins. Co., 169 Neb. 233, 99 N.W.2d 26 (1959).</para><para>Application for certificate of title conformed to requirements of this section. State Farm Mutual Auto Ins. Co. v. Drawbaugh, 159 Neb. 149, 65 N.W.2d 542 (1954).</para><para>Assignment of certificate of title must be sworn to in order to be valid. Loyal's Auto Exchange, Inc. v. Munch, 153 Neb. 628, 45 N.W.2d 913 (1951).</para><para>Form of certificate of title to motor vehicle prescribed by this section provides headings and space for the notation of liens thereon. Securities Credit Corp. v. Pindell, 153 Neb. 298, 44 N.W.2d 501 (1950).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>