<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,298"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,298</statuteno><catchline>Vehicles; size; weight; load; overweight;
special, continuing, or continuous permit; issuance discretionary; conditions;
penalty; continuing permit; fees.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The Department of
Roads or the Nebraska State Patrol, with respect to highways under its jurisdiction
including the National System of Interstate and Defense Highways, and local
authorities, with respect to highways under their jurisdiction, may in their
discretion upon application and good cause being shown therefor issue a special,
continuing, or continuous permit in writing authorizing the applicant or his
or her designee:</para>
<para>(i) To operate or move a vehicle, a combination of vehicles, or objects
of a size or weight of vehicle or load exceeding the maximum specified by
law when such permit is necessary:</para>
<para>(A) To further the national defense or the general welfare;</para>
<para>(B) To permit movement of cost-saving equipment to be used in highway
or other public construction or in agricultural land treatment; or</para>
<para>(C) Because of an emergency, an unusual circumstance, or a very special
situation;</para>
<para>(ii) To operate vehicles, for a distance up to one hundred twenty miles,
loaded up to fifteen percent greater than the maximum weight specified by
law, or up to ten
percent greater than the maximum length specified by law, or both, except that any combination with two or more cargo-carrying units,
not including the truck-tractor, also known as a longer combination vehicle,
may only operate for a distance up to seventy miles loaded up to fifteen percent
greater than the maximum weight specified by law, or up to ten percent greater than the
maximum length specified by law, or both, when carrying grain or other seasonally
harvested products from the field where such grain or products are harvested
to storage, market, or stockpile in the field or from stockpile to market
or factory when failure to move such grain or products in abundant quantities
would cause an economic loss to the person or persons whose grain or products
are being transported or when failure to move such grain or products in as
large quantities as possible would not be in the best interests of the national
defense or general welfare. The distance limitation may be waived for vehicles
when carrying dry beans from the field where harvested to storage or market
when dry beans are not normally stored, purchased, or used within the permittee's
local area and must be transported more than one hundred twenty miles to an
available marketing or storage destination. No permit shall authorize a weight
greater than twenty thousand pounds on any single axle;</para>
<para>(iii) To transport an implement of husbandry which does not exceed twelve
and one-half feet in width during daylight hours, except that the permit shall
not allow transport on holidays;</para>
<para>(iv) To operate one or more recreational vehicles, as defined in section
71-4603, exceeding the maximum width specified by law if movement of the recreational
vehicles is prior to retail sale and the recreational vehicles comply with
subdivision (2)(k) of section 60-6,288; or</para>
<para>(v) To operate an emergency vehicle for purposes of sale, demonstration,
exhibit, or delivery, if the applicant or his or her designee is a manufacturer
or sales agent of the emergency vehicle. No permit shall be issued for an
emergency vehicle which weighs over sixty thousand pounds on the tandem axle.</para>
<para>(b) No permit shall be issued under subdivision (a)(i) of this subsection
for a vehicle carrying a load unless such vehicle is loaded with an object
which exceeds the size or weight limitations, which cannot be dismantled or
reduced in size or weight without great difficulty, and which of necessity
must be moved over the highways to reach its intended destination. No permit
shall be required for the temporary movement on highways other than dustless-surfaced
state highways and for necessary access to points on such highways during
daylight hours of cost-saving equipment to be used in highway or other public
construction or in agricultural land treatment when such temporary movement
is necessary and for a reasonable distance.</para>
<para>(2) The application for any such permit shall specifically describe
the vehicle, the load to be operated or moved, whenever possible the particular
highways for which permit to operate is requested, and whether such permit
is requested for a single trip or for continuous or continuing operation. The permit shall include a signed affirmation
under oath that, for any load sixteen feet high or higher, the applicant has
contacted any and all electric utilities that have high voltage conductors
and infrastructure that cross over the roadway affected by the move and made
arrangements with such electric utilities for the safe movement of the load
under any high voltage conductors owned by such electric utilities.</para>
<para>(3) The department or local authority is authorized to issue or withhold
such permit at its discretion or, if such permit is issued, to limit the number
of days during which the permit is valid, to limit the number of trips, to
establish seasonal or other time limitations within which the vehicles described
may be operated on the highways indicated, or to issue a continuous or continuing
permit for use on all highways, including the National System of Interstate
and Defense Highways. The permits are subject to reasonable conditions as
to periodic renewal of such permit and as to operation or movement of such
vehicles. The department or local authority may otherwise limit or prescribe
conditions of operation of such vehicle or vehicles, when necessary to assure
against undue damage to the road foundations, surfaces, or structures or undue
danger to the public safety. The department or local authority may require
such undertaking or other security as may be deemed necessary to compensate
for any injury to any roadway or road structure.</para>
<para>(4) Every such permit shall be carried in the vehicle to which it refers
and shall be open to inspection by any peace officer, carrier enforcement
officer, or authorized agent of any authority granting such permit. Each such
permit shall state the maximum weight permissible on a single axle or combination
of axles and the total gross weight allowed. No person shall violate any of
the terms or conditions of such special permit. In case of any violation,
the permit shall be deemed automatically revoked and the penalty of the original
limitations shall be applied unless:</para>
<para>(a) The violation consists solely of exceeding the size or weight specified
by the permit, in which case only the penalty of the original size or weight
limitation exceeded shall be applied; or</para>
<para>(b) The total gross load is within the maximum authorized by the permit,
no axle is more than ten percent in excess of the maximum load for such axle
or group of axles authorized by the permit, and such load can be shifted to
meet the weight limitations of wheel and axle loads authorized by such permit.
Such shift may be made without penalty if it is made at the state or commercial
scale designated in the permit. The vehicle may travel from its point of origin
to such designated scale without penalty, and a scale ticket from such scale,
showing the vehicle to be properly loaded and within the gross and axle weights
authorized by the permit, shall be reasonable evidence of compliance with
the terms of the permit.</para>
<para>(5) The department or local authority issuing a permit as provided in
this section may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations with respect to
the issuance of permits provided for in this section.</para>
<para>(6) The department shall make available applications for permits authorized
pursuant to subdivisions (1)(a)(ii) and (1)(a)(iii) of this section in the
office of each county treasurer. The department may make available applications
for all other permits authorized by this section to the office of the county
treasurer and may make available applications for all permits authorized by
this section to any other location chosen by the department.</para>
<para>(7) The department or local authority issuing a permit may require a
permit fee of not to exceed twenty-five dollars, except that:</para>
<para>(a) The fee for a continuous or continuing permit may not exceed twenty-five
dollars for a ninety-day period, fifty dollars for a one-hundred-eighty-day
period, or one hundred dollars for a one-year period; and</para>
<para>(b) The fee for permits issued pursuant to subdivision (1)(a)(ii) of
this section shall be twenty-five dollars. Permits issued pursuant to such subdivision
shall be valid for thirty days and shall be renewable three times for a total number of days not to
exceed one hundred twenty days per calendar year.</para>
<para>A vehicle or combination of vehicles for which an application for a
permit is requested pursuant to this section shall be registered under section
60-3,147 or 60-3,198 for the maximum gross vehicle weight that is permitted
pursuant to section 60-6,294 before a permit shall be issued.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 156, &#167; 4, p. 565; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 183, &#167; 1, p. 546; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 220, &#167; 3, p. 695; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 226, &#167; 1, p. 708; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 214, &#167; 1, p. 627; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 235, &#167; 1, p. 627; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1337, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 152, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 39-722.01; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 287, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 842, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 285, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 122, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 833, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,181; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 176, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 394; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1061, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 467, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1306, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 122, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 261, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 376, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 563, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 82, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 246; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB820, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB35, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB841, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB997, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Rules and regulations of Department of Roads,</emphasis> adoption, penalty, see sections 39-102 and 39-103.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under the permit exemption contained in subsection (1) of this section, the language "access to points on (dustless-surfaced) highways" means that if there is no other route available, one may move the qualified equipment over a dustless-surfaced highway. State v. Quandt, 234 Neb. 402, 451 N.W.2d 272 (1990).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>