<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id193" statutenumber="60-6,288"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,288</statuteno><catchline id="id196">Vehicles;
width limit; exceptions; conditions; Director-State Engineer; powers.</catchline>
<para>(1) No vehicle which exceeds a total outside width of one hundred two
inches, including any load but excluding designated safety devices, shall
be permitted on any portion of the National System of Interstate and Defense
Highways. The Director-State Engineer shall adopt and promulgate rules and
regulations, consistent with federal requirements, designating safety devices
which shall be excluded in determining vehicle width.</para>
<para>(2) No vehicle which exceeds a total outside width of one hundred two
inches, including any load but excluding designated safety devices, shall
be permitted on any highway which is not a portion of the National System
of Interstate and Defense Highways, except that such prohibition shall not
apply to:</para>
<para>(a) Farm equipment in temporary movement, during daylight hours or during
hours of darkness when the clearance light requirements of section 60-6,235
are fully complied with, in the normal course of farm operations;</para>
<para>(b) Combines eighteen feet or less in width, while in the normal course
of farm operations and while being driven during daylight hours or during
hours of darkness when the clearance light requirements of section 60-6,235
are fully complied with;</para>
<para>(c) Combines in excess of eighteen feet in width, while in the normal
course of farm operations, while being driven during daylight hours for distances
of twenty-five miles or less on highways and while preceded by a well-lighted
pilot vehicle or flagperson, except that such combines may be driven on highways
while in the normal course of farm operations for distances of twenty-five
miles or less and while preceded by a well-lighted pilot vehicle or flagperson
during hours of darkness when the clearance light requirements of section
60-6,235 are fully complied with;</para>
<para>(d) Combines and vehicles used in transporting combines or other implements
of husbandry, and only when transporting combines or other implements of husbandry,
to be engaged in harvesting or other agricultural work, while being transported
into or through the state during daylight hours, when the total width including
the width of the combine or other implement of husbandry being transported
does not exceed fifteen feet, except that vehicles used in transporting combines
or other implements of husbandry may, when necessary to the harvesting operation
or other agricultural work, travel unloaded for distances not to exceed twenty-five
miles, while the combine or other implement of husbandry to be transported
is engaged in a harvesting operation or other agricultural work;</para>
<para>(e) Farm equipment dealers or their representatives as authorized
under section 60-6,382 driving, delivering, or picking up farm
equipment, including portable livestock buildings not exceeding fourteen feet
in width, or implements of husbandry during daylight hours;</para>
<para>(f) Livestock forage vehicles loaded or unloaded that comply with subsection
(2) of section 60-6,305;</para>
<para>(g) During daylight hours only, vehicles en route to pick up, delivering,
or returning unloaded from delivery of baled livestock forage which, including
the load if any, may be twelve feet in width;</para>
<para>(h) Mobile homes or prefabricated livestock buildings not exceeding
sixteen feet in width and with an outside tire width dimension not exceeding
one hundred twenty inches moving during daylight hours;</para>
<para>(i) Self-propelled specialized mobile equipment with a fixed load when:</para>
<para>(i) The self-propelled specialized mobile equipment will be transported
on a state highway, excluding any portion of the National System of Interstate
and Defense Highways, on a city street, or on a road within the corporate
limits of a city;</para>
<para>(ii) The city in which the self-propelled specialized mobile equipment
is intended to be transported has authorized a permit pursuant to section
60-6,298 for the transportation of the self-propelled specialized mobile equipment,
specifying the route to be used and the hours during which the self-propelled
specialized mobile equipment can be transported, except that no permit shall
be issued by a city for travel on a state highway containing a bridge or structure
which is structurally inadequate to carry the self-propelled specialized mobile
equipment as determined by the Department of Roads;</para>
<para>(iii) The self-propelled specialized mobile equipment's gross weight
does not exceed ninety-four thousand pounds if the self-propelled specialized
mobile equipment has four axles or seventy-two thousand pounds if the self-propelled
specialized mobile equipment has three axles; and</para>
<para>(iv) If the self-propelled specialized mobile equipment has four axles,
the maximum weight on each set of tandem axles does not exceed forty-seven
thousand pounds, or if the self-propelled specialized mobile equipment has
three axles, the maximum weight on the front axle does not exceed twenty-five
thousand pounds and the total maximum weight on the rear tandem axles does
not exceed forty-seven thousand pounds;</para>
<para>(j) Vehicles which have been issued a permit pursuant to section 60-6,299;
or</para>
<para>(k) A motor home or travel trailer, as those terms are defined in section
71-4603, which may exceed one hundred and two inches if such excess width
is attributable to an appurtenance that extends no more than six inches beyond
the body of the vehicle. For purposes of this subdivision, the term appurtenance
includes (i) an awning and its support hardware and (ii) any appendage that
is intended to be an integral part of a motor home or travel trailer and that
is installed by the manufacturer or dealer. The term appurtenance does not
include any item that is temporarily affixed or attached to the exterior of
the motor home or travel trailer for purposes of transporting the vehicular
unit from one location to another. Appurtenances shall not be considered in
calculating the gross trailer area as defined in section 71-4603.</para>
<para>(3) The Director-State Engineer, with respect to highways under his
or her jurisdiction, may designate certain highways upon which vehicles of
no more than ninety-six inches in width may be permitted to travel. Highways
so designated shall be limited to one or more of the following:</para>
<para>(a) Highways with traffic lanes of ten feet or less;</para>
<para>(b) Highways upon which are located narrow bridges; and</para>
<para>(c) Highways which because of sight distance, surfacing, unusual curves,
topographic conditions, or other unusual circumstances would not in the opinion
of the Director-State Engineer safely accommodate vehicles of more than ninety-six
inches in width.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 105, &#167; 1, p. 425; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-1032; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-719; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 156, &#167; 1, p. 563; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 182, &#167; 1, p. 544; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 219, &#167; 1, p. 691; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 220, &#167; 1, p. 693; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 221, &#167; 1, p. 697; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 212, &#167; 1, p. 621; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 308, &#167; 2, p. 1101; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 491, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1973, &#167; 39-719; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 593, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 306, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 427, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 576, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 750, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 284, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws
1981, LB 285, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 417, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 244, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 553, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 369, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-6,177; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 384; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 413, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 226, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1361, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 376, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1039, &#167; 3.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Weighing
stations,</emphasis> see sections 60-1301 to 60-1309.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Under
the exemption to the width limitations prescribed by subdivision (2)(f) of
this section, the language "access to points on (dustless-surfaced) highways"
means that if there is no other route available, one may move the qualified
equipment over a dustless-surfaced highway. State v. Quandt, 234 Neb. 402,
451 N.W.2d 272 (1990).</para><para>Violation of a statute is evidence of negligence,
but not negligence per se. Clark Bilt, Inc. v. Wells Dairy Co., 200 Neb. 20,
261 N.W.2d 772 (1978).</para><para>Exception in this section for unbaled livestock
forage applied to load only and not to vehicle. State v. Sabin, 184 Neb. 784,
172 N.W.2d 89 (1969).</para><para>Width of vehicle may not exceed eight feet
unless special permit is obtained. Frasier v. Gilchrist, 165 Neb. 450, 86
N.W.2d 65 (1957).</para><para>Where truck loaded with combine exceeded statutory
permissible width and was over centerline of the highway, it was evidence
of negligence. Novak v. Laptad, 152 Neb. 87, 40 N.W.2d 331 (1949).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>