<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id251">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id253" statutenumber="60-4,120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,120</statuteno><catchline id="id256">Operator's
license; state identification card; duplicate or replacement.</catchline>
<para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section
for persons temporarily out of the state, any person duly licensed or holding
a valid state identification card issued under the Motor Vehicle Operator's
License Act who loses his or her operator's license or card may make application to the department reporting such loss and furnishing
proof of identification in accordance with section 60-484. The department shall cause
to be issued, upon the payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115,
a duplicate license or card. Upon the issuance of any duplicate or replacement
license or card, the license or card from which the duplicate or replacement
is issued shall be void.</para>
<para>(2) If any person changes his or her name because of marriage
or divorce or by court order or a common-law name change, he or she shall
apply to the department for a replacement
operator's license or state identification card and furnish proof of identification
in accordance with section 60-484. If any person changes his or her address,
the person shall apply to the department for
a replacement operator's license or state identification card and furnish
satisfactory evidence of such change. The application shall be made within
sixty days after the change of name or address. The license or card shall
be issued upon payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115.</para>
<para>(3) In the event a mutilated and unreadable operator's license
is held by any person duly licensed under the act or a mutilated and unreadable
state identification card which was issued under the act is held by a person,
such person may obtain a replacement license or card upon showing the original
mutilated or unreadable license or card to the department. A replacement license or card may
be issued, without a photograph, to any person who is out of the state at
the time of application for the replacement license or card. Such license
or card shall state on its face that it shall become invalid thirty days after
such person resumes residence in the state. If the department is satisfied that the license or
card is mutilated or unreadable, the department shall
cause to be issued, upon the payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115,
a replacement license or card.</para>
<para>(4) If any person duly licensed under the act loses his or
her operator's license or if any holder of a state identification card loses
his or her card while temporarily out of the state, he or she may make application to the department for a duplicate
operator's license or card without a photograph by applying
to the department and reporting such loss. Upon receipt of a correctly completed application, the department shall cause to be issued, upon the
payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115, a duplicate operator's
license or card without a photograph. Upon the issuance of the duplicate,
the original license or card shall be void.</para>
<para>(5) Any person holding a valid operator's license or state
identification card without a photograph shall surrender such license or card
to the department within
thirty days after resuming residency in this state. After the thirty-day period,
such license or card shall be considered invalid. Upon the timely surrender
of the license or card and payment of the fee prescribed in section 60-4,115,
such person shall be issued an operator's license or card with a color photograph
or digital image of the licensee included.</para>
<para>(6) An application form for a replacement or duplicate operator's
license or state identification card shall include a voter registration portion
pursuant to section 32-308 and the following specific question: Do you wish
to register to vote as part of this application process?</para>
<para>(7) An applicant may obtain a replacement or duplicate operator's
license or state identification card pursuant to subsection (1), (3), or (4)
of this section by electronic means in a manner prescribed by the department.
If the applicant has a digital image and digital signature preserved in the
digital system, the replacement or duplicate shall be issued with the preserved
digital image and digital signature.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 148, &#167; 9, p. 517; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 60-409; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 19, p. 517; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 176, &#167; 2, p. 689; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-409; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-415; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 141, &#167; 8, p. 453; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 207, &#167; 4, p. 678; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 315, &#167; 10, p. 1005; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 316, &#167; 10, p. 1015; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 234, &#167; 7, p. 626; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 506, &#167; 2, p. 2083; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 134, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 371, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1296, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 90, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 606, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 46, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 811, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 575, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 284, &#167; 9; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-415; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 126, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 201, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 572; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 1, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB751, &#167; 26.</para><operativedate>May 1, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>