<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,188"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,188</statuteno><catchline>Driver improvement course; reduce point assessment.</catchline><para>Any person who has fewer than twelve points assessed against his or her driving record under section 60-4,182 may voluntarily enroll in a driver improvement course approved by the Department of Motor Vehicles. Upon notification of successful completion of such a course by the conducting organization, the department shall reduce by two the number of points assessed against such person's driving record within the previous two years. This section shall only apply to persons who have successfully completed such driver improvement course prior to committing any traffic offense for which a conviction and point assessment against their driving record would otherwise result in a total of twelve or more points assessed against their record. No person required to enroll in a driver improvement course pursuant to section 60-4,130, 60-4,130.03, or 60-4,183 shall be eligible for a reduction in points assessed against his or her driving record upon the successful completion of such course. If a person has only one point assessed against his or her record within the previous two years, upon notification of successful completion of such a course by the conducting organization, the department shall reduce one point from such person's driving record. Such reduction shall be allowed only once within a five-year period. Notification of completion of an approved driver improvement course shall be sent to the department, upon successful completion thereof, by the conducting organization. Such course shall consist of at least four hours of instruction and shall follow such other guidelines as are established by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 204, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-669.37; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 320, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB113, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB750, &#167; 67. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>