<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id111" statutenumber="60-149"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>60-149</statuteno><catchline id="id114">Application; documentation required.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If a certificate of title has previously been issued for a vehicle in this state, the application for a new certificate of title shall be accompanied by the certificate of title duly assigned except as otherwise provided in the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act.</para><para>(b) Except for manufactured homes or mobile homes as provided in subsection (2) of this section, if a certificate of title has not previously been issued for the vehicle in this state or if a certificate of title is unavailable, the application shall be accompanied by:</para><para>(i) A manufacturer's or importer's certificate except as otherwise provided in subdivision (viii) of this subdivision; </para><para>(ii) A duly certified copy of the manufacturer's or importer's certificate;</para><para>(iii) An affidavit by the owner affirming ownership in the case of an all-terrain vehicle, a utility-type vehicle, or a minibike;</para><para>(iv) A certificate of title from another state;</para><para>(v) A court order issued by a court of record, a manufacturer's certificate of origin, or an assigned registration certificate, if the law of the state from which the vehicle was brought into this state does not have a certificate of title law;</para><para>(vi) Evidence of ownership as provided for in section 30-24,125, sections 52-601.01 to 52-605, sections 60-1901 to 60-1911, or sections 60-2401 to 60-2411;</para><para>(vii) Documentation prescribed in section 60-142.01, 60-142.02, 60-142.04, 60-142.05, 60-142.09, or 60-142.11 or documentation of compliance with section 76-1607;</para><para>(viii) A manufacturer's or importer's certificate and an affidavit by the owner affirming ownership in the case of a minitruck; or</para><para>(ix) In the case of a motor vehicle, a trailer, an all-terrain vehicle, a utility-type vehicle, or a minibike, an affidavit by the holder of a motor vehicle auction dealer's license as described in subdivision (11) of section 60-1406 affirming that the certificate of title is unavailable and that the vehicle (A) is a salvage vehicle through payment of a total loss settlement, (B) is a salvage vehicle purchased by the auction dealer, or (C) has been donated to an organization operating under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code as defined in section 49-801.01.</para><para>(c) If the application for a certificate of title in this state is accompanied by a valid certificate of title issued by another state which meets that state's requirements for transfer of ownership, then the application may be accepted by this state.</para><para>(d) If a certificate of title has not previously been issued for the vehicle in this state and the applicant is unable to provide such documentation, the applicant may apply for a bonded certificate of title as prescribed in section 60-167.</para><para>(2)(a) If the application for a certificate of title for a manufactured home or a mobile home is being made in accordance with subdivision (4)(b) of section 60-137 or if the certificate of title for a manufactured home or a mobile home is unavailable, the application shall be accompanied by proof of ownership in the form of:</para><para>(i) A duly assigned manufacturer's or importer's certificate;</para><para>(ii) A certificate of title from another state;</para><para>(iii) A court order issued by a court of record;</para><para>(iv) Evidence of ownership as provided for in section 30-24,125, sections 52-601.01 to 52-605, sections 60-1901 to 60-1911, or sections 60-2401 to 60-2411, or documentation of compliance with section 76-1607; or</para><para>(v) Assessment records for the manufactured home or mobile home from the county assessor and an affidavit by the owner affirming ownership.</para><para>(b) If the applicant cannot produce proof of ownership described in subdivision (a) of this subsection, he or she may submit to the department such evidence as he or she may have, and the department may thereupon, if it finds the evidence sufficient, issue the certificate of title or authorize the county treasurer to issue a certificate of title, as the case may be.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, certificate of title includes a salvage certificate, a salvage branded certificate of title, or any other document of ownership issued by another state or jurisdiction for a salvage vehicle. Only a salvage branded certificate of title shall be issued to any vehicle conveyed upon a salvage certificate, a salvage branded certificate of title, or any other document of ownership issued by another state or jurisdiction for a salvage vehicle.</para><para>(4) The county treasurer shall retain the evidence of title presented by the applicant and on which the certificate of title is issued.</para><para>(5)(a) If an affidavit is submitted under subdivision (1)(b)(ix) of this section, the holder of a motor vehicle auction dealer's license shall certify that (i) it has made at least two written attempts and has been unable to obtain the properly endorsed certificate of title to the property noted in the affidavit from the owner and (ii) thirty days have expired after the mailing of a written notice regarding the intended disposition of the property noted in the affidavit by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the last-known address of the owner and to any lien or security interest holder of record of the property noted in the affidavit.</para><para>(b) The notice under subdivision (5)(a)(ii) of this section shall contain a description of the property noted in the affidavit and a statement that title to the property noted in the affidavit shall vest in the holder of the motor vehicle auction dealer's license thirty days after the date such notice was mailed.</para><para>(c) The mailing of notice and the expiration of thirty days under subdivision (5)(a)(ii) of this section shall extinguish any lien or security interest of a lienholder or security interest holder in the property noted in the affidavit, unless the lienholder or security interest holder has claimed such property within such thirty-day period. The holder of a motor vehicle auction dealer's license shall transfer possession of the property noted in the affidavit to the lienholder or security interest holder claiming such property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 663, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB933, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB492, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB275, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB270, &#167; 8. </para></source><annotation><para>Certificate of title, based upon a duplicate issued in another state, is not protected. Allstate Ins. Co. v. Enzolera, 164 Neb. 38, 81 N.W.2d 588 (1957).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>