<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id305" statutenumber="60-6,356"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,356</statuteno><catchline id="id308">All-terrain vehicle; utility-type vehicle; operation; restrictions; city or village ordinance; county board resolution.</catchline><para>(1) An all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle shall not be operated on any controlled-access highway with more than two marked traffic lanes. The crossing of any controlled-access highway with more than two marked traffic lanes shall not be permitted except as provided in subsections (9) and (10) of this section. Subsections (2), (3), and (5) through (8) of this section authorize and apply to operation of an all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle only on a highway other than a controlled-access highway with more than two marked traffic lanes.</para><para>(2) An all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle may be operated in accordance with the operating requirements of subsection (3) of this section:</para><para>(a) Outside the corporate limits of a city, village, or unincorporated village if incidental to the vehicle's use for agricultural purposes;</para><para>(b) Within the corporate limits of a city or village if authorized by the city or village by ordinance adopted in accordance with this section; or</para><para>(c) Within an unincorporated village if authorized by the county board of the county in which the unincorporated village is located by resolution in accordance with this section.</para><para>(3) An all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle may be operated as authorized in subsection (2) of this section when such operation occurs only between the hours of sunrise and sunset. Any person operating an all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle as authorized in subsection (2) of this section shall have a valid Class O operator's license or a farm permit as provided in section 60-4,126, shall have liability insurance coverage for the all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle while operating the all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle on a highway, and shall not operate such vehicle at a speed in excess of thirty miles per hour. The person operating the all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle shall provide proof of such insurance coverage to any peace officer requesting such proof within five days of such a request. When operating an all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle as authorized in subsection (2) of this section, the headlight and taillight of the vehicle shall be on and the vehicle shall be equipped with a bicycle safety flag which extends not less than five feet above ground attached to the rear of such vehicle. The bicycle safety flag shall be triangular in shape with an area of not less than thirty square inches and shall be day-glow in color.</para><para>(4) All-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles may be operated without complying with subsection (3) of this section on highways in parades which have been authorized by the State of Nebraska or any department, board, commission, or political subdivision of the state.</para><para>(5) The crossing of a highway other than a controlled-access highway with more than two marked traffic lanes shall be permitted by an all-terrain vehicle or a utility-type vehicle without complying with subsection (3) of this section only if:</para><para>(a) The crossing is made at an angle of approximately ninety degrees to the direction of the highway and at a place where no obstruction prevents a quick and safe crossing;</para><para>(b) The vehicle is brought to a complete stop before crossing the shoulder or roadway of the highway;</para><para>(c) The operator yields the right-of-way to all oncoming traffic that constitutes an immediate potential hazard;</para><para>(d) In crossing a divided highway, the crossing is made only at an intersection of such highway with another highway; and</para><para>(e) Both the headlight and taillight of the vehicle are on when the crossing is made.</para><para>(6) All-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles may be operated outside the corporate limits of any municipality by electric utility personnel within the course of their employment in accordance with the operation requirements of subsection (3) of this section, except that the operation of the vehicle pursuant to this subsection need not be limited to the hours between sunrise and sunset.</para><para>(7) A city or village may adopt an ordinance authorizing the operation of all-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles within the corporate limits of the city or village if the operation is in accordance with subsection (3) of this section. The city or village may place other restrictions on the operation of all-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles within its corporate limits.</para><para>(8) A county board may adopt a resolution authorizing the operation of all-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles within any unincorporated village within the county if the operation is in accordance with subsection (3) of this section. The county may place other restrictions on the operation of all-terrain vehicles and utility-type vehicles within the unincorporated village.</para><para>(9) Except as provided in subsection (10) of this section, the crossing of a controlled-access highway with more than two marked traffic lanes shall be permitted by a utility-type vehicle if the operation is in accordance with the operation requirements of subsection (3) of this section and if the following requirements are met:</para><para>(a) The crossing is made at an intersection that:</para><para>(i) Is controlled by a traffic control signal; or</para><para>(ii) For any intersection located outside the corporate limits of a city or village, is controlled by stop signs;</para><para>(b) The crossing at such intersection is made in compliance with the traffic control signal or stop signs; and</para><para>(c) The crossing at such intersection is specifically authorized as follows:</para><para>(i) If such intersection is located within the corporate limits of a city or village, by ordinance of such city or village;</para><para>(ii) If such intersection is located within an unincorporated village, by resolution of the county board of the county in which such unincorporated village is located; or</para><para>(iii) If such intersection is located outside the corporate limits of a city or village and outside any unincorporated village, by resolution of the county board of the county in which such intersection is located.</para><para>(10) When the use of the all-terrain vehicle or utility-type vehicle is for an agricultural purpose, the crossing of a controlled-access highway with more than two marked traffic lanes shall be permitted if such vehicle is operated in accordance with subsection (3) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 80, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 114, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 138; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 60-2802; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 452; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB307, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB122, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB944, &#167; 72. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>