<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-498"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-498</statuteno><catchline>Revocation; when mandatory.</catchline><para>The director shall immediately revoke the operator's license of any person upon receiving a copy of judgment of such person's conviction of any of the following offenses when such conviction becomes final:</para><para>(1) Manslaughter resulting from the operation of a motor vehicle;</para><para>(2) Driving a motor vehicle while under the influence of alcoholic liquor or any drug as provided in city or village ordinances or in section 60-6,196. The period of revocation shall, in each case except for revocations pursuant to sections 60-498.01 to 60-498.04 and offenses specified in section 60-4,168, correspond with the period that is determined by the court;</para><para>(3) Any felony in the commission of which a motor vehicle is used;</para><para>(4) Failure to stop and render aid as required under the laws of this state in the event of a motor vehicle accident resulting in the death or personal injury of another;</para><para>(5) Perjury or making of a false affidavit or statement under oath to the director, examining officer, or other officer under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act or under any law relating to the ownership or operation of motor vehicles;</para><para>(6) Conviction or forfeiture of bail, not vacated, upon three charges of reckless driving committed within a period of twelve months; or</para><para>(7) Willful reckless driving as provided in city or village ordinances or as described in section 60-6,214.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 141, &#167; 23, p. 518; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 124, &#167; 4, p. 472; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 60-428; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 60-424; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 214, &#167; 7, p. 759; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-424; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 420, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 291, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Conclusory notation of "D.U.I." provides no factual reason for an officer's decision to arrest a driver on suspicion of driving under the influence of alcohol instead of merely citing the driver for speeding when excessive speed was the initial reason for the stop. Snyder v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 274 Neb. 168, 736 N.W.2d 731 (2007).</para><para>In an administrative license revocation proceeding, the sworn report of the arresting officer must, at a minimum, contain the information specified in subsection (3) of section 60-498.01 in order to confer jurisdiction. Snyder v. Department of Motor Vehicles, 274 Neb. 168, 736 N.W.2d 731 (2007).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 