<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-512"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-512</statuteno><catchline>Compliance with law; person with no license or registration; nonresident; resident with accident occurring in other state.</catchline><para>(1) In case the operator or the owner of a motor vehicle involved in an accident within this state has no license or registration, such operator or owner shall not be allowed a license or registration until he or she has complied with the requirements of the Motor Vehicle Safety Responsibility Act to the same extent that would be necessary if, at the time of the accident, he or she had held a license and registration.</para><para>(2) When a nonresident's operating privilege is suspended pursuant to section 60-507 or 60-511, the department shall transmit a certified copy of the record of such action to the official in charge of the issuance of licenses and registration certificates in the state in which such nonresident resides, if the law of such other state provides for action in relation thereto similar to that provided for in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of certification that the operating privilege of a resident of this state has been suspended or revoked in any other state pursuant to a law providing for its suspension or revocation for failure to deposit security for the payment of judgments arising out of a motor vehicle accident, or for failure to deposit both security and proof of financial responsibility, under circumstances which would require the department to suspend a nonresident's operating privilege had the accident occurred in this state, the department shall suspend the license and registrations of such resident. Such suspension shall continue until such resident furnishes evidence of compliance with the law of the other state relating to the deposit of security and until such resident files proof of financial responsibility if required by the law of the other state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 178, &#167; 12, p. 489; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 298, &#167; 10, p. 1115; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB174, &#167; 24. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>