<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-152"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>60-152</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of title; issuance; delivery
of copies; seal; county treasurer; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) The county treasurer shall
issue a certificate of title for a vehicle in duplicate and retain one copy
in his or her office. An electronic copy, in a form prescribed by the department,
shall be transmitted on the day of issuance to the department. The county treasurer shall sign and affix
the appropriate seal to the original certificate of title and, if there are
no liens on the vehicle, deliver the certificate to the applicant. If there
are one or more liens on the vehicle, the certificate of title shall be handled
as provided in section 60-164 or 60-165.</para>
<para>(2) The county treasurers of the various counties shall adopt a circular
seal with the words County Treasurer
of ........... (insert name) County thereon. Such seal shall be used by the county treasurer
or the deputy or legal authorized agent of such officer, without charge to
the applicant, on any certificate of title, application for certificate of
title, duplicate copy, assignment or reassignment, power of attorney, statement,
or affidavit pertaining to the issuance of a Nebraska certificate of title.</para>
<para>(3) The department shall prescribe a uniform method of numbering certificates
of title.</para>
<para>(4) The county treasurer shall
(a) file all certificates of title according to rules and regulations adopted
and promulgated by the department, (b) maintain in the office indices for
such certificates of title, (c) be authorized to destroy all previous records
five years after a subsequent transfer has been made on a vehicle, and (d)
be authorized to destroy all certificates of title and all supporting records
and documents which have been on file for a period of five years or more from
the date of filing the certificate or a notation of lien, whichever occurs
later.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 35.</para></source><annotation><para>There is no legal requirement that a lien be noted on a certificate of title purportedly covering property not subject to the Certificate of Title Act, even though a certificate of title for such property has been issued. Cushman Sales &amp; Service of Nebraska, Inc. v. Muirhead, 201 Neb. 495, 268 N.W.2d 440 (1978).</para><para>Legislature contemplated that form provided must be fully and properly executed. Loyal's Auto Exchange, Inc. v. Munch, 153 Neb. 628, 45 N.W.2d 913 (1951).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>