<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,303</statuteno><catchline>Vehicles; overloading; powers of peace officer or carrier enforcement officer; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>Any peace officer or carrier enforcement officer having reason to believe that the weight of a vehicle and load is unlawful is authorized to require the driver to stop and submit to a weighing of the vehicle and load. Upon weighing a vehicle and load, if the officer determines that the weight on any axle exceeds the lawful weight, that the weight on any group of two consecutive axles exceeds their lawful weight, or that the weight is unlawful on any axle or group of consecutive axles on any road restricted in accordance with section 60-6,294, the officer may require the driver to stop the vehicle in a suitable place and remain standing until such portion of the load is removed as may be necessary to reduce the gross weight of such vehicle to such limit as permitted under such section. All material so unloaded shall be cared for by the owner or driver of such vehicle at the risk of such owner or driver.</para><para>For purposes of this section, lawful weight shall mean the maximum weight permitted by section 60-6,294.</para><para>Any driver of a vehicle who refuses to stop and submit the vehicle and load to a weighing or who refuses, when directed by a peace officer or carrier enforcement officer upon a weighing of the vehicle, to stop the vehicle and otherwise comply with the provisions of this section shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 131, &#167; 10, p. 407; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 318, &#167; 5, p. 1157; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-723.08; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 726, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,186; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 399. </para></source></law></legaldoc>