<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id37" statutenumber="60-6,175"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,175</statuteno><catchline id="id40">School bus; safety requirements;
use of stop signal arm; use of warning signal lights; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Upon meeting or overtaking, from the front or rear, any school bus
on which the yellow warning signal lights are flashing, the driver of a motor
vehicle shall reduce the speed of such vehicle to not more than twenty-five
miles per hour, shall bring such vehicle to a complete stop when the school
bus is stopped, the stop signal arm is extended, and the flashing red signal
lights are turned on, and shall remain stopped until the flashing red signal
lights are turned off, the stop signal arm is retracted, and the school bus
resumes motion. This section shall not apply to approaching traffic in the
opposite direction on a divided highway or to approaching traffic when there
is displayed a sign as provided in subsection (8) of this section directing
traffic to proceed. Any person violating this subsection shall be guilty of
a Class IV misdemeanor, shall be fined five hundred dollars, and shall be
assessed points on his or her motor vehicle operator's license pursuant to
section 60-4,182.</para>
<para>(2) Except as provided in subsection (8) of this section, the driver
of any school bus, when stopping to receive or discharge pupils, shall turn
on flashing yellow warning signal lights at a distance of not less than three
hundred feet when inside the corporate limits of any city or village and not
less than five hundred feet nor more than one thousand feet in any area outside
the corporate limits of any city or village from the point where such pupils
are to be received or discharged from the bus. At the point of receiving or
discharging pupils, the bus driver shall bring the school bus to a stop, extend
a stop signal arm, and turn on the flashing red signal lights. After receiving
or discharging pupils, the bus driver shall turn off the flashing red signal
lights, retract the stop signal arm, and then proceed on the route.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (b) of this subsection, no
school bus shall stop to load or unload pupils outside of the corporate limits of any city or village or
on any part of the state highway system within the corporate limits of a city
or village, unless there is at least four hundred feet of clear
vision in each direction of travel.</para>
<para>(b) If four hundred feet of clear vision in each direction of travel
is not possible as determined by the school district, a school bus may stop
to load or unload pupils if there is proper signage installed indicating that
a school bus stop is ahead.</para>
<para>(4) All pupils shall be received and discharged from the right front
entrance of every school bus. If such pupils must cross a roadway, the bus
driver shall instruct such pupils to cross in front of the school bus and
the bus driver shall keep such school bus halted with the flashing red signal
lights turned on and the stop signal arm extended until such pupils have reached
the opposite side of such roadway.</para>
<para>(5) The driver of a vehicle upon a divided highway need not stop upon
meeting or passing a school bus which is on a different roadway or when upon
a freeway and such school bus is stopped in a loading zone which is a part
of or adjacent to such highway and where pedestrians are not permitted to
cross the roadway.</para>
<para>(6) Every school bus shall bear upon the front and rear thereof plainly
visible signs containing the words school bus in letters not less than eight
inches high.</para>
<para>(7) When a school bus is being operated upon a highway for purposes
other than the actual transportation of children either to or from school
or school-sponsored activities, all markings thereon indicating school bus
shall be covered or concealed. The stop signal arm and system of flashing
yellow warning signal lights and flashing red signal lights shall not be operable
through the usual controls.</para>
<para>(8) When a school bus is (a) parked in a designated school bus loading
area which is out of the flow of traffic and which is adjacent to a school
site or (b) parked on a roadway which possesses more than one lane of traffic
flowing in the same direction and which is adjacent to a school site, the
bus driver shall engage only the hazard warning flasher lights when receiving
or discharging pupils if a school bus loading area warning sign is displayed.
Such signs shall not be directly attached to any school bus but shall be free
standing and placed at the rear of a parked school bus or line of parked school
buses. No school district shall utilize a school bus loading area warning
sign unless such sign complies with the requirements of section 60-6,176.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 863, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 41, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 347, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-660; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 271; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 575, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1039, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB500, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>