<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id13"  statutenumber="60-6,378"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,378</statuteno><catchline>Stopped authorized emergency vehicle or road assistance vehicle; driver; duties; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A driver in a vehicle on a controlled-access highway approaching or passing a stopped authorized emergency vehicle or road assistance vehicle which makes use of proper audible or visual signals shall proceed with due care and caution as described in subdivision (b) of this subsection.</para><para>(b) On a controlled-access highway with at least two adjacent lanes of travel in the same direction on the same side of the highway where a stopped authorized emergency vehicle or road assistance vehicle is using proper audible or visual signals, the driver of the vehicle shall proceed with due care and caution and yield the right-of-way by moving into a lane at least one moving lane apart from the stopped authorized emergency vehicle or road assistance vehicle unless directed otherwise by a peace officer or other authorized emergency personnel. If moving into another lane is not possible because of weather conditions, road conditions, or the immediate presence of vehicular or pedestrian traffic or because the controlled-access highway does not have two available adjacent lanes of travel in the same direction on the same side of the highway where such a stopped authorized emergency vehicle or road assistance vehicle is located, the driver of the approaching or passing vehicle shall reduce his or her speed, maintain a safe speed with regard to the location of the stopped authorized emergency vehicle or road assistance vehicle, the weather conditions, the road conditions, and vehicular or pedestrian traffic, and proceed with due care and caution or proceed as directed by a peace officer or other authorized emergency personnel or road assistance personnel.</para><para>(c) Any person who violates this subsection is guilty of a traffic infraction for a first offense and Class IIIA misdemeanor for a second or subsequent offense.</para><para>(2) The Department of Transportation shall erect and maintain or cause to be erected and maintained signs giving notice of subsection (1) of this section along controlled-access highways.</para><para>(3) Enforcement of subsection (1) of this section shall not be accomplished using simulated situations involving an authorized emergency vehicle or a road assistance vehicle.</para><para>(4) This section does not relieve the driver of an authorized emergency vehicle or a road assistance vehicle from the duty to drive with due regard for the safety of all persons using the highway.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, road assistance vehicle includes a vehicle operated by the Nebraska Department of Transportation, a Nebraska State Patrol motorist assistance vehicle, a United States Department of Transportation registered towing or roadside assistance vehicle, and a utility service vehicle operated by a utility company. A road assistance vehicle shall emit a warning signal utilizing properly displayed emergency indicators such as strobe, rotating, or oscillating lights when stopped along a highway.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB92, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB154, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 231. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>