<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,181"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,181</statuteno><catchline>State identification cards; issuance;
requirements; form; delivery; cancellation.</catchline><para>(1) Each
applicant for a state identification card shall provide the information and
documentation required by section 60-484 and
also, beginning on an implementation date designated by the director on or
before January 1, 2014, the information and documentation required by section
60-484.04. The form of the state identification card shall comply
with section 60-4,117. Upon presentation of an applicant's issuance certificate,
the county treasurer shall collect the fee and surcharge as prescribed in
section 60-4,115 and issue a receipt to the applicant which is valid up to
thirty days. The state identification card shall be delivered to the applicant
as provided in section 60-4,113.</para>
<para>(2) The director may summarily
cancel any state identification card, and any judge or magistrate may order
a state identification card canceled in a judgment of conviction, if the application
or issuance certificate for the
card contains any false or fraudulent statements which were deliberately and
knowingly made as to any matter material to the issuance of the card or if
the application or issuance certificate does not contain required
or correct information. Any state identification card so obtained shall be
void from the date of issuance. Any judgment of conviction ordering cancellation
of a state identification card shall be transmitted to the director who shall
cancel the card.</para>
<para>(3) This subsection applies
beginning on an implementation date designated by the director on or before
January 1, 2014. No person shall be a holder of a state identification card
and an operator's license at the same time.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws
1989, LB 284, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1178, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 576; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 467, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1073, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 21, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 635, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 147, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1317, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 34, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 228, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 559, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB911, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB215, &#167; 23.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
