<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id103" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="60-6,211.05">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id105">60-6,211.05</statuteno><catchline id="id106">Ignition
interlock device; continuous alcohol monitoring device and abstention from
alcohol use; orders authorized; prohibited acts; violation; penalty; costs;
tampering with device; hearing.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If an order is granted under
section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197, as such sections existed prior to July 16, 2004,
or section 60-6,196 or 60-6,197 and sections 60-6,197.02 and 60-6,197.03,
as such sections existed on or after July 16, 2004, the court may order that
the defendant install an ignition interlock device of a type approved by the
Director of Motor Vehicles on each motor vehicle operated by the defendant
during the period of probation. Upon sufficient evidence of installation,
the defendant may apply to the director for an ignition interlock permit pursuant
to section 60-4,118.06. The device shall, without tampering or the intervention
of another person, prevent the defendant from operating the motor vehicle
when the defendant has an alcohol concentration greater than three-hundredths
of one gram or more by weight of alcohol per one hundred milliliters of his
or her blood or three-hundredths of one gram or more by weight of alcohol
per two hundred ten liters of his or her breath.</para>
<para>(b) If the court orders an ignition interlock permit and installation
of an ignition interlock device as part of the judgment of conviction pursuant
to section 60-6,197.03, the device shall be of a type approved
by the director and shall be installed on each motor vehicle operated by the
defendant. The device shall, without tampering or the intervention of another
person, prevent the defendant from operating the motor vehicle when the defendant
has an alcohol concentration greater than three-hundredths of one gram or
more by weight of alcohol per one hundred milliliters of his or her blood
or three-hundredths of one gram or more by weight of alcohol per two hundred
ten liters of his or her breath.</para>
<para>(2) If the court orders installation of an ignition interlock device
and issuance of an ignition interlock permit pursuant to subsection (1) of
this section, the court may also order the use of a continuous alcohol monitoring
device and abstention from alcohol use at all times. The device shall, without
tampering or the intervention of another person, test and record the alcohol
consumption level of the defendant on a periodic basis and transmit such information
to probation authorities.</para>
<para>(3) Any order issued by the court pursuant to this section shall not
take effect until the defendant is eligible to operate a motor vehicle pursuant
to subsection (3) of section 60-498.02.</para>
<para>(4)(a) If the court orders an ignition interlock device or the Board
of Pardons orders an ignition interlock device under section 83-1,127.02,
the court or the Board of Pardons shall order the defendant to apply for an
ignition interlock permit as provided in section 60-4,118.06 which indicates
that the defendant is only allowed to operate a motor vehicle equipped with
an ignition interlock device.</para>
<para>(b) Such court order shall remain in effect for a period of time as
determined by the court not to exceed the maximum term of revocation which
the court could have imposed according to the nature of the violation and
shall allow operation of an ignition-interlock-equipped motor vehicle only
to and from the defendant's residence, the defendant's place of employment,
the defendant's school, an alcohol treatment program, or
an ignition interlock service facility.</para>
<para>(c) Such Board of Pardons order shall remain in effect for a period
of time not to exceed any period of revocation the applicant is subject to
at the time the application for a reprieve is made.</para>
<para>(5) A person who tampers with or circumvents an ignition interlock device
installed under a court order while the order is in effect, who operates a
motor vehicle which is not equipped with an ignition interlock device in violation
of a court order made pursuant to this section, or who otherwise operates
a motor vehicle equipped with an ignition interlock device in violation of
the requirements of the court order under which the device was installed shall
be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para>
<para>(6) Any person restricted to operating a motor vehicle equipped with
an ignition interlock device, pursuant to a Board of Pardons order, who operates
upon the highways of this state a motor vehicle without such device or if
the device has been disabled, bypassed, or altered in any way, shall be punished
as provided in subsection (3) of section 83-1,127.02.</para>
<para>(7) If a person ordered to use a continuous alcohol monitoring device
and abstain from alcohol use pursuant to a court order as provided in subsection
(2) of this section violates the provisions of such court order by removing,
tampering with, or otherwise bypassing the continuous alcohol monitoring device
or by consuming alcohol while required to use such device, he or she shall
have his or her ignition interlock permit revoked and be unable to apply for
reinstatement for the duration of the revocation period imposed by the court.</para>
<para>(8) The director shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations regarding
the approval of ignition interlock devices, the means of installing ignition
interlock devices, and the means of administering the ignition interlock permit
program.</para>
<para>(9) The costs incurred in order to comply with the ignition interlock
requirements of this section shall be paid by the person complying with an
order for an ignition interlock permit and installation of an ignition interlock
device unless the court or the Board of Pardons has determined the person
to be incapable of paying for the cost of installation, removal, or maintenance
of the ignition interlock device in accordance with this subsection.</para>
<para>(10)(a) An ignition interlock service facility shall notify the appropriate
district probation office, if the order is made pursuant to subdivision (1)(a)
of this section, or notify the appropriate court if the order is made pursuant
to subdivision (1)(b) of this section, of any evidence of tampering with or
circumvention of an ignition interlock device, or any attempts to do so, when
the facility becomes aware of such evidence.</para>
<para>(b) If a district probation office receives evidence of tampering with
or circumvention of an ignition interlock device, or any attempts to do so,
from an ignition interlock service facility, the district probation office
shall notify the appropriate court of such violation. The court shall immediately
schedule an evidentiary hearing to be held within fourteen days after receiving
such evidence, either from the district probation office or an ignition interlock
service facility, and the court shall cause notice of the hearing to be given
to the person operating a motor vehicle pursuant to an order under subsection
(1) of this section. If the person who is the subject of such evidence does
not appear at the hearing and show cause why the order made pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section should remain in effect, the court shall rescind the original
order. Nothing in this subsection shall apply to an order made by the Board
of Pardons pursuant to section 83-1,127.02.</para>
<para>(11) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the costs associated
with the installation, maintenance, and removal of a court-ordered ignition
interlock device by the Office of Probation Administration shall not be construed
so as to create an order of probation when an order for the installation of
an ignition interlock device and ignition interlock permit was made pursuant
to subdivision (1)(b) of this section as part of a conviction.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 564, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 309, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 208, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 925, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB736, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB497, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB924, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>