<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id37" statutenumber="60-168.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>60-168.02</statuteno><catchline id="id40">Certificate of title in dealer's name; issuance authorized; documentation and fees required; dealer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) When a motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer is purchased by a motor vehicle dealer or trailer dealer and the original assigned certificate of title has been lost or mutilated, the dealer selling such motor vehicle or trailer may apply for an original certificate of title in the dealer's name. The following documentation and fees shall be submitted by the dealer:</para><para>(a) An application for a certificate of title in the name of such dealer;</para><para>(b) A photocopy from the dealer's records of the front and back of the lost or mutilated original certificate of title assigned to a dealer;</para><para>(c) A notarized affidavit from the purchaser of such motor vehicle or trailer for which the original assigned certificate of title was lost or mutilated stating that the original assigned certificate of title was lost or mutilated; and</para><para>(d) The appropriate certificate of title fee.</para><para>(2) The application and affidavit shall be on forms prescribed by the department. When the motor vehicle dealer or trailer dealer receives the new certificate of title in such dealer's name and assigns it to the purchaser, the dealer shall record the original sale date and provide the purchaser with a copy of the front and back of the original lost or mutilated certificate of title as evidence as to why the purchase date of the motor vehicle or trailer is prior to the issue date of the new certificate of title.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 21. </para><operativedate>August 24, 2017</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>