<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,141"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,141</statuteno><catchline>Operation outside classification
of license; restrictions; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Except
as provided in subsections (2), (3), and (4) of this section, no person shall operate
any class of commercial motor vehicle upon the highways of this state unless
such person possesses a valid commercial driver's license authorizing the
operation of the class of commercial motor vehicle being operated, except
that (a) any person possessing a valid commercial driver's license authorizing
the operation of a Class A commercial motor vehicle may lawfully operate any
Class B or C commercial motor vehicle and (b) any person possessing a valid
commercial driver's license authorizing the operation of a Class B commercial
motor vehicle may lawfully operate a Class C commercial motor vehicle. No
person shall operate upon the highways of this state any commercial motor
vehicle which requires a specific endorsement unless such person possesses
a valid commercial driver's license with such endorsement. No person possessing
a restricted commercial driver's license shall operate upon the highways of
this state any commercial motor vehicle to which such restriction is applicable.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Any person holding a CLP-commercial learner's permit
may operate a commercial motor vehicle for learning purposes upon the highways
of this state if accompanied by a person who is twenty-one years of age or
older, who holds a commercial driver's license valid for the class of commercial
motor vehicle being operated, and who occupies the seat beside the person
for the purpose of giving instruction in the operation of the commercial motor
vehicle. Any person holding a
CLP-commercial learner's permit may operate a commercial motor
vehicle upon the highways of this state for purposes of taking a driving skills
examination if accompanied by licensing
staff who is designated by the director under section 60-4,149
or an examiner employed
by a third-party tester certified pursuant to section 60-4,158 and who occupies
the seat beside the person for the purpose of giving the examination. A person
holding a CLP-commercial learner's permit
shall not operate a commercial motor vehicle transporting hazardous materials. A holder of a commercial learner's permit
may operate a Class A combination vehicle, Class B heavy straight vehicle,
or Class C small vehicle, as appropriate.</para>
<para>(b) A CLP-commercial
learner's permit shall only be allowed to bear any of the following endorsements:
(i) P &#8212;€” Passenger; (ii) S &#8212;€” School bus; and (iii) N &#8212;€” Tank vehicle.</para>
<para>(c) A CLP-commercial
learner's permit shall only be allowed to bear any of the following restrictions:
(i) K &#8212;€” Operation of a commercial motor vehicle only in intrastate commerce;
(ii) L &#8212;€” Operation of only a commercial motor vehicle which is not equipped
with air brakes; (iii) V &#8212;€” Operation of a commercial motor vehicle for drivers
with medical variance documentation; (iv) P &#8212;€” No passengers in commercial
motor vehicle bus; and (v) X &#8212;€” No cargo in commercial motor vehicle tank vehicle.</para>
<para>(3) Except
for nonresident individuals who are enrolled and taking training in a driver
training school in this state, any holder of a nonresident commercial learner's
permit or nonresident commercial driver's license who is in this
state for a period of thirty consecutive days or more shall apply for a Nebraska-issued CLP-commercial learner's permit or commercial
driver's license and shall surrender to the department any
operator's license issued to such nonresident by any other state.</para>
<para>(4) Except for individuals
who are enrolled and taking training in a driver training school in this state,
any holder of a nondomiciled commercial learner's permit or nondomiciled commercial
driver's license issued by another state who is in this state for a period
of thirty consecutive days or more shall apply for a Nebraska-issued CLP-commercial
learner's permit or commercial driver's license and shall surrender to the
department any operator's license issued to such individual by any other state.</para>
<para>(5) An operator's license
surrendered pursuant to this section may be returned to the driver after the
license has been perforated with the word "VOID".</para><para>(6) Any person who operates a commercial motor
vehicle upon the highways of this state in violation of this section shall,
upon conviction, be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 91; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 980, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 7, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 76, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB983, &#167; 26.</para><operativedate>July 8, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>