<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-4,109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,109</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Operating motor vehicle during period of suspension, revocation, or impoundment; city or village ordinance; penalties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Upon conviction of any person in any court within this state of a violation of any city or village ordinance pertaining to the operation of a motor vehicle by such person during any period that he or she is subject to a court order not to operate any motor vehicle for any purpose or during any period that his or her operator's license has been revoked or impounded pursuant to any law of this state, such person shall (a) for a first such offense, be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to operate any motor vehicle for any purpose for a period of one year from the date ordered by the court and also order the operator's license of such person to be revoked for a like period, unless the person was placed on probation, then revocation may be ordered at the court's discretion, and (b) for each subsequent such offense, be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor, and the court shall, as a part of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to operate any motor vehicle for any purpose for a period of two years from the date ordered by the court and also order the operator's license of such person to be revoked for a like period. Such orders of the court shall be administered upon sentencing, upon final judgment of any appeal or review, or upon the date that any probation is revoked.</para><para id="id00">(2) Upon conviction of any person in any court within this state of a violation of any city or village ordinance pertaining to the operation of a motor vehicle by such person (a) during any period that his or her operator's license has been suspended pursuant to any law of this state, (b) after a period of revocation but before issuance of a new license, or (c) after a period of impoundment but before the return of the license, such person shall be guilty of a Class III misdemeanor, and the court may, as a part of the judgment of conviction, order such person not to operate any motor vehicle for any purpose for a period of one year from the date ordered by the court, except that if the person at the time of sentencing shows proof of reinstatement of his or her suspended operator's license, proof of issuance of a new license, or proof of return of the impounded license, the person shall only be fined in an amount not to exceed one hundred dollars. If the court orders the person not to operate a motor vehicle for a period of one year after the date ordered by the court, the court shall also order the operator's license of such person to be revoked for a like period. Such orders of the court shall be administered upon sentencing, upon final judgment of any appeal or review, or upon the date that any probation is revoked.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 293, &#167; 4, p. 1099; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 60-430.05; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 772, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 38, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 66. </para></source><annotation><para>This section authorizes a city or village to prohibit the operation of a motor vehicle by a driver while his license is suspended. State v. Smith, 181 Neb. 846, 152 N.W.2d 16 (1967).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>