<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-6,195"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-6,195</statuteno><catchline>Racing on highways; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) No person shall drive any vehicle on any highway in any race, speed competition or contest, drag race or acceleration contest, test of physical endurance, or exhibition of speed or acceleration or for the purpose of making a speed record, and no person shall in any manner participate in any such race, competition, contest, test, or exhibition.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Drag race shall mean the operation of two or more vehicles from a point side by side at accelerating speeds in a competitive attempt to outdistance each other or the operation of one or more vehicles over a common selected course, each starting at the same point and proceeding to the same point, for the purpose of comparing the relative speeds or power of acceleration of such vehicle or vehicles within a certain distance or time limit; and</para><para>(b) Racing shall mean the use of one or more vehicles in an attempt to outgain or outdistance another vehicle, to prevent another vehicle from passing, to arrive at a given destination ahead of another vehicle or vehicles, or to test the physical stamina or endurance of drivers over long-distance driving routes.</para><para>(3) Any person convicted of violating this section shall be guilty of a Class II misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 45, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 39-668; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 291. </para></source><annotation><para>Where a person is injured by the racing of two or more other parties on a public highway, all engaged in the race are liable, although only one of the vehicles came in contact with the injured person or the vehicle in which he was riding. Janssen v. Trennepohl, 228 Neb. 6, 421 N.W.2d 4 (1988).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 