<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-147"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-147</statuteno><catchline>Mobile home or cabin trailer; application;
contents; mobile home transfer statement.</catchline><para>(1) An application
for a certificate of title for a mobile home or cabin trailer shall be accompanied
by a certificate that states that sales or use tax has been paid on the purchase
of the mobile home or cabin trailer or that the transfer of title was exempt
from sales and use taxes. The county treasurer shall
issue a certificate of title for a mobile home or cabin trailer but shall
not deliver the certificate of title unless the certificate required under
this subsection accompanies the application for certificate of title for the
mobile home or cabin trailer, except that the failure of the application to
be accompanied by such certificate shall not prevent the notation of a lien
on the certificate of title to the mobile home or cabin trailer pursuant to
section 60-164.</para>
<para>(2) An application for a certificate of title to a mobile home shall
be accompanied by a mobile home transfer statement prescribed by the Tax Commissioner.
The mobile home transfer statement shall be filed by the applicant with the
county treasurer of
the county of application for title. The county treasurer shall issue a certificate
of title to a mobile home but shall not deliver the certificate of title unless
the mobile home transfer statement accompanies the application for title,
except that the failure to provide the mobile home transfer statement shall
not prevent the notation of a lien on the certificate of title to the mobile
home pursuant to section 60-164 and delivery to the holder of the first lien.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB166, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>