<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id449"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,115.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,115.01</statuteno><catchline>Fee payment returned or not honored; department powers; notice to applicant; contents; payment; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If a fee required under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act for issuance of any operator's license or state identification card has been paid by check, draft, or other financial transaction, including an electronic financial transaction, and the check, draft, or financial transaction has been returned or not honored because of insufficient funds, no account, a stop-payment order, or any other reason, the department may cancel or refuse to issue or renew the operator's license or state identification card. Such license shall remain canceled or shall not be issued until the applicant has made full payment as required by subsection (4) of this section.</para><para>(2) Prior to taking action described in subsection (1) of this section, the department shall notify the applicant of the proposed action and the reasons for such action in writing, by first-class mail, mailed to the applicant's last-known mailing address provided by the applicant at the time of application.</para><para>(3) The department may take the action described in subsection (1) of this section no sooner than seven days after the notice required in subsection (2) of this section has been made.</para><para>(4) If an operator's license or state identification card is canceled or refused by the department pursuant to this section, the department shall issue or reinstate the operator's license or state identification card without delay upon the full payment of the fees owed by the applicant and payment of costs as authorized by section 84-620.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB311, &#167; 11. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>