<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-168.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-168.01</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of title; failure to note required brand or lien; notice to holder of title; corrected certificate of title; failure of holder to deliver certificate; effect; removal of improperly noted lien on certificate of title; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The department, upon receipt of clear and convincing evidence of a failure to note a required brand or failure to note a lien on a certificate of title, shall notify the holder of such certificate of title to deliver to the county treasurer or the department, within fifteen days after the date on the notice, such certificate of title to permit the noting of such brand or lien. After notation, the county treasurer or the department shall deliver the corrected certificate of title to the holder as provided by section 60-152. If a holder fails to deliver a certificate of title to the county treasurer or to the department, within fifteen days after the date on the notice for the purpose of noting such brand or lien on the certificate of title, the department shall cancel the certificate of title. This subsection does not apply when noting a lien in accordance with subsection (6) of section 60-164.</para><para>(2) The department may remove a lien on a certificate of title when such lien was improperly noted if evidence of the improperly noted lien is submitted to the department and the department finds the evidence sufficient to support removal of the lien. The department shall send notification prior to removal of the lien to the last-known address of the lienholder. The lienholder must respond within thirty days after the date on the notice and provide sufficient evidence to support that the lien should not be removed. If the lienholder fails to respond to the notice, the lien may be removed by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB286, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB202, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB909, &#167; 30. </para><effectivedate>April 12, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>