<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-4,118.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-4,118.02</statuteno><catchline>Health Advisory Board; created; members; terms; meetings.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Health Advisory Board which shall consist of six health care providers appointed by the director with the advice and recommendation of the Department of Health and Human Services. The members of the board shall consist of one general practice physician, one physician engaged in the practice of ophthalmology, one physician engaged in the practice of orthopedic surgery, one physician engaged in the practice of neurological medicine and surgery, one optometrist, and one psychiatrist. Each member of the board shall be licensed to practice his or her profession pursuant to the Uniform Credentialing Act.</para><para>(2) Of the initial members of the board, two shall be appointed for four years, two shall be appointed for three years, and two shall be appointed for two years. Thereafter, each member shall be appointed for a term of four years and until a successor is appointed and qualified. If a vacancy occurs for any reason other than the expiration of a term, the Director of Motor Vehicles may appoint a person licensed in the same type of professional practice as the member being replaced to serve out the unexpired term. Members of the board shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(3) The board shall meet as necessary at the call of the director. At the initial meeting of the board following completion of the initial appointments, the board shall select from among its members a chairperson and shall designate any other officers or committees as it deems necessary. The board may select officers and committees annually or as necessary to fill vacancies and to carry out duties of the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 211, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 281; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 230; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1174.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>