<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id00" statutenumber="60-681"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>60-681</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Highways, travel on; regulation by local authorities; when authorized; signs.</catchline><para>Local authorities may by ordinance or resolution prohibit the operation of vehicles upon any highway or impose restrictions as to the weight of vehicles, for a total period not to exceed one hundred eighty days in any one calendar year, when operated upon any highway under the jurisdiction of and for the maintenance of which such local authorities are responsible whenever any such highway by reason of deterioration, rain, snow, or other climatic condition will be seriously damaged or destroyed unless the use of vehicles thereon is prohibited or the permissible weight thereof reduced. Such local authorities enacting any such ordinance or resolution shall erect or cause to be erected and maintained signs designating the provisions of the ordinance or resolution at each end of that portion of any highway affected thereby, and the ordinance or resolution shall not be effective until such signs are erected and maintained.</para><para>Local authorities may also, by ordinance or resolution, prohibit the operation of trucks or other commercial vehicles or impose limitations as to the weight thereof on designated highways, which prohibitions and limitations shall be designated by appropriate signs placed on such highways.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1931, c. 110, &#167; 35, p. 316; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 39-1166; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 39-770; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,189; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB977, &#167; 21. </para></source><annotation><para>A city ordinance prohibiting vehicles weighing over five tons from using city streets except when such vehicles are delivering goods to or from city residences or businesses is constitutional. State v. Davison, 213 Neb. 173, 328 N.W.2d 206 (1982).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>