<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1407"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1407</statuteno><catchline>Application for license; contents.</catchline><para>Any person desiring to apply for one or more of the types of licenses described in the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act shall submit to the board, in writing, the following required information:</para><para>(1) The name and address of the applicant, if the applicant is an individual, his or her social security number, and the name under which he or she intends to conduct business. If the applicant is a partnership or limited liability company, it shall set forth the name and address of each partner or member thereof and the name under which the business is to be conducted. If the applicant is a corporation, it shall set forth the name of the corporation and the name and address of each of its principal officers;</para><para>(2) The place or places, including the city or village and the street and street number, if any, where the business is to be conducted;</para><para>(3) If the application is for a motor vehicle dealer's license, trailer dealer's license, or motorcycle dealer's license (a) the name or names of the new motor vehicle or vehicles, new trailer or trailers, or new motorcycle or motorcycles which the applicant has been enfranchised to sell or exchange, (b) the name or names and address or addresses of the manufacturer or distributor who has enfranchised the applicant, (c) a current copy of each existing franchise, and (d) a description of the community;</para><para>(4) If the application is for any of the above-named classes of dealer's licenses, the name and address of the person who is to act as a motor vehicle, trailer, or motorcycle salesperson under such license if issued;</para><para>(5) If the application is for a dealer's agent, the dealers for which the agent will be buying;</para><para>(6) A description of the proposed place or places of business proposed to be operated in the event a license is granted together with (a) a statement whether the applicant owns or leases the proposed established place of business and, if the proposed established place of business is leased, the applicant shall file a true and correct copy of the lease agreement, and (b) a description of the facilities for the display of motor vehicles, trailers, and motorcycles;</para><para>(7) If the application is for a manufacturer's license, a statement regarding the manufacturer's compliance with the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act; and</para><para>(8) A statement that the licensee will comply with and be subject to the act, the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the board, and any amendments to the act and the rules and regulations existing on the date of application.</para><para>Subdivision (3)(d) of this section shall not be construed to require any licensee who has a franchise on August 31, 2003, to show good cause to be in the same community as any other licensee who has a franchise of the same line-make in the same community on August 31, 2003.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 280, &#167; 7, p. 1017; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 286, &#167; 9, p. 1087; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 365, &#167; 5, p. 1172; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 394, &#167; 5, p. 1231; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 768, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1335, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 390; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 146; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 182, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 498, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB346, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>