<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id12">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id14" statutenumber="60-1420"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1420</statuteno><catchline id="id17">Franchise; termination; noncontinuance; change community; hearing;
when required.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection
(2) or (3) of this
section, no franchisor shall terminate or refuse to continue any franchise or change a franchisee's community unless
the franchisor has first established, in a hearing held pursuant to section
60-1425, that:</para>
<para>(a) The franchisor has good cause for termination, noncontinuance, or change;</para>
<para>(b) Upon termination or noncontinuance, another franchise
in the same line-make will become effective in the same community, without
diminution of the franchisee's service formerly provided, or that the community
cannot be reasonably expected to support such a dealership; and</para>
<para>(c) Upon termination or noncontinuance, the franchisor
is willing and able to comply with section 60-1430.02.</para>
<para>(2) Upon providing good and sufficient evidence to the board,
a franchisor may terminate a franchise without such hearing (a) for a particular
line-make if the franchisor discontinues that line-make, (b) if the franchisee's
license as a motor vehicle, combination motor vehicle and trailer, motorcycle,
or trailer dealer is revoked pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation
Act, or (c) upon a mutual written agreement of the franchisor and franchisee.</para>
<para>(3) A franchisor
may change a franchisee's community without a hearing if the franchisor notifies
the franchisee of the proposed change at least thirty days before the change,
provides the franchisee an opportunity to object, and enters into an agreement
with the franchisee regarding the change of the franchisee's community. If
no agreement is reached, the franchisor shall comply with sections 60-1420
to 60-1435 prior to changing the franchisee's community.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 768, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 327, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 280, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB477, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The Federal Arbitration Act preempts Nebraska law which is in conflict with the act. Cornhusker Internat. Trucks v. Thomas Built Buses, 263 Neb. 10, 637 N.W.2d 876 (2002).</para><para>The means by which a dealership can be terminated are found solely within this section. Chrysler Motors Corp. v. Lee Janssen Motor Co., 248 Neb. 322, 534 N.W.2d 309 (1995).</para><para>Where the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Board's order is clearly conditional, operating only in the event that the franchisor finds another franchisee and notifies the board of the fact that it has done so, it is not a final order and is therefore not appealable. Garber v. State, 241 Neb. 523, 489 N.W.2d 550 (1992).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>