<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1402</statuteno><catchline>Board; creation; membership; qualifications;
appointment; term; per diem; traveling expenses.</catchline><para>(1) There
is hereby established the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Board
which shall consist of the Director of Motor Vehicles, who shall be the chairperson of the board, and nine members
appointed by the Governor as follows: One factory representative, one member
of the general public, and one motorcycle dealer, all of whom shall be appointed
from the state at large, one new motor vehicle dealer from each of the three
congressional districts of the state as the districts are constituted on October
19, 1963, and two used motor vehicle dealers and one trailer dealer or combination
motor vehicle or trailer dealer, not more than one used motor vehicle dealer
being appointed from the same congressional district as they are constituted
on October 19, 1963, and the trailer dealer or combination motor vehicle or
trailer dealer being appointed from the state at large. No member of the board shall participate in any
manner in a proceeding before the board involving his or her licensed business.</para>
<para>(2) On October 19, 1963, the Governor shall appoint a new motor vehicle
dealer and a trailer dealer or combination motor vehicle or trailer dealer
to the board. In making the appointments, the Governor shall appoint one of
the new members for one year and one for two years as designated by the Governor in making the appointments. On
January 1, 1972, the Governor shall appoint one factory representative and
one member of the general public to the board, designating one to serve for
a term of one year and one for a term of two years. On January 1, 1974, the
Governor shall appoint one motorcycle dealer to serve for a term of three
years. At the expiration of the term of any appointed member of the board,
the Governor shall appoint a successor for a term of three years. In the event
of a vacancy on the board, the Governor shall fill such vacancy by appointing
a member to serve during the unexpired term of the member whose office has
become vacant. No member appointed shall serve more than two consecutive terms.
The action of the majority of the members of the board shall be deemed the
action of the board. All appointments made to the board, except the Director
of Motor Vehicles, shall be confirmed by the Legislature if in session. In
the event the Legislature is not in session all appointments including appointments
to fill a vacancy shall be temporary appointments until the next meeting of
the Legislature when the Governor shall nominate some person to fill the office.
Any person so nominated who is confirmed by the Legislature shall hold office during the remainder
of the term. No appointed person may act as a member of the board while holding
any other elective or appointive state or federal office except the Director
of Motor Vehicles. All appointed members of the board shall be paid fifty
dollars for each day actually engaged in the performance of their duties and
be entitled to their reasonable traveling expenses in the performance of their
duties.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 280, &#167; 2, p. 1014; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 282, &#167; 2, p. 823; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 365, &#167; 3, p. 1169; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 768, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 443, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 754, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 248, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 54.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For current limits and designation of congressional districts,</emphasis> see section 32-504.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The composition of the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Board is not inherently biased against automobile manufacturers, and therefore, the composition of the board does not violate the manufacturer's due process rights. Chrysler Motors Corp. v. Lee Janssen Motor Co., 248 Neb. 322, 534 N.W.2d 309 (1995).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>