<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id104">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id106" statutenumber="60-1438"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1438</statuteno><catchline id="id109">Manufacturer
or distributor; warranty obligation;
prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Each new motor
vehicle manufacturer or distributor shall specify in writing to each of its
new motor vehicle dealers licensed in this state the dealer's obligations
for preparation, delivery, and warranty service on its products. The manufacturer
or distributor shall compensate the new motor vehicle dealer for warranty
service which such manufacturer or distributor requires the dealer to provide, including warranty and recall obligations
related to repairing and servicing motor vehicles and all parts and components
included in or manufactured for installation in the motor vehicles of the
manufacturer or distributor. The manufacturer or distributor shall
provide the new motor vehicle dealer with the schedule of compensation to
be paid to the dealer for parts, work, and service and the time allowance
for the performance of the work and service.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The schedule of compensation
shall include reasonable compensation for diagnostic work, as well as repair
service, parts, and labor. Time allowances for the diagnosis and performance
of warranty work and service shall be reasonable and adequate for the work
to be performed. In the determination of what constitutes reasonable compensation
under this section, the principal factors to be given consideration shall
be the prevailing wage rates being paid by dealers in the community in which
the dealer is doing business, and in no event shall the compensation of the
dealer for warranty parts and labor be less than the rates charged by the
dealer for like parts and service to retail or fleet customers, as long as
such rates are reasonable. In
determining prevailing wage rates, the rate of compensation for labor for
that portion of repair orders for routine maintenance, such as oil and fluid
changes, shall not be used.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes
of this section, compensation for parts may be determined by calculating the
price paid by the dealer for parts, including all shipping and other charges,
multiplied by the sum of one and the dealer's average percentage markup over
the price paid by the dealer for parts purchased by the dealer from the manufacturer
and sold at retail. The dealer may establish average percentage markup by
submitting to the manufacturer one hundred sequential customer-paid service
repair orders or ninety days of customer-paid service repair orders, whichever
is less, covering repairs made no more than one hundred eighty days before
the submission and declaring what the average percentage markup is. Within
thirty days after receipt of the repair orders, the manufacturer may audit
the submitted repair orders and approve or deny approval of the average percentage
markup based on the audit. The average percentage markup shall go into effect
forty-five days after the approval based on that audit. If the manufacturer
denies approval of the average percentage markup declared by the dealer, the
dealer may file a complaint with the board. The manufacturer shall have the
burden to establish that the denial was reasonable. If the board determines
that the denial was not reasonable, the denial shall be deemed a violation
of the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act subject to the enforcement procedures
of the act. Only retail sales not involving warranty repairs or parts supplied
for routine vehicle maintenance shall be considered in calculating average
percentage markup. No manufacturer shall require a dealer to establish average
percentage markup by a methodology, or by requiring information, that is unduly
burdensome or time consuming to provide, including, but not limited to, part-by-part
or transaction-by-transaction calculations. A dealer shall not request a change
in the average percentage markup more than twice in one calendar year.</para>
<para>(3) A manufacturer or distributor shall not do any of the
following:</para>
<para>(a) Fail to perform any warranty obligation;</para>
<para>(b) Fail to include in written notices of factory recalls
to new motor vehicle owners and dealers the expected date by which necessary
parts and equipment will be available to dealers for the correction of the
defects; or</para>
<para>(c) Fail to compensate any of the new motor vehicle dealers
licensed in this state for repairs effected by the recall.</para>
<para>(4) A dealer's
claim for warranty compensation may be denied only if:</para>
<para>(a) The dealer's
claim is based on a nonwarranty repair;</para><para>(b) The dealer lacks documentation for
the claim;</para><para>(c) The dealer fails to comply with specific substantive terms
and conditions of the franchisor's warranty compensation program; or</para>
<para>(d) The manufacturer
has a bona fide belief based on competent evidence that the dealer's claim
is intentionally false, fraudulent, or misrepresented.</para>
<para>(5) All claims made by a new
motor vehicle dealer pursuant to this section for labor and parts shall be made within six months after completing
the work and shall be paid within thirty days after their approval.
All claims shall be either approved or disapproved by the manufacturer or
distributor within thirty days after their receipt on a proper form generally
used by the manufacturer or distributor and containing the usually required
information therein. Any claim not specifically disapproved in writing within
thirty days after the receipt of the form shall be considered to be approved
and payment shall be made within thirty days. The manufacturer has the right
to audit the claims for one year after
payment, except that if the
manufacturer has reasonable cause to believe that a claim submitted by a dealer
is intentionally false or fraudulent, the manufacturer has the right to audit
the claims for four years after payment. For purposes of this subsection,
reasonable cause means a bona fide belief based upon evidence that the issues
of fact are such that a person of ordinary caution, prudence, and judgment
could believe that a claim was intentionally false or fraudulent. As a result
of an audit authorized under this subsection, the manufacturer has the right to charge back to the
new motor vehicle dealer the amount of any previously
paid claim after
the new motor vehicle dealer has had notice and an opportunity to participate
in all franchisor internal appeal processes as well as all available legal
processes. The
requirement to approve and pay the claim within thirty days after receipt
of the claim does not preclude chargebacks for any fraudulent claim previously
paid. A manufacturer may not deny a claim based solely on a dealer's
incidental failure to comply with a specific claim processing requirement,
such as a clerical error that does not put into question the legitimacy of
the claim. If a claim is rejected for a clerical error, the dealer may resubmit
a corrected claim in a timely manner.</para>
<para>(6) The warranty obligations
set forth in this section shall also apply to any manufacturer of a new motor
vehicle transmission, engine, or rear axle that separately warrants its components
to customers.</para>
<para>(7) This section
does not apply to recreational vehicles.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 825, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 393, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 371, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB477, &#167; 9.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>