<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id391"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1446"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1446</statuteno><catchline>Board; hearing officer; investigators; powers and duties; seal; records; authentication; review of action; when.</catchline><para>(1) The board may:</para><para>(a) Regulate the issuance and revocation of licenses in accordance with and subject to the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act and the Recreational Vehicle Industry Regulation Act;</para><para>(b) Perform all acts and duties provided for in the Recreational Vehicle Industry Regulation Act that are necessary to the administration and enforcement of the act;</para><para>(c) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations relating to the administration of but not inconsistent with the Recreational Vehicle Industry Regulation Act;</para><para>(d) Enforce rules and regulations that were adopted and promulgated by the board; and</para><para>(e) Employ a hearing officer who shall conduct preliminary hearings on behalf of the board and make recommendations to the board on any issue or matter that the board deems proper.</para><para>(2) The seal of the board shall be used to authenticate the acts of the board. Copies of all records and papers in the office of the board under the hand and seal of the office shall be received in evidence in all cases equally and with like effect as the original.</para><para>(3) Investigators employed by the board may enter upon and inspect the facilities, the required records, and any recreational vehicles found in any licensee's established place or places of business.</para><para>(4) With respect to any action taken by the board, if a controlling number of the members of the board are active participants in the recreational vehicle market in which the action is taken, the chairperson of the board shall review the action taken and, upon completion of such review, modify, alter, approve, or reject the board's action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB972, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2026</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 60-1401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>