<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id855"><amendatorysection statutenumber="60-1903.02" chaptername="Motor Vehicles"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1903.02</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement agency; authority to remove abandoned or trespassing vehicle; private towing service; notice; contents.</catchline><para>(1) A law enforcement agency is authorized to remove an abandoned or trespassing vehicle from private property upon the request of the private property owner on whose property the vehicle is located and upon information indicating that the vehicle is an abandoned or trespassing vehicle. After removal, the law enforcement agency with custody of the vehicle shall follow the procedures in sections 60-1902 and 60-1903.</para><para>(2) A law enforcement agency is authorized to contact a private towing service in order to remove an abandoned or trespassing vehicle from private property upon the request of the private property owner on whose property the vehicle is located and upon information indicating that the vehicle is an abandoned or trespassing vehicle. A vehicle towed away under this subsection is subject to sections 52-601.01 to 52-605 and 60-2410 by the private towing service which towed the vehicle.</para><para>(3) A private property owner is authorized to remove or cause the removal of an abandoned or trespassing vehicle from such property and may contact a private towing service for such removal. A private towing service that tows the vehicle shall notify, within twenty-four hours, the designated law enforcement agency in the jurisdiction from which the vehicle is removed and provide the registration plate number, the vehicle identification number, if available, the make, model, and color of the vehicle, and the name of the private towing service and the location, if applicable, where the private towing service is storing the vehicle. A vehicle towed away under this subsection is subject to sections 52-601.01 to 52-605 and 60-2410 by the private towing service that towed the vehicle.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, a trespassing vehicle is a vehicle that is parked without permission on private property that is not typically made available for public parking.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB275, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>