<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1411"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1411</statuteno><catchline>Notice of changes; return of pocket card; required when.</catchline><para>If a motor vehicle dealer, motorcycle dealer, or trailer dealer changes the address of his or her place of business, changes franchise, adds another franchise, or loses a franchise for sale of new motor vehicles, motorcycles, or trailers, the dealer shall notify the board of such change within ten days prior to such change. Thereupon the license shall be corrected for the unexpired portion of the term at no additional fee except as provided in section 60-1411.01.</para><para>If any motor vehicle, trailer, or motorcycle salesperson is discharged, leaves his or her employer, or changes his or her place of employment, the employer who last employed the salesperson shall forthwith return the license to the board. The salesperson's pocket card shall thereupon be returned by the salesperson. The salesperson shall be notified at his or her last-known place of residence that his or her license has been returned to the board. It shall be unlawful for the salesperson to act as a motor vehicle, motorcycle, or trailer salesperson until a new license is secured.</para><para>If a dealer's agent changes his or her agent's status with any dealer, the agent shall notify the board. If the agent is no longer contracting with any dealer, the dealer's agent license shall lapse and the license and pocket card shall be returned to the board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 280, &#167; 11, p. 1020; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 365, &#167; 8, p. 1174; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 768, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1335, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 498, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 