<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id628"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1470"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1470</statuteno><catchline>New recreational vehicle; delivery to dealer; damage in transit; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) If a new recreational vehicle is damaged prior to transit to a dealer or is damaged in transit to a dealer and the carrier or means of transportation was selected by the manufacturer or distributor, the dealer shall notify the manufacturer or distributor of the damage within the timeframe specified in the manufacturer-dealer agreement and:</para><para>(a) Request authorization from the manufacturer or distributor to replace or correct any component, part, or accessory that was damaged; or</para><para>(b) Not take delivery of the recreational vehicle.</para><para>(2) The ownership of a new recreational vehicle described in subsection (1) of this section reverts to the manufacturer or distributor if:</para><para>(a) A dealer requests authorization under subdivision (1)(a) of this section and the manufacturer or distributor refuses or fails to make such authorization within ten business days after receiving the notification described in subsection (1) of this section; or</para><para>(b) The dealer does not take delivery of the recreational vehicle.</para><para>(3) A dealer that takes custody of a recreational vehicle described in subsection (1) of this section shall exercise due care with such recreational vehicle, but such dealer shall have no other obligations, financial or otherwise, with respect to such recreational vehicle.</para><para>(4)(a) For purposes of this subsection, unreasonable amount of miles means any amount determined by the dealer that is not less than the sum of:</para><para>(i) For recreational vehicles delivered from a manufacturer, one hundred miles plus the shortest distance over paved roads beginning at the location where the recreational vehicle was manufactured and ending at the dealership location; or</para><para>(ii) For recreational vehicles delivered from a distributor, one hundred miles plus the shortest distance over paved roads beginning from the location where the recreational vehicle was manufactured, through the location of the distributor, and ending at the dealership location.</para><para>(b) A dealer may choose to not take delivery of any new recreational vehicle if the odometer for such recreational vehicle indicates an unreasonable amount of miles. The ownership of such recreational vehicle shall revert to the manufacturer or distributor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB972, &#167; 29. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>