<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id5" statutenumber="60-1901"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1901</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Abandoned vehicle, defined.</catchline><para>(1) A motor vehicle is an abandoned vehicle:</para><para>(a) If left unattended, with no license plates or valid In Transit stickers issued pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Registration Act affixed thereto, for more than six hours on any public property;</para><para>(b) If left unattended for more than twenty-four hours on any public property, except a portion thereof on which parking is legally permitted;</para><para>(c) If left unattended for more than forty-eight hours, after the parking of such vehicle has become illegal, if left on a portion of any public property on which parking is legally permitted;</para><para>(d) If left unattended for more than seven days on private property if left initially without permission of the owner, or after permission of the owner is terminated;</para><para>(e) If left for more than thirty days in the custody of a law enforcement agency after the agency has sent a letter to the last-registered owner and lienholder under section 60-1903.01; or</para><para>(f) If removed from private property by a municipality pursuant to a municipal ordinance.</para><para>(2) An all-terrain vehicle, a utility-type vehicle, or a minibike is an abandoned vehicle:</para><para>(a) If left unattended for more than twenty-four hours on any public property, except a portion thereof on which parking is legally permitted;</para><para>(b) If left unattended for more than forty-eight hours, after the parking of such vehicle has become illegal, if left on a portion of any public property on which parking is legally permitted;</para><para>(c) If left unattended for more than seven days on private property if left initially without permission of the owner, or after permission of the owner is terminated;</para><para>(d) If left for more than thirty days in the custody of a law enforcement agency after the agency has sent a letter to the last-registered owner and lienholder under section 60-1903.01; or</para><para>(e) If removed from private property by a municipality pursuant to a municipal ordinance.</para><para>(3) A mobile home is an abandoned vehicle if left in place on private property for more than thirty days after a local governmental unit, pursuant to an ordinance or resolution, has sent a certified letter to each of the last-registered owners and posted a notice on the mobile home, stating that the mobile home is subject to sale or auction or vesting of title as set forth in section 60-1903.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Mobile home means a movable or portable dwelling constructed to be towed on its own chassis, connected to utilities, and designed with or without a permanent foundation for year-round living. It may consist of one or more units that can be telescoped when towed and expanded later for additional capacity, or of two or more units, separately towable but designed to be joined into one integral unit, and shall include a manufactured home as defined in section 71-4603. Mobile home does not include a mobile home or manufactured home for which an affidavit of affixture has been recorded pursuant to section 60-169;</para><para>(b) Public property means any public right-of-way, street, highway, alley, or park or other state, county, or municipally owned property; and</para><para>(c) Private property means any privately owned property which is not included within the definition of public property.</para><para>(5) No motor vehicle subject to forfeiture under section 28-431 shall be an abandoned vehicle under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 295, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 90, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 560, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 263; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB60, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1044, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB616, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>