
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1409"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1409</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Fund; created; collections; disbursements; investment; audited.</catchline><para>The Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Fund is created. All fees collected under the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act shall be remitted by the board, as collected, to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. Such fund shall be appropriated by the Legislature for the operations of the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Board and shall be paid out from time to time by warrants of the Director of Administrative Services on the State Treasurer for authorized expenditures upon duly itemized vouchers executed as provided by law and approved by the chairperson of the board or the executive secretary, except that transfers from the fund to the General Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature through June 30, 2018. The expenses of conducting the office must always be kept within the income collected and reported to the State Treasurer by such board. Such office and expense thereof shall not be supported or paid from the General Fund, and all money deposited in the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Fund shall be expended only for such office and expense thereof and, unless determined by the board, it shall not be required to expend any funds to any person or any other governmental agency.</para><para>Any money in the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The fund shall be audited by the Auditor of Public Accounts at such time as he or she determines necessary.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer five hundred thousand dollars from the Nebraska Motor Vehicle Industry Licensing Fund to the General Fund on or before June 30, 2018, on such dates and in such amounts as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 280, &#167; 9, p. 1019; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 60, p. 2382; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1335, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 754, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 248, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1310, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB337, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 29. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>