<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1513"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1513</statuteno><catchline>Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund is hereby created. The fund shall be administered by the Director of Motor Vehicles. In addition to money credited or remitted to the fund, the fund may also receive reimbursement from counties. The fund shall be used by the Department of Motor Vehicles to carry out its duties as deemed necessary by the Director of Motor Vehicles, except that transfers from the fund to the General Fund or the Vehicle Title and Registration System Replacement and Maintenance Cash Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer five million three hundred twenty-five thousand dollars from the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund to the Vehicle Title and Registration System Replacement and Maintenance Cash Fund on or before June 30, 2017, as directed by the budget administrator of the budget division of the Department of Administrative Services.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 467, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1191, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB271, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2022</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>