<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1306" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1306</statuteno><catchline>Carrier enforcement officers; powers; funding of firearms.</catchline><para>The carrier enforcement officers shall have the power (1) of peace officers solely for the purpose of enforcing the International Fuel Tax Agreement Act and the provisions of law relating to the size, weight, and load and the Motor Vehicle Registration Act pertaining to buses, motor trucks, truck-tractors, semitrailers, trailers, and towed vehicles, (2) when in uniform, to require the driver thereof to stop and exhibit his or her operator's license and registration issued for the vehicle and submit to an inspection of such vehicle, the license plates, the registration thereon, and licenses and permits required under the motor fuel laws, (3) to make arrests upon view and without warrant for any violation committed in their presence of the provisions of the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act or of any other law regulating the operation of vehicles or the use of the highways while in the performance of their duties referred to in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section and of sections 60-1308, 60-1309, and 75-362 to 75-369.07, (4) to make arrests upon view and without warrant for any violation committed in their presence which is a misdemeanor or felony under the laws of this state while in the performance of their duties referred to in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section and of sections 60-1308, 60-1309, and 75-362 to 75-369.07, and (5) to make arrests on warrant for any violation which is a misdemeanor or felony under the laws of this state while in the performance of their duties referred to in subdivisions (1) and (2) of this section and of sections 60-1308, 60-1309, and 75-362 to 75-369.07.</para><para>Any funds used to arm carrier enforcement officers shall be paid solely from the Carrier Enforcement Cash Fund. The amount of funds shall be determined by the Superintendent of Law Enforcement and Public Safety.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 145, &#167; 6, p. 407; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 373, &#167; 6, p. 1197; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 412, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 395, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 783, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 627, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 28, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1218, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 499, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 480, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 983, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 254; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1007, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>International Fuel Tax Agreement Act,</emphasis> see section 66-1401.</para><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act,</emphasis> see section 60-462.</para><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The arrest powers granted to carrier enforcement officers under this section do not allow arrests for all stated law violations which are observed while on duty, but are limited to arrests only for such stated violations which are viewed by the officer while performing a function specifically related to the duties enumerated in subsections (1) and (2) of this section or a function specifically related to those duties addressed in the statutes and laws referred to in subsections (3), (4), and (5) of this section. State v. Langan, 6 Neb. App. 739, 577 N.W.2d 752 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>