<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1406"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1406</statuteno><catchline>Licenses; classes.</catchline><para>Licenses issued by the board under the Motor Vehicle Industry Regulation Act shall be of the classes set out in this section and shall permit the business activities described in this section:</para><para>(1) Motor vehicle dealer's license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the business of selling or exchanging new, used, or new and used motor vehicles, trailers, and manufactured homes at the established place of business designated in the license and another place or places of business located within three hundred feet of the designated place of business and within the city or county described in the original license. This license permits the sale of a trade-in or consignment mobile home greater than forty feet in length and eight feet in width and located at a place other than the dealer's established place of business. This license permits one person, either the licensee, if he or she is the individual owner of the licensed business, or a stockholder, officer, partner, or member of the licensee, to act as a motor vehicle, trailer, and manufactured home salesperson and the name of the authorized person shall appear on the license;</para><para>(2) Manufacturer license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the activities of a motor vehicle, motorcycle, or trailer manufacturer or manufacturer's factory branch;</para><para>(3) Distributor license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the activities of a motor vehicle, motorcycle, or trailer distributor;</para><para>(4) Factory representative license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the activities of a factory branch representative;</para><para>(5) Factory branch license. This license permits the licensee to maintain a branch office in this state;</para><para>(6) Distributor representative license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the activities of a distributor representative;</para><para>(7) Finance company license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the activities of repossession of motor vehicles or trailers and the sale of such motor vehicles or trailers so repossessed;</para><para>(8) Wrecker or salvage dealer license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the business of acquiring motor vehicles or trailers for the purpose of dismantling the motor vehicles or trailers and selling or otherwise disposing of the parts and accessories of motor vehicles or trailers;</para><para>(9) Supplemental motor vehicle, motorcycle, or trailer dealer's license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the business of selling or exchanging motor vehicles, motorcycles, or trailers of the type designated in his or her dealer's license at a specified place of business which is located more than three hundred feet from any part of the place of business designated in the original motor vehicle, motorcycle, or trailer dealer's license but which is located within the city or county described in such original license;</para><para>(10) Motorcycle dealer's license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the business of selling or exchanging new, used, or new and used motorcycles at the established place of business designated in the license and another place or places of business located within three hundred feet of the designated place of business and within the city or county described in the original license. This form of license permits one person named on the license, either the licensee, if he or she is the individual owner of the licensed business, or a stockholder, officer, partner, or member of the licensee, to act as a motorcycle salesperson and the name of the authorized person shall appear on the license;</para><para>(11) Motor vehicle auction dealer's license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the business of selling motor vehicles and trailers. This form of license permits one person named on the license, either the licensee, if he or she is the individual owner of the licensed business, or a stockholder, officer, partner, or member of the licensee, to act as a motor vehicle auction dealer's salesperson and the name of the authorized person shall appear on the license;</para><para>(12) Trailer dealer's license. This license permits the licensee to engage in the business of selling or exchanging new, used, or new and used trailers and manufactured homes at the established place of business designated in the license and another place or places of business located within three hundred feet of the designated place of business and within the city or county described in the original license. This form of license permits one person named on the license, either the licensee, if he or she is the individual owner of the licensed business, or a stockholder, officer, partner, or member of the licensee, to act as a trailer and manufactured home salesperson and the name of the authorized person shall appear on the license; and</para><para>(13) Dealer's agent license. This license permits the licensee to act as the buying agent for one or more licensed motor vehicle dealers, motorcycle dealers, or trailer dealers. The agent shall act in accordance with a written contract and file a copy of the contract with the board. The dealer shall be bound by and liable for the actions of the agent. The dealer's agent shall disclose in writing to each dealer with which the agent contracts as an agent the names of all other dealers contracting with the agent. The agent shall make each purchase on behalf of and in the name of only one dealer and may purchase for dealers only at auctions and only from licensed dealers. The agent shall not act as a licensed dealer and is not authorized to sell any vehicle pursuant to this license.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 280, &#167; 6, p. 1016; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 307, &#167; 8, p. 977; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 365, &#167; 4, p. 1170; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 394, &#167; 4, p. 1229; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 768, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1335, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 754, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 248, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 825, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 389; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 564, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 632, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1018, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 498, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB816, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB346, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>