
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1515"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1515</statuteno><catchline>Department of Motor Vehicles Cash
Fund; use; legislative intent.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature hereby
finds and declares that a statewide system for the collection, storage, and
transfer of data on vehicle titles and registration and the cooperation of
state and local government in implementing such a system is essential to the
efficient operation of state and local government in vehicle titling and registration.
The Legislature hereby finds and declares that the electronic issuance of
operators' licenses and state identification cards using a digital system
as described in section 60-484.01 and the cooperation of state and local government
in implementing such a system is essential to the efficient operation of state
and local government in issuing operators' licenses and state identification
cards.</para>
<para>(2) It is therefor the intent of the Legislature that the Department
of Motor Vehicles shall use a portion of the fees appropriated by the Legislature
to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund as follows:</para>
<para>(a) To pay for the cost of issuing motor vehicle titles and registrations
on a system designated by the department. The costs shall include, but not
be limited to, software and software maintenance, programming, processing
charges, and equipment including such terminals, printers, or other devices
as deemed necessary by the department after consultation with the county to
support the issuance of motor vehicle titles and registrations. The costs
shall not include the cost of county personnel or physical facilities provided
by the counties;</para>
<para>(b) To fund the centralization
of renewal notices for motor vehicle registration and to furnish
to the counties the certificate of registration forms specified in section
60-390. The certificate of registration form shall be prescribed by the department;</para>
<para>(c) To pay for the costs of an operator's license system as specified
in sections 60-484.01 and 60-4,119 and designated by the department. The costs
shall be limited to such terminals, printers, software, programming, and other
equipment or devices as deemed necessary by the department to support the
issuance of such licenses and state identification cards in the counties and
by the department; and</para>
<para>(d) To pay for the motor vehicle insurance database created under section
60-3,136.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 467, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 574, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 488, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 258; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB207, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>