<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id99" statutenumber="60-1506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1506</statuteno><catchline id="id102">Registration and titling; records; copy or extract provided; electronic access; fee.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, vehicle means any motor vehicle, trailer, motorboat, all-terrain vehicle, utility-type vehicle, snowmobile, or minibike.</para><para>(2) The Department of Motor Vehicles shall keep a record of each vehicle registered or titled in this state, alphabetically by name of the owner, with cross reference in each instance to the registration number assigned to such vehicle. The record may be destroyed by any public officer having custody of it after three years from the date of its issuance.</para><para>(3)(a) The department shall issue a copy of the record of a registered or titled vehicle to any person after receiving from the person the name on the registration or certificate of title, the license plate number, the vehicle identification or other type of identification number, or the title number of a vehicle, if the person provides to the department verification of identity and purpose pursuant to section 60-2906 or 60-2907. A fee of three dollars shall be charged for the copy. Any fee received by the department pursuant to this subdivision shall be deposited into the License Plate Cash Fund.</para><para>(b)(i) An extract of the entire file of vehicles registered or titled in the state or updates to the entire file may be provided to a person upon payment of the following fee per one thousand records:</para><para>(A) Prior to July 1, 2026, twenty-five dollars; and</para><para>(B) Beginning July 1, 2026, thirty-five dollars.</para><para>(ii) Any fee received by the department pursuant to this subdivision (b) shall be deposited into the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund.</para><para>(4)(a) The record of each vehicle registration or title maintained by the department pursuant to this section may be made available electronically through the portal established under section 84-1204 so long as the Uniform Motor Vehicle Records Disclosure Act is not violated.</para><para>(b) There shall be a fee of three dollars per record for individual records and for data-to-data requests for multiple vehicle title and registration records.</para><para>(c) The following fees apply for bulk record requests of multiple vehicle titles and registrations selected on the basis of criteria of the individual making the request:</para><para>(i) Fifty dollars for every request under two thousand records;</para><para>(ii) Per one thousand records for any number of records over two thousand:</para><para>(A) Prior to July 1, 2026, twenty-five dollars; and</para><para>(B) Beginning July 1, 2026, thirty-five dollars; and</para><para>(iii) A reasonable programming fee not to exceed five hundred twenty dollars.</para><para>(d)(i) All fees collected pursuant to this subsection for electronic access to records through the portal shall be remitted to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit:</para><para>(A) For each fee paid under subdivision (b) of this subsection, two dollars per record to the License Plate Cash Fund and the remainder of such fee to the Records Management Cash Fund;</para><para>(B) For each fee paid under subdivision (c)(ii)(A) of this subsection, seven dollars per one thousand records for any number of records over two thousand to the License Plate Cash Fund and the remainder of such fee to the Records Management Cash Fund; and</para><para>(C) For each fee paid under subdivision (c)(ii)(B) of this subsection, seventeen dollars per one thousand records for any number of records over two thousand to the License Plate Cash Fund and the remainder of such fee to the Records Management Cash Fund.</para><para>(ii) All fees credited to the Records Management Cash Fund pursuant to this subsection shall be distributed as provided in any agreements between the State Records Board and the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 161; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB756, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB719, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2016, &#167; 60-3,161; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB263, &#167; 76; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB398, &#167; 52. </para><operativedate> July 1, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Motor Vehicle Records Disclosure Act,</emphasis> see section 60-2901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>