<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1903"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1903</statuteno><catchline>Local authorities or state agency; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Except for vehicles governed by section 60-1902, the local authority or state agency having custody of an abandoned vehicle shall make an inquiry concerning the last-registered owner of such vehicle as follows:</para><para>(a) Abandoned vehicle with license plates affixed, to the jurisdiction which issued such license plates; or</para><para>(b) Abandoned vehicle with no license plates affixed, to the Department of Motor Vehicles.</para><para>(2) The local authority or state agency shall notify the last-registered owner, if any, that the vehicle in question has been determined to be an abandoned vehicle and that, if unclaimed, either (a) it will be sold or will be offered at public auction after five days from the date such notice was mailed or (b) title will vest in the local authority or state agency thirty days after the date such notice was mailed. If the agency described in subdivision (1)(a) or (b) of this section also notifies the local authority or state agency that a lien or mortgage exists, such notice shall also be sent to the lienholder or mortgagee. Any person claiming such vehicle shall be required to pay the cost of removal and storage of such vehicle.</para><para>(3) Title to an abandoned vehicle, if unclaimed, shall vest in the local authority or state agency (a) five days after the date the notice is mailed if the vehicle will be sold or offered at public auction under subdivision (2)(a) of this section, (b) thirty days after the date the notice is mailed if the local authority or state agency will retain the vehicle, or (c) if the last-registered owner cannot be ascertained, when notice of such fact is received.</para><para>(4) After title to the abandoned vehicle vests pursuant to subsection (3) of this section, the local authority or state agency may retain for use, sell, or auction the abandoned vehicle. If the local authority or state agency has determined that the vehicle should be retained for use, the local authority or state agency shall, at the same time that the notice, if any, is mailed, publish in a newspaper of general circulation in the jurisdiction an announcement that the local authority or state agency intends to retain the abandoned vehicle for its use and that title will vest in the local authority or state agency thirty days after the publication.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 295, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 90, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 