<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id366">
<sectno id="id367" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 46.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id368" statutenumber="60-1901">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id370">60-1901</statuteno><catchline id="id371">Abandoned vehicle,
defined.</catchline><para>(1) A motor vehicle is an abandoned vehicle:</para>
<para>(a) If left unattended, with no license plates or valid In
Transit stickers issued pursuant to the Motor Vehicle Registration Act affixed
thereto, for more than six hours on any public property;</para>
<para>(b) If left unattended for more than twenty-four hours on
any public property, except a portion thereof on which parking is legally
permitted;</para>
<para>(c) If left unattended for more than forty-eight hours, after
the parking of such vehicle has become illegal, if left on a portion of any
public property on which parking is legally permitted;</para>
<para>(d) If left unattended for more than seven days on private
property if left initially without permission of the owner, or after permission
of the owner is terminated;</para>
<para>(e) If left for more than thirty days in the custody of a
law enforcement agency after the agency has sent a letter to the last-registered
owner under section 60-1903.01; or</para>
<para>(f) If removed from private property by a municipality pursuant
to a municipal ordinance.</para>
<para>(2) An all-terrain vehicle,
a utility-type vehicle, or a minibike
is an abandoned vehicle:</para>
<para>(a) If left unattended for more than twenty-four hours on
any public property, except a portion thereof on which parking is legally
permitted;</para>
<para>(b) If left unattended for more than forty-eight hours, after
the parking of such vehicle has become illegal, if left on a portion of any
public property on which parking is legally permitted;</para>
<para>(c) If left unattended for more than seven days on private
property if left initially without permission of the owner, or after permission
of the owner is terminated;</para>
<para>(d) If left for more than thirty days in the custody of a
law enforcement agency after the agency has sent a letter to the last-registered
owner under section 60-1903.01; or</para>
<para>(e) If removed from private property by a municipality pursuant
to a municipal ordinance.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Public property means any public right-of-way, street,
highway, alley, or park or other state, county, or municipally owned property;
and</para>
<para>(b) Private property means any privately owned property which
is not included within the definition of public property.</para>
<para>(4) No motor vehicle subject to forfeiture under section
28-431 shall be an abandoned vehicle under this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 295, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 90, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 560, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 263; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB60, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 46.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>