<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-1513"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>60-1513</statuteno><catchline>Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund is hereby created. The fund shall be administered by the Director of Motor Vehicles. In addition to money paid to the department or credited or remitted to the fund, the fund may also receive reimbursement from counties. The fund shall be used by the Department of Motor Vehicles to carry out its duties as deemed necessary by the Director of Motor Vehicles, except that transfers from the fund to the General Fund, the Operator's License Services System Replacement and Maintenance Fund, or the Vehicle Title and Registration System Replacement and Maintenance Cash Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning October 1, 2024, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 491, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 467, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1191, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 209, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1061, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB957, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB271, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2024, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB97, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 141. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB97, section 41, with LB264, section 141, to reflect all amendments.</note>
<note>Changes made by LB97 became operative April 15, 2025. Changes made by LB264 became operative May 22, 2025.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>