<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-2131"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-2131</statuteno><catchline>Certification of motorcycle safety course, motorcycle safety instructor's
certificate, or motorcycle trainer's certificate; denial, suspension,
or revocation; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The
director may cancel, suspend, revoke, or refuse to issue or renew certification of a motorcycle safety course, a
motorcycle safety instructor's certificate,
or a motorcycle trainer's certificate in any case when the director
finds the certificate holder or applicant
has not complied with or has violated the Motorcycle Safety Education Act
or any rule or regulation adopted and promulgated by the director. </para>
<para>(2) No person or provider whose certificate
has been canceled, suspended, revoked, or refused shall be certified until
the person or provider meets the requirements of rules and regulations of
the department and shows that the event or occurrence that caused the director
to take action has been corrected and will not affect future performance.
Persons or providers who are suspended may be summarily reinstated upon the
director's acceptance of a demonstration of compliance and satisfactory correction
of any noncompliance. All other persons or providers shall reapply for certification.
A person or provider may contest action taken by the director
to cancel, suspend, revoke, or refuse to issue or renew a certificate by filing a written petition
with the department within thirty days after the date of the director's action.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 22, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 60-2115; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1004, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 136; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 704, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB170, &#167; 12.</para></source> </law>
</legaldoc>
