<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-2909.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>60-2909.01</statuteno><catchline>Disclosure; purposes authorized.</catchline>
<para>The department and any officer, employee, agent, or contractor of the
department having custody of a motor vehicle record shall, upon the verification
of identity and purpose of a requester, disclose and make available the requested
motor vehicle record, including the sensitive personal information in the
record, other than the social security number, for the following purposes:</para>
<para>(1) For use by any federal, state, or local governmental agency, including
any court or law enforcement agency, in carrying out the agency's functions
or by a private person or entity acting on behalf of a governmental agency
in carrying out the agency's functions;</para>
<para>(2) For use in connection with any civil, criminal, administrative,
or arbitral proceeding in any federal, state, or local court or governmental
agency or before any self-regulatory body, including service of process, investigation
in anticipation of litigation, and execution or enforcement of judgments and
orders, or pursuant to an order of a federal, state, or local court, an administrative
agency, or a self-regulatory body;</para>
<para>(3) For use by any insurer or insurance support organization, or by
a self-insured entity, or its agents, employees, or contractors, in connection
with claims investigation activities, anti-fraud activities, rating, or underwriting;</para>
<para>(4) For use by an employer or the employer's agent or insurer to obtain
or verify information relating to a holder of a commercial driver's license
that is required under the Commercial Motor Vehicle Safety Act of 1986, 49
U.S.C. 31301 et seq., or pursuant to sections 60-4,132 and 60-4,141; and </para>
<para>(5) For use by employers
of commercial driver's license holders and by the Commercial Driver License
Information System as provided in section 60-4,144.02 and 49 C.F.R. 383.73.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 1317, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB178, &#167; 20.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>