<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-2129"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-2129</statuteno><catchline>Motorcycle
trainers; requirements; certificates; person
certified by another state; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing minimum
education requirements for motorcycle
trainers. The director shall issue certificates in
the manner and form prescribed by the director to no more than two motorcycle trainers who
meet the minimum education,
skill, and experience requirements. The department may reimburse documented expenses incurred
by a person in connection with taking and successfully passing an educational
course to become a motorcycle trainer, as provided in sections 81-1174 to
81-1177, when there are less than two motorcycle trainers working in this
state. In return for the reimbursement of such documented expenses, motorcycle
trainers shall teach the motorcycle safety instructor preparation
course as assigned by the director.</para>
<para>(2) If the
certification requirements are comparable to the requirements in this state,
a person currently certified as a motorcycle
trainer by another state or recognized accrediting organization
may be issued a motorcycle
trainer's certificate by the department without having to receive
the training required by this section.</para>
<para>(3) A person who holds
a valid, unexpired permit issued by the department to be a chief instructor
for motorcycle safety before January 1, 2012, shall be recognized as a motorcycle
trainer until January 1, 2014, or until the expiration date of such permit,
whichever is earlier. At that time the permit holder may apply for and be
recertified as a motorcycle trainer to teach a motorcycle safety instructor
preparation class in this state as provided in rules and regulations of the
department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1004, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB170, &#167; 10.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
