<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-2126"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-2126</statuteno><catchline>Motorcycle safety course; approval
by director; application; contents; certified motorcycle safety instructor
required; fee; course audits.</catchline>
<para>(1) A school,
business, or organization may
apply to the department to provide a motorcycle safety course or courses in this state. Prospective
providers of such course or courses shall submit an application for approval of such course or courses to
the director. The application
shall include a list of instructors of the course or courses. Such instructors
shall be or shall become motorcycle safety instructors certified by the department
prior to teaching any motorcycle safety course in this state. Applications
for certification of motorcycle safety instructors may be included along with
an application for approval of a motorcycle safety course or courses. The
director shall approve such course if it meets the requirements set forth by the department by rule and
regulation and will be taught by a certified motorcycle safety instructor or instructors.</para>
<para>(2) The application for
certification or renewal of a certification of each motorcycle safety course
shall be accompanied by a fee of one hundred dollars. The fee shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Motor Vehicles Cash
Fund. Motorcycle safety course certification shall expire two years from the
date of the director's certification.</para><para>(3) Motorcycle safety courses shall be subject to
audits by the department to assure compliance with the Motorcycle Safety Education
Act and rules and regulations of the department.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 22, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 60-2111; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1004, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB170, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>