
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-2410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-2410</statuteno><catchline>Towing and storage fees; liability;
lien; notice.</catchline><para>(1) The owner or other person lawfully entitled
to the possession of any vehicle towed or stored shall be charged with the
reasonable cost of towing and storage fees. Any such towing or storage fee
shall be a lien upon the vehicle under Chapter 52, article 6, and, except
as provided in subsection (3) of this section, shall be prior to all other
claims. Any person towing or storing a vehicle may retain possession of such
vehicle until such charges are paid or, after ninety days, may dispose of
such vehicle to satisfy the lien. Upon
payment of such charges, the person towing or storing the vehicle shall return
possession of the vehicle to the (a) owner, (b) lienholder, or (c) any other
person lawfully entitled to the possession of such vehicle making payment
of such charges. The lien provided for in this section shall not
apply to the contents of any vehicle.</para>
<para>(2) The person towing the vehicle
shall, within fifteen business days after
towing, notify any lienholder appearing on the certificate of title of the vehicle and the owner
of the vehicle
of the towing of the vehicle.
The notice shall be sent by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the
last-known address of the lienholder and owner of the vehicle. The notice shall contain:</para>
<para>(a) The make, model, color, year, and vehicle identification number
of the vehicle;</para>
<para>(b) The name, address, and telephone number of the person who towed
the vehicle;</para>
<para>(c) The date of towing;</para>
<para>(d) The daily storage fee and the storage fee accrued as of the date
of the notification; and</para>
<para>(e) A statement that the vehicle
is subject to lien and disposition by sale or other manner ninety days after
the date of towing under Chapter 52, article 6.</para>
<para>(3) Failure to provide notice as prescribed in subsection (2) of this
section shall result in the lien of the person who towed the vehicle being subordinate to the lien
of the lienholder appearing on the certificate of title and render void any
disposition of the vehicle
by the person who towed the vehicle.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 348, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 833, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 82, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1065, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not provide for a lien for protection of the tower in collecting fees. The reference in this section to section 60-2405 is an obvious error because section 60-2405 does not concern a lien. Section 60-2404 was apparently intended. Packett v. Lincolnland Towing, 227 Neb. 595, 419 N.W.2d 149 (1988).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>