<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-2127"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-2127</statuteno><catchline>Motorcycle safety instructors; certificate; requirements; renewal; person certified by another state;
how treated.</catchline><para>(1) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing minimum standards, skills' qualifications, and education
requirements for motorcycle safety instructors. The director shall issue or renew a certificate in
the manner and form prescribed by the director to motorcycle safety instructor
applicants who meet such requirements. A
motorcycle safety instructor certificate shall expire two years after the
date of issuance. To renew a certificate, a person shall submit an application
demonstrating compliance with rules and regulations of the department.</para>
<para>(2) If the certification requirements are comparable to the requirements
in this state, a person currently certified as a motorcycle safety instructor
by another state or recognized accrediting organization may be issued a motorcycle
safety instructor's certificate by the department
without having to take the course established in section 60-2128.</para>
<para>(3) A person who holds
a valid, unexpired permit issued by the department to be a motorcycle safety
instructor before January 1, 2012, shall be recognized as a certified motorcycle
safety instructor until January 1, 2014, or until the expiration date of such
permit, whichever is earlier. At that time the permit holder may apply for
and become a certified motorcycle safety instructor to teach a motorcycle
safety class in this state as provided in rules and regulations of the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 22, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 60-2112; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1004, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB170, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
