<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id361">
<sectno id="id362">Sec. 37.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Motor Vehicles" id="id363" statutenumber="60-2132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id365">60-2132</statuteno><catchline id="id366">Motorcycle
Safety Education Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>There
is hereby created a Motorcycle Safety Education Fund in the state treasury
which shall consist of money transferred pursuant to sections 39-2215 and
60-4,115 and such money as may be appropriated by the Legislature. The fund
shall be administered by the department. The fund shall be used for the administration
of the Motorcycle Safety Education Act, to reimburse approved schools, businesses,
or organizations for conducting approved basic motorcycle safety courses,
to provide educational assistance, to prepare sites for offering the basic
motorcycle safety course, to reimburse approved schools, businesses, or organizations
for conducting approved advanced motorcycle safety courses, and to promote
motorcycle safety, except that
transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of
the Legislature. Any money in the Motorcycle
Safety Education Fund available for investment shall be invested
by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion
Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 22, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 469, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1089, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 5, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1984), &#167; 60-2116; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1004, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 285, &#167; 137; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB219, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 37.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>