<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id801"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3206"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3206</statuteno><catchline>Governmental entity; duties; report; contents.</catchline><para>Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (3)(b) of this section, any governmental entity that uses an automatic license plate reader system shall:</para><para>(1) Adopt a policy governing use of the system and conspicuously post the policy on the governmental entity's Internet website or, if no website is available, in its main office;</para><para>(2) Adopt a privacy policy to ensure that captured plate data is not shared in violation of the Automatic License Plate Reader Privacy Act or any other law and conspicuously post the privacy policy on its Internet website or, if no website is available, in its main governmental office; and</para><para>(3)(a) Report annually to the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice on its automatic license plate reader practices and usage. The report shall also be conspicuously posted on the governmental entity's Internet website or, if no website is available, in its main office. The report shall include the following information, if captured by the automatic license plate reader system:</para><para>(i) The names of each list against which captured plate data was checked, the number of confirmed matches, and the number of matches that upon further investigation did not correlate to an alert; and</para><para>(ii) The number of manually-entered license plate numbers under subsection (3) of section 60-3204, the number of confirmed matches, and the number of matches that upon further investigation did not correlate to an alert.</para><para>(b) The reporting requirements of this subsection shall not apply to governmental entities using an automatic license plate reader system pursuant to subdivisions (2)(b) through (e) of section 60-3203.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB93, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>