<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id436"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3402</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Peer-to-Peer Vehicle Sharing Program Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Agreement means the terms and conditions applicable to an owner and a driver that govern the use of a vehicle shared through a peer-to-peer vehicle sharing program. Agreement does not mean a rental agreement as defined in section 44-4067;</para><para>(2) Delivery period means the period of time during which a vehicle is being delivered to the location at which the start time begins, if applicable, as documented by the agreement;</para><para>(3) Driver means an individual who has been authorized to drive a vehicle by an owner under an agreement;</para><para>(4) Owner means the registered owner, or a person or entity designated by the registered owner, of a vehicle made available for sharing through a peer-to-peer vehicle sharing program;</para><para>(5) Peer-to-peer vehicle sharing program or program means a business platform that connects owners with drivers to enable the sharing of vehicles for financial consideration. A program is not a transportation network company as defined in section 75-323 or a rental car company as defined in section 44-4067;</para><para>(6) Sharing means the authorized use of a vehicle by an individual other than an owner through a peer-to-peer vehicle sharing program;</para><para>(7) Sharing period means the period of time that commences with the delivery period or, if there is no delivery period, that commences with the start time and, in either case, ends at the termination time;</para><para>(8) Start time means the time when a vehicle becomes subject to the control of a driver at or after the time the reservation is scheduled to begin as documented in the records of a program;</para><para>(9) Termination time means the earliest of the following events:</para><para>(a) The expiration of the agreed upon period of time established for the use of a vehicle according to the terms of the agreement if the vehicle is delivered to the location specified in the agreement;</para><para>(b) When a vehicle is returned to an alternative location as agreed upon by the owner and driver as communicated through the peer-to-peer vehicle sharing program. Such alternative location shall be incorporated into the agreement; and</para><para>(c) When an owner, or the owner's authorized designee, takes possession and control of the vehicle; and</para><para>(10) Vehicle means a motor vehicle as defined in section 60-471 that is available for use through a peer-to-peer vehicle sharing program. Vehicle does not include any motor vehicle used as or offered for use as a rental vehicle under section 44-4067, any commercial motor vehicle as defined in section 60-465, or any vehicle subject to section 75-363.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1073, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>