<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id850"><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" statutenumber="60-3303"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3303</statuteno><catchline>Automated-driving-system-equipped vehicle; operation; authorized; provisions applicable; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the operation on the public roads of this state of an automated-driving-system-equipped vehicle capable of performing the entire dynamic driving task within its operational design domain while a conventional human driver is present is lawful. Such operation shall be subject to the Nebraska Rules of the Road, as applicable. In addition, the conventional human driver shall be licensed as required under the Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act, shall remain subject to the Nebraska Rules of the Road, shall operate the automated-driving-system-equipped vehicle according to the manufacturer's requirements and specifications, and shall regain manual control of the vehicle upon the request of the automated driving system.</para><para>(2) The automated driving system feature, while engaged, shall be designed to operate within its operational design domain in compliance with the Nebraska Rules of the Road, including, but not limited to, safely negotiating railroad crossings, unless an exemption has been granted by the department. The department shall consult with the railroad companies operating in this state when considering an exemption that affects vehicle operations at railroad crossings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB989, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Operator's License Act,</emphasis> see section 60-462.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Rules of the Road,</emphasis> see section 60-601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>