<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Motor Vehicles" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="60-3101" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>60-3101</statuteno><catchline>State fleet card programs; Department of Transportation; University of Nebraska; State Treasurer; duties; political subdivisions; utilization authorized; unauthorized use prohibited.</catchline><para>(1) State fleet card programs shall be created and shall be administered separately by the Department of Transportation and the University of Nebraska. The Department of Transportation shall administer a fleet card program on behalf of state government and political subdivisions other than the University of Nebraska under a contract through the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall determine the type of fleet card or cards utilized in the state fleet card program. The State Treasurer shall contract with one or more financial institutions, card-issuing banks, credit card companies, charge card companies, debit card companies, or third-party merchant banks capable of operating a fleet card program on behalf of the state, including the University of Nebraska, and political subdivisions that participate in the state contract for such services. Rules and regulations may be adopted and promulgated as needed by the Department of Transportation or the University of Nebraska for the operation of the state fleet card programs. The rules and regulations shall provide authorization instructions for all transactions. Expenses associated with the state fleet card programs shall be considered as an administrative or operational expense.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, fleet card means a payment card used for gasoline, diesel, and other fuels. Fleet cards may also be used to pay for vehicle and equipment maintenance and expenses at the discretion of the program administrator. The Department of Transportation and the University of Nebraska shall each designate a program administrator.</para><para>(3) Any state official, agency, board, or commission may utilize a state fleet card for the purchase of goods and services described in subsection (2) of this section for and on behalf of the State of Nebraska. Any political subdivision may utilize a fleet card for the purchase of goods and services described in subsection (2) of this section for lawful government purposes of the political subdivision. No disbursements or cash back on fleet card transactions shall be allowed.</para><para>(4) Vendors accepting a state fleet card shall obtain authorization for all transactions in accordance with instructions from the program administrator. Transaction authorization shall be from the financial institution, card-issuing bank, credit card company, charge card company, debit card company, or third-party merchant bank contracted to provide such service to the State of Nebraska. Each transaction shall be authorized in accordance with the instructions provided by the program administrator for each state official, agency, board, or commission or each political subdivision.</para><para>(5) Detailed transaction information for the purposes of tracking expenditures shall include fleet card identification, merchant name and address, transaction number, date, time, product, quantity, cost, and equipment meter reading if applicable. A state fleet card program may require an itemized receipt for purposes of tracking expenditures of a state fleet card purchase from a commercial vendor as acceptable detailed transaction information. If detailed transaction information is not provided, the program administrator shall have the authority to temporarily or permanently suspend state fleet card purchases in accordance with rules and regulations.</para><para>(6) No officer or employee of the state or of a political subdivision shall use a state fleet card for any unauthorized use.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB137, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 236. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>