<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id266"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-617"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>30-617</statuteno><catchline>Health care facility; rights; health care provider; rights.</catchline><para>(1) Nothing in the Health Care Surrogacy Act obligates a health care facility to honor a health care decision by a surrogate that the health care facility would not honor if the decision had been made by the individual because the decision is contrary to a formally adopted policy of the health care facility that is expressly based on religious beliefs or sincerely held ethical or moral convictions central to the operating principles of the health care facility. The health care facility may refuse to honor the decision whether made by the individual or by the surrogate if the health care facility has informed the individual or the surrogate of such policy, if reasonably possible. If the surrogate is unable or unwilling to arrange a transfer to another health care facility, the health care facility refusing to honor the decision may intervene to facilitate such a transfer.</para><para>(2) Nothing in the Health Care Surrogacy Act obligates a health care provider to honor or cooperate with a health care decision by a surrogate that the health care provider would not honor or cooperate with if the decision had been made by the individual because the decision is contrary to the health care provider's religious beliefs or sincerely held moral or ethical convictions. The health care provider shall promptly inform the surrogate and the health care facility of his or her refusal to honor or cooperate with the decision of the surrogate. In such event, the health care facility shall promptly assist in the transfer of the individual to a health care provider selected by the individual or the surrogate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB104, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>