<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id385"><amendatorysection statutenumber="30-706" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>30-706</statuteno><catchline>Petition; contents; confidential; stay; when.</catchline><para>(1) Any action under sections 30-701 to 30-713 shall be commenced by filing in the county court a verified petition described in section 30-703. The family member petitioner shall include, if reasonably ascertainable under oath, the places where the resident has resided and the names and present addresses of the persons with whom the resident has lived during the previous five years. The petition shall include a statement under oath identifying whether:</para><para>(a) The family member petitioner has participated as a party, as a witness, or in any other capacity or in any other proceeding concerning custody or visitation with the resident and if so, identify the court, the case number, and the date of any order which may affect visitation;</para><para>(b) The family member petitioner knows of any proceeding that could affect the current proceeding relating to domestic violence, a protective order, termination of parental rights, adoption, guardianship, conservatorship, or habeas corpus or any other civil or criminal proceeding, and if so, identify the court, the case number, and the date of any order which may affect visitation;</para><para>(c) The family member petitioner knows the name and address of any person not a party to the proceeding who has physical custody of, is residing with, or is providing residential services to the resident and if so, the name and address of such person;</para><para>(d) The resident needs a guardian ad litem or a visitor appointed;</para><para>(e) Any other state would have jurisdiction under the Nebraska Uniform Adult Guardianship and Protective Proceedings Jurisdiction Act;</para><para>(f) A bond or probation condition exists which would affect the case; and</para><para>(g) The family member petitioner has filed petitions under section 30-703 within the preceding five years and if so, the court, the case number, and the date of any order resolving the prior petitions.</para><para>(2) Any matters which may be confidential under court rule or statute shall be filed as a confidential document for review by the court as to whether such matters shall remain filed as confidential matters.</para><para>(3) If the information required by subsection (1) of this section is not furnished, the court, upon the motion of a party or its own motion, may stay the proceeding until the information is furnished.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB845, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Adult Guardianship and Protective Proceedings Jurisdiction Act,</emphasis> see section 30-3901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>