<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id641"><amendatorysection amended="no" statutenumber="30-515" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-515</statuteno><catchline>Fiduciary duty and authority.</catchline><para>(a) The legal duties imposed on a fiduciary charged with managing tangible property apply to the management of digital assets, including:</para><para>(1) the duty of care;</para><para>(2) the duty of loyalty; and</para><para>(3) the duty of confidentiality.</para><para>(b) A fiduciary’s or designated recipient's authority with respect to a digital asset of a user:</para><para>(1) except as otherwise provided in section 30-504, is subject to the applicable terms-of-service agreement;</para><para>(2) is subject to other applicable law, including copyright law;</para><para>(3) in the case of a fiduciary, is limited by the scope of the fiduciary’s duties; and</para><para>(4) may not be used to impersonate the user.</para><para>(c) A fiduciary with authority over the property of a decedent, protected person, principal, or settlor has the right to access any digital asset in which the decedent, protected person, principal, or settlor had a right or interest and that is not held by a custodian or subject to a terms-of-service agreement.</para><para>(d) A fiduciary acting within the scope of the fiduciary’s duties is an authorized user of the property of the decedent, protected person, principal, or settlor for the purpose of applicable computer-fraud and unauthorized-computer-access laws, including the Computer Crimes Act and section 86-2,104.</para><para>(e) A fiduciary with authority over the tangible personal property of a decedent, protected person, principal, or settlor:</para><para>(1) has the right to access the property and any digital asset stored in it; and</para><para>(2) is an authorized user for the purpose of computer-fraud and unauthorized-computer-access laws, including the Computer Crimes Act and section 86-2,104.</para><para>(f) A custodian may disclose information in an account to a fiduciary of the user when the information is required to terminate an account used to access digital assets licensed to the user.</para><para>(g) A fiduciary of a user may request a custodian to terminate the user's account. A request for termination must be in writing, in either physical or electronic form, and accompanied by:</para><para>(1) if the user is deceased, a certified copy of the death certificate of the user;</para><para>(2) a certified copy of the letter of appointment of the representative or a small-estate affidavit or court order, power of attorney, or trust giving the fiduciary authority over the account; and</para><para>(3) if requested by the custodian:</para><para>(A) a number, username, address, or other unique subscriber or account identifier assigned by the custodian to identify the user’s account;</para><para>(B) evidence linking the account to the user; or</para><para>(C) a finding by the court that the user had a specific account with the custodian, identifiable by the information specified in subdivision (3)(A) of this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB829, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Computer Crimes Act,</emphasis> see section 28-1341.</para> </crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>