<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id915"><amendatorysection statutenumber="30-516" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>30-516</statuteno><catchline>Custodian compliance and immunity.</catchline><para>(a) Not later than sixty days after receipt of the information required under sections 30-507 to 30-515, a custodian shall comply with a request under the Revised Uniform Fiduciary Access to Digital Assets Act (2015) from a fiduciary or designated recipient to disclose digital assets or terminate an account. If the custodian fails to comply, the fiduciary or designated recipient may apply to the court for an order directing compliance.</para><para>(b) An order under subsection (a) of this section directing compliance must contain a finding that compliance is not in violation of 18 U.S.C. 2702, as amended.</para><para>(c) A custodian may notify the user that a request for disclosure or to terminate an account was made under the Revised Uniform Fiduciary Access to Digital Assets Act (2015).</para><para>(d) A custodian may deny a request under the Revised Uniform Fiduciary Access to Digital Assets Act (2015) from a fiduciary or designated recipient for disclosure of digital assets or to terminate an account if the custodian is aware of any lawful access to the account following the receipt of the fiduciary’s request.</para><para>(e) The Revised Uniform Fiduciary Access to Digital Assets Act (2015) does not limit a custodian's ability to obtain or require a fiduciary or designated recipient requesting disclosure or termination under the act to obtain a court order which:</para><para>(1) specifies that an account belongs to the protected person or principal;</para><para>(2) specifies that there is sufficient consent from the protected person or principal to support the requested disclosure; and</para><para>(3) contains a finding required by law other than the act.</para><para>(f) A custodian and its officers, employees, and agents are immune from liability for an act or omission done in good faith in compliance with the Revised Uniform Fiduciary Access to Digital Assets Act (2015).</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB829, &#167; 16. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2017</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>