<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id140">
<sectno id="id141" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 23.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id142" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="30-2715.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2715.01</statuteno><catchline>Motor vehicle; transfer on death;
certificate of title.</catchline><para>(1) A person who owns a motor vehicle may provide for the
transfer of such vehicle upon his or her death or the death of the last survivor
of a joint tenancy with right of survivorship by including in the certificate
of title a designation of beneficiary or beneficiaries to whom the vehicle
will be transferred on the death of the owner or the last survivor, subject
to the rights of all lienholders, whether created before, simultaneously with,
or after the creation of the transfer-on-death interest. A trust may be the
beneficiary of a transfer-on-death certificate of title. The certificate of
title shall include the name of the owner, the name of any tenant-in-common
owner or the name of any joint-tenant-with-right-of-survivorship owner, followed
in substance by the words transfer on death to (name of beneficiary or beneficiaries
or name of trustee if a trust is to be the beneficiary). The abbreviation
TOD may be used instead of the words transfer on death to.</para>
<para>(2) A transfer-on-death
beneficiary shall have no interest in the motor vehicle until the death of
the owner or the last survivor of the joint-tenant-with-right-of-survivorship
owners. A beneficiary designation may be changed at any time by the owner
or by the joint-tenant-with-right-of-survivorship owners then surviving without
the consent of any beneficiary by filing an application for a subsequent certificate
of title.</para><para>(3) Ownership of a motor vehicle which has a designation of beneficiary
as provided in subsection (1) of this section and for which an application
for a subsequent certificate of title has not been filed shall vest in the
designated beneficiary or beneficiaries on the death of the owner or the last
of the joint-tenant-with-right-of-survivorship owners, subject to the rights
of all lienholders.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 23.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>