<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id365">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates" id="id367" statutenumber="30-2628">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2628</statuteno><catchline id="id370">General powers,
rights, and duties of guardian;
inventory.</catchline><para>(a) Except as limited by section
30-2620, a guardian of an incapacitated person has the same powers, rights,
and duties respecting the guardian's ward
that a parent has respecting the parent's unemancipated
minor child, except that a guardian is not liable to third persons for acts
of the ward solely by reason of the parental relationship. In particular,
and without qualifying the foregoing, a guardian has the following powers
and duties, except as may be specified by order of the court:</para>
<para>(1) To the extent that it is consistent with the terms of
any order by a court of competent jurisdiction relating to detention or commitment
of the ward, a guardian is entitled to
custody of the person of his or her ward and may establish the ward's place
of abode within this state or, with court permission, outside of  this state. When establishing
the ward's place of abode, a guardian shall make every reasonable effort to
ensure that the placement is the least restrictive alternative. A guardian
shall authorize a placement to a more restrictive environment only after careful
evaluation of the need for such placement. The guardian may obtain a professional
evaluation or assessment that such placement is in the best interest of the
ward.</para>
<para>(2) If entitled to custody of his or her ward, a guardian shall make provision for the care,
comfort, and maintenance of his or her ward and, whenever appropriate, arrange
for the ward's training and education.
Without regard to custodial rights of the ward's person, a
guardian shall take reasonable care of his or her ward's clothing,
furniture, vehicles, and other personal effects and commence protective proceedings
if other property of his or her ward is in need of protection.</para>
<para>(3) A guardian may give any consents or approvals that may
be necessary to enable the ward to receive medical, psychiatric, psychological,
or other professional care, counsel, treatment, or service. When making such
medical or psychiatric decisions, the guardian shall consider and carry out
the intent of the ward expressed prior to incompetency to the extent allowable
by law. Notwithstanding this provision or any other provision of the Nebraska
Probate Code, the ward may authorize the release of financial, medical, and
other confidential records pursuant to sections 20-161 to 20-166.</para>
<para>(4) If no
conservator for the estate of the ward has been appointed, a guardian shall,
within thirty days after appointment, prepare and file with the appointing
court a complete inventory of the ward's estate together with the guardian's
oath or affirmation that the inventory is complete and accurate so far as
the guardian is informed. The guardian shall mail a copy thereof by first-class
mail to the ward, if the ward can be located and has attained the age of fourteen
years, and to all other interested persons as defined in section 30-2601.
The guardian shall keep suitable records of the guardian's administration
and exhibit the same on request of any interested person. To the extent a
guardian, who has not been named a conservator, has possession or control
of the ward's estate, the guardian shall file with the court an updated inventory
every year along with an affidavit of mailing showing that copies were sent
to all interested persons and, if a bond has been required, to the bonding
company by first-class mail along with a form to send back to the court that
indicates if such person wants to continue receiving notifications about the
proceedings.</para><para>(5) If
no conservator for the estate of the ward has been appointed, a
guardian may:</para>
<para>(i) Institute proceedings to compel any person under a duty
to support the ward or to pay sums for the welfare of the ward to perform such person's duty;</para>
<para>(ii) Receive money and tangible property deliverable to the
ward and apply the money and property for support, care, and education of
the ward; but a guardian may not use funds
from his or her ward's estate for room and board which the guardian or the guardian's spouse, parent,
or child has furnished the ward unless a charge for the service is approved
by order of the court made upon notice to at least one of the next of kin
of the ward, if notice is possible. A guardian must
exercise care to conserve any excess for the ward's needs; and</para>
<para>(iii) Exercise a settlor's powers with respect to revocation,
amendment, or distribution of trust property when authorized by a court acting
under the authority of subsection (f) of section 30-3854. In acting under
the authority of subsection (f) of section 30-3854, the court shall proceed
in the same manner as provided under subdivision (3) of section 30-2637.</para>
<para>(6) A guardian is required
to report the condition of his or her ward and of the estate which has been
subject to the guardian's possession
or control, at least every year and as required by the court or court rule.
The court shall receive from any interested person, for a period of thirty
days after the filing of the guardian's report, any comments with regard to
the need for continued guardianship or amendment of the guardianship order.
If the court has reason to believe that additional rights should be returned
to the ward or assigned to the guardian, the court shall set a date for a
hearing and may provide all protections as set forth for the original finding
of incapacity and appointment of a guardian.</para>
<para>(7) If a conservator has been
appointed, all of the ward's estate received by the guardian in excess of
those funds expended to meet current expenses for support, care, and education
of the ward must be paid to the conservator for management as provided in
the Nebraska Probate Code, and the guardian must account to the conservator
for funds expended.</para>
<para>(b) Any guardian of one for whom a conservator also has been
appointed shall control the custody and care of the ward and is entitled to receive reasonable sums
for the guardian's services and
for room and board furnished to the ward as agreed upon between the guardian and the conservator if the
amounts agreed upon are reasonable under the circumstances. The guardian may
request the conservator to expend the ward's estate by payment to third persons
or institutions for the ward's care and maintenance.</para>
<para>(c) Nothing in subdivision (a)(3) of this section or in any
other part of this section shall be construed to alter the decisionmaking
authority of an attorney in fact designated and authorized under sections
30-3401 to 30-3432 to make health care decisions pursuant to a power of attorney
for health care.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 246, UPC &#167; 5-312; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 428, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 782, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 466, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 130; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 39.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2012</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Placing the establishment of a visitation schedule in the guardian is anticipated by the statutory duties assigned to a guardian with full powers. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Karin P., 271 Neb. 917, 716 N.W.2d 681 (2006).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>