<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-2211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2211</statuteno><catchline>Subject matter jurisdiction.</catchline><para>(a) To the full extent permitted by the Constitution of Nebraska, the court has jurisdiction over all subject matter relating to (1) estates of decedents, including construction of wills and determination of heirs and successors of decedents, and estates of protected persons; and (2) protection of minors and incapacitated persons.</para><para>(b) The court has full power to make orders, judgments, and decrees and take all other action necessary and proper to administer justice in the matters which come before it.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 11, UPC &#167; 1-302; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 123.</para></source><annotation><para>In common-law and equity actions relating to decedents' estates, the county courts have concurrent original jurisdiction with the district courts. When the jurisdiction of the county court and district court is concurrent, the basic principles of judicial administration require that the court which first acquires jurisdiction should retain it to the exclusion of the other court. Washington v. Conley, 273 Neb. 908, 734 N.W.2d 306 (2007).</para><para>To the extent permitted by the Nebraska Constitution, the county court has jurisdiction over all subject matter relating to estates of decedents, including the determination of heirs, subject to administration. Mischke v. Mischke, 253 Neb. 439, 571 N.W.2d 248 (1997).</para><para>County courts, in exercising exclusive original jurisdiction over estates, may apply equitable principles to matters within probate jurisdiction. In re Estate of Steppuhn, 221 Neb. 329, 377 N.W.2d 83 (1985).</para><para>In an equity action to determine title to joint bank accounts based on constructive trust or conversion, the county courts cannot acquire jurisdiction under this section since they have no equity jurisdiction over this type of action. Miller v. Janecek, 210 Neb. 316, 314 N.W.2d 250 (1982).</para><para>County courts have exclusive original jurisdiction of all matters related to decedents' estates, including the probate of wills and the construction thereof, and all other jurisdiction heretofore provided and not specifically repealed by Laws 1972, LB 1032, and such other jurisdiction as thereafter provided by law. County courts, in exercising exclusive original jurisdiction over estates, may apply equitable principles to matters within probate jurisdiction. In re Estate of Layton, 207 Neb. 646, 300 N.W.2d 802 (1981).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>