<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2726"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2726</statuteno><catchline>Rights of creditors and others.</catchline><para>(a) If other assets of the estate are insufficient, a transfer resulting from a right of survivorship or POD designation under sections 30-2716 to 30-2733 is not effective against the estate of a deceased party to the extent needed to pay claims against the estate, statutory allowances to the surviving spouse and children, taxes, and expenses of administration.</para><para>(b) A surviving party or beneficiary who receives payment from an account after death of a party is liable to account to the personal representative of the decedent for a proportionate share of the amount received to which the decedent, immediately before death, was beneficially entitled under section 30-2722, to the extent necessary to discharge the amounts described in subsection (a) of this section remaining unpaid after application of the decedent's estate. A proceeding to assert the liability for claims against the estate and statutory allowances may not be commenced unless the personal representative has received a written demand by the surviving spouse, a creditor, a child, or a person acting for a child of the decedent. The proceeding must be commenced within one year after death of the decedent.</para><para>(c) A surviving party or beneficiary under sections 30-2716 to 30-2733 against whom a proceeding to account is brought may join as a party to the proceeding a surviving party or beneficiary of any other account of the decedent or a surviving owner or beneficiary under sections 30-2734 to 30-2745 of any securities or securities account of the decedent or proceeds thereof.</para><para>(d) Sums recovered by the personal representative must be administered as part of the decedent's estate. This section does not affect the protection from claims of the personal representative or estate of a deceased party provided in section 30-2732 for a financial institution that makes payment in accordance with the terms of the account.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 250, &#167; 12. </para></source><annotation><para>The purpose of this section is to alert the personal representative of the need to recover nonprobate assets and to trigger the personal representative's duty and authority to initiate proceedings to do so. In re Estate of Lorenz, 292 Neb. 543, 873 N.W.2d 396 (2016).</para><para>This section protects the beneficiaries of such nonprobate assets from incurring liability for claims made against the estate more than 1 year after the death of the decedent. In re Estate of Lorenz, 292 Neb. 543, 873 N.W.2d 396 (2016).</para><para>This section requires more than notice&#8212;it requires a written demand upon the personal representative before a proceeding to recover nonprobate assets may be commenced. In re Estate of Lorenz, 292 Neb. 543, 873 N.W.2d 396 (2016).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>