<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2401</statuteno><catchline>Devolution of estate at death; restrictions.</catchline><para>The power of a person to leave property by will, and the rights of creditors, devisees, and heirs to his property are subject to the restrictions and limitations contained in this code to facilitate the prompt settlement of estates. Upon the death of a person, his real and personal property devolves to the persons to whom it is devised by his last will or to those indicated as substitutes for them in cases involving lapse, renunciation, or other circumstances affecting the devolution of testate estate or, in the absence of testamentary disposition, to his heirs, or to those indicated as substitutes for them in cases involving renunciation or other circumstances affecting devolution of intestate estates, subject to homestead allowance, exempt property and family allowance, to rights of creditors, elective share of the surviving spouse, and to administration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 79, UPC &#167; 3-101.</para></source><annotation>
<para>In Nebraska, title to both real and personal property passes immediately upon death to the decedent's devisees or heirs, subject to administration, allowances, and a surviving spouse's elective share. Wilson v. Fieldgrove, 280 Neb. 548, 787 N.W.2d 707 (2010).</para>
<para>This section does not create an absolute right in the heir of a deceased person whose estate is being administered to sue to recover property alleged to be a part of the estate, in derogation of those interests to which the potential rights of the heir are subordinate, including the rights of creditors and the orderly administration of the decedent's estate. Beachy v. Becerra, 259 Neb. 299, 609 N.W.2d 648 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>