<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id229" statutenumber="30-2640"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2640</statuteno><catchline id="id232">Bond.</catchline><para>For estates with a net value of more than ten thousand dollars, the bond for a conservator shall be in the amount of the aggregate capital value of the personal property of the estate in the conservator's control plus one year's estimated income from all sources minus the value of securities and other assets deposited under arrangements requiring an order of the court for their removal. The bond of the conservator shall be conditioned upon the faithful discharge of all duties of the trust according to law, with sureties as the court shall specify. The court, in lieu of sureties on a bond, may accept other security for the performance of the bond, including a pledge of securities or a mortgage of land owned by the conservator. For good cause shown, the court may eliminate the requirement of a bond or decrease or increase the required amount of any such bond previously furnished. The court shall not require a bond if the protected person executed a written, valid power of attorney that specifically nominates a guardian or conservator and specifically does not require a bond. The court shall consider as one of the factors of good cause, when determining whether a bond should be required and the amount thereof, the protected person's choice of any attorney in fact or alternative attorney in fact. No bond shall be required of any financial institution, as that term is defined in section 8-101.03, or any officer, director, employee, or agent of the financial institution serving as a conservator, or any trust company serving as a conservator. The Public Guardian shall not be required to post bond.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 258, UPC &#167; 5-411; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 292, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB920, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB140, &#167; 152. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>