<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id00" statutenumber="30-2619"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2619</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Procedure for court appointment of a guardian or standby guardian of a person alleged to be incapacitated.</catchline><para>(a) The person alleged to be incapacitated or any person interested in his or her welfare may petition for a finding of incapacity and appointment of a guardian or a standby guardian. The petition shall be verified and shall contain specific allegations with regard to each of the areas as provided under section 30-2619.01 in which the petitioner claims that the person alleged to be incapacitated lacks sufficient understanding to make or communicate responsible decisions concerning his or her own person. An interested person may file a motion to make more definite and certain requesting a specific description of the functional limitations and physical and mental condition of the person alleged to be incapacitated with the specific reasons prompting the request for guardianship.</para><para>(b) Upon the filing of a petition, the court shall set a date for hearing on the issues of incapacity and unless the person alleged to be incapacitated has retained counsel of his or her own choice or has otherwise indicated a desire for an attorney of his or her own choice, the court may appoint an attorney to represent him or her in the proceeding. The court may appoint a guardian ad litem to advocate for the best interests of the person alleged to be incapacitated.</para><para>(c) The person alleged to be incapacitated may be examined by a physician appointed by the court. The physician shall submit his or her report in writing to the court and may be interviewed by a visitor, if so appointed pursuant to sections 30-2619.01 and 30-2624, sent by the court.</para><para>(d) The person alleged to be incapacitated is entitled to be present at the hearing in person and to see and hear all evidence bearing upon his or her condition. He or she is entitled to be present by counsel, to compel the attendance of witnesses, to present evidence, to cross-examine witnesses, including the court-appointed physician and the visitor appointed by the court pursuant to sections 30-2619.01 and 30-2624, and to appeal any final orders or judgments. The issue may be determined at a closed hearing only if the person alleged to be incapacitated or his or her counsel so requests.</para><para>(e) At any hearing conducted under this section, the court may designate one or more standby guardians of the person whose appointment will become effective immediately upon the death, unwillingness or inability to act, resignation, or removal by the court of the initially appointed guardian and upon compliance with any rules promulgated by the Supreme Court. The standby guardian shall have the same powers and duties as the initially appointed guardian. The standby guardian shall receive a copy of the order establishing or modifying the initial guardianship and the order designating the standby guardian. Upon assuming office, the standby guardian shall so notify the court in writing. Upon notification and upon compliance with any rules promulgated by the Supreme Court, the court shall issue new letters of guardianship that specify that the standby guardianship appointment is permanent. A standby guardian shall complete the training required by section 30-2601.01 at the time or times required by rules promulgated by the Supreme Court or as otherwise provided by order of the county court.</para><para>(f) The Public Guardian shall not be appointed as a standby guardian.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 237, UPC &#167; 5-303; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 650, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 428, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 782, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 466, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB43, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>An evidentiary hearing should be held expediently on a guardianship or conservatorship petition, and temporary guardians and conservators are intended to exercise their powers in a limited manner and for a limited period of time. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Larson, 270 Neb. 837, 708 N.W.2d 262 (2006).</para><para>Proceedings initiated to appoint a guardian are special proceedings. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Larson, 270 Neb. 837, 708 N.W.2d 262 (2006).</para><para>The rule that a true evidentiary hearing is required to support a finding of incompetency cannot be circumvented by continuous extensions of a temporary guardianship, nor are numerous reports by a guardian ad litem a substitute for an evidentiary hearing. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Larson, 270 Neb. 837, 708 N.W.2d 262 (2006).</para><para>Subsection (a) of this section is neither unconstitutionally vague nor overbroad. In re Guardianship and Conservatorship of Sim, 225 Neb. 181, 403 N.W.2d 721 (1987).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>