<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id442">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id444" statutenumber="30-2648"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2648</statuteno><catchline id="id447">Accounts.</catchline>
<para>Every conservator must account to the court for his or her administration of the
trust annually, upon
his or her resignation
or removal, and at such other
times as the court may direct. On termination of the protected person's minority
or disability, a conservator may account to the court, or the
conservator may account to the former protected person or the former protected person's personal representative.
Subject to appeal or vacation within the time permitted, an order, made upon
notice and hearing, allowing an intermediate account of a conservator, adjudicates
as to the conservator's liabilities
concerning the matters considered in connection therewith; and an order, made
upon notice and hearing, allowing a final account adjudicates as to all previously
unsettled liabilities of the conservator to the protected person or the protected person's successors relating to
the conservatorship. In connection with any account, the court may require
a conservator to submit to a physical check of the estate in his or her control, to be made
in any manner the court may specify.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 266, UPC &#167; 5-419; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 45.</para></source><annotation><para>There is no final adjudication of an intermediate account without an evidentiary hearing. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Cordel, 274 Neb. 545, 741 N.W.2d 675 (2007).</para><para>The word "compensation" in the context of letters of conservatorship and Neb. Ct. R. of Cty. Cts. 43 (rev. 2000) includes any form of payment or remuneration made to the conservator from assets of the protected person. In re Conservatorship of Hanson, 268 Neb. 200, 682 N.W.2d 207 (2004).</para><para>An order allowing an intermediate account adjudicates as to the liabilities of the conservator only if made upon notice and hearing and then only concerning the matters considered. In re Conservatorship of Estate of Lindauer, 221 Neb. 146, 376 N.W.2d 1 (1985).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
