<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2303</statuteno><catchline>Share of heirs other than surviving spouse.</catchline><para>The part of the intestate estate not passing to the surviving spouse under section 30-2302, or the entire intestate estate if there is no surviving spouse, passes as follows:</para><para>(1) to the issue of the decedent; if they are all of the same degree of kinship to the decedent they take equally, but if of unequal degree, then those of more remote degree take by representation;</para><para>(2) if there is no surviving issue, to his parent or parents equally;</para><para>(3) if there is no surviving issue or parent, to the issue of the parents or either of them by representation;</para><para>(4) if there is no surviving issue, parent or issue of a parent, but the decedent is survived by one or more grandparents or issue of grandparents, half of the estate passes to the paternal grandparents if both survive, or to the surviving paternal grandparent, or to the issue of the paternal grandparents if both are deceased, the issue taking equally if they are all of the same degree of kinship to the decedent, but if of unequal degree those of more remote degree take by representation; and the other half passes to the maternal relatives in the same manner; but if there be no surviving grandparent or issue of grandparent on either the paternal or the maternal side, the entire estate passes to the relatives on the other side in the same manner as the half;</para><para>(5) if there is no surviving issue, parent, issue of a parent, grandparent or issue of a grandparent, the entire estate passes to the next of kin in equal degree, excepting that when there are two or more collateral kindred in equal degree, but claiming through different ancestors, those who claim through the nearest ancestor shall be preferred to those claiming through a more remote ancestor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 25, UPC &#167; 2-103. </para></source>
<annotation><para>Grandchildren are "issue of parents" under subsection (3) of this section according to the definition of "issue of a person" found in section 30-2209(23). In re Estate of Evans, 20 Neb. App. 602, 827 N.W.2d 314 (2013).</para><para>Modern per stirpes distribution begins division of shares of the estate at the first generation where there is living issue. In re Estate of Evans, 20 Neb. App. 602, 827 N.W.2d 314 (2013).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc>