<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2427"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2427</statuteno><catchline>Formal testacy proceeding; notice of hearing on petition.</catchline><para>(a) Upon commencement of a formal testacy proceeding, the court shall fix a time and place of hearing. Notice shall be given in the manner prescribed by section 30-2220 by the petitioner under subdivision 30-2220(a)(1) to the persons herein enumerated and to any additional person who has filed a demand for notice under section 30-2413.</para><para>Notice shall be given to the following persons: The surviving spouse, children, and other heirs of the decedent, the devisees and executors named in any will that is being, or has been, probated, or offered for informal or formal probate in the county, or that is known by the petitioner to have been probated, or offered for informal or formal probate elsewhere, and any personal representative of the decedent whose appointment has not been terminated. Notice may be given to other persons. In addition, the clerk shall publish notice to all unknown persons and to all known persons whose addresses are unknown who have any interest in the matters being litigated in accordance with section 30-2220(a)(2). The party instituting or maintaining the proceeding or his or her attorney is required to mail the published notice and give proof thereof in accordance with section 25-520.01.</para><para>(b) If it appears by the petition or otherwise that the fact of the death of the alleged decedent may be in doubt, or on the written demand of any interested person, a copy of the notice of the hearing on the petition shall be sent by certified or registered mail to the alleged decedent at his or her last-known address. The court shall direct the petitioner to report the results of, or make and report back concerning, a reasonably diligent search for the alleged decedent in any manner that may seem advisable, including any or all of the following methods:</para><para>(1) By inserting in one or more suitable periodicals a notice requesting information from any person having knowledge of the whereabouts of the alleged decedent;</para><para>(2) By notifying law enforcement officials and public welfare agencies in appropriate locations of the disappearance of the alleged decedent;</para><para>(3) By engaging the services of an investigator. The costs of any search so directed shall be paid by the petitioner if there is no administration or by the estate of the decedent in case there is administration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 105, UPC &#167; 3-403; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 93, &#167; 10. </para></source><annotation><para>There is no statutory requirement that the interested parties be notified as to the content or date of execution of the document or documents offered for probate. The statutory requirement is for notice that there is a petition to probate the estate. In re Estate of Seidler, 241 Neb. 402, 490 N.W.2d 453 (1992).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>