<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2346"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2346</statuteno><catchline>Nonademption of specific devises in certain cases; sale by conservator; unpaid proceeds of sale, condemnation, or insurance.</catchline><para>(a) If specifically devised property is sold by a conservator or guardian, or if a condemnation award or insurance proceeds are paid to a conservator or guardian as a result of condemnation, fire, or casualty, the specific devisee has the right to a general pecuniary devise equal to the net sale price, the condemnation award, or the insurance proceeds. This subsection does not apply if, subsequent to the sale, condemnation, or casualty, it is adjudicated that the disability of the testator has ceased and the testator survives the adjudication by one year. The right of the specific devisee under this subsection is reduced by any right he has under subsection (b).</para><para>(b) A specific devisee has the right to the remaining specifically devised property and:</para><para>(1) any balance of the purchase price (together with any security interest) owing from a purchaser to the testator at death by reason of sale of the property;</para><para>(2) any amount of a condemnation award for the taking of the property unpaid at death;</para><para>(3) any proceeds unpaid at death on fire or casualty insurance on the property; and</para><para>(4) property owned by testator at his death as a result of foreclosure, or obtained in lieu of foreclosure, of the security for a specifically devised obligation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 68, UPC &#167; 2-608.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not create an exception to the common-law rule of implied revocation when property is sold by an attorney in fact under a durable power of attorney. In re Estate of Bauer, 270 Neb. 91, 700 N.W.2d 572 (2005).</para><para>Where a testator has, during his lifetime, sold specifically devised property and, at his death, an unpaid balance remains owing to him from the sale, the beneficiary of the specific bequest is entitled to receive the unpaid balance. In re Estate of McClow, Reed v. McClow, 205 Neb. 739, 290 N.W.2d 186 (1980).</para><para>When a conservator or guardian, not the testator, sells specifically devised property during the testator's lifetime, no ademption occurs. The proceeds of the sale are not included in the testator's residuary estate, but, rather, are given to the specific devisee to honor the specific devise. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Mueller, 23 Neb. App. 430, 872 N.W.2d 906 (2015).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>