<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2426"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2426</statuteno><catchline>Formal testacy or appointment proceedings; petition; contents.</catchline><para>(a) Petitions for formal probate of a will, or for adjudication of intestacy with or without request for appointment of a personal representative, must be directed to the court, request a judicial order after notice and hearing and contain further statements as indicated in this section. A petition for formal probate of a will</para><para>(1) requests an order as to the testacy of the decedent in relation to a particular instrument which may or may not have been informally probated and determining the heirs,</para><para>(2) contains the statements required for informal applications as stated in subdivisions (1)(i) through (v) of section 30-2414, the statements required by subdivisions (2)(ii) and (iii) of section 30-2414, and</para><para>(3) states whether the original of the last will of the decedent is in the possession of the court, accompanies the petition, or has been filed electronically and will be delivered to the court within ten days after the filing of the application.</para><para>The petition also must state the contents of the will and indicate that it is lost, destroyed, or otherwise unavailable if the original will or an authenticated copy of the will probated in another jurisdiction:</para><para>(i) is not in the possession of the court;</para><para>(ii) did not accompany the application; and</para><para>(iii) has not been filed electronically, subject to delivery within ten days after the filing of the application.</para><para>(b) A petition for adjudication of intestacy and appointment of an administrator in intestacy must request a judicial finding and order that the decedent left no will and determining the heirs, contain the statements required by subdivisions (1) and (4) of section 30-2414 and indicate whether supervised administration is sought. A petition may request an order determining intestacy and heirs without requesting the appointment of an administrator, in which case the statements required by subdivision (4)(ii) of section 30-2414 may be omitted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 104, UPC &#167; 3-402; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB966, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>