<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id154">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id156" statutenumber="30-2626"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2626</statuteno><catchline id="id159">Temporary guardians;
power of court.</catchline><para>(a) If a person alleged to be
incapacitated has no guardian and an emergency exists, the court may, pending
notice and hearing, exercise the power of a guardian or enter an ex parte
order appointing a temporary guardian to address the emergency. The order
and letters of temporary guardianship shall specify the powers and duties
of the temporary guardian limiting the powers and duties to those necessary
to address the emergency.</para>
<para>(b) When the court takes action to exercise the powers of
a guardian or to appoint a temporary guardian under subsection (a) of this
section, an expedited hearing shall be held if requested by the person alleged
to be incapacitated, or by any interested person, if the request is filed
more than ten business days prior to the date set for the hearing on the petition
for appointment of the guardian. If an expedited hearing is to be held, the
hearing shall be held within ten business days after the request is received.
At the hearing on the temporary appointment, the petitioner shall have the
burden of showing by a preponderance of the evidence that temporary guardianship
continues to be necessary to address the emergency situation. Unless the person
alleged to be incapacitated has counsel of his or her own choice, the court
may appoint an attorney to represent the person alleged to be incapacitated
at the hearing as provided in section 30-2619.</para>
<para>(c) If an expedited hearing is requested, notice shall be
served as provided in section 30-2625. The notice shall specify that a temporary
guardian has been appointed and shall be given at least twenty-four hours
prior to the expedited hearing.</para>
<para>(d) At the expedited hearing, the court may render a judgment
authorizing the temporary guardianship to continue beyond the original ten-day
period. The judgment shall prescribe the specific powers and duties of the
temporary guardian in the letters of temporary guardianship and shall be effective
for a single ninety-day period. For good cause shown, the court may extend
the temporary guardianship for successive ninety-day periods.</para>
<para>(e) The temporary guardianship shall terminate at the end
of the ninety-day period in which the temporary guardianship is valid or at
any time prior thereto if the court deems the circumstances leading to the
order for temporary guardianship no longer exist or if an order has been entered
as a result of a hearing pursuant to section 30-2619 which has been held during
the ninety-day period.</para>
<para>(f) If the court denies the request for the ex parte order,
the court may, in its discretion, enter an order for an expedited hearing
pursuant to subsections (b) through (e) of this section.</para>
<para>(g) If the petitioner requests the entry of an order of temporary
guardianship pursuant to subsection (a) of this section without requesting
an ex parte order, the court may hold an expedited hearing pursuant to subsections
(b) through (e) of this section.</para>
<para>(h) If an appointed guardian is not effectively performing
his or her duties and the court further finds that the welfare of the incapacitated
person requires immediate action, it may, pending notice and hearing in accordance
with section 30-2220, appoint a temporary guardian for the incapacitated person
for a specified period not to exceed ninety days. For good cause shown, the
court may extend the temporary guardianship for successive ninety-day periods.
A temporary guardian appointed pursuant to this subsection has only the powers
and duties specified in the previously appointed guardian's letters of guardianship,
and the authority of any permanent guardian previously appointed by the court
is suspended so long as a temporary guardian has authority.</para>
<para>(i) A temporary guardian may be removed at any time. A temporary
guardian shall make any report the court requires, except that a temporary
guardian shall not be required to provide the check or report under section
30-2602.02. In other respects the provisions of the Nebraska Probate Code
concerning guardians apply to temporary guardians.</para>
<para>(j) The court
may appoint the Public Guardian as the temporary guardian pursuant to the
Public Guardianship Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 244, UPC &#167; 5-310; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 650, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 782, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 466, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB920, &#167; 22.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Public Guardianship Act,</emphasis> see section 30-4101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>An evidentiary hearing should be held expediently on a guardianship or conservatorship petition, and temporary guardians and conservators are intended to exercise their powers in a limited manner and for a limited period of time. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Larson, 270 Neb. 837, 708 N.W.2d 262 (2006).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>