<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2611"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2611</statuteno><catchline>Court appointment of guardian of minor; procedure.</catchline><para>(a) Notice of the time and place of hearing of a petition for the appointment of a guardian of a minor is to be given by the petitioner in the manner prescribed by section 30-2220 to:</para><para>(1) the minor, if he is fourteen or more years of age;</para><para>(2) the person who has had the principal care and custody of the minor during the sixty days preceding the date of the petition; and</para><para>(3) any living parent of the minor.</para><para>(b) Upon hearing, if the court finds that a qualified person seeks appointment, venue is proper, the required notices have been given, the requirements of section 30-2608 have been met, and the welfare and best interests of the minor will be served by the requested appointment, it shall make the appointment. In other cases the court may dismiss the proceedings, or make any other disposition of the matter that will best serve the interest of the minor.</para><para>(c) If necessary, the court may appoint a temporary guardian, with the status of an ordinary guardian of a minor, but the authority of a temporary guardian shall not last longer than six months. In an emergency, the court may appoint a temporary guardian of a minor without notice, pending notice and hearing.</para><para>(d) If, at any time in the proceeding, the court determines that the interests of the minor are or may be inadequately represented, it may appoint an attorney to represent the minor, giving consideration to the preference of the minor if the minor is fourteen years of age or older.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 229, UPC &#167; 5-207; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 650, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>