<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2619.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2619.01</statuteno><catchline>Visitor appointment; conduct evaluation; duties.</catchline><para>Following the filing of a petition, the court may appoint a visitor and direct such visitor to conduct an evaluation of the allegations of incapacity as provided under this section. To conduct the evaluation of the allegations of incapacity, the visitor shall interview the allegedly incapacitated person, the person seeking appointment as guardian, the agencies providing services to the allegedly incapacitated person, and other persons and agencies that may provide relevant information. The visitor shall also visit the present place of abode of the person alleged to be incapacitated and, if any change of residence is anticipated, the place it is proposed that he or she will be detained or reside if the requested appointment is made, and submit his or her report in writing to the court.</para><para>As part of the evaluation of allegations of incapacity, a visitor, if appointed, shall obtain evidence relating to the allegedly incapacitated person's ability to make, communicate, or carry out responsible decisions concerning his or her person with regard to:</para><para>(1) Selecting his or her place of abode within or without this state;</para><para>(2) Arranging for his or her medical care;</para><para>(3) Protecting his or her personal effects;</para><para>(4) Giving necessary consents, approvals, or releases;</para><para>(5) Arranging for training, education, or other habilitating services appropriate to him or her;</para><para>(6) Applying for private or governmental benefits to which he or she may be entitled;</para><para>(7) Instituting proceedings to compel any person liable for the support of the proposed ward to support him or her if no conservator has been appointed for the proposed ward;</para><para>(8) Entering into contractual agreements if no conservator has been appointed for the proposed ward;</para><para>(9) Receiving money and tangible property deliverable to him or her and applying such money and property to his or her expenses for room and board, medical care, personal effects, training, education, and habilitative services; and</para><para>(10) Any other area of inquiry which the court may direct.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 428, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For fees and costs of visitor,</emphasis> see sections 30-2620.01 and 30-2643.</para><para><emphasis>For qualifications of visitor,</emphasis> see section 30-2624.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Section is neither vague nor overbroad. In re Guardianship and Conservatorship of Sim, 225 Neb. 181, 403 N.W.2d 721 (1987).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>