<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2743"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2743</statuteno><catchline>Transfer; when not effective.</catchline><para>(a) If other assets of the estate are insufficient, a transfer resulting from a right of survivorship, POD designation or TOD registration under sections 30-2734 to 30-2745 is not effective against the estate of a deceased owner to the extent needed to pay claims against the estate, statutory allowances to the surviving spouse and children, taxes, and expenses of administration.</para><para>(b) A surviving owner or beneficiary who receives registered or reregistered securities or securities accounts or proceeds thereof after the death of a party is liable to account to the personal representative of the decedent for a proportionate share of the amount received to which the decedent, immediately before death, was beneficially entitled, to the extent necessary to discharge the amounts described in subsection (a) of this section remaining unpaid after application of the decedent's estate. A proceeding to assert the liability for claims against the estate and statutory allowances may not be commenced unless the personal representative has received a written demand by the surviving spouse, a creditor, a child, or a person acting for a child of the decedent. The proceeding must be commenced within one year after the death of the decedent.</para><para>(c) A surviving owner or beneficiary against whom a proceeding to account is brought may join as a party to the proceeding a surviving owner or beneficiary under sections 30-2734 to 30-2745 of any other security or securities account of the decedent or proceeds thereof or a surviving party or beneficiary of any account under sections 30-2716 to 30-2733.</para><para>(d) Sums recovered by the personal representative must be administered as a part of the decedent's estate. This section does not affect the protection from claims of the personal representative or estate of a deceased owner provided in section 30-2741 for an issuer or registering entity that makes payment in accordance with the terms of the security registration.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 250, &#167; 29. </para></source></law></legaldoc>