<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-2647"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2647</statuteno><catchline>Inventory and records.</catchline><para>Within ninety days after his appointment, every conservator shall prepare and file with the appointing court a complete inventory of the estate of the protected person together with his oath or affirmation that it is complete and accurate so far as he is informed. The conservator shall provide a copy thereof to the protected person if he can be located, has attained the age of fourteen years, and has sufficient mental capacity to understand these matters, and to any parent or guardian with whom the protected person resides. The conservator shall keep suitable records of his administration and exhibit the same on request of any interested person.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 265, UPC &#167; 5-418. </para></source><annotation><para>A conservator has a duty to provide suitable records of his or her administration under this section, and therefore, probate courts have the power to enforce compliance with this section in proper situations. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Borowiak, 10 Neb. App. 22, 624 N.W.2d 72 (2001).</para><para>Generally, "suitable records" means those papers and original documents supporting and verifying the conservator's accounts, but a more precise definition depends on the case before the court dealing with a request for compliance with this section. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Borowiak, 10 Neb. App. 22, 624 N.W.2d 72 (2001).</para><para>The term "suitable records" within this section may include bank statements, canceled checks, deposit slips, and certificates of deposit. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Borowiak, 10 Neb. App. 22, 624 N.W.2d 72 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>