<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-2324"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2324</statuteno><catchline>Family allowance.</catchline><para>In addition to the right to homestead allowance and exempt property, if the decedent was domiciled in this state, the surviving spouse and minor children whom the decedent was obligated to support and children who were in fact being supported by him are entitled to a reasonable allowance in money out of the estate for their maintenance during the period of administration, which allowance may not continue for longer than one year if the estate is inadequate to discharge allowed claims. The allowance may be paid as a lump sum or in periodic installments. It is payable to the surviving spouse, if living, for the use of the surviving spouse and minor and dependent children; otherwise to the children, or persons having their care and custody; but in case any minor child or dependent child is not living with the surviving spouse, the allowance may be made partially to the child or his guardian or other person having his care and custody, and partially to the spouse, as their needs may appear. The family allowance is exempt from and has priority over all claims except for costs and expenses of administration and the homestead allowance.</para><para>The family allowance is not chargeable against any benefit or share passing to the surviving spouse or children by the will of the decedent unless otherwise provided therein, by intestate succession, or by way of elective share. The death of any person entitled to family allowance, other than the surviving spouse, terminates his right to allowances not yet paid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 46, UPC &#167; 2-403; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 650, &#167; 6. </para></source><annotation><para>Under this section and section 30-2325, a right to allowances for homestead, exempt property, and unpaid spousal support survives the claimant's death to the extent of unpaid support. In re Estate of Stephenson, 243 Neb. 890, 503 N.W.2d 540 (1993).</para><para>The rights granted herein are specific, vested, and indefeasible and accrue to the recipient statutorily upon the decedent's death. In re Estate of Carman, 213 Neb. 98, 327 N.W.2d 611 (1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>