<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2207"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2207</statuteno><catchline>Evidence as to death or status.</catchline><para>In proceedings under this code the rules of evidence in courts of general jurisdiction, including any relating to simultaneous deaths, are applicable unless specifically displaced by the code. In addition, the following rules relating to determination of death and status are applicable:</para><para>(1) a certified or authenticated copy of a death certificate purporting to be issued by an official or agency of the place where the death purportedly occurred is prima facie proof of the fact, place, date and time of death and the identity of the decedent;</para><para>(2) a certified or authenticated copy of any record or report of a governmental agency, domestic or foreign, that a person is missing, detained, dead, or alive is prima facie evidence of the status and of the dates, circumstances and places disclosed by the record or report;</para><para>(3) a person who is absent for a continuous period of five years, during which he has not been heard from, and whose absence is not satisfactorily explained after diligent search or inquiry is presumed to be dead. His death is presumed to have occurred at the end of the period unless there is sufficient evidence for determining that death occurred earlier.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 7, UPC &#167; 1-107. </para></source><annotation><para>This section does not preclude the establishment of death by circumstantial evidence before the expiration of the 5-year statutory period. State v. Edwards, 278 Neb. 55, 767 N.W.2d 784 (2009).</para><para>This section sets forth the evidence that can be used to prove the fact of death in proceedings under the Nebraska Probate Code, not the Nebraska Criminal Code. State v. Edwards, 278 Neb. 55, 767 N.W.2d 784 (2009).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>