<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id238">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates" id="id240" statutenumber="30-2601">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2601</statuteno><catchline id="id243">Definitions
and use of terms.</catchline><para>Unless otherwise apparent from
the context, in the Nebraska Probate Code:</para>
<para>(1) Incapacitated person means any person who is impaired
by reason of mental illness, mental deficiency, physical illness or disability,
chronic use of drugs, chronic intoxication, or other cause (except minority)
to the extent that the person lacks sufficient understanding or capacity to
make or communicate responsible decisions concerning himself or herself;</para>
<para>(2) A protective proceeding is a proceeding under the provisions
of section 30-2630 to determine that a person cannot effectively manage or
apply his or her estate to necessary ends, either because the person lacks
the ability or is otherwise inconvenienced, or because the person is a minor,
and to secure administration of the person's estate by a conservator or other
appropriate relief;</para>
<para>(3) A protected person is a minor or other person for whom
a conservator has been appointed or other protective order has been made;</para>
<para>(4) A ward is a person for whom a guardian has been appointed.
A minor ward is a minor for whom a guardian has been appointed solely because
of minority;</para>
<para>(5) Full guardianship means the guardian has been granted
all powers which may be conferred upon a guardian by law;</para>
<para>(6) Limited guardianship means any guardianship which is
not a full guardianship; and</para>
<para>(7) For purposes
of article 26 of the Nebraska Probate Code, interested person means children,
spouses, those persons who would be the heirs if the ward or person alleged
to be incapacitated died without leaving a valid last will and testament who
are adults and any trustee of any trust executed by the ward or person alleged
to be incapacitated. The meaning of interested person as it relates to particular
persons may vary from time to time and must be determined according to the
particular purposes of, and matter involved in, any proceeding. If there are
no persons identified as interested persons above, then interested person
shall also include any person or entity named as a devisee in the most recently
executed last will and testament of the ward or person alleged to be incapacitated.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 219, UPC &#167; 5-101; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 466, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 32.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
