<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" id="id24" statutenumber="30-2647"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2647</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Conservator;
duties; inventory and records.</catchline><para>Within
thirty days after appointment, every conservator shall prepare and file with
the appointing court a complete inventory of the estate of the protected person
together with the conservator's oath or affirmation that the inventory is
complete and accurate so far as he or she is informed. The conservator shall
mail a copy thereof by first-class mail to the protected person, if the protected
person can be located and has attained the age of fourteen years, and to all
other interested persons as defined in section 30-2601. The conservator shall file with the court a certificate
of mailing showing that copies were sent to all interested persons by first-class
mail along with a form to send back to the court that indicates if such person
wants to continue receiving notifications about the proceedings. Every
conservator shall file an updated inventory with the annual accounting required
under section 30-2648. The conservator shall keep suitable records of his
or her administration and exhibit the same on request of any interested person.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 265, UPC &#167; 5-418; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB172, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>A conservator has a duty to provide suitable records of his or her administration under this section, and therefore, probate courts have the power to enforce compliance with this section in proper situations. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Borowiak, 10 Neb. App. 22, 624 N.W.2d 72 (2001).</para><para>Generally, "suitable records" means those papers and original documents supporting and verifying the conservator's accounts, but a more precise definition depends on the case before the court dealing with a request for compliance with this section. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Borowiak, 10 Neb. App. 22, 624 N.W.2d 72 (2001).</para><para>The term "suitable records" within this section may include bank statements, canceled checks, deposit slips, and certificates of deposit. In re Guardianship &amp; Conservatorship of Borowiak, 10 Neb. App. 22, 624 N.W.2d 72 (2001).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>