<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-2634"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2634</statuteno><catchline>Notice; waiver.</catchline><para>(a) In a proceeding for appointment of a conservator or other protective order, notice of hearing shall be given to each of the following:</para><para>(1) The person to be protected and his or her spouse, parents, and adult children;</para><para>(2) Any person who is serving as guardian or conservator or who has care and custody of the person to be protected; and</para><para>(3) If no other person is notified under subdivision (1) of this subsection, at least one of the closest adult relatives of the person to be protected, if any can be found.</para><para>(b) Notice which is appropriate to the circumstances of the person to be protected shall be served personally at least fourteen days prior to the hearing on the person to be protected and his or her spouse and parents if they can be found within the state. The court may require the petitioner to serve notice in alternative formats or with appropriate auxiliary aids and services if necessary to ensure equally effective communication with the protected person or person in need of protection, including, but not limited to, the use of braille, sign language, large print, reading aloud, or other reasonable accommodation for the known disabilities of the individual based on the allegations specified in the petition.</para><para>(c) If petitioners are the natural parents or if petitioner is a surviving natural parent or a parent who has been given sole and exclusive custody of the minor in a legal proceeding, petitioners or petitioner may waive notice to parents and may also waive notice to the minor, if the minor is under the age of fourteen years. Waiver of notice by the person to be protected shall not be effective unless he or she attends the hearing and the court determines that the waiver is appropriate. The court may, in its discretion, direct that notice be given as provided in section 30-2220 or in any other manner and to any other persons as the court may determine.</para><para>(d) Notice of a petition for appointment of a conservator or other initial protective order, and of any subsequent hearing, must be given to any person who has filed a request for notice under section 30-2635 and to interested persons and other persons as the court may direct. Except as otherwise provided in subsections (a) and (b) of this section, notice shall be given in accordance with section 30-2220.</para><para>(e) In addition to notifying him or her of the filing of the petition and the time and place of the hearing on the petition, the notice required to be served upon the person to be protected shall list the following rights of the person:</para><para>(1) The right to request the appointment of an attorney;</para><para>(2) The right to present evidence in his or her own behalf;</para><para>(3) The right to be notified regarding how to contact the temporary conservator if a temporary conservator is appointed;</para><para>(4) The right to compel attendance of witnesses;</para><para>(5) The right to cross-examine witnesses, including the court-appointed physician;</para><para>(6) The right to appeal any final order; and</para><para>(7) The right to request a hearing closed to the public.</para><para>(f) If a temporary conservator has been appointed, the notice required in subsection (e) of this section shall include a notice of such appointment and the right to request an expedited hearing pursuant to section 30-2630.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 252, UPC &#167; 5-405; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 650, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 782, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 466, &#167; 15. </para></source></law></legaldoc>