<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id191">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id193" statutenumber="30-2630.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>30-2630.01</statuteno><catchline id="id196">Temporary
conservator; power of court.</catchline><para>(a) If a person alleged
to be in need of protection under section 30-2630 has no conservator and an
emergency exists, the court may, pending notice and hearing, exercise the
power of a conservator or enter an emergency protective order appointing a
temporary conservator, who
may be the Public Guardian, to address the emergency.</para>
<para>(b) When the court takes action to exercise the powers of
a conservator or to appoint a temporary conservator under subsection (a) of
this section, an expedited hearing shall be held if requested by the person
alleged to be in need of protection, or by any interested person, if the request
is filed more than ten business days prior to the date set for the hearing
on the petition for appointment of the conservator. If an expedited hearing
is to be held, the hearing shall be held within ten business days after the
request is received. At the hearing on the temporary appointment, the petitioner
shall have the burden of showing by a preponderance of the evidence that temporary
conservatorship continues to be necessary to address the emergency situation.
Unless the person alleged to be in need of protection has counsel of his or
her own choice, the court may appoint an attorney to represent the person
at the hearing as provided in section 30-2636.</para>
<para>(c) If an expedited hearing is requested, notice shall be
served as provided in section 30-2634. The notice shall specify that a temporary
conservator has been appointed and shall be given at least twenty-four hours
prior to the expedited hearing.</para>
<para>(d) At the expedited hearing, the court may render a judgment
authorizing the temporary conservatorship to continue beyond the original
ten-day period. The judgment shall prescribe the specific powers and duties
of the temporary conservator in the letters of temporary conservatorship and
shall be effective for a ninety-day period. For good cause shown, the court
may extend the temporary conservatorship for successive ninety-day periods.</para>
<para>(e) The temporary conservatorship shall terminate at the
end of the ninety-day period in which the temporary conservatorship is valid
or at any time prior thereto if the court deems the circumstances leading
to the order for temporary conservatorship no longer exist or if an order
has been entered as a result of a hearing pursuant to section 30-2636 which
has been held during the ninety-day period.</para>
<para>(f) If the court denies the request for the ex parte order,
the court may, in its discretion, enter an order for an expedited hearing
pursuant to subsections (b) through (e) of this section.</para>
<para>(g) If the petitioner requests the entry of an order of temporary
conservatorship pursuant to subsection (a) of this section without requesting
an ex parte order, the court may hold an expedited hearing pursuant to subsections
(b) through (e) of this section.</para>
<para>(h) A temporary conservator may be removed at any time. A
temporary conservator shall make any report the court requires, except that
a temporary conservator shall not be required to provide the national criminal
history record check and report under section 30-2602.02. In other respects
the provisions of the Nebraska Probate Code concerning conservators apply
to temporary conservators.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 782, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 466, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB920, &#167; 24.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>