<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3816"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3816</statuteno><catchline>Duty to register trusts.</catchline><para>(1) The trustee of a trust having its principal place of administration in this state may register the trust in the county court of this state at the principal place of administration. Unless otherwise designated in the trust instrument, the principal place of administration of a trust is the trustee's usual place of business where the records pertaining to the trust are kept, or at the trustee's residence if he or she has no such place of business.</para><para>(2) In the case of cotrustees, the principal place of administration, if not otherwise designated in the trust instrument, is (a) the usual place of business of the corporate trustee if there is one corporate cotrustee, (b) the usual place of business or residence of the individual trustee who is a professional fiduciary if there is one such person and no corporate cotrustee, and (c) the usual place of business or residence of any of the cotrustees as agreed upon by such cotrustees.</para><para>(3) If there is more than one trustee, any trustee may register the trust in the county in which the principal place of administration is located under subsection (2). If the principal place of administration is determined under subdivision (2)(c) and the cotrustees cannot agree on the principal place of administration, a proceeding may be filed under section 30-3812 by any interested person to determine the principal place of administration.</para><para>(4) The right to register under sections 30-3816 to 30-3820 does not apply to the trustee of a trust if registration would be inconsistent with the retained jurisdiction of a foreign court from which the trustee cannot obtain release.</para><para>(5) No one other than a trustee shall register a trust. Registration of a trust is not required in order for a court to exercise jurisdiction over a trust, a trustee, or the beneficiaries.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 296, UPC &#167; 7-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1995), &#167; 30-2801; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1195, &#167; 7. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>When a person has been removed as trustee of a trust, that person no longer has standing under this section to register the trust in Nebraska. In re Trust Created by Del Castillo, 268 Neb. 671, 686 N.W.2d 900 (2004).</para><para>Where principal place of administration of testamentary trust was in Iowa, trust could not have been registered in Nebraska under this section. Raynor v. Northwestern National Bank, 211 Neb. 119, 317 N.W.2d 786 (1982).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>