<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id5"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-38,113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>30-38,113</statuteno><catchline>State agency; means-tested programs; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) Each state agency that provides governmental benefits to individuals of any age with disabilities through means-tested programs, including the medical assistance program, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that:</para><para>(a) Are not more restrictive than existing federal law, regulations, or policies with regard to the treatment of a special needs trust, including a trust defined in 42 U.S.C. 1396p(c)(2) and 42 U.S.C. 1396p(d)(4);</para><para>(b) Are not more restrictive than any state law regarding trusts, including any state law relating to the reasonable exercise of discretion by a trustee, guardian, or conservator in the best interests of the beneficiary;</para><para>(c) Do not require disclosure of a beneficiary's personal or confidential information without the consent of the beneficiary;</para><para>(d) Allow an individual account in a pooled special needs trust to be funded without financial limit;</para><para>(e) Allow an individual to establish or fund an individual account in a pooled special needs trust without an age limit or a transfer penalty;</para><para>(f) Allow an individual to fund a special needs trust for the individual's child with disabilities without a transfer penalty and regardless of the child's age; and</para><para>(g) Allow all legally assignable income or resources to be assigned to any special needs trust without limit.</para><para>(2) Nothing in this section may be interpreted to require a court order to authorize the funding of, or a disbursement from, a special needs trust.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1074, &#167; 77. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>