<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3837"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3837</statuteno><catchline>(UTC 411) Modification or termination of noncharitable irrevocable trust by consent.</catchline><para>(UTC 411) (a) If, upon petition, the court finds that the settlor and all beneficiaries consent to the modification or termination of a noncharitable irrevocable trust, the court shall approve the modification or termination even if the modification or termination is inconsistent with a material purpose of the trust. A settlor's power to consent to a trust's modification or termination may be exercised by an agent under a power of attorney only to the extent expressly authorized by the power of attorney or the terms of the trust; by the settlor's conservator with the approval of the court supervising the conservatorship if an agent is not so authorized; or by the settlor's guardian with the approval of the court supervising the guardianship if an agent is not so authorized and a conservator has not been appointed.</para><para>(b) A noncharitable irrevocable trust may be terminated upon consent of all of the beneficiaries if the court concludes that continuance of the trust is not necessary to achieve any material purpose of the trust. A noncharitable irrevocable trust may be modified upon consent of all of the beneficiaries if the court concludes that modification is not inconsistent with a material purpose of the trust.</para><para>(c) A spendthrift provision in the terms of the trust is presumed to constitute a material purpose of the trust.</para><para>(d) Upon termination of a trust under subsection (a) or (b) of this section, the trustee shall distribute the trust property as agreed by the beneficiaries.</para><para>(e) If not all of the beneficiaries consent to a proposed modification or termination of the trust under subsection (a) or (b) of this section, the modification or termination may be approved by the court if the court is satisfied that:</para><para>(1) if all of the beneficiaries had consented, the trust could have been modified or terminated under this section; and</para><para>(2) the interests of a beneficiary who does not consent will be adequately protected.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 41. </para></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (b) of this section, the party seeking a modification of a trust must affirmatively demonstrate that all beneficiaries have consented to the modification. The issue of consent for unknown beneficiaries must be resolved pursuant to sections 30-3825 and 30-3826. In re Trust of Shire, 299 Neb. 25, 907 N.W.2d 263 (2018).</para><para>Under subsection (e) of this section, there must be a showing that the interests of nonconsenting beneficiaries will be adequately protected by a modification. For the interests of nonconsenting beneficiaries to be adequately protected, the court must determine that modification will not affect those interests and impose safeguards to prevent them from being affected, when deemed necessary. In re Trust of Shire, 299 Neb. 25, 907 N.W.2d 263 (2018).</para><para>Although subsection (e) of this section authorizes a court to modify a trust without the consent of all beneficiaries, it can only do so if the modification is not inconsistent with a material purpose of the trust and any nonconsenting beneficiary would be adequately protected. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para><para>While this section refers to a noncharitable irrevocable trust, and the trusts at issue here were revocable when made, this section's application is nevertheless appropriate because of the death of the last surviving grantor/settlor. A trust which is revocable when made remains revocable during the settlor's lifetime; however, a revocable trust necessarily becomes irrevocable upon the settlor's death. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>