<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-3209"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3209</statuteno><catchline>Corporate trustee; retirement or
pension funds of governmental employees; investments authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) Corporate trustees authorized by Nebraska law to exercise fiduciary
powers and holding retirement or pension funds for the benefit of employees
or former employees of cities, villages, school districts, public power districts,
or other governmental or political subdivisions may invest and reinvest such
funds in such securities and investments as are authorized for trustees, guardians,
conservators, personal representatives, or administrators under the laws of
Nebraska. Retirement or pension funds of such cities, villages, districts,
or subdivisions may be invested in annuities issued by life insurance companies
authorized to do business in Nebraska. Except as provided in subsection (2)
of this section, any other retirement or pension funds of cities, including
cities operating under home rule charters, villages, school districts except
as provided in section 79-9,107, public power districts, and all other governmental
or political subdivisions may be invested and reinvested, as the governing
body of such city, village, school district, public power district, or other
governmental or political subdivision may determine, in the following classes
of securities and investments: (a) Bonds, notes, or other obligations of the
United States or those guaranteed by or for which the credit of the United
States is pledged for the payment of the principal and interest or dividends
thereof; (b) bonds or other evidences of indebtedness of the State of Nebraska
and full faith and credit obligations of or obligations unconditionally guaranteed
as to principal and interest by any other state of the United States; (c)
bonds, notes, or obligations of any municipal or political subdivision of
the State of Nebraska which are general obligations of the issuer thereof
and revenue bonds or debentures of any city, county, or utility district of
this state when the earnings available for debt service have, for a five-year
period immediately preceding the date of purchase, averaged not less than
one and one-half times such debt service requirements; (d) bonds and debentures
issued either singly or collectively by any of the twelve federal land banks,
the twelve intermediate credit banks, or the thirteen banks for cooperatives
under the supervision of the Farm Credit Administration; (e) certificates
of deposit of banks which are members of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation
or capital stock financial institutions, and if the amount deposited exceeds
the amount of insurance available thereon, then the excess shall be secured
in the same manner as for the deposit of public funds; (f) accounts with building
and loan associations, qualifying mutual financial institutions, or federal
savings and loan associations in the State of Nebraska to the extent that
such accounts are insured or
guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation; (g) bonds
or other interest-bearing obligations of any corporation organized under the
laws of the United States or any state thereof if (i) at the time the purchase
is made, they are given, by at least one statistical organization whose publication
is in general use, one of the three highest ratings given by such organization
and (ii) not more than five percent of the fund shall be invested in the obligations
of any one issuer; (h) direct short-term obligations, generally classified
as commercial paper, of any corporation organized or existing under the laws
of the United States or any state thereof with a net worth of ten million
dollars or more; and (i) preferred or common stock of any corporation organized
under the laws of the United States or of any state thereof with a net worth
of ten million dollars or more if (i) not more than fifty percent of the total
investments at the time such investment is made is in this class and not more
than five percent is invested in each of the first five years and (ii) not
more than five percent thereof is invested in the securities of any one corporation.
Notwithstanding the percentage limits stated in this subsection, the cash
proceeds of the sale of such preferred or common stock may be reinvested in
any securities authorized under this subdivision. No city, village, school
district, public power district, or other governmental subdivision or the
governing body thereof shall be authorized to sell any securities short, buy
on margin, or buy, sell, or engage in puts and calls. Section 77-2366 shall
apply to deposits in capital stock financial institutions. Section 77-2365.01
shall apply to deposits in qualifying mutual financial institutions.</para>
<para>(2) Notwithstanding the limitations prescribed in subsection (1) of
this section, trustees holding retirement or pension funds for the benefit
of employees or former employees of any city of the metropolitan class, metropolitan
utilities district, or county in which a city of the metropolitan class is
located shall invest such funds in investments of the nature which individuals
of prudence, discretion, and intelligence acquire or retain in dealing with
the property of another. Such investments shall not be made for speculation
but for investment, considering the probable safety of their capital as well
as the probable income to be derived. The trustees shall not buy on margin,
buy call options, or buy put options. The trustees may lend any security if
cash, United States Government obligations, or United States Government agency
obligations with a market value equal to or exceeding the market value of
the security lent are received as collateral. If shares of stock are purchased
under this subsection, all proxies may be voted by the trustees. The asset
allocation restrictions set forth in subsection (1) of this section shall
not be applicable to the funds of pension or retirement systems administered
by or on behalf of a city of the metropolitan class, metropolitan utilities
district, or county in which a city of the metropolitan class is located.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 257, &#167; 1, p. 678; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 752, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 33, &#167; 25; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1989, &#167; 24-601.04; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 757, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1036; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 78; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>