<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3118</statuteno><catchline>Fiduciary duties; general principles.</catchline><para>(a) In allocating receipts and disbursements to or between principal and income, and with respect to any matter within the scope of sections 30-3122 to 30-3126, a fiduciary:</para><para>(1) shall administer a trust or estate in accordance with the terms of the trust or the will, even if there is a different provision in the Uniform Principal and Income Act;</para><para>(2) may administer a trust or estate by the exercise of a discretionary power of administration given to the fiduciary by the terms of the trust or the will, even if the exercise of the power produces a result different from a result required or permitted by the act, and no inference that the fiduciary has abused its discretion arises solely from the fact that the fiduciary has exercised an express power given to the fiduciary by the terms of the trust or the will;</para><para>(3) shall administer a trust or estate in accordance with the act if the terms of the trust or the will do not contain a different provision or do not give the fiduciary a discretionary power of administration; and</para><para>(4) shall add a receipt or charge a disbursement to principal to the extent that the terms of the trust and the act do not provide a rule for allocating the receipt or disbursement to or between principal and income.</para><para>(b) In exercising the power to adjust under subsection (a) of section 30-3119 or a discretionary power of administration regarding a matter within the scope of the act, whether granted by the terms of a trust, a will, or the act, a fiduciary shall administer a trust or estate impartially, based on what is fair and reasonable to all of the beneficiaries, except to the extent that the terms of the trust or the will clearly manifest an intention that the fiduciary shall or may favor one or more of the beneficiaries. A determination in accordance with the act is presumed to be fair and reasonable to all of the beneficiaries.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 56, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>