<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-3816"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3816</statuteno><catchline>Duty to register trusts.</catchline><para>The trustee of a trust having its principal place of administration in this state may register the trust in the county court of this state at the principal place of administration. Unless otherwise designated in the trust instrument, the principal place of administration of a trust is the trustee's usual place of business where the records pertaining to the trust are kept, or at the trustee's residence if he or she has no such place of business. In the case of cotrustees, the principal place of administration, if not otherwise designated in the trust instrument, is (1) the usual place of business of the corporate trustee if there is but one corporate cotrustee, or (2) the usual place of business or residence of the individual trustee who is a professional fiduciary if there is but one such person and no corporate cotrustee, and otherwise (3) the usual place of business or residence of any of the cotrustees as agreed upon by them. The right to register under sections 30-3816 to 30-3820 does not apply to the trustee of a trust if registration would be inconsistent with the retained jurisdiction of a foreign court from which the trustee cannot obtain release.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 296, UPC &#167; 7-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1995), &#167; 30-2801; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 16.</para></source><annotation><para>When a person has been removed as trustee of a trust, that person no longer has standing under this section to register the trust in Nebraska. In re Trust Created by Del Castillo, 268 Neb. 671, 686 N.W.2d 900 (2004).</para><para>Where principal place of administration of testamentary trust was in Iowa, trust could not have been registered in Nebraska under this section. Raynor v. Northwestern National Bank, 211 Neb. 119, 317 N.W.2d 786 (1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>