<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id80">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id82" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="30-3905"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3905</statuteno><catchline>Cooperation between courts.</catchline>
<para>(1) In a guardianship
or protective proceeding in this state, a court of this state may request
the appropriate court of another state to do any of the following:</para>
<para>(a) Hold an
evidentiary hearing;</para><para>(b) Order a person in that state to produce evidence or give testimony
pursuant to procedures of that state;</para><para>(c) Order that an evaluation or assessment
be made of the respondent;</para><para>(d) Order any appropriate investigation
of a person involved in a proceeding;</para><para>(e) Forward to the court of this state a
certified copy of the transcript or other record of a hearing under subdivision
(a) of this subsection or any other proceeding, any evidence otherwise produced
under subdivision (b) of this subsection, and any evaluation or assessment
prepared in compliance with an order under subdivision (c) or (d) of this
subsection;</para><para>(f) Issue any order necessary to assure the appearance in the proceeding
of a person whose presence is necessary for the court to make a determination,
including the respondent or the incapacitated or protected person; or</para>
<para>(g) Issue an
order authorizing the release of medical, financial, criminal, or other relevant
information in that state, including protected health information as defined
in 45 C.F.R. 160.103, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2011.</para>
<para>(2) If a court
of another state in which a guardianship or protective proceeding is pending
requests assistance of the kind provided in subsection (1) of this section,
a court of this state has jurisdiction for the limited purpose of granting
the request or making reasonable efforts to comply with the request.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB157, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>