<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3517"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3517</statuteno><catchline>Limitations of action against custodial trustee.</catchline><para>(a) Except as provided in subsections (b) and (c) of this section, unless previously barred by adjudication, consent, or limitation, a claim for relief against a custodial trustee for accounting or breach of duty is barred as to a beneficiary, a person to whom custodial trust property is to be paid or delivered, or the legal representative of an incapacitated or deceased beneficiary or payee:</para><para>(1) Who has received a final account or statement fully disclosing the matter unless an action or proceeding to assert the claim is commenced within six months after receipt of the final account or statement; or</para><para>(2) Who has not received a final account or statement fully disclosing the matter unless an action or proceeding to assert the claim is commenced within four years after the termination of the custodial trust.</para><para>(b) Except as provided in subsection (c) of this section, a claim for relief to recover from a custodial trustee for fraud, misrepresentation, or concealment related to the final settlement of the custodial trust or concealment of the existence of the custodial trust is barred unless an action or proceeding to assert the claim is commenced within five years after the termination of the custodial trust.</para><para>(c) A claim for relief is not barred by this section if the claimant:</para><para>(1) Is a minor, until the earlier of two years after the claimant becomes an adult or dies;</para><para>(2) Is an incapacitated adult, until the earliest of two years after (i) the appointment of a conservator, (ii) the removal of the incapacity, or (iii) the death of the claimant; or</para><para>(3) Was an adult, now deceased, who was not incapacitated at the time of his or her death, until two years after the claimant's death.</para><para>(d) For purposes of this section, a beneficiary or other person is deemed to have received an account or statement if, being an adult, it is received by him or her personally or if, being a minor or incapacitated person, it is received by his or her representative as described in subdivision (3) of section 30-2222.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 51, &#167; 17. </para></source></law></legaldoc>