<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-3854"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3854</statuteno><catchline>(UTC 602) Revocation or amendment of revocable trust.</catchline><para>(UTC 602) (a) Unless the terms of a trust expressly provide that the trust is irrevocable, the settlor may revoke or amend the trust. This subsection does not apply to a trust created under an instrument executed before January 1, 2005.</para><para>(b) If a revocable trust is created or funded by more than one settlor:</para><para>(1) to the extent the trust consists of community property, the trust may be revoked by either spouse acting alone but may be amended only by joint action of both spouses;</para><para>(2) to the extent the trust consists of property other than community property, each settlor may revoke or amend the trust with regard to the portion of the trust property attributable to that settlor's contribution; and</para><para>(3) upon the revocation or amendment of the trust by fewer than all of the settlors, the trustee shall promptly notify the other settlors of the revocation or amendment.</para><para>(c) The settlor may revoke or amend a written revocable trust:</para><para>(1) by substantial compliance with a method provided in the terms of the trust; or</para><para>(2) if the terms of the trust do not provide a method or the method provided in the terms is not expressly made exclusive, by:</para><para>(A) a later will or codicil that expressly refers to the trust or specifically devises property that would otherwise have passed according to the terms of the trust; or</para><para>(B) an instrument evidencing an intent to amend or revoke the trust signed by the settlor, or in the settlor's name by some other individual in the presence of and by the direction of the settlor. The instrument must have an indication of the date of the writing or signing and, in the absence of such indication of the date, be the only such writing or contain no inconsistency with any other like writing or permit determination of such date of writing or signing from the content of such writing, from extrinsic circumstances, or from any other evidence.</para><para>(d) Upon revocation of a revocable trust, the trustee shall deliver the trust property as the settlor directs.</para><para>(e) A settlor's powers with respect to revocation, amendment, or distribution of trust property may be exercised by an agent under a power of attorney only to the extent expressly authorized by the terms of the trust or the power.</para><para>(f) A conservator of the settlor or, if no conservator has been appointed, a guardian of the settlor may exercise a settlor's powers with respect to revocation, amendment, or distribution of trust property only with the approval of the court supervising the conservatorship or guardianship.</para><para>(g) A trustee who does not know that a trust has been revoked or amended is not liable to the settlor or settlor's successors in interest for distributions made and other actions taken in reliance on the terms of the trust.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 26. </para></source></law></legaldoc>