<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-3420"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3420</statuteno><catchline>Power of attorney; health care decision; revocation; limitations; effect.</catchline><para>(1) A power of attorney for health care or a health care decision made by an attorney in fact may be revoked at any time by a principal who is competent and in any manner by which the principal is able to communicate his or her intent to revoke. Revocation shall be effective upon communication to the attending physician, the health care provider who shall promptly inform the attending physician of the revocation, or the attorney in fact who shall promptly inform the attending physician of the revocation.</para><para>(2) The creation by the principal of written wishes or instructions about health care or limitations upon the attorney in fact's authority shall not revoke a power of attorney for health care unless such wishes, instructions, or limitations expressly provide otherwise.</para><para>(3) Upon learning of the revocation of the power of attorney for health care, the attending physician shall cause the revocation to be made a part of the principal's medical records.</para><para>(4) Unless the power of attorney for health care provides otherwise, execution of a valid power of attorney for health care shall revoke any previously executed power of attorney for health care.</para><para>(5) Unless the power of attorney for health care provides otherwise, a power of attorney for health care shall supersede:</para><para>(a) Any conflicting preexisting directive;</para><para>(b) Any guardianship proceedings under the Nebraska Probate Code to the extent the proceedings involve the right to make health care decisions for the protected person; and</para><para>(c) Any conservatorship proceedings under the Nebraska Probate Code to the extent the proceedings involve the right to make health care decisions for the protected person.</para><para>(6) A decree of divorce or legal separation entered into pursuant to sections 42-347 to 42-380 may specify whether the choice of the principal's spouse as attorney in fact under a power of attorney for health care shall be revoked or remain effective. If the decree does not specify whether the choice of the spouse as the principal's attorney in fact for health care is revoked or remains effective, the choice of the principal's spouse as attorney in fact for health care shall be deemed revoked upon entry of the decree.</para><para>(7) The revocation of a power of attorney for health care shall not revoke or terminate the authority as to the attorney in fact or other person who acts in good faith under the power of attorney for health care and without actual knowledge of the revocation. An action taken without knowledge of the revocation, unless the action is otherwise invalid or unenforceable, shall bind the principal and his or her heirs, devisees, and personal representatives.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 696, &#167; 20. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Probate Code,</emphasis> see section 30-2201.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>