<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3819"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3819</statuteno><catchline>Effect of registration.</catchline><para>(a) By registering a trust, or accepting the trusteeship of a registered trust, the trustee submits personally to the jurisdiction of the court of registration in any proceeding under section 30-3812 relating to the trust that may be initiated by any interested person while the trust remains registered. Notice of any proceeding shall be delivered to the trustee or mailed to him or her by ordinary first-class mail at his or her address as listed in the registration or as thereafter reported to the court and to his or her address as then known to the petitioner.</para><para>(b) To the extent of their interests in the trust, all beneficiaries of a trust properly registered in this state are subject to the jurisdiction of the court of registration for the purposes of proceedings under section 30-3812, provided notice is given pursuant to section 30-2220.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 354, &#167; 298, UPC &#167; 7-103; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1995), &#167; 30-2803; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 19. </para></source><annotation><para>The act of registering a trust gives the county court jurisdiction over the interests of all notified beneficiaries to decide issues related to any matter involving the trust's administration, including a request for instructions or an action to declare rights. In re Trust Created by Hansen, 274 Neb. 199, 739 N.W.2d 170 (2007).</para><para>Under this section, the county court of Dakota County, Nebraska, could not acquire jurisdiction of a trust having principal place of administration in Iowa since the trust could not be registered in Nebraska under section 30-2801. Raynor v. Northwestern National Bank, 211 Neb. 119, 317 N.W.2d 786 (1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>