<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3836"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3836</statuteno><catchline>(UTC 410) Modification or termination of trust; proceeding for approval or disapproval.</catchline><para>(UTC 410) (a) In addition to the methods of termination prescribed by sections 30-3837 to 30-3840, a trust terminates to the extent the trust is revoked or expires pursuant to its terms, no purpose of the trust remains to be achieved, or the purposes of the trust have become unlawful, contrary to public policy, or impossible to achieve.</para><para>(b) A proceeding to approve or disapprove a proposed modification or termination under sections 30-3837 to 30-3842, or trust combination or division under section 30-3843, may be commenced by a trustee or beneficiary. The settlor of a charitable trust may maintain a proceeding to modify the trust under section 30-3839.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 533, &#167; 40. </para></source><annotation><para>When a trust does not contain a termination clause, its termination date is implied from its terms. In re Estate of Hedke, 278 Neb. 727, 775 N.W.2d 13 (2009).</para><para>Where a trust did not contain a termination clause, the trust impliedly terminated with the settlor's death, because the settlor's beneficial interests in the trust ended upon her death when providing for her care and support was the only purpose for the trust. The trustee's payments for a settlor's outstanding debts, taxes, and expenses upon the settlor's death are part of the trustee's winding-up duties after a trust terminates. In re Estate of Hedke, 278 Neb. 727, 775 N.W.2d 13 (2009).</para><para>A trust may expire or terminate by its own terms, thereby triggering the period for winding up the trust; the winding-up period continues to exist until the trust is fully terminated by distribution of the trust property. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para><para>If a trustee knows or should know of circumstances that justify judicial action to modify an administrative or distributive provision of a trust because of circumstances not anticipated by the settlor, the trustee has a duty to petition the court for appropriate modification of, or deviation from, the terms of the trust. The possible imposition of such a duty on a trustee further supports permitting a trustee to seek modification under section 30-3838 even in those instances where a trust may have terminated or expired by its own terms, but the winding up and distribution of trust property is still pending. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para><para>If the trustees fail to distribute the property once the purpose of the trust was fulfilled, a court can enter an order fully terminating the trust with directions to distribute the trust property in accordance with the terms of the trust or, if appropriate, enter an order modifying (or reforming) the trust terms. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para><para>Regardless of how a trust may terminate, subsection (b) of this section authorizes a trustee or beneficiary to commence a proceeding to approve or disapprove a proposed modification or termination under sections 30-3837 to 30-3842. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para><para>The Nebraska Uniform Trust Code allows a beneficiary or trustee to petition a county court to consider modification or termination of a trust which has expired or terminated pursuant to its own terms but remains in the winding-up period, including the possible modification of, or deviation from, dispositive terms. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para><para>The Nebraska Uniform Trust Code provides statutory options for a trustee to seek a modification of the trust during the winding-up period following the expiration or termination of a trust by its own terms. In re Trust Created by Augustin, 27 Neb. App. 593, 935 N.W.2d 493 (2019).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>