<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" statutenumber="30-3811"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3811</statuteno><catchline>(UTC 111) Nonjudicial settlement agreements.</catchline><para>(UTC 111) (a) For purposes of this section, "interested persons" means persons whose consent would be required in order to achieve a binding settlement were the settlement to be approved by the court.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (c) of this section, interested persons may enter into a binding nonjudicial settlement agreement with respect to any matter involving a trust.</para><para>(c) A nonjudicial settlement agreement is valid only to the extent it does not violate a material purpose of the trust and includes terms and conditions that could be properly approved by the court under the Nebraska Uniform Trust Code or other applicable law. A spendthrift provision in the terms of the trust is presumed to constitute a material purpose of the trust.</para><para>(d) Matters that may be resolved by a nonjudicial settlement agreement include:</para><para>(1) the interpretation or construction of the terms of the trust;</para><para>(2) the approval of a trustee's report or accounting;</para><para>(3) direction to a trustee to refrain from performing a particular act or the grant to a trustee of any necessary or desirable power;</para><para>(4) the resignation or appointment of a trustee and the determination of a trustee's compensation;</para><para>(5) transfer of a trust's principal place of administration; and</para><para>(6) liability of a trustee for an action relating to the trust.</para><para>(e) Any interested person may request the court to approve a nonjudicial settlement agreement, to determine whether the representation as provided in sections 30-3822 to 30-3826 was adequate, and to determine whether the agreement contains terms and conditions the court could have properly approved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 24. </para></source></law></legaldoc>