<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-38,100"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-38,100</statuteno><catchline>(UTC 1011) Interest as general partner.</catchline><para>(UTC 1011) (a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (c) of this section or unless personal liability is imposed in the contract, a trustee who holds an interest as a general partner in a general or limited partnership is not personally liable on a contract entered into by the partnership after the trust's acquisition of the interest if the fiduciary capacity was disclosed in the contract or in a statement previously filed pursuant to the Uniform Partnership Act of 1998 or the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act.</para><para>(b) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (c) of this section, a trustee who holds an interest as a general partner is not personally liable for torts committed by the partnership or for obligations arising from ownership or control of the interest unless the trustee is personally at fault.</para><para>(c) The immunity provided by this section does not apply if an interest in the partnership is held by the trustee in a capacity other than that of trustee or is held by the trustee's spouse or one or more of the trustee's descendants, siblings, or parents, or the spouse of any of them.</para><para>(d) If the trustee of a revocable trust holds an interest as a general partner, the settlor is personally liable for contracts and other obligations of the partnership as if the settlor were a general partner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 100. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act,</emphasis> see section 67-296.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Partnership Act of 1998,</emphasis> see section 67-401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>