<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-3890"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3890</statuteno><catchline>(UTC 1001) Remedies for breach of trust.</catchline><para>(UTC 1001) (a) A violation by a trustee of a duty the trustee owes to a beneficiary is a breach of trust.</para><para>(b) To remedy a breach of trust that has occurred or may occur, the court may:</para><para>(1) compel the trustee to perform the trustee's duties;</para><para>(2) enjoin the trustee from committing a breach of trust;</para><para>(3) compel the trustee to redress a breach of trust by paying money, restoring property, or other means;</para><para>(4) order a trustee to account;</para><para>(5) appoint a special fiduciary to take possession of the trust property and administer the trust;</para><para>(6) suspend the trustee;</para><para>(7) remove the trustee as provided in section 30-3862;</para><para>(8) reduce or deny compensation to the trustee;</para><para>(9) subject to section 30-38,101, void an act of the trustee, impose a lien or a constructive trust on trust property, or trace trust property wrongfully disposed of and recover the property or its proceeds; or</para><para>(10) order any other appropriate relief.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 90. </para></source><annotation><para>An accounting is ordinarily an appropriate remedy for a breach of a trustee’s duty to inform and report on a trust and its administration. In re Rolf H. Brennemann Testamentary Trust, 288 Neb. 389, 849 N.W.2d 458 (2014).</para><para>A beneficiary of property left to a trust has standing to raise the trustee's self-dealing and to seek damages, an accounting, and a constructive trust. In re Estate of Hedke, 278 Neb. 727, 775 N.W.2d 13 (2009).</para>
<para>Under subsection (b) of this section, the court has various options available to remedy a violation by a trustee of a duty the trustee owes to a beneficiary. In re Louise V. Steinhoefel Trust, 22 Neb. App. 293, 854 N.W.2d 792 (2014).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>