<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id00" statutenumber="30-3882"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>30-3882</statuteno><catchline id="id00">(UTC 817) Distribution upon termination.</catchline><para>(UTC 817) (a) Upon termination or partial termination of a trust, the trustee may send to the beneficiaries a proposal for distribution. The right of any beneficiary to object to the proposed distribution terminates if the beneficiary does not notify the trustee of an objection within thirty days after the proposal was sent but only if the proposal informed the beneficiary of the right to object and of the time allowed for objection.</para><para>(b) Upon the occurrence of an event terminating or partially terminating a trust, the trustee shall proceed expeditiously to distribute the trust property to the persons entitled to it, subject to the right of the trustee to retain a reasonable reserve for the payment of debts, expenses, and taxes.</para><para>(c) A release by a beneficiary of a trustee from liability for breach of trust is invalid to the extent:</para><para>(1) it was induced by improper conduct of the trustee; or</para><para>(2) the beneficiary, at the time of the release, did not know of the beneficiary's rights or of the material facts relating to the breach.</para><para>(d) The changes made to this section by Laws 2019, LB593, shall apply retroactively to August 30, 2015.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 130, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB72, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB268, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB593, &#167; 4. </para></source><annotation><para>Pursuant to subsection (b) of this section, after a trust has been terminated, a trustee must expeditiously exercise the powers appropriate to wind up the administration of the trust and distribute the trust property to the persons entitled to it. In re Estate of Barger, 303 Neb. 817, 931 N.W.2d 660 (2019).</para><para>Under this section, a trustee's duty to pay the settlor's debts, expenses, and taxes does not normally justify a trustee's failure to make distributions. An unduly delayed distribution is a breach of the duty of care unless the trustee shows that some realistic complication prevented the trustee from determining in a timely manner a reasonable sum to reserve for winding-up costs. In re Estate of Hedke, 278 Neb. 727, 775 N.W.2d 13 (2009).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>