<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" id="id104" publishedsource="New" statutenumber="30-4116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4116</statuteno><catchline>Public Guardian; appointment; powers; duties.</catchline><para>(1) When the court appoints the Public Guardian as guardian or conservator for an individual, the Public Guardian immediately succeeds to (a) all powers and duties of a guardian provided in sections 30-2626 and 30-2628, if appointed a guardian, or (b) all powers and duties of a conservator provided in sections 30-2646, 30-2647, 30-2653, 30-2654, 30-2655, 30-2656, and 30-2657, if appointed a conservator.</para><para>(2) The Public Guardian shall:</para><para>(a) Be considered as an interested party in the welfare of the ward or protected person to which the Public Guardian is nominated. If the office is unable to accept the nomination due to its caseload or the status of its client-to-staff average ratio under section 30-4115, good cause shall be presumed to exist to deny its appointment. In such event, the appearance of the office shall no longer be required and the Public Guardian shall no longer be considered an interested party;</para><para>(b) Not file petitions for guardianships or conservatorships. After being appointed in a case, the Public Guardian may file a motion for termination, a motion for modification, or take any other legal action required to fulfill the duties and responsibilities of a guardian or conservator in accordance with the Public Guardianship Act;</para><para>(c) Visit the facility in which the ward or protected person is to be placed if it is proposed that the individual be placed outside his or her home; and</para><para>(d) Monitor the ward or protected person and his or her care and progress on a continuing basis. Monitoring shall, at a minimum, consist of monthly personal contact with the ward or protected person. The Public Guardian shall maintain a written record of each visit with a ward or protected person. The Public Guardian shall maintain periodic contact with all individuals and agencies, public or private, providing care or related services to the ward or protected person.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB920, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB934, &#167; 31. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>