<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id995"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-4502"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4502</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>In the Uniform Trust Decanting Act:</para><para>(1) Appointive property means the property or property interest subject to a power of appointment.</para><para>(2) Ascertainable standard has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para><para>(3) Authorized fiduciary means:</para><para>(A) a trustee or other fiduciary, other than a settlor, that has discretion to distribute or direct a trustee to distribute part or all of the principal of the first trust to one or more current beneficiaries;</para><para>(B) a special fiduciary appointed under section 30-4509; or</para><para>(C) a special-needs fiduciary under section 30-4513.</para><para>(4) Beneficiary means a person that:</para><para>(A) has a present or future, vested or contingent, beneficial interest in a trust;</para><para>(B) holds a power of appointment over trust property; or</para><para>(C) is an identified charitable organization that will or may receive distributions under the terms of the trust.</para><para>(5) Charitable interest means an interest in a trust which:</para><para>(A) is held by an identified charitable organization and makes the organization a qualified beneficiary;</para><para>(B) benefits only charitable organizations and, if the interest were held by an identified charitable organization, would make the organization a qualified beneficiary; or</para><para>(C) is held solely for charitable purposes and, if the interest were held by an identified charitable organization, would make the organization a qualified beneficiary.</para><para>(6) Charitable organization means:</para><para>(A) a person, other than an individual, organized and operated exclusively for charitable purposes; or</para><para>(B) a government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, to the extent it holds funds exclusively for a charitable purpose.</para><para>(7) Charitable purpose has the same meaning as the description of a charitable trust in section 30-3831.</para><para>(8) Court means the court in this state having jurisdiction in matters relating to trusts.</para><para>(9) Current beneficiary means a beneficiary that on the date the beneficiary's qualification is determined is a distributee or permissible distributee of trust income or principal. The term includes the holder of a presently exercisable general power of appointment but does not include a person that is a beneficiary only because the person holds any other power of appointment.</para><para>(10) Decanting power or the decanting power means the power of an authorized fiduciary under the act to distribute property of a first trust to one or more second trusts or to modify the terms of the first trust.</para><para>(11) Expanded distributive discretion means a discretionary power of distribution that is not limited to an ascertainable standard or a reasonably definite standard.</para><para>(12) First trust means a trust over which an authorized fiduciary may exercise the decanting power.</para><para>(13) First-trust instrument means the trust instrument for a first trust.</para><para>(14) General power of appointment means a power of appointment exercisable in favor of a powerholder, the powerholder's estate, a creditor of the powerholder, or a creditor of the powerholder's estate.</para><para>(15) Jurisdiction has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para><para>(16) Person means an individual, estate, business or nonprofit entity, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or other legal entity.</para><para>(17) Power of appointment means a power that enables a powerholder acting in a nonfiduciary capacity to designate a recipient of an ownership interest in or another power of appointment over the appointive property. The term does not include a power of attorney.</para><para>(18) Powerholder means a person in which a donor creates a power of appointment.</para><para>(19) Presently exercisable power of appointment means a power of appointment exercisable by the powerholder at the relevant time. The term:</para><para>(A) includes a power of appointment exercisable only after the occurrence of a specified event, the satisfaction of an ascertainable standard, or the passage of a specified time only after:</para><para>(i) the occurrence of the specified event;</para><para>(ii) the satisfaction of the ascertainable standard; or</para><para>(iii) the passage of the specified time; and</para><para>(B) does not include a power exercisable only at the powerholder's death.</para><para>(20) Qualified beneficiary has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para><para>(21) Reasonably definite standard means a clearly measurable standard under which a holder of a power of distribution is legally accountable within the meaning of 26 U.S.C. 674(b)(5)(A), as such section existed on November 14, 2020, and any applicable regulations.</para><para>(22) Record means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium and is retrievable in perceivable form.</para><para>(23) Second trust means:</para><para>(A) a first trust after modification under the Uniform Trust Decanting Act; or</para><para>(B) a trust to which a distribution of property from a first trust is or may be made under the act.</para><para>(24) Second-trust instrument means the trust instrument for a second trust.</para><para>(25) Settlor, except as otherwise provided in section 30-4525, has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para><para>(26) Sign means, with present intent to authenticate or adopt a record:</para><para>(A) to execute or adopt a tangible symbol; or</para><para>(B) to attach to or logically associate with the record an electronic symbol, sound, or process.</para><para>(27) State has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para><para>(28) Terms of the trust means:</para><para>(A) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (B) of this subdivision, the manifestation of the settlor's intent regarding a trust's provisions as:</para><para>(i) expressed in the trust instrument; or</para><para>(ii) established by other evidence that would be admissible in a judicial proceeding; or</para><para>(B) the trust's provisions as established, determined, or amended by:</para><para>(i) a trustee or other person in accordance with applicable law;</para><para>(ii) a court order; or</para><para>(iii) a nonjudicial settlement agreement under section 30-3811.</para><para>(29) Trust instrument means a record executed by the settlor to create a trust or by any person to create a second trust which contains some or all of the terms of the trust, including any amendments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>