<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id662"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-4702"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4702</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Uniform Community Property Disposition at Death Act:</para><para>(1) Community-property spouse means an individual in a marriage or other relationship:</para><para>(A) under which community property could be acquired during the existence of the relationship; and</para><para>(B) that remains in existence at the time of death of either party to the relationship.</para><para>(2) Electronic means relating to technology having electrical, digital, magnetic, wireless, optical, electromagnetic, or similar capabilities.</para><para>(3) Jurisdiction means the United States, a state, a foreign country, or a political subdivision of a foreign country.</para><para>(4) Partition means voluntarily divide property to which the Uniform Community Property Disposition at Death Act otherwise would apply.</para><para>(5) Person means an individual, estate, business or nonprofit entity, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or other legal entity.</para><para>(6) Personal representative includes an executor, administrator, successor personal representative, special administrator, and other person that performs substantially the same function.</para><para>(7) Property means anything that may be the subject of ownership, whether real or personal, tangible or intangible, legal or equitable, or any interest therein.</para><para>(8) Reclassify means change the characterization or treatment of community property to property owned separately by community-property spouses.</para><para>(9) Record means information:</para><para>(A) inscribed on a tangible medium; or</para><para>(B) stored in an electronic or other medium and retrievable in perceivable form.</para><para>(10) Sign means, with present intent to authenticate or adopt a record:</para><para>(A) execute or adopt a tangible symbol; or</para><para>(B) attach to or logically associate with the record an electronic symbol, sound, or process.</para><para>(11) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any other territory or possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States. The term includes a federally recognized Indian tribe.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB83, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>