<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property"  statutenumber="30-4020"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4020</statuteno><catchline>Liability for refusal to accept acknowledged
power of attorney.</catchline><para>(1)
Except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) of this section:</para>
<para>(a) A person shall either
accept an acknowledged power of attorney or request a certification, a translation,
or an opinion of counsel under subsection (4) of section 30-4019 no later
than seven business days after presentation of the power of attorney for acceptance;</para>
<para>(b) If a person requests
a certification, a translation, or an opinion of counsel under subsection
(4) of section 30-4019, the person shall accept the power of attorney no later
than five business days after receipt of the certification, translation, or
opinion of counsel; and</para><para>(c)
A person may not require an additional or different form of power of attorney
for authority granted in the power of attorney presented.</para>
<para>(2) A person is not required
to accept an acknowledged power of attorney if:</para><para>(a) The person is not otherwise
required to engage in a transaction with the principal in the same circumstances;</para>
<para>(b) Engaging in a transaction
with the agent or the principal in the same circumstances would be inconsistent
with state or federal law;</para><para>(c) The person has actual knowledge of the termination
of the agent's authority or of the power of attorney before exercise of the
power;</para><para>(d)
A request for a certification, a translation, or an opinion of counsel under
subsection (4) of section 30-4019 is refused;</para><para>(e) The person in good faith believes
that the power is not valid or that the agent does not have the authority
to perform the act requested, whether or not a certification, a translation,
or an opinion of counsel under subsection (4) of section 30-4019 has been
requested or provided;</para><para>(f)
The person makes, or has actual knowledge that another person has made, a
report to the local adult protective services office stating a good faith
belief that the principal may be subject to physical or financial abuse, neglect,
exploitation, or abandonment by the agent or a person acting for or with the
agent;</para><para>(g)
The person brought, or has actual knowledge that another person has brought,
a judicial proceeding for construction of a power of attorney or review of
the agent's conduct; or</para><para>(h)
The power of attorney becomes effective upon the occurrence of an event or
contingency, and neither a certification nor evidence of the occurrence of
the event or contingency is presented to the person being asked to accept
the power of attorney.</para><para>(3)
A person may not refuse to accept an acknowledged power of attorney if any
of the following applies:</para><para>(a)
The person's reason for refusal is based exclusively upon the date the power
of attorney was executed; or</para><para>(b) The person's refusal is based exclusively on a
mandate that an additional or different power of attorney form must be used.</para>
<para>(4) A person that refuses
in violation of this section to accept an acknowledged power of attorney is
subject to:</para><para>(a)
A court order mandating acceptance of the power of attorney; and</para>
<para>(b) Liability for reasonable
attorney's fees and costs incurred in any action or proceeding that confirms
the validity of the power of attorney or mandates acceptance of the power
of attorney.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1113, &#167; 20.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>