<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection Of Persons And Property" statutenumber="30-4002"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4002</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Nebraska Uniform Power of Attorney Act:</para><para>(1) Agent means a person granted authority to act for a principal under a power of attorney, whether denominated an agent, attorney in fact, or otherwise. The term includes an original agent, coagent, successor agent, and a person to which an agent's authority is delegated;</para><para>(2) Business day means any day other than a Saturday, Sunday, or state or nationally observed legal holiday;</para><para>(3) Durable, with respect to a power of attorney, means not terminated by the principal's incapacity;</para><para>(4) Electronic means relating to technology having electrical, digital, magnetic, wireless, optical, electromagnetic, or similar capabilities;</para><para>(5) Good faith means honesty in fact;</para><para>(6) Incapacity means inability of an individual to manage property or property affairs effectively because the individual:</para><para>(a) Has an impairment in the ability to receive and evaluate information or make or communicate responsible decisions even with the use of technological assistance for reasons such as mental illness, mental deficiency, physical illness or disability, chronic use of drugs, chronic intoxication, or lack of discretion in managing benefits received from public funds; or</para><para>(b) Is:</para><para>(i) Missing;</para><para>(ii) Detained, including incarcerated in a penal system; or</para><para>(iii) Outside the United States and unable to return;</para><para>(7) Person means an individual, corporation, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, limited liability company, association, joint venture, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or any other legal or commercial entity;</para><para>(8) Power of attorney means a writing or other record that grants authority to an agent to act in the place of the principal, whether or not the term power of attorney is used;</para><para>(9) Presently exercisable general power of appointment, with respect to property or a property interest subject to a power of appointment, means power exercisable at the time in question to vest absolute ownership in the principal individually, the principal's estate, the principal's creditors, or the creditors of the principal's estate. The term includes a power of appointment not exercisable until the occurrence of a specified event, the satisfaction of an ascertainable standard, or the passage of a specified period only after the occurrence of the specified event, the satisfaction of the ascertainable standard, or the passage of the specified period. The term does not include a power exercisable in a fiduciary capacity or only by will;</para><para>(10) Principal means an individual, who is eighteen years of age or older or is not a minor, who grants authority to an agent in a power of attorney;</para><para>(11) Property means anything that may be the subject of ownership, whether real or personal, legal or equitable, or any interest or right therein;</para><para>(12) Record means information that is inscribed on a tangible medium or that is stored in an electronic or other medium and is retrievable in perceivable form;</para><para>(13) Sign means, with present intent to authenticate or adopt a record:</para><para>(a) To execute or adopt a tangible symbol; or</para><para>(b) To attach to or logically associate with the record an electronic sound, symbol, or process;</para><para>(14) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any territory or insular possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States; and</para><para>(15) Stocks and bonds means stocks, bonds, mutual funds, and all other types of securities and financial instruments, whether held directly, indirectly, or in any other manner. The term does not include commodity futures contracts and call or put options on stocks or stock indexes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1113, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1195, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>