<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="30-4037"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4037</statuteno><catchline>Benefits from governmental programs
or civil or military service.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, benefits from governmental
programs or civil or military service means any benefit, program, or assistance
provided under a statute or regulation including social security, medicare,
and medicaid.</para>
<para>(2) Unless the power
of attorney otherwise provides, language in a power of attorney granting general
authority with respect to benefits from governmental programs or civil or
military service authorizes the agent to:</para><para>(a) Execute vouchers in the name of the principal
for allowances and reimbursements payable by the United States or a foreign
government or by a state or subdivision of a state to the principal, including
allowances and reimbursements for transportation of the individuals described
in subdivision (1)(a) of section 30-4036 and for shipment of their household
effects;</para><para>(b)
Take possession and order the removal and shipment of property of the principal
from a post, warehouse, depot, dock, or other place of storage or safekeeping,
either governmental or private, and execute and deliver a release, voucher,
receipt, bill of lading, shipping ticket, certificate, or other instrument
for that purpose;</para><para>(c)
Enroll in, apply for, select, reject, change, amend, or discontinue, on the
principal's behalf, a benefit or program;</para><para>(d) Prepare, file, and maintain a claim of the principal
for a benefit or assistance, financial or otherwise, to which the principal
may be entitled under a statute or regulation;</para><para>(e) Initiate, participate in, submit
to alternative dispute resolution, settle, oppose, or propose or accept a
compromise with respect to litigation concerning any benefit or assistance
the principal may be entitled to receive under a statute or regulation; and</para>
<para>(f) Receive the financial
proceeds of a claim described in subdivision (2)(d) of this section and conserve,
invest, disburse, or use for a lawful purpose anything so received.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1113, &#167; 37.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>