<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="30-4038"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4038</statuteno><catchline>Retirement plans.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, retirement
plan means a plan or account created by an employer, the principal, or another
individual to provide retirement benefits or deferred compensation of which
the principal is a participant, beneficiary, or owner, including a plan or
account under the following sections of the Internal Revenue Code:</para>
<para>(a) An individual retirement
account under section 408 of the Internal Revenue Code, 26 U.S.C. 408;</para>
<para>(b) A Roth individual
retirement account under section 408A of the Internal Revenue Code, 26 U.S.C.
408A;</para><para>(c)
A deemed individual retirement account under section 408(q) of the Internal
Revenue Code, 26 U.S.C. 408(q);</para><para>(d) An annuity or mutual fund custodial account under
section 403(b) of the Internal Revenue Code, 26 U.S.C. 403(b);</para>
<para>(e) A pension, profit-sharing,
stock bonus, or other retirement plan qualified under section 401(a) of the
Internal Revenue Code, 26 U.S.C. 401(a);</para><para>(f) A plan under section 457(b) of the Internal Revenue
Code, 26 U.S.C. 457(b); and</para><para>(g) A nonqualified deferred compensation plan under
section 409A of the Internal Revenue Code, 26 U.S.C. 409A.</para>
<para>(2) Unless the power
of attorney otherwise provides, language in a power of attorney granting general
authority with respect to retirement plans authorizes the agent to:</para>
<para>(a) Select the form and
timing of payments under a retirement plan and withdraw benefits from a plan;</para>
<para>(b) Make a rollover,
including a direct trustee-to-trustee rollover, of benefits from one retirement
plan to another;</para><para>(c)
Establish a retirement plan in the principal's name, including a beneficiary
individual retirement plan;</para><para>(d) Make contributions to a retirement plan;</para>
<para>(e) Exercise investment
powers available under a retirement plan; and</para><para>(f) Borrow from, sell assets to,
or purchase assets from a retirement plan.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1113, &#167; 38.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>