<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id129"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-4512"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4512</statuteno><catchline>Decanting power under limited distributive discretion.</catchline><para>(a) In this section, limited distributive discretion means a discretionary power of distribution that is limited to an ascertainable standard or a reasonably definite standard.</para><para>(b) An authorized fiduciary that has limited distributive discretion over the principal of the first trust for benefit of one or more current beneficiaries may exercise the decanting power over the principal of the first trust.</para><para>(c) Under this section and subject to section 30-4514, a second trust may be created or administered under the law of any jurisdiction. Under this section, the second trusts, in the aggregate, must grant each beneficiary of the first trust beneficial interests which are substantially similar to the beneficial interests of the beneficiary in the first trust.</para><para>(d) A power to make a distribution under a second trust for the benefit of a beneficiary who is an individual is substantially similar to a power under the first trust to make a distribution directly to the beneficiary. A distribution is for the benefit of a beneficiary if:</para><para>(1) the distribution is applied for the benefit of the beneficiary;</para><para>(2) the beneficiary is under a legal disability or the trustee reasonably believes the beneficiary is incapacitated, and the distribution is made as permitted under the Nebraska Uniform Trust Code; or</para><para>(3) the distribution is made as permitted under the terms of the first-trust instrument and the second-trust instrument for the benefit of the beneficiary.</para><para>(e) If an authorized fiduciary has limited distributive discretion over part but not all of the principal of a first trust, the fiduciary may exercise the decanting power under this section over that part of the principal over which the authorized fiduciary has limited distributive discretion.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 22. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Trust Code,</emphasis> see section 30-3801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>