<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id236"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-4515"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4515</statuteno><catchline>Trust limitation on decanting.</catchline><para>(a) An authorized fiduciary may not exercise the decanting power to the extent the first-trust instrument expressly prohibits exercise of:</para><para>(1) the decanting power; or</para><para>(2) a power granted by state law to the fiduciary to distribute part or all of the principal of the trust to another trust or to modify the trust.</para><para>(b) Exercise of the decanting power is subject to any restriction in the first-trust instrument that expressly applies to exercise of:</para><para>(1) the decanting power; or</para><para>(2) a power granted by state law to a fiduciary to distribute part or all of the principal of the trust to another trust or to modify the trust.</para><para>(c)(1) An authorized fiduciary who is a current beneficiary of the first trust or a beneficiary to which the net income or principal of the first trust would be distributed if the first trust were terminated may not exercise the decanting power under the Uniform Trust Decanting Act in a manner to eliminate or restrict a spendthrift clause or a clause restraining the voluntary or involuntary transfer of a beneficiary's interest in the first trust.</para><para>(2) Subject to subdivision (c)(1) of this section, a general prohibition of the amendment or revocation of a first trust, a spendthrift clause, or a clause restraining the voluntary or involuntary transfer of a beneficiary's interest does not preclude exercise of the decanting power.</para><para>(d) Subject to subsections (a) and (b) of this section, an authorized fiduciary may exercise the decanting power under the Uniform Trust Decanting Act even if the first-trust instrument permits the authorized fiduciary or another person to modify the first-trust instrument or to distribute part or all of the principal of the first trust to another trust.</para><para>(e) If a first-trust instrument contains an express prohibition described in subsection (a) of this section or an express restriction described in subsection (b) of this section, the provision must be included in the second-trust instrument.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB808, &#167; 25. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>