<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id437"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-4638"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4638</statuteno><catchline>Application to existing relationships.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act, on and after August 28, 2021:</para><para>(1) the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act applies to a power of appointment created before, on, or after August 28, 2021;</para><para>(2) the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act applies to a judicial proceeding concerning a power of appointment commenced on or after August 28, 2021;</para><para>(3) the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act applies to a judicial proceeding concerning a power of appointment commenced before August 28, 2021, unless the court finds that application of a particular provision of the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act would interfere substantially with the effective conduct of the judicial proceeding or prejudice a right of a party, in which case the particular provision of the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act does not apply and the superseded law applies;</para><para>(4) a rule of construction or presumption provided in the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act applies to an instrument executed before August 28, 2021, unless there is a clear indication of a contrary intent in the terms of the instrument; and</para><para>(5) except as otherwise provided in subdivisions (1) through (4) of this subsection, an action done before August 28, 2021, is not affected by the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act.</para><para>(b) If a right is acquired, extinguished, or barred on the expiration of a prescribed period that commenced under law of this state other than the Uniform Powers of Appointment Act before August 28, 2021, the law continues to apply to the right.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB501, &#167; 61. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>