<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id974"><amendatorysection chaptername="Decedents' Estates; Protection of Persons and Property" statutenumber="30-4302"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>30-4302</statuteno><catchline>(UDTA 2) Definitions.</catchline><para>(UDTA 2) In the Nebraska Uniform Directed Trust Act:</para><para>(1) Breach of trust includes a violation by a trust director or trustee of a duty imposed on that director or trustee by the terms of the trust, the Nebraska Uniform Directed Trust Act, or law of this state other than the Nebraska Uniform Directed Trust Act pertaining to trusts.</para><para>(2) Directed trust means a trust for which the terms of the trust grant a power of direction.</para><para>(3) Directed trustee means a trustee that is subject to a trust director's power of direction.</para><para>(4) Person means an individual, estate, business or nonprofit entity, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or other legal entity.</para><para>(5) Power of direction means a power over a trust granted to a person by the terms of the trust to the extent the power is exercisable while the person is not serving as a trustee. The term includes a power over the investment, management, or distribution of trust property or other matters of trust administration, including, but not limited to, amendment, reform, or termination of the trust. The term excludes the powers described in subsection (b) of section 30-4305.</para><para>(6) Settlor has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para><para>(7) State means a state of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, or any other territory or possession subject to the jurisdiction of the United States.</para><para>(8) Terms of a trust means:</para><para>(A) except as otherwise provided in subdivision (8)(B) of this section, the manifestation of the settlor's intent regarding a trust's provisions as:</para><para>(i) expressed in the trust instrument; or</para><para>(ii) established by other evidence that would be admissible in a judicial proceeding; or</para><para>(B) the trust's provisions as established, determined, or amended by:</para><para>(i) a trustee or trust director in accordance with applicable law;</para><para>(ii) court order; or</para><para>(iii) a nonjudicial settlement agreement under section 30-3811.</para><para>(9) Trust director means a person that is granted a power of direction by the terms of a trust to the extent the power is exercisable while the person is not serving as a trustee. The person is a trust director whether or not the terms of the trust refer to the person as a trust director and whether or not the person is a beneficiary or settlor of the trust.</para><para>(10) Trustee has the same meaning as in section 30-3803.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB536, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>