<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id281"><amendatorysection chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-901"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>55-901</statuteno><catchline>Military Base Development and Support Fund; created; use; investment; matching funds.</catchline><para>(1) The Military Base Development and Support Fund is created. The fund shall be used to contribute to construction, development, or support on any military base, located in Nebraska, for purposes of improving mission retention and recruitment; supporting the morale, health, and mental wellness of military members and families; and growing the economic impact of military bases in Nebraska. The Department of Veterans' Affairs shall administer the fund. The fund shall consist of transfers authorized by the Legislature and any gifts, grants, or bequests from any source, including federal, state, public, and private sources, for such purposes. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(2) The fund may be used for projects on military bases located in Nebraska, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(a) An outdoor airman amenity pavilion;</para><para>(b) Track and field stadium improvements;</para><para>(c) A parade-ground walking trail;</para><para>(d) Improvements at Willow Lakes Golf Course;</para><para>(e) Base Lake improvements;</para><para>(f) Landscape enhancements;</para><para>(g) Deterrence Park;</para><para>(h) Looking Glass Heritage Park;</para><para>(i) Quarters 13 comprehensive repairs, design, and construction; and</para><para>(j) B1000 Rooftop Garden.</para><para>(3) The Department of Veterans' Affairs shall require a match of private funding in an amount equal to or greater than one-half of the total cost of any project listed in subsection (2) of this section prior to authorizing an expenditure from the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para>
</crossreference>
    </law>
</legaldoc>