<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-126"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>55-126</statuteno><catchline>Adjutant General; assistants; duties;
bond or insurance; salary.</catchline><para>The deputy adjutant general or civilian deputy director shall
aid the Adjutant General by the performance of such duties as may be assigned
by the Adjutant General. In case of absence or inability of the Adjutant General,
the deputy adjutant general or civilian deputy director shall perform all or
such portion of the duties of the Adjutant General as the latter may expressly
delegate to him or her. If
the Adjutant General has appointed a civilian deputy director the Adjutant
General may, in the event of the Adjutant General's absence, delegate the
authority to perform the military duties of the Adjutant General to any active
officer of the Nebraska National Guard who shall hold the minimum grade of
colonel. In the case of absence of both the Adjutant General and
the deputy adjutant general or civilian deputy director, the Adjutant General
may delegate the authority to perform the military duties
of the Adjutant General to any active officer of the Nebraska National
Guard who shall hold the minimum grade of colonel and the Adjutant General may delegate
the authority to perform state duties to any member of his or her appointed
executive staff. The deputy adjutant general or civilian deputy director shall
be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201. The deputy adjutant general or civilian deputy director shall
receive such salary as the Adjutant General shall direct, payable biweekly.
Such salary for the deputy
adjutant general shall not exceed the annual pay and allowances
of regular military officers of equal rank and
time in service, except that when funds made available by the
federal government are in excess of the amount payable as directed by the
Adjutant General, the excess shall be used to reduce the amount required to
be paid by the State of Nebraska. Except
when called or ordered to active duty of the United States under 10 U.S.C.
in support of missions authorized by the President of the United States or
Secretary of Defense, the deputy adjutant general shall not be required to
take either paid or unpaid leave, or a leave of absence or a reduction in
salary, when performing his or her federal duties whether or not under federal
orders.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 205, &#167; 4, p. 486; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 121, &#167; 2, p. 290; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 234, &#167; 1, p. 834; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3305; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 55-125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 55-144; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 196, &#167; 2, p. 639; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 182, &#167; 2, p. 685; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 321, &#167; 4, p. 976; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 55-144; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 459, &#167; 24, p. 1589; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 170, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 963, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB550, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB806, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>