
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>55-125</statuteno><catchline>Adjutant General; assistants; qualifications.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Adjutant General shall appoint a deputy adjutant general or
a civilian deputy
director. An officer appointed as a deputy adjutant general shall
hold the minimum grade of colonel as provided in section 55-120. No person
shall be eligible for appointment
and service as the deputy adjutant
general unless he or she is an active member of the Nebraska National
Guard. The deputy adjutant general shall
have had at least four years of commissioned service in the Nebraska National
Guard immediately prior to appointment and shall have attained at least the
grade of lieutenant colonel and be eligible for promotion to colonel prior
to his or her appointment as deputy adjutant general.</para>
<para>(2) The chief of the National Guard Bureau shall appoint a United States
property and fiscal officer. The officer shall hold the minimum grade of colonel.
The Governor shall nominate one or more officers for the position of United
States property and fiscal officer after consultation with the Adjutant General.
All nominees shall have attained at least the grade of lieutenant colonel
and be eligible for promotion to colonel prior to his or her nomination. The
United States property and fiscal officer may appoint, with the approval of
the Adjutant General, one or more assistant United States property and fiscal
officers, each with the minimum grade of captain. The United States property
and fiscal officer and each assistant United States property and fiscal officer
shall be appointed from among the active officers of the Nebraska National
Guard and shall have been commissioned officers in the Nebraska National Guard
for a period of at least four years immediately prior to appointment.</para>
<para>(3) The Adjutant General shall appoint all additional officers, clerks,
and caretakers as may be required.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 205, &#167; 4, p. 485; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 121, &#167; 2, p. 290; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 234, &#167; 1, p. 833; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3305; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 55-125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 55-143; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 188, &#167; 20, p. 600; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 321, &#167; 3, p. 976; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 55-143; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 459, &#167; 23, p. 1589; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 983, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 614, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 963, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB550, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB806, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>