<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id320">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" id="id322"  statutenumber="55-131"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id324">55-131</statuteno><catchline id="id325">Adjutant General;
property; receipt as trustee; control; disposition; Military Department Cash
Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>The Military Department
Cash Fund is created. The fund shall be administered by the Adjutant General.
The fund shall consist of all nonfederal revenue received by the National
Guard pursuant to this section. The Adjutant General is hereby authorized
to accept by devise, gift, or otherwise and hold, as trustee, for the benefit
and use of the National Guard or any part thereof any property, real or personal;
to invest and reinvest the property; to collect, receive, and recover the
rents, incomes, and issues from the property; and to expend them as provided
by the terms of the devise or gift, or if not so provided, to expend them
for the benefit and use of the National Guard as he or she in his or her discretion
shall determine, subject to the approval of the Governor. Except as otherwise
provided by law, all other money received by the National Guard and derived
from any other source shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Military Department Cash Fund. Transfers
may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any
money in the Military Department Cash Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 189, &#167; 20, p. 662; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 55-126; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 55-150; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 342, &#167; 1, p. 973; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 55-150; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 459, &#167; 29, p. 1591; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 55, p. 2379; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 787, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 31.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>