<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate=" ">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-126"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>55-126</statuteno><catchline>Adjutant General; assistants; duties;
bond or insurance; salary.</catchline><para>The deputy adjutant general, chief
of staff of the Military Department, or deputy director shall aid the Adjutant
General by the performance of such duties as may be assigned by the Adjutant
General. In case of absence or inability of the Adjutant General, the deputy
adjutant general, chief of staff of the Military Department, or deputy director
shall perform all or such portion of the duties of the Adjutant General as
the latter may expressly delegate to him or her. In
the case of absence of both the Adjutant General and the deputy
adjutant general, chief of staff of the Military Department, or deputy director, the Adjutant General
may delegate the authority to perform the duties of the Adjutant General to
any active officer of the Nebraska military who shall hold at least the rank
of colonel. The deputy adjutant general, chief of staff of the Military Department,
or deputy director shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201.
The deputy adjutant general, chief of staff of the Military Department, or
deputy director shall receive such salary as the Adjutant General shall direct,
payable biweekly. Such salary shall
not exceed the annual pay and allowances of regular military officers of equal
rank, except that when funds made available by the federal government are
in excess of the amount payable as directed by the Adjutant General, the excess
shall be used to reduce the amount required to be paid by the State of Nebraska.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 205, &#167; 4, p. 486; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 121, &#167; 2, p. 290; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 234, &#167; 1, p. 834; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3305; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 55-125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 55-144; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 196, &#167; 2, p. 639; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 182, &#167; 2, p. 685; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 321, &#167; 4, p. 976; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 55-144; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 459, &#167; 24, p. 1589; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 653, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 170, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 963, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB550, &#167;  5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>