<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-121"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>55-121</statuteno><catchline>Adjutant General; qualifications;
salary; sources for payment; performance of federal duties; effect.</catchline><para>The Adjutant General shall be appointed by the Governor from the active
or retired commissioned officers of the National Guard of this state. Such
Adjutant General shall be or have been a commissioned officer who has actively
served in the National Guard of this state for at least five years, shall
have attained at least the grade of lieutenant colonel, and shall be able
to become eligible for promotion to general officer. If a retired officer
is appointed, he or she shall not have been retired for more than two years
at the time he or she is considered for appointment. He or she shall hold
his or her office as provided in section 55-136. He or she shall receive for
his or her services such salary as the Governor shall direct, payable biweekly, except that such salary shall not
exceed the annual pay and allowances of regular military officers of equal
rank. If funds made available by the federal government are in excess of the
amount payable as directed by the Governor, the excess shall be used to reduce
the amount required to be paid by the state. Due to the interrelated nature
of the Adjutant General's state and federal duties, the Adjutant General shall
not be required to take paid or unpaid leave or leaves of absence to perform
his or her federal duties, whether or not under federal orders. The Adjutant
General shall continue to receive his or her salary during all such periods.
The Adjutant General shall only be required to take leave or leaves of absence
during those times when he or she is absent and performing neither his or
her state nor federal duties as Adjutant General. This section shall not apply
if the Adjutant General is called to active duty of the United States under
10 U.S.C.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 205, &#167; 4, p. 485; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 121, &#167; 2, p. 290; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 234, &#167; 1, p. 834; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3305; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 55-125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 55-141; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 196, &#167; 1, p. 639; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 182, &#167; 1, p. 685; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 273, &#167; 1, p. 807; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 341, &#167; 2, p. 972; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 55-141; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 459, &#167; 19, p. 1587; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 983, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 963, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB550, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>