<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>55-601</statuteno><catchline>Commission on Military and Veteran Affairs; created; members; terms; vacancy.</catchline><para>(1) The Commission on Military and Veteran Affairs is created. The commission shall consist of the following voting members:</para><para>(a) The Director of Economic Development;</para><para>(b) The Adjutant General or his or her designee;</para><para>(c) The Director of Veterans’ Affairs; and</para><para>(d) Three residents of the State of Nebraska, one from each congressional district. At least one of the three residents shall have current or prior military experience and at least one shall have a background in business.</para><para>(2) The commission shall have the following nonvoting, ex officio members:</para><para>(a) The veterans' program coordinator of the Department of Labor;</para><para>(b) The chair of the State Committee of Employer Support of the Guard and Reserve;</para><para>(c) The commander of the 55th Wing of the Air Combat Command or his or her designee;</para><para>(d) The commander of the United States Strategic Command or his or her designee; and</para><para>(e) The commander of the 557th Weather Wing of the United States Air Force or his or her designee.</para><para>(3) The members of the commission described in subdivision (1)(d) of this section shall be appointed by the Governor. The Governor shall designate the initial terms of the members described in subdivision (1)(d) of this section so that one member serves for a term of two years, one member serves for a term of three years, and one member serves for a term of four years. Succeeding appointments shall be for terms of four years and shall be made in the same manner as the original appointments. The terms of the members shall begin on October 1 of the year in which they are appointed unless appointed to fill a vacancy. Appointments to fill a vacancy, occurring other than by the expiration of a term of office, shall be made for the unexpired term of the member whose office is vacated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB754, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB138, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>