<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Militia" statutenumber="55-157"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>55-157</statuteno><catchline>Militia; active duty; personnel; compensation; travel expenses; health insurance
reimbursement.</catchline><para>(1) When an active or retired officer or enlisted
person of the National Guard is ordered to active service of the state by
the Governor or Adjutant General, he or she shall receive compensation as
provided in this subsection. For service during a disaster or emergency, an officer or enlisted person
shall be entitled to the same pay, subsistence, and quarters allowance as
officers and enlisted personnel of corresponding grades of the Army and Air
Force of the United States and
shall be reimbursed for travel expenses in accordance with the Joint Federal
Travel Regulations. For advice, counsel, duties, or service to
the Governor or Adjutant General, an officer or enlisted person may, at the
discretion of the Adjutant General, be in a pay or nonpay status. If in a
pay status, the officer or enlisted person shall be entitled to the same pay,
subsistence, and quarters allowance as officers and enlisted personnel of
corresponding grades of the Army and Air Force of the United States and shall be reimbursed for travel expenses
in accordance with the Joint Federal Travel Regulations.</para>
<para>(2) For any period of active service of the state in excess of thirty
consecutive days, performed at the order of the Governor or Adjutant General
or at the request of the federal government, a state, or other agency or entity,
an officer or enlisted person shall be entitled to reimbursement of one hundred
percent of the cost of his or her privately purchased health insurance or
up to one hundred two percent of the cost of his or her employer-provided
health insurance. The officer or enlisted person shall provide evidence of
payment and shall be reimbursed to the extent that evidence of payment can
be provided. The reimbursement for health insurance shall be treated as an
allowance but may be paid separately once received by the State of Nebraska
from the federal government, a state, or other agency or entity requesting
the services of the officer or enlisted person. The State of Nebraska will
not pay or advance the cost of such health insurance reimbursement for the
federal government, a state, or other agency or entity. The State of Nebraska
is exempt from the requirement under this subsection to reimburse officers
and enlisted persons for their health insurance costs.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 90, &#167; 44, p. 380; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3943; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3343; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 55-170; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 55-184; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 188, &#167; 33, p. 606; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 55-184; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 459, &#167; 55, p. 1599; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 934, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 930, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 963, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1141, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>