<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-607"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-607</statuteno><catchline>Contract for invention development services; voidable; when; civil action authorized; additional amount distributed to common schools; when; rebuttable presumption.</catchline><para>(1) Any contract for invention development services which does not substantially comply with the Invention Development Services Disclosure Act shall be voidable at the option of the customer. Any contract for invention development services entered into in reliance upon any false, fraudulent, or misleading information, representation, notice, or advertisement of the invention developer shall be voidable at the option of the customer. Any waiver by the customer of any of the provisions of the act shall be deemed contrary to public policy and shall be void and unenforceable.</para><para>(2) Any customer who has been injured by a violation of the act by an invention developer, by any false or fraudulent statement, representation, or omission of material fact by an invention developer, or by failure of an invention developer to make all the disclosures required by the act may recover in a civil action against the invention developer, in addition to reasonable costs and attorney's fees, the amount of actual damages sustained by the customer.</para><para>(3) If a customer establishes a claim and secures judgment on such claim under subsection (2) of this section, an amount up to two times the judgment may be recovered from the invention developer, if ordered by the court. Any amount recovered pursuant to this subsection shall be placed in a fund to be distributed to the common schools of this state.</para><para>(4) A substantial violation of any provision of the act by an invention developer or the execution by the customer of a contract for invention development services in reliance on any such false or fraudulent statements, representations, or material omissions shall establish a rebuttable presumption of injury.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 96, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc>