<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id162">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" id="id164" statutenumber="87-211"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>87-211</statuteno><catchline id="id167">Trade name;
registration; term effective; renewal; fee; statement.</catchline><para>Registration
of a trade name under sections 87-208 to 87-219.01 shall be effective
for a term of ten years from the date of registration and, upon application
filed in duplicate within six months prior to the expiration of such term
on a form to be furnished by the Secretary of State, the registration may
be renewed for a like term. A renewal fee of one hundred dollars payable to
the Secretary of State shall accompany the application for renewal of the
registration.</para>
<para>A trade name registration may be renewed for successive periods
of ten years in like manner.</para>
<para>The Secretary of State shall notify registrants of trade
names under sections 87-208 to 87-219.01 of the necessity
of renewal within the year next preceding the expiration of the ten years
from the date of registration or of last renewal by writing to the last-known
street address of the registrants.</para>
<para>Any registration in force on August 27, 1971, shall expire
ten years from the date of the registration or of the last renewal thereof,
whichever is later, and may be renewed by filing an application with the Secretary
of State on a form furnished by him or her and paying the renewal fee as provided
in this section within six months prior to the expiration of the registration.</para>
<para>All applications for renewals under sections 87-208 to 87-219.01 whether of registrations made under
sections 87-208 to 87-219.01 or of registrations
effected under any prior act shall include a statement that the trade name
is still in use in this state.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 628, &#167; 4, p. 2101; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 486, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 95, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1016, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 453, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB462, &#167; 11.</para><effectivedate>August 27, 2011</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>