<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" id="id5" statutenumber="87-301"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>87-301</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Access software provider means a provider of software, including client or server software, or enabling tools that do any one or more of the following: (a) Filter, screen, allow, or disallow content; (b) pick, choose, analyze, or digest content; or (c) transmit, receive, display, forward, cache, search, subset, organize, reorganize, or translate content;</para><para>(2) Appropriate inventory repurchase program means a program by which a plan or operation repurchases, upon request and upon commercially reasonable terms, when the salesperson's business relationship with the company ends, current and marketable inventory in the possession of the salesperson that was purchased by the salesperson for resale. Any such plan or operation shall clearly describe the program in its recruiting literature, sales manual, or contract with independent salespersons, including the disclosure of any inventory that is not eligible for repurchase under the program;</para><para>(3) Article means a product as distinguished from its trademark, label, or distinctive dress in packaging;</para><para>(4) Attorney General means the Attorney General of the State of Nebraska or the county attorney of any county with the consent and advice of the Attorney General;</para><para>(5) Cable operator means any person or group of persons (a) who provides cable service over a cable system and directly or through one or more affiliates owns a significant interest in such cable system or (b) who otherwise controls or is responsible for, through any arrangement, the management and operation of such a cable system;</para><para>(6) Certification mark means a mark used in connection with the goods or services of a person other than the certifier to indicate geographic origin, material, mode of manufacture, quality, accuracy, or other characteristics of the goods or services or to indicate that the work or labor on the goods or services was performed by members of a union or other organization;</para><para>(7) Collective mark means a mark used by members of a cooperative, association, or other collective group or organization to identify goods or services and distinguish them from those of others, or to indicate membership in the collective group or organization;</para><para>(8) Commercially reasonable terms means the repurchase of current and marketable inventory within twelve months from the date of purchase at not less than ninety percent of the original net cost, less appropriate setoffs and legal claims, if any;</para><para>(9) Compensation means a payment of any money, thing of value, or financial benefit;</para><para>(10) Consideration means anything of value, including the payment of cash or the purchase of goods, services, or intangible property. The term does not include the purchase of goods or services furnished at cost to be used in making sales and not for resale or time and effort spent in pursuit of sales or recruiting activities;</para><para>(11) Covered file-sharing program means a computer program, application, or software that enables the computer on which such program, application, or software is installed to designate files as available for searching by and copying to one or more other computers, to transmit such designated files directly to one or more other computers, and to request the transmission of such designated files directly from one or more other computers. Covered file-sharing program does not mean a program, application, or software designed primarily to operate as a server that is accessible over the Internet using the Internet Domain Name System, to transmit or receive email messages, instant messaging, real-time audio or video communications, or real-time voice communications, or to provide network or computer security, network management, hosting and backup services, maintenance, diagnostics, technical support or repair, or to detect or prevent fraudulent activities;</para><para>(12) Current and marketable has its plain and ordinary meaning but excludes inventory that is no longer within its commercially reasonable use or shelf-life period, was clearly described to salespersons prior to purchase as seasonal, discontinued, or special promotion products not subject to the plan or operation's inventory repurchase program, or has been used or opened;</para><para>(13) Information content provider means any person or entity that is responsible, in whole or in part, for the creation or development of information provided through the Internet or any other interactive computer service;</para><para>(14) Interactive computer service means any information service, system, or access software provider that provides or enables computer access by multiple users to a computer server, including specifically a service or system that provides access to the Internet and such systems operated or services offered by libraries or educational institutions;</para><para>(15) Inventory includes both goods and services, including company-produced promotional materials, sales aids, and sales kits that the plan or operation requires independent salespersons to purchase;</para><para>(16) Inventory loading means that the plan or operation requires or encourages its independent salespersons to purchase inventory in an amount which exceeds that which the salesperson can expect to resell for ultimate consumption or to a consumer in a reasonable time period, or both;</para><para>(17) Investment means any acquisition, for a consideration other than personal services, of personal property, tangible or intangible, for profit or business purposes, and includes, without limitation, franchises, business opportunities, and services. It does not include real estate, securities registered under the Securities Act of Nebraska, or sales demonstration equipment and materials furnished at cost for use in making sales and not for resale;</para><para>(18) Mark means a word, a name, a symbol, a device, or any combination of a word, name, symbol, or device in any form or arrangement;</para><para>(19) Person means a natural person, a corporation, a government, a governmental subdivision or agency, a business trust, an estate, a trust, a partnership, a joint venture, a limited liability company, an unincorporated association, a sole proprietorship, or two or more of any of such persons having a joint or common interest or any other legal or commercial entity;</para><para>(20) Pyramid promotional scheme means any plan or operation in which a participant gives consideration for the right to receive compensation that is derived primarily from the recruitment of other persons as participants in the plan or operation rather than from the sales of goods, services, or intangible property to participants or by participants to others. A limitation as to the number of persons who may participate, or the presence of additional conditions affecting eligibility, or upon payment of anything of value by a person whereby the person obtains any other property in addition to the right to receive consideration, does not change the identity of the scheme as a pyramid promotional scheme;</para><para>(21) Referral or chain referral sales or leases means any sales technique, plan, arrangement, or agreement whereby the seller or lessor gives or offers to give a rebate or discount or otherwise pays or offers to pay value to the buyer or lessee as an inducement for a sale or lease in consideration of the buyer or lessee giving to the seller or lessor the names of prospective buyers or lessees or otherwise aiding the seller or lessor in making a sale or lease to another person if the earning of the rebate, discount, or other value is contingent upon the occurrence of an event subsequent to the time the buyer or lessee agrees to buy or lease;</para><para>(22) Service mark means a mark used in the sale or advertising of services to identify the services of one person and distinguish them from the services of others;</para><para>(23) Substance means any lookalike substance as defined in section 28-401;</para><para>(24) Telecommunications service means the offering of telecommunications for a fee directly to the public, or to such classes of users as to be effectively available directly to the public, regardless of the facilities used;</para><para>(25) Trademark means a word, a name, a symbol, a device, or any combination of a word, name, symbol, or device adopted and used by a person to identify goods made or sold by such person and to distinguish such goods from goods made or sold by others;</para><para>(26) Trade name means a word, a name, or any combination of a word or name in any form or arrangement used by a person to identify such person's business, vocation, or occupation and distinguish such business, vocation, or occupation from the business, vocation, or occupation of others; and</para><para>(27) Use or promote the use of, for purposes of subdivision (a)(13) of section 87-302, means contrive, prepare, establish, plan, operate, advertise, or otherwise induce or attempt to induce another person to participate in a pyramid promotional scheme, including a pyramid promotional scheme run through the Internet, email, or other electronic communications.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 855, &#167; 1, p. 3221; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 327, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 557; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 857, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB801, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB835, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1009, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Securities Act of Nebraska,</emphasis> see section 8-1123.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The terms of the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act provide only for equitable relief consistent with general principles of equity. State ex rel. Stenberg v. Consumer's Choice Foods, 276 Neb. 481, 755 N.W.2d 583 (2008).</para><para>Attorney General and associates immune from suit for libel after initiating deceptive practices suit against plaintiffs. Ledwith v. Douglas, 568 F.2d 117 (8th Cir. 1978).</para><para>Successor to manufacturer in representing it owned trademark owned by distributor and in using trademark in its corporate name violated this act. Wrist-Rocket Manuf. Co., Inc. v. Saunders, 379 F.Supp. 902 (D. Neb. 1974).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>