<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-132</statuteno><catchline>Certificate of registration; contents;
how treated.</catchline><para>Upon compliance by the applicant with the requirements
of the Trademark Registration Act, the secretary shall return the duplicate
copy of the application stamped with the filing date to the applicant. The
certificate of registration shall be issued under the signature of the secretary
and the seal of the state, and it shall show the name and business address
and, if a corporation or other
type of business entity except a partnership, the state of incorporation or organization, or if a
partnership, the state in which the partnership is organized and the names
of the general partners, as specified by the secretary, of the person claiming
ownership of the mark, the date claimed for the first use of the mark anywhere
and the date claimed for the first use of the mark in this state, the class
of goods or services and a description of the goods or services on or in connection
with which the mark is used, a reproduction of the mark, the registration
date, and the term of the registration. An original, a duplicate original,
or a certified copy of an application for trademark which has the file stamp
and date of the secretary shall be admissible in evidence as competent and
sufficient proof of the registration of such mark in any actions or judicial
proceedings in any court of this state. Registration of a mark with the secretary
shall be prima facie evidence of the right to use the mark shown in the registration
on or in connection with the class or classes of goods or services designated
in the registration.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 626, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB886, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>