<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-603"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-603</statuteno><catchline>Contract for invention development services; requirements; option to terminate.</catchline><para>(1) Every contract for invention development services shall be in writing and shall be subject to the Invention Development Services Disclosure Act. A copy of the written contract shall be given to the customer at the time he or she signs the contract.</para><para>(2) If it is the invention developer's normal practice to seek more than one contract in connection with an invention or if the invention developer normally seeks to perform services in connection with an invention in more than one phase with the performance of each phase covered in one or more subsequent contracts, the invention developer shall so state in writing at the time the customer signs the first contract and shall supply to the customer such writing together with a written summary of the developer's normal terms, if any, of such subsequent contracts, including the approximate amount of the developer's normal fees or other consideration, if any, that may be required from the customer.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding any contractual provision to the contrary, no payment for invention development services shall be required, made, or received until three business days after the date on which the customer receives a copy of the contract for invention development services signed by the invention developer and the customer. Delivery of a promissory note, check, bill of exchange, or negotiable instrument of any kind to the invention developer or to a third party for the benefit of the invention developer, irrespective of the date or dates appearing in such instrument, shall be deemed payment for the purpose of this section.</para><para>(4) The parties to a contract for invention development services shall have the option to terminate the contract until payment is made. The customer may exercise the option by refraining from making payment to the invention developer. The invention developer may exercise the option to terminate by giving to the customer a written notice of its exercise of the option, which written notice shall become effective upon receipt by the customer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 96, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>