<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-402</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Franchise Practices Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Franchise shall mean (a) a written arrangement for a definite or indefinite period, in which a person grants to another person for a franchise fee a license to use a trade name, trademark, service mark, or related characteristics and in which there is a community of interest in the marketing of goods or services at wholesale or retail or by lease, agreement, or otherwise and (b) any arrangement, agreement, or contract, either expressed or implied, for the sale, distribution, or marketing of nonalcoholic beverages at wholesale, retail, or otherwise. Franchise shall not include any arrangement, agreement, or contract, either expressed or implied, for the sale, distribution, or marketing of petroleum products at wholesale, retail, or otherwise;</para><para>(2) Person shall mean every natural person, firm, partnership, limited liability company, association, or corporation;</para><para>(3) Franchisor shall mean a person who grants a franchise to another person;</para><para>(4) Franchisee shall mean a person to whom a franchise is offered or granted;</para><para>(5) Franchise fee shall include any payment made by the franchisee to the franchisor other than a payment for the purchase of goods or services, for a surety bond, for a surety deposit, or for security for payment of debts due;</para><para>(6) Sale, transfer, or assignment shall mean any disposition of a franchise or any interest therein, with or without consideration, which shall include, but not be limited to, bequest, inheritance, gift, exchange, lease, or license;</para><para>(7) Place of business shall mean a fixed geographical location at which the franchisee displays for sale and sells the franchisor's goods or offers for sale and sells the franchisor's services. Place of business shall not mean an office, a warehouse, a place of storage, a residence, or a vehicle; and</para><para>(8) Good cause for terminating, canceling, or failure to renew a franchise shall be limited to failure by the franchisee to substantially comply with the requirements imposed upon him or her by the franchise.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 202, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 371, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 559. </para></source><annotation><para>Franchise agreements are not required to be written. Regnev, Inc. v. Shasta Beverages, 215 Neb. 230, 337 N.W.2d 783 (1983).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>