<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-304</statuteno><catchline>Applicability of act.</catchline><para>(a) The Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act does not apply to:</para><para>(1) Conduct in compliance with the orders or rules of, or a statute administered by, a federal, state, or local governmental agency;</para><para>(2) Publishers, broadcasters, printers, or other persons engaged in the dissemination of information or reproduction of printed or pictorial matters who publish, broadcast, or reproduce material without knowledge of its deceptive character; or</para><para>(3) Actions or appeals pending (a) on December 25, 1969, under the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act as such act existed immediately prior to March 25, 1974, or (b) under such act as amended and sections 87-303.01 to 87-303.09 on March 25, 1974.</para><para>(b) Subdivisions (a)(2) and (a)(3) of section 87-302 do not apply to the use of a service mark, trademark, certification mark, collective mark, trade name, or other trade identification that was used and not abandoned before December 25, 1969, if the use was in good faith and is otherwise lawful except for the Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act.</para><para>(c) The Uniform Deceptive Trade Practices Act shall apply to deceptive trade practices conducted in whole or in part within the State of Nebraska against residents or nonresidents of this state. The act shall also apply to deceptive trade practices conducted outside of Nebraska against residents of this state if there is a direct connection to any deceptive trade practices conducted in whole or in part within this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 855, &#167; 4, p. 3224; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 327, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB781, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
