<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-604</statuteno><catchline>Contract for invention development services; cover sheet; contents; invention developer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Every contract for invention development services shall have a conspicuous and legible cover sheet attached with the following notice printed thereon in boldface of at least ten-point type:</para><para>THIS CONTRACT BETWEEN YOU AND AN INVENTION DEVELOPER IS REGULATED BY THE INVENTION DEVELOPMENT SERVICES DISCLOSURE ACT. YOU ARE NOT PERMITTED OR REQUIRED TO MAKE ANY PAYMENTS UNDER THIS CONTRACT UNTIL THREE BUSINESS DAYS AFTER YOU SIGN THIS CONTRACT AND RECEIVE A COMPLETED COPY OF IT.</para><para>IF YOU ASSIGN EVEN A PARTIAL INTEREST IN THE IDEA OR INVENTION TO THE INVENTION DEVELOPER, THE INVENTION DEVELOPER MAY HAVE THE RIGHT TO SELL OR DISPOSE OF THE IDEA OR INVENTION WITHOUT YOUR CONSENT AND MAY NOT HAVE TO SHARE THE PROFITS WITH YOU.</para><para>THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CUSTOMERS WHO HAVE CONTRACTED WITH THE INVENTION DEVELOPER SINCE ..(date).. IS ............. . THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CUSTOMERS KNOWN BY THIS INVENTION DEVELOPER TO HAVE RECEIVED, BY VIRTUE OF THIS INVENTION DEVELOPER'S PERFORMANCE, AN AMOUNT OF MONEY IN EXCESS OF THE AMOUNT PAID BY THE CUSTOMER TO THIS INVENTION DEVELOPER IS .............. .</para><para>THIS CONTRACT DOES NOT PROVIDE ANY PATENT, COPYRIGHT, OR TRADEMARK PROTECTION FOR YOUR IDEA OR INVENTION. YOU ARE ENCOURAGED TO CONSULT WITH A QUALIFIED ATTORNEY BEFORE SIGNING THIS CONTRACT. BY PROCEEDING WITHOUT THE ADVICE OF A QUALIFIED ATTORNEY, YOU COULD LOSE ANY RIGHTS YOU MIGHT HAVE IN YOUR IDEA OR INVENTION.</para><para>(2) The invention developer shall complete the cover sheet with the proper information to be provided in the blanks. The invention developer shall insert in the first blank the date the invention developer began business or September 6, 1991, whichever is later. The numbers to be inserted in the last two blanks may be rounded to the nearest one hundred and do not need to include those who have contracted within the three immediately preceding calendar months or parts thereof. If the number to be inserted in the third blank is zero, it shall be so stated.</para><para>(3) The cover sheet shall only contain the information required by this section and the name, primary office address, and local office address of the invention developer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 96, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>