
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" id="id00"  statutenumber="87-802"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-802</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Financial Data Protection and Consumer Notification of Data Security Breach Act of 2006:</para><para>(1) Breach of the security of the system means the unauthorized acquisition of unencrypted computerized data that compromises the security, confidentiality, or integrity of personal information maintained by an individual or a commercial entity. Good faith acquisition of personal information by an employee or agent of an individual or a commercial entity for the purposes of the individual or the commercial entity is not a breach of the security of the system if the personal information is not used or subject to further unauthorized disclosure. Acquisition of personal information pursuant to a search warrant, subpoena, or other court order or pursuant to a subpoena or order of a state agency is not a breach of the security of the system;</para><para>(2) Commercial entity includes a corporation, business trust, estate, trust, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability partnership, limited liability company, association, organization, joint venture, government, governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or any other legal entity, whether for profit or not for profit;</para><para>(3) Encrypted means converted by use of an algorithmic process to transform data into a form in which the data is rendered unreadable or unusable without use of a confidential process or key. Data shall not be considered encrypted if the confidential process or key was or is reasonably believed to have been acquired as a result of the breach of the security of the system;</para><para>(4) Notice means:</para><para>(a) Written notice;</para><para>(b) Telephonic notice;</para><para>(c) Electronic notice, if the notice provided is consistent with the provisions regarding electronic records and signatures set forth in 15 U.S.C. 7001, as such section existed on January 1, 2006;</para><para>(d) Substitute notice, if the individual or commercial entity required to provide notice demonstrates that the cost of providing notice will exceed seventy-five thousand dollars, that the affected class of Nebraska residents to be notified exceeds one hundred thousand residents, or that the individual or commercial entity does not have sufficient contact information to provide notice. Substitute notice under this subdivision requires all of the following:</para><para>(i) Electronic mail notice if the individual or commercial entity has electronic mail addresses for the members of the affected class of Nebraska residents;</para><para>(ii) Conspicuous posting of the notice on the website of the individual or commercial entity if the individual or commercial entity maintains a website; and</para><para>(iii) Notice to major statewide media outlets; or</para><para>(e) Substitute notice, if the individual or commercial entity required to provide notice has ten employees or fewer and demonstrates that the cost of providing notice will exceed ten thousand dollars. Substitute notice under this subdivision requires all of the following:</para><para>(i) Electronic mail notice if the individual or commercial entity has electronic mail addresses for the members of the affected class of Nebraska residents;</para><para>(ii) Notification by a paid advertisement in a local newspaper that is distributed in the geographic area in which the individual or commercial entity is located, which advertisement shall be of sufficient size that it covers at least one-quarter of a page in the newspaper and shall be published in the newspaper at least once a week for three consecutive weeks;</para><para>(iii) Conspicuous posting of the notice on the website of the individual or commercial entity if the individual or commercial entity maintains a website; and</para><para>(iv) Notification to major media outlets in the geographic area in which the individual or commercial entity is located;</para><para>(5) Personal information means either of the following:</para><para>(a) A Nebraska resident's first name or first initial and last name in combination with any one or more of the following data elements that relate to the resident if either the name or the data elements are not encrypted, redacted, or otherwise altered by any method or technology in such a manner that the name or data elements are unreadable:</para><para>(i) Social security number;</para><para>(ii) Motor vehicle operator's license number or state identification card number;</para><para>(iii) Account number or credit or debit card number, in combination with any required security code, access code, or password that would permit access to a resident's financial account;</para><para>(iv) Unique electronic identification number or routing code, in combination with any required security code, access code, or password; or</para><para>(v) Unique biometric data, such as a fingerprint, voice print, or retina or iris image, or other unique physical representation; or</para><para>(b) A user name or email address, in combination with a password or security question and answer, that would permit access to an online account.</para><para>Personal information does not include publicly available information that is lawfully made available to the general public from federal, state, or local government records; and</para><para>(6) Redact means to alter or truncate data such that no more than the last four digits of a social security number, motor vehicle operator's license number, state identification card number, or account number is accessible as part of the personal information.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB835, &#167; 27. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>