<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" id="id00"  statutenumber="87-803"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>87-803</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Breach of security; investigation; notice to resident; notice to Attorney General.</catchline><para>(1) An individual or a commercial entity that conducts business in Nebraska and that owns or licenses computerized data that includes personal information about a resident of Nebraska shall, when it becomes aware of a breach of the security of the system, conduct in good faith a reasonable and prompt investigation to determine the likelihood that personal information has been or will be used for an unauthorized purpose. If the investigation determines that the use of information about a Nebraska resident for an unauthorized purpose has occurred or is reasonably likely to occur, the individual or commercial entity shall give notice to the affected Nebraska resident. Notice shall be made as soon as possible and without unreasonable delay, consistent with the legitimate needs of law enforcement and consistent with any measures necessary to determine the scope of the breach and to restore the reasonable integrity of the computerized data system.</para><para>(2) If notice of a breach of security of the system is required by subsection (1) of this section, the individual or commercial entity shall also, not later than the time when notice is provided to the Nebraska resident, provide notice of the breach of security of the system to the Attorney General.</para><para>(3) An individual or a commercial entity that maintains computerized data that includes personal information that the individual or commercial entity does not own or license shall give notice to and cooperate with the owner or licensee of the information of any breach of the security of the system when it becomes aware of a breach if use of personal information about a Nebraska resident for an unauthorized purpose occurred or is reasonably likely to occur. Cooperation includes, but is not limited to, sharing with the owner or licensee information relevant to the breach, not including information proprietary to the individual or commercial entity.</para><para>(4) Notice required by this section may be delayed if a law enforcement agency determines that the notice will impede a criminal investigation. Notice shall be made in good faith, without unreasonable delay, and as soon as possible after the law enforcement agency determines that notification will no longer impede the investigation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 876, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB835, &#167; 28. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>