<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-130"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>87-130</statuteno><catchline>Application for registration; contents.</catchline><para>Subject to the limitations set forth in the Trademark Registration Act, any person who uses a mark may file in the office of the secretary, in a manner complying with the requirements of the secretary, an application for registration of that mark including, but not limited to, the following information:</para><para>(1) The name and business address of the person applying for such registration and, if a corporation or other type of business entity except a partnership, the state of incorporation or organization, or if a partnership, the state in which the partnership is organized and the names of the general partners, as specified by the secretary;</para><para>(2) The goods or services on or in connection with which the mark is used and the mode or manner in which the mark is used on or in connection with such goods or services and the class in which such goods or services fall;</para><para>(3) The date when the mark was first used anywhere and the date when it was first used in this state by the applicant or a predecessor in interest; and</para><para>(4) A statement that the applicant is the owner of the mark, that the mark is in use, and that, to the knowledge of the person verifying the application, no other person has registered, either federally or in this state, or has the right to use such mark either in the identical form or in such near resemblance as to be likely, when applied to the goods or services of such other person, to cause confusion or mistake or to deceive.</para><para>The secretary may also require a statement as to whether an application to register the mark, or portions or a composite thereof, has been filed by the applicant or a predecessor in interest in the United States Patent and Trademark Office, and if so, the applicant shall provide full particulars with respect thereto, including the filing date and serial number of each application, the status of each application, and if any application was finally refused registration or has otherwise not resulted in a registration, the reasons for the refusal or rejection. The secretary may also require that a drawing of the mark, complying with such requirements as the secretary may specify, accompany the application. The application shall be signed and verified, by oath, affirmation, or declaration subject to perjury laws, by the applicant or by a member of the firm or an officer of the corporation or association applying. The application shall be submitted in duplicate and shall be accompanied by three specimens showing the mark as actually used and by the application fee of one hundred ten dollars if submitted in writing and one hundred dollars if submitted electronically pursuant to section 84-511. The fee for filing under this section shall be payable to the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State shall remit all such fees collected to the State Treasurer. The State Treasurer shall credit sixty percent of the fees to the General Fund and forty percent of the fees to the Secretary of State Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 626, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB886, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 39. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>