<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-708"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>87-708</statuteno><catchline>Death or incapacity of dealer; heirs or personal representative; rights and remedies.</catchline><para>(1) In the event of the death or incapacity of a dealer or the majority stockholder of a corporation operating as a dealer, the supplier shall, at the option of the heirs at law if the dealer or majority stockholder died intestate or the personal representative under the terms of the deceased dealer's or majority stockholder's last will and testament if the dealer or majority stockholder died testate, repurchase the inventory and specialized repair tools from the estate as provided in section 87-707 as if the supplier had terminated the dealer agreement. The heirs or personal representative shall have twelve months from the date of the death of the dealer or majority stockholder to exercise the option. Nothing in this section shall require the repurchase if the heirs or personal representative and the supplier enter into a new dealer agreement. Nothing in this section shall prevent the application of any provisions of the dealer agreement pertaining to death of the dealer or succession to the extent such provisions are not inconsistent with this section. Nothing in this section shall entitle an heir, devisee, or personal representative of a deceased dealer or majority stockholder to continue to operate the dealership without the consent of the supplier.</para><para>(2) This section shall be supplemental to any provisions of the dealer agreement covering the return of inventory or specialized repair tools which provide the dealer with greater protection. The heirs or personal representative may pursue either the contract remedy or the remedy provided in this section, and an election to pursue the contract remedy shall not bar pursuit of the remedy provided in this section as to inventory or tools not affected by the contract remedy. Nothing in this section shall preclude a price for the inventory or tools which is greater than the total provided for in section 87-707.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 123, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>