<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-134"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>87-134</statuteno><catchline>Registration; assignment; change of
name; other recordings.</catchline><para>(1) Any mark and its registration
under the Trademark Registration Act is assignable with the goodwill of the
business in which the mark is used or with that part of the goodwill of the
business connected with the use of and symbolized by the mark. Assignment
shall be by instruments in writing duly executed and may be recorded with
the secretary upon the payment of the recording fee payable to the secretary
who, upon recording of the assignment, shall issue in the name of the assignee
a new certificate for the remainder of the term of the registration or of
the last renewal thereof. An assignment of any registration under the Trademark
Registration Act is void as against any subsequent purchaser for valuable
consideration without notice unless it is recorded with the secretary within
three months after the date of the assignment or prior to such subsequent
purchase.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Any
registrant or applicant effecting a change of the name of the person to whom
the mark was issued or for whom an application was filed or a change of address or state of incorporation or organization may
record a certificate of such change with
the secretary upon the payment of the recording fee. A registrant or an applicant may be required to submit documented
proof of its name change at the discretion of the secretary.</para>
<para>(b) The secretary may issue
in the name of the assignee a certificate of registration of an assigned application.
The secretary may issue in the name of the assignee a new certificate of registration
for the remainder of the term of the registration or last renewal of the registration.</para>
<para>(3) Other instruments which relate to a mark registered or application
pending pursuant to the act, such as licenses, security interests, or mortgages,
may be recorded in the discretion of the secretary if the instrument is in
writing and duly executed.</para>
<para>(4) Acknowledgment shall be prima facie evidence of the execution of
an assignment or other instrument and, when recorded by the secretary, the
record shall be prima facie evidence of execution.</para>
<para>(5) A photocopy of any instrument referred to in this section shall
be accepted for recording if it is certified by any of the parties to the
instrument, or their successors, to be a true and correct copy of the original.</para>
<para>(6) In a registration
that resulted from an application that was filed before the effective date
of a change to the Trademark Registration Act or any rules or regulations
adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act, the registrant may be allowed
to file an amendment to the registration in order to comply with the current
requirements of the act and the rules and regulations. The registrant shall
pay a recording fee for such amendment.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 626, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB886, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>