<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id657"><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-1305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>87-1305</statuteno><catchline>Covered online service; personal data; collection and use.</catchline><para>(1) A covered online service shall only collect and use the minimum amount of a covered minor's personal data necessary to provide the specific elements of an online service with which the covered minor has knowingly engaged. Such personal data shall not be used for reasons other than those for which it was collected.</para><para>(2) A covered online service shall not be required to collect the personal data of a user to comply with the Age-Appropriate Online Design Code Act. A covered online service that collects personal data of a user for age verification cannot use such personal data for other purposes and shall delete such personal data after use for age verification.</para><para>(3) A covered online service shall only retain the personal data of a covered minor as long as necessary to provide the specific elements of an online service with which the covered minor has knowingly engaged.</para><para>(4) A covered online service shall not facilitate targeted advertising to a covered minor.</para><para>(5) A covered online service shall provide an obvious sign to a covered minor when precise geolocation information is being collected or used.</para><para>(6) The use of notifications and push alerts to a covered minor is prohibited between the hours of 10 p.m. and 6 a.m. and between the hours of 8 a.m. and 4 p.m. on week days during the school year in the covered minor's local time zone.</para><para>(7) A covered online service shall not profile a covered minor unless profiling is necessary to provide a covered online service requested by such covered minor, and only with respect to the aspects of the covered online service with which the covered minor is actively and knowingly engaged.</para><para>(8) A covered online service shall ensure that the default settings for the protections required pursuant to this section are set at the highest protection available for the safety of the covered minor.</para><para>(9) If a covered online service allows parental monitoring, the covered online service shall provide an obvious signal to a covered minor when such minor is being monitored.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB504, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>