<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id185"><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-1201"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>87-1201</statuteno><catchline>Cybersecurity event; liability of private entity.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Cybersecurity event means an event resulting in unauthorized access to, or disruption or misuse of, an information system or nonpublic information stored on an information system;</para><para>(b) Information system means:</para><para>(i) A discrete set of electronic information resources organized for the collection, processing, maintenance, use, sharing, dissemination, or disposition of electronic nonpublic information; or</para><para>(ii) A specialized system, including an industrial or process control system, a telephone switching and private branch exchange system, and an environmental control system;</para><para>(c) Nonpublic information means information that is not publicly available and concerns a person that, because of a name, number, personal mark, or other identifier, can be used to identify such person, in combination with the following:</para><para>(i) A social security number;</para><para>(ii) A driver's license number or state identification card number;</para><para>(iii) A financial account number or credit or debit card number;</para><para>(iv) A security code, access code, or password that would permit access to such person's financial accounts; or</para><para>(v) Any biometric record;</para><para>(d) Private entity means a corporation, religious or charitable organization, association, partnership, limited liability company, limited liability partnership, or other private business entity, whether organized for-profit or not-for-profit; and</para><para>(e) Publicly available information means information that is lawfully made available through federal, state, or local government records or information that a private entity has a reasonable basis to believe is lawfully made available to the general public.</para><para>(2) A private entity shall not be liable in a class action resulting from a cybersecurity event unless the cybersecurity event was caused by willful, wanton, or gross negligence on the part of the private entity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB241, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate></effectivedate>September 3, 2025</source></law>
</legaldoc>