<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id181"><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-1303"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>87-1303</statuteno><catchline>Act; applicability.</catchline><para>(1) The Age-Appropriate Online Design Code Act does not apply to:</para><para>(a) A federal, state, tribal, or local government entity in the ordinary course of its operations;</para><para>(b) Personal data subject to a statute or regulation that is controlled by a covered online service that is required to comply with:</para><para>(i) Title V of the federal Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act;</para><para>(ii) The federal Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health Act; or</para><para>(iii) Regulations promulgated under section 264 of the federal Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996; and</para><para>(c) Information, including, but not limited to, personal data, collected as part of a clinical trial subject to the federal policy for the protection of human subjects in accordance with:</para><para>(i) Good clinical practice guidelines issued by the International Council for Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Pharmaceuticals for Human Use; or</para><para>(ii) Human subject protection requirements of the federal Food and Drug Administration.</para><para>(2) The requirements of the Age-Appropriate Online Design Code Act are in addition to and shall not limit or restrict in any way the application of other laws, including, but not limited to, statutes, rules and regulations, and the common law of Nebraska.</para><para>(3) In the event of a conflict between the Age-Appropriate Online Design Code Act and one or more other laws, the law that affords the greatest protection from harm to minors shall control.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB504, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>