<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id532"><amendatorysection chaptername="Trade Practices" statutenumber="87-1304"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>87-1304</statuteno><catchline>Covered online service; provide safeguards for minors.</catchline><para>(1) A covered online service shall provide each covered minor with accessible and easy-to-use tools that accomplish the following with respect to covered design features:</para><para>(a) Limit the ability of other users or visitors to communicate with the covered minor;</para><para>(b) Prevent other individuals from viewing the personal data of the covered minor;</para><para>(c) Control the operation of all design features, including, but not limited to, all covered design features, that are unnecessary in order to provide the covered online service by allowing a covered minor to opt out of the use of all unnecessary covered design features or categories of unnecessary covered design features;</para><para>(d) Control personalized recommendation systems by allowing a covered minor to opt in to a chronological feed or by preventing categories of content from being recommended;</para><para>(e) Control the use of in-game purchases or other transactions by allowing a covered minor to opt out of all such purchases and transactions or to place limits on such purchases and transactions; and</para><para>(f) Restrict the sharing of the precise geolocation information of the covered minor and provide notice regarding tracking of the covered minor's precise geolocation information.</para><para>(2) A covered online service shall provide a covered minor with accessible and easy-to-use options to limit the amount of time the covered minor spends on the covered online service.</para><para>(3) A covered online service shall establish default settings for the safeguards required by subsection (1) of this section at the option or level that provides the highest protection available for the safety of the covered minor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB504, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>