<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00" statutenumber="83-1,114"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,114</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board; deferment of parole; grounds.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever the board considers the release of a committed offender who is eligible for release on parole, it shall order his or her release unless it is of the opinion that his or her release should be deferred because:</para><para id="id00">(a) There is a substantial risk that he or she will not conform to the conditions of parole;</para><para id="id00">(b) His or her release would depreciate the seriousness of his or her crime or promote disrespect for law;</para><para id="id00">(c) His or her release would have a substantially adverse effect on institutional discipline; or</para><para id="id00">(d) His or her continued correctional treatment, medical care, or vocational or other training in the facility will substantially enhance his or her capacity to lead a law-abiding life when released at a later date.</para><para id="id00">(2) In making its determination regarding a committed offender's release on parole, the board shall give consideration to the decision guidelines as set forth in its rules and regulations and shall take into account each of the following factors:</para><para id="id00">(a) The adequacy of the offender's parole plan, including sufficiency of residence, employment history, and employability;</para><para id="id00">(b) The offender's prior criminal record, including the nature and circumstances, dates, and frequency of previous offenses;</para><para id="id00">(c) The offender's institutional behavior; </para><para>(d) The offender's previous experience on parole and how recent such experience is;</para><para id="id00">(e) Whether the offender has completed a risk and needs assessment completed pursuant to section 83-192; and</para><para>(f) Any testimony or written statement by a victim as provided in section 81-1848.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 45, p. 3095; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB50, &#167; 51. </para></source><annotation><para>The expectancy of release created by this section is not entitled to constitutional protection. Greenholtz v. Inmates of Nebraska Penal &amp; Correctional Complex, 442 U.S. 1 (1979).</para><para>The procedure in use under this section, which requires at least one hearing per year for each inmate, provides all necessary due process with respect to the discretionary parole decision. Greenholtz v. Inmates of Nebraska Penal &amp; Correctional Complex, 442 U.S. 1 (1979).</para><para>The argument that a facially neutral parole policy has a racially disproportionate impact, and is unconstitutional, is without merit. Inmates of Nebraska Penal &amp; Correctional Complex v. Greenholtz, 436 F.Supp. 432 (D. Neb. 1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>