<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00" statutenumber="83-1,122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,122</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Parolee; violation of parole; action of Board of Parole.</catchline><para>(1) If the board finds that the parolee has engaged in criminal conduct, the board may order revocation of the parolee's parole.</para><para>(2) If the board finds that the parolee did violate a condition of parole but is of the opinion that revocation of parole is not appropriate, the board may order that:</para><para>(a) The parolee receive a reprimand and warning;</para><para>(b) Parole supervision and reporting be intensified;</para><para>(c) Good time granted pursuant to section 83-1,108 be forfeited or withheld;</para><para>(d) The parolee serve a custodial sanction of up to thirty days in a correctional facility or a contract facility as defined in section 83-1,119; or</para><para>(e) The parolee be required to conform to one or more additional conditions of parole which may be imposed in accordance with the Nebraska Treatment and Corrections Act.</para><para>(3) Cumulative custodial sanctions in a correctional facility or a contract facility under this section and section 83-1,119 shall not exceed sixty days. If a parolee has previously received sixty days of cumulative custodial sanctions before the current violation, the board shall either order revocation of the parolee's parole or one or more of the other sanctions described in subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(4) Time spent in custodial sanctions under this section and section 83-1,119 shall be credited to the parolee's sentence.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 53, p. 3100; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 816, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 371, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 38. </para><effectivedate>April 20, 2016</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>