<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id840"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1,111.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,111.01</statuteno><catchline>Qualified offender; streamlined parole contract; effect on release.</catchline><para>(1) A qualified offender serving a sentence imposed prior to September 2, 2023, who has not yet received a review from the board shall, at the review, enter into a streamlined parole contract under this section.</para><para>(2) A qualified offender serving a sentence imposed on or after September 2, 2023, shall, at the qualified offender's first review from the board, enter into a streamlined parole contract under this section.</para><para>(3) Under a streamlined parole contract, a qualified offender shall be released on parole on the qualified offender's parole eligibility date, without a hearing before the board, if:</para><para>(a) In the twenty-four-month period prior to the eligibility date, the qualified offender has not committed a Class I offense under the department's disciplinary code; and</para><para>(b) The qualified offender has completed all diagnostic evaluations provided by the department and any programming or treatment required by the department for substance abuse, sex offenses, and violence reduction.</para><para>(4) If a qualified offender does not meet the requirements of subsection (3) of this section, the board shall consider the offender's parole eligibility as provided for nonqualified offenders under section 83-1,111.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Qualified offender means a committed offender who is serving an indeterminate sentence under which the committed offender may become eligible for parole and who is not serving a sentence for a violent felony;</para><para>(b) Serious bodily injury has the same meaning as in section 28-109;</para><para>(c) Sexual contact and sexual penetration have the same meanings as in section 28-318; and</para><para>(d) Violent felony means an offense which is a Class IIIA felony or higher which:</para><para>(i) Includes, as an element of the offense:</para><para>(A) Sexual contact or sexual penetration;</para><para>(B) The threat to inflict serious bodily injury or death on another person, the infliction of serious bodily injury on another person, or causing the death of another person; or</para><para>(C) The use of physical force against another person; or</para><para>(ii) Consists of attempt, conspiracy, being an accessory to, or aiding and abetting a felony with any of the offenses described in subdivision (5)(d)(i) of this section as the underlying offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB50, &#167; 50. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>