<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-954"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-954</statuteno><catchline>Medium-minimum correctional facilities; where located; how designed; cost; duties of Department of Correctional Services.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Correctional Services is hereby authorized to revise program statements, develop physical plans, and initiate construction for two medium-minimum facilities with a total project cost not to exceed nine million dollars.</para><para>The revised program statements and physical plans shall provide for one medium-minimum security correctional facility to be located in Lancaster County and an additional facility to be located in Douglas County.</para><para>(2) The correctional facility to be located in Lancaster County may be built at the present site of the men's reformatory in Lincoln, Nebraska, and shall be designed to house two hundred persons. The ancillary services shall be designed to provide for future expansion to serve an additional fifty persons. Total project cost for the medium-minimum correctional facility to be located in Lancaster County shall not exceed five million dollars. Construction shall begin not later than July 1, 1976.</para><para>(3) The medium-minimum correctional facility to be located in Douglas County shall be designed to house one hundred seventy-five persons. Ancillary services shall be designed to provide for future expansion to serve an additional twenty-five persons. Total project cost for the medium-minimum correctional facility to be located in Douglas County shall not exceed four million dollars. It is the intent of the Legislature that construction begin not later than January 1, 1977.</para><para>(4) The Department of Correctional Services shall develop a program statement and preliminary plans for a maximum security facility designed to accommodate not more than two hundred fifty persons. The program statement shall include an assessment of the current facility's location and structure, and a determination as to the adequacy of such facility when compared to complete replacement and relocation.</para><para>(5) In planning the construction of these new correctional facilities, consideration shall be given to providing separate, noncell-type housing units. Each correctional facility shall also include adequate space for administrative offices, kitchen, and dining facilities, and other space necessary for the efficient operation of the facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 417, &#167; 38. </para></source></law></legaldoc>