<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-106"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>83-106</statuteno><catchline>Inpatient adolescent psychiatric unit; needs assessment and cost analysis; contract; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health and Human Services shall contract for the completion of a needs assessment and cost analysis for the establishment of an inpatient adolescent psychiatric unit housed within the Lincoln Regional Center. The department shall contract with an outside consultant with expertise in needs assessment and cost analysis of health care facilities within sixty days after May 26, 2021, for the purpose of conducting such assessment and analysis.</para><para>(2) The department shall submit a report electronically to the Health and Human Services Committee of the Legislature and the Clerk of the Legislature on or before December 1, 2021. Such report shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) A needs assessment, including the number of adolescents expected to use such inpatient adolescent psychiatric unit;</para><para>(b) The cost of opening an existing facility at the Lincoln Regional Center for use as an inpatient adolescent psychiatric unit;</para><para>(c) The cost of reopening the facility at the Lincoln Regional Center, including the costs for necessary construction, upgrades, or repairs;</para><para>(d) Annual operating costs of such unit, including, but not limited to, any federal funds available to operate the unit in addition to General Fund appropriations; and</para><para>(e) Cost savings realized by moving adolescents from out-of-state institutions back to Nebraska for treatment at such unit.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, adolescent means a person under the jurisdiction of the juvenile court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1140, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB428, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>May 26, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>