<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00" statutenumber="83-962"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>83-962</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Correctional system overcrowding emergency; Governor; declaration; when; effect.</catchline><para>(1) Until July 1, 2020, the Governor may declare a correctional system overcrowding emergency whenever the director certifies that the department's inmate population is over one hundred forty percent of design capacity. Beginning July 1, 2020, a correctional system overcrowding emergency shall exist whenever the director certifies that the department's inmate population is over one hundred forty percent of design capacity. The director shall so certify within thirty days after the date on which the population first exceeds one hundred forty percent of design capacity.</para><para>(2) During a correctional system overcrowding emergency, the board shall immediately consider or reconsider committed offenders eligible for parole who have not been released on parole.</para><para>(3) Upon such consideration or reconsideration, and for all other consideration of committed offenders eligible for parole while the correctional system overcrowding emergency is in effect, the board shall order the release of each committed offender unless it is of the opinion that such release should be deferred because:</para><para>(a) The board has determined that it is more likely than not that the committed offender will not conform to the conditions of parole;</para><para>(b) The board has determined that release of the committed offender would have a very significant and quantifiable effect on institutional discipline; or</para><para>(c) The board has determined that there is a very substantial risk that the committed offender will commit a violent act against a person.</para><para>(4) In making the determination regarding the risk that a committed offender will not conform to the conditions of parole, the board shall take into account the factors set forth in subsection (2) of section 83-1,114.</para><para>(5) The board shall continue granting parole to offenders under this section until the director certifies that the population is at operational capacity. The director shall so certify within thirty days after the date on which the population first reaches operational capacity.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 38. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>