<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-182" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>83-182</statuteno><catchline>Director; establish programs; educational services and educational programming; State Department of Education; State Board of Education; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) The director shall establish appropriate programs for each facility designed as far as practical to prepare and assist each person committed to the department to assume his or her responsibilities as a useful citizen. In developing such programs, the director shall seek to make available to each person capable of benefiting therefrom academic or vocational training, participation in productive work, religious and recreational activities, and such therapeutic measures as are practicable. No person shall be ordered or compelled to participate in religious activities.</para><para>(2)(a) The director shall offer and make available educational services and educational programming to any person committed to the department who is under twenty-one years of age and who has not previously earned a high school diploma or diploma of high school equivalency. The director shall ensure special education services are provided as required by state and federal law. Nothing in this subsection requires participation by any person committed to the department in educational services or educational programming except to the extent necessary to provide services required by law.</para><para>(b) Such educational services shall be substantially similar to the minimum standards as determined by the State Department of Education, including a minimum curriculum that includes language arts, social science, science, and mathematics, and may include other subjects including, but not limited to, vocational education, computer education, arts, and physical fitness. Such programs may be offered by the department or through partnerships with educational institutions.</para><para>(3) The State Board of Education may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section and to ensure the educational services and educational programming meet any applicable educational requirements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 13, p. 3079; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 31, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB1216, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Evidence held insufficient to show denial of property rights afforded under sections 83-182 and 83-183. Journey v. Vitek, 685 F.2d 239 (8th Cir. 1982).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>