<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1,125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,125</statuteno><catchline>Warrant or detainer; administrator; board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If a warrant or detainer is placed against a committed offender by a court, parole agency, or other authority of this or any other jurisdiction, the administrator shall inquire before such offender becomes eligible for parole whether the authority concerned intends to execute or withdraw the warrant or detainer when the offender is released.</para><para>(2) If the authority notifies the administrator that it intends to execute the warrant or detainer when the offender is released, the administrator shall advise the authority concerned of the sentence under which the offender is held, the time of parole eligibility, any decision of the board relating to the offender, and the nature of the offender's adjustment during imprisonment and shall give reasonable notice to such authority of the offender's release date.</para><para>(3) The board may parole an offender who is eligible for release to a warrant or detainer. If an offender is paroled to such a warrant or detainer, the board may provide, as a condition of release, that if the charge or charges on which the warrant or detainer is based are dismissed, or are satisfied after conviction and sentence, prior to the expiration of the offender's parole term, the authority to whose warrant or detainer the offender is released shall return the offender to serve the remainder of the parole term or such part as the board may determine.</para><para>(4) If a person paroled to a warrant or detainer is thereafter sentenced and placed on probation, or released on parole in another jurisdiction, prior to the expiration of the parole term less good time in this state, the board may permit the person to serve the remainder of the parole term or such part as the board may determine concurrently with the person's new probation or parole term. Such concurrent terms may be served in either of the two jurisdictions, and supervision shall be administered in accordance with the Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 56, p. 3101; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 816, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 46, &#167; 27. </para><note>Laws 2003, LB 46, section 51, provided this section became operative "when thirty-five states have adopted the Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision". By June 2002, the compact had reached this threshold. (see www.interstatecompact.org) LB 46 became effective May 24, 2003.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interstate Compact for Adult Offender Supervision,</emphasis> see section 29-2639.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>