
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id765" statutenumber="83-4,124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-4,124</statuteno><catchline id="id768">Legislative intent; Jail Standards Board; created; administration by Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice; members; qualifications; terms; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) It is hereby declared to be the policy of the State of Nebraska that all criminal detention facilities in this state shall conform to certain minimum standards of construction, maintenance, and operation and that all juvenile detention facilities and staff secure juvenile facilities in this state shall conform to certain minimum standards relating to the operation and physical structure of such facilities and the care of, programs for, and discipline of juveniles at such facilities.</para><para>(2) To further such policy, the Jail Standards Board is hereby created. For administrative and budgetary purposes such board shall be within the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice. The board shall consist of the Director of Correctional Services or, if the Director of Correctional Services chooses not to serve on the board, a person appointed by the director to serve in lieu of the director, the State Fire Marshal or his or her designee, and ten appointive members, three of whom shall be from each of the three congressional districts, to be appointed by the Governor. The appointive members of the board shall be appointed from recommendation lists containing at least three names submitted by the Nebraska Association of County Officials, the Nebraska County Sheriffs Association, the Nebraska State Bar Association, and the Police Officers Association of Nebraska. The appointive members of the board shall consist of: (a) Two county commissioners or supervisors; (b) one county sheriff; (c) one municipal police chief; (d) one member of the Nebraska State Bar Association; (e) two lay people; (f) one person who at the time of his or her appointment is serving as an administrator responsible for the operation and maintenance of a juvenile detention facility; (g) one person who at the time of his or her appointment is serving as an administrator responsible for the operation and maintenance of a staff secure juvenile facility; and (h) one person who at the time of his or her appointment is serving as an administrator or jailer responsible for the operation and maintenance of a criminal detention facility having an average daily population of greater than fifty persons.</para><para>(3) The terms of office for all members initially appointed shall be three years. Upon completion of the initial term of the board, the Governor shall appoint one member from each congressional district for a term of one year, one member from each congressional district for a term of two years, and one member from each congressional district for a term of three years. Succeeding appointees shall be representative of the same congressional district and shall be appointed for terms of three years. An appointee to a vacancy occurring from an unexpired term shall serve out the term of his or her predecessor. Members whose terms have expired shall continue to serve until their successors have been appointed. The member authorized by Laws 2013, LB561, shall be appointed by the Governor within ninety days after May 30, 2013.</para><para>(4) The members of the board shall serve without compensation, but they shall be reimbursed for expenses while engaged in the performance of their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 417, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 212, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 700, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 83-945; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 208; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 328, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 461, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 925, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 93, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 131. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>