
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="STATE INSTITUTIONS" statutenumber="83-966"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-966</statuteno><catchline>Lethal injection; participation of professional; how treated under other law.</catchline><para>Notwithstanding any other provision of law:</para><para>(1) Any prescription, preparation, compounding, dispensing, obtaining, or administration of the substances deemed necessary to perform a lethal injection shall not constitute the practice of medicine or any other profession relating to health care which is subject by law to regulation, licensure, or certification;</para><para>(2) A pharmacist or pharmaceutical supplier may dispense the designated substances, without a prescription, to the Director of Correctional Services or the director's designee upon production of a written request from the director for the designated substances necessary to conduct an execution;</para><para>(3) Obtaining, preparing, compounding, dispensing, and administering the substance or substances designated by the execution protocol does not violate the Uniform Controlled Substances Act or sections 71-2501 to 71-2512; and</para><para>(4) If a person who is a member of the execution team is licensed by a board or department, the licensing board or department shall not censure, reprimand, suspend, revoke, or take any other disciplinary action against that person's license as a result of that person's participation in a court-ordered execution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB36, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 35; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The repeal of section 83-966 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 35, is not effective because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Controlled Substances Act,</emphasis> see section 28-401.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>