<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00" statutenumber="83-1,100"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,100</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Division of Parole Supervision; created; duties; parole officer compensation.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Division of Parole Supervision within the department. The employees of the division shall consist of the Director of Supervision and Services, the field parole service officers, and all other division staff. The division shall be responsible for the following:</para><para>(a) The administration of parole services in the community, including administration of the Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act;</para><para>(b) The maintenance of all records and files associated with the Board of Parole;</para><para>(c) The daily supervision and training of staff members of the division, including training regarding evidence-based practices in supervision pursuant to section 83-1,100.02; and</para><para>(d) The assessment, evaluation, and supervision of individuals who are subject to parole supervision, including lifetime community supervision pursuant to section 83-174.03.</para><para>(2) Parole officers shall be compensated with salaries substantially equal to other state employees who have similar responsibilities, including employees of the Office of Probation Administration. This subsection shall apply only to field parole service officers and support staff and shall not apply to the Director of Supervision and Services or any other management-level position.</para><para>(3) This section does not prohibit the division from maintaining daily records and files associated with the Board of Pardons.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 31, p. 3088; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 13, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 677, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB598, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 30. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreferences><para><emphasis>Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act,</emphasis> see section 47-1101.</para></crossreferences></law>
</legaldoc>