<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00" statutenumber="83-1,110.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,110.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">See note regarding referendum petition following the source at the end of the section. Medical parole; eligibility; conditions; term.</catchline><para>(1) A committed offender who is otherwise eligible for parole, who is not under sentence of life imprisonment, and who because of an existing medical or physical condition is determined by the department to be terminally ill or permanently incapacitated may be considered for medical parole by the board. A committed offender may be eligible for medical parole in addition to any other parole. The department shall identify committed offenders who may be eligible for medical parole based upon their medical records.</para><para>(2) The board shall decide to grant medical parole only after a review of the medical, institutional, and criminal records of the committed offender and such additional medical evidence from board-ordered examinations or investigations as the board in its discretion determines to be necessary. The decision to grant medical parole and to establish conditions of release on medical parole in addition to the conditions stated in subsection (3) of this section is within the sole discretion of the board.</para><para>(3) As conditions of release on medical parole, the board shall require that the committed offender agree to placement for medical treatment and that he or she be placed for a definite or indefinite period of time in a hospital, a hospice, or another housing accommodation suitable to his or her medical condition, including, but not limited to, his or her family's home, as specified by the board.</para><para>(4) The parole term of a medical parolee shall be for the remainder of his or her sentence as reduced by any adjustment for good conduct pursuant to the Nebraska Treatment and Corrections Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 32. </para><note>Section 83-1,110.02 was amended by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 32. According to Article III, section 3, of the Constitution of Nebraska, the provisions of LB 268 have been suspended due to the certification by the Secretary of State of sufficient signatures on referendum petitions to suspend the taking effect of such act until the same has been approved by the electors of the state. The question will be submitted to the voters at the November 2016 general election. The prior version of section 83-1,110.02 is found in the 2014 Reissue of Volume 5A of the Revised Statutes of Nebraska.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>