<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id773">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id775" statutenumber="83-4,125"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>83-4,125</statuteno><catchline id="id778">Detention and staff secure juvenile facilities,
defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 83-4,124 to
83-4,134:</para>
<para>(1) Criminal detention facility means any
institution operated by a political subdivision or a combination of political
subdivisions for the careful keeping or rehabilitative needs of adult or juvenile
criminal offenders or those persons being detained while awaiting disposition
of charges against them. Criminal detention facility does not
include any institution operated by the Department of Correctional Services.
Criminal detention facilities shall be classified as follows:</para>
<para>(a) Type I Facilities means criminal
detention facilities used for the detention of persons for not more than twenty-four
hours, excluding nonjudicial days;</para>
<para>(b) Type II Facilities means criminal
detention facilities used for the detention of persons for not more than ninety-six
hours, excluding nonjudicial days; and</para>
<para>(c) Type III Facilities means criminal
detention facilities used for the detention of persons beyond ninety-six hours;</para>
<para>(2) Juvenile detention facility means an
institution operated by a political subdivision or political subdivisions
for the secure detention and treatment of persons younger than eighteen years
of age, including persons under the jurisdiction of a juvenile court, who
are serving a sentence pursuant to a conviction in a county or district court
or who are detained while waiting disposition of charges against them. Juvenile
detention facility does not include any institution
operated by the department;
and</para>
<para>(3) Staff
secure juvenile facility means a juvenile residential facility operated by
a political subdivision (a) which does not include construction designed to
physically restrict the movements and activities of juveniles who are in custody
in the facility, (b) in which physical restriction of movement or activity
of juveniles is provided solely through staff, (c) which may establish reasonable
rules restricting ingress to and egress from the facility, and (d) in which
the movements and activities of individual juvenile residents may, for treatment
purposes, be restricted or subject to control through the use of intensive
staff supervision. Staff secure juvenile facility does not include any institution
operated by the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 417, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 212, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 83-946; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 461, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1167, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 760, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 65.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>