<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id811">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id813" statutenumber="83-4,133"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>83-4,133</statuteno><catchline id="id816">Detention and staff secure juvenile facility;
governing body; failure to take corrective action; petition by Jail Standards
Board; hearing; order; appeal.</catchline><para>If the governing
body of the juvenile detention facility, criminal detention facility, or staff secure juvenile facility fails
to initiate corrective action within six months after the receipt of such
inspection report, fails to correct the disclosed conditions, or fails to
close the criminal detention facility, juvenile detention facility, or staff secure juvenile facility or
the objectionable portion thereof, the Jail Standards Board may petition the
district court within the judicial district in which such facility is located
to close the facility. Such petition shall include the inspection report regarding
such facility. The local governing body shall then have thirty days to respond
to such petition and shall serve a copy of the response on the Jail Standards
Board by certified mail, return receipt requested. Thereafter, a hearing shall
be held on the petition before the district court, and an order shall be rendered
by such court which either:</para>
<para>(1) Dismisses the petition of the Jail Standards Board;</para>
<para>(2) Directs that corrective action be initiated in some form
by the local governing body of the facility in question; or</para>
<para>(3) Directs that the facility be closed. An appeal from the
decision of the district court may be taken to the Court of Appeals.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 417, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 212, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 83-952; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 154; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 695, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB218, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB561, &#167; 69.</para><effectivedate>May 30, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>