<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-4,164"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-4,164</statuteno><catchline>Peer review and quality assurance program.</catchline><para>The peer review and quality assurance program developed and implemented by the medical director shall provide for the ongoing review of the quality of health care services. This peer review and quality assurance program shall be carried out by a peer review and quality assurance panel comprised of medical doctors providing health care services and such other health care staff as the department designates. The peer review and quality assurance program shall be conducted through regular periodic meetings of the peer review and quality assurance panel for the purpose of examining issues pertaining to the quality of health care services. The peer review and quality assurance panel shall also conduct a regular review of selected cases arising in order to identify, critique, and correct errors in the practices and procedures of the health care staff. The peer review and quality assurance panel shall also review (1) all cases in which there has been a death of an inmate and (2) all cases in which there have been deviations from the approved medical treatment protocols of the department. The medical director shall develop and implement a procedure for the direct feedback to the peer review and quality assurance panel of inmate complaints and other information from inmates pertaining to health care services. A permanent record of the meetings and deliberations of the peer review and quality assurance panel shall be maintained, but the records and all other evidence pertaining directly to the deliberations of the peer review and quality assurance panel are not subject to discovery in any civil action arising out of the health care services provided by or on behalf of the department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 154, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>