<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00"  statutenumber="83-1,114"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,114</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board; deferment of parole; grounds.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Whenever the board considers the release of a committed offender who is eligible for release on parole, it shall order his or her release unless it is of the opinion that his or her release should be deferred because:</para><para id="id00">(a) There is a substantial risk that he or she will not conform to the conditions of parole;</para><para id="id00">(b) His or her release would depreciate the seriousness of his or her crime or promote disrespect for law;</para><para id="id00">(c) His or her release would have a substantially adverse effect on institutional discipline; or</para><para id="id00">(d) His or her continued correctional treatment, medical care, or vocational or other training in the facility will substantially enhance his or her capacity to lead a law-abiding life when released at a later date.</para><para id="id00">(2) In making its determination regarding a committed offender's release on parole, the board shall give consideration to its decision guidelines as set forth in its rules and regulations and shall take into account each of the following factors:</para><para id="id00">(a) The offender's personality, including his or her maturity, stability, and sense of responsibility and any apparent development in his or her personality which may promote or hinder his or her conformity to law;</para><para id="id00">(b) The adequacy of the offender's parole plan;</para><para id="id00">(c) The offender's ability and readiness to assume obligations and undertake responsibilities;</para><para id="id00">(d) The offender's intelligence and training;</para><para id="id00">(e) The offender's family status and whether he or she has relatives who display an interest in him or her or whether he or she has other close and constructive associations in the community;</para><para id="id00">(f) The offender's employment history, his or her occupational skills, and the stability of his or her past employment;</para><para id="id00">(g) The type of residence, neighborhood, or community in which the offender plans to live;</para><para id="id00">(h) The offender's past use of narcotics or past habitual and excessive use of alcohol;</para><para id="id00">(i) The offender's mental or physical makeup, including any disability or handicap which may affect his or her conformity to law;</para><para id="id00">(j) The offender's prior criminal record, including the nature and circumstances, dates, and frequency of previous offenses;</para><para id="id00">(k) The offender's attitude toward law and authority;</para><para id="id00">(l) The offender's conduct in the facility, including particularly whether he or she has taken advantage of the opportunities for self-improvement, whether he or she has been punished for misconduct within six months prior to his or her hearing or reconsideration for parole release, whether any reductions of term have been forfeited, and whether such reductions have been restored at the time of hearing or reconsideration;</para><para id="id00">(m) The offender's behavior and attitude during any previous experience of probation or parole and how recent such experience is; </para><para id="id00">(n) The risk and needs assessment completed pursuant to section 83-192; and</para><para id="id00">(o) Any other factors the board determines to be relevant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 45, p. 3095; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 43. </para></source><annotation><para>The expectancy of release created by this section is not entitled to constitutional protection. Greenholtz v. Inmates of Nebraska Penal &amp; Correctional Complex, 442 U.S. 1 (1979).</para><para>The procedure in use under this section, which requires at least one hearing per year for each inmate, provides all necessary due process with respect to the discretionary parole decision. Greenholtz v. Inmates of Nebraska Penal &amp; Correctional Complex, 442 U.S. 1 (1979).</para><para>The argument that a facially neutral parole policy has a racially disproportionate impact, and is unconstitutional, is without merit. Inmates of Nebraska Penal &amp; Correctional Complex v. Greenholtz, 436 F.Supp. 432 (D. Neb. 1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>