<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id104" statutenumber="83-1,119"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,119</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Parolee; violation of parole; parole officer; administrative sanction; report to Board of Parole; action of board.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Absconding parole supervision means a parolee has purposely avoided supervision for a period of at least two weeks and reasonable efforts by a parole officer and staff to locate the parolee in person have proven unsuccessful;</para><para>(b) Administrative sanction means additional parole requirements imposed upon a parolee by his or her parole officer, with the full knowledge and consent of the parolee, designed to hold the parolee accountable for substance abuse or technical violations of conditions of parole, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(i) Counseling or reprimand by the Division of Parole Supervision;</para><para>(ii) Increased supervision contact requirements;</para><para>(iii) Increased substance abuse testing;</para><para>(iv) Referral for substance abuse or mental health evaluation or other specialized assessment, counseling, or treatment;</para><para>(v) Imposition of a designated curfew for a period to be determined by the division; and</para><para>(vi) Travel restrictions to stay within his or her county of residence or employment unless otherwise permitted by the division;</para><para>(c) Contract facility means a county jail that contracts with the department to house parolees or other offenders under the jurisdiction of the department;</para><para>(d) Substance abuse violation means a parolee's activities or behaviors associated with the use of chemical substances or related treatment services resulting in a violation of an original condition of parole, including:</para><para>(i) Positive breath test for the consumption of alcohol if the parolee is required to refrain from alcohol consumption;</para><para>(ii) Positive urinalysis for the illegal use of drugs;</para><para>(iii) Failure to report for alcohol testing or drug testing; and</para><para>(iv) Failure to appear for or complete substance abuse or mental health treatment evaluations or inpatient or outpatient treatment; and</para><para>(e) Technical violation means a parolee's activities or behaviors which create the opportunity for re-offending or diminish the effectiveness of parole supervision resulting in a violation of an original condition of parole and includes:</para><para>(i) Moving traffic violations;</para><para>(ii) Failure to report to his or her parole officer;</para><para>(iii) Leaving the state without the permission of the Board of Parole;</para><para>(iv) Failure to work regularly or attend training or school;</para><para>(v) Failure to notify his or her parole officer of change of address or employment;</para><para>(vi) Frequenting places where controlled substances are illegally sold, used, distributed, or administered; and</para><para>(vii) Failure to pay fines, court costs, restitution, or any fees imposed pursuant to section 83-1,107.01 as directed.</para><para>Technical violation does not include absconding parole supervision.</para><para>(2) The division shall develop a matrix of rewards for compliance and positive behaviors and graduated administrative sanctions and custodial sanctions for use in responding to and deterring substance abuse violations and technical violations. A custodial sanction of thirty days in a correctional facility or a contract facility shall be designated as the most severe response to a violation in lieu of revocation.</para><para>(3) Whenever a parole officer has reasonable cause to believe that a parolee has committed or is about to commit a substance abuse violation or technical violation while on parole, but that the parolee will not attempt to leave the jurisdiction and will not place lives or property in danger, the parole officer shall either:</para><para>(a) Impose one or more administrative sanctions based upon the parolee's risk level, the severity of the violation, and the parolee's response to the violation. If administrative sanctions are to be imposed, the parolee shall acknowledge in writing the nature of the violation and agree upon the administrative sanction. The parolee has the right to decline to acknowledge the violation. If he or she declines to acknowledge the violation, the parole officer shall take action pursuant to subdivision (3)(b) of this section. A copy of the report shall be submitted to the Board of Parole; or</para><para>(b) Submit a written report to the Board of Parole, outlining the nature of the parole violation, and request the imposition of a custodial sanction of up to thirty days in a correctional facility or a contract facility. On the basis of the report and such further investigation as the board may deem appropriate, the board shall determine whether and how the parolee violated the conditions of parole and may:</para><para>(i) Dismiss the charge of violation; or</para><para>(ii) If the board finds a violation justifying a custodial sanction, issue a warrant if necessary and impose a custodial sanction of up to thirty days in a correctional facility or a contract facility.</para><para>(4) Whenever a parole officer has reasonable cause to believe that a parolee has violated or is about to violate a condition of parole by a violation other than a substance abuse violation or a technical violation and the parole officer has reasonable cause to believe that the parolee will not attempt to leave the jurisdiction and will not place lives or property in danger, the parole officer shall submit a written report to the Board of Parole which may, on the basis of such report and such further investigation as it may deem appropriate:</para><para>(a) Dismiss the charge of violation;</para><para>(b) Determine whether the parolee violated the conditions of his or her parole;</para><para>(c) Impose a custodial sanction of up to thirty days in a correctional facility or a contract facility;</para><para>(d) Revoke his or her parole in accordance with the Nebraska Treatment and Corrections Act; or</para><para>(e) Issue a warrant for the arrest of the parolee.</para><para>(5) Whenever a parole officer has reasonable cause to believe that a parolee has violated or is about to violate a condition of parole and that the parolee will attempt to leave the jurisdiction or will place lives or property in danger, the parole officer shall arrest the parolee without a warrant and call on any peace officer to assist him or her in doing so.</para><para>(6) Whenever a parolee is arrested with or without a warrant, he or she shall be detained in a local jail or other detention facility operated by the Department of Correctional Services pending completion of review of parole proceedings by the Board of Parole. Immediately after such arrest and detention, the parole officer shall notify the Board of Parole and submit a written report of the reason for such arrest. A complete investigation shall be made by the Division of Parole Supervision and submitted to the board. After prompt consideration of such written report, the board shall order the parolee's release from detention or continued confinement to await a final decision on imposition of a custodial sanction or the revocation of parole.</para><para>(7) The Board of Parole shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations necessary to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 50, p. 3099; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 524, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 396, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB907, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 45. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>