<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-102"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>83-102</statuteno><catchline>Youth rehabilitation and treatment centers; placement; programming and services provided; accreditation.</catchline><para>(1) Youth rehabilitation and treatment centers shall be operated to provide programming and services to rehabilitate and treat juveniles committed under the Nebraska Juvenile Code. Each youth rehabilitation and treatment center shall be considered a separate placement. Each youth rehabilitation and treatment center shall provide:</para><para>(a) Safe and sanitary space for sleeping, hygiene, education, programming, treatment, recreation, and visitation for each juvenile;</para><para>(b) Health care and medical services;</para><para>(c) Appropriate physical separation and segregation of juveniles based on gender;</para><para>(d) Sufficient staffing to comply with state and federal law and protect the safety and security of each juvenile;</para><para>(e) Training that is specific to the population being served at the youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(f) A facility administrator for each youth rehabilitation and treatment center who has the sole responsibility for administration of a single youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(g) An evaluation process for the development of an individualized treatment plan within fourteen days after admission to the youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(h) An age-appropriate and developmentally appropriate education program for each juvenile that can award relevant and necessary credits toward high school graduation that will be accepted by any public school district in the State of Nebraska. Juveniles committed to the youth rehabilitation and treatment centers are entitled to receive an appropriate education equivalent to educational opportunities offered within the regular settings of public school districts across the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(i) A case management and coordination process, designed to assure appropriate reintegration of the juvenile with his or her family, school, and community;</para><para>(j) Compliance with the requirements stated in Title XIX and Title IV-E of the federal Social Security Act, as such act existed on January 1, 2020, the Special Education Act, or other funding guidelines as appropriate;</para><para>(k) Research-based or evidence-based programming for all juveniles that includes a strong academic program and classes in health education, living skills, vocational training, behavior management and modification, money management, family and parent responsibilities, substance use awareness, physical education, job skills training, and job placement assistance; and</para><para>(l) Research-based or evidence-based treatment service for behavioral impairment, severe emotional disturbance, sex offender behavior, other mental health or psychiatric disorder, drug and alcohol addiction, physical or sexual abuse, and any other treatment indicated by a juvenile's individualized treatment plan.</para><para>(2) Each youth rehabilitation and treatment center shall be accredited by a nationally recognized entity that provides accreditation for juvenile facilities and shall maintain accreditation as provided in section 79-703 to provide an age-appropriate and developmentally appropriate education program.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1140, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB428, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB376, &#167; 37. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Special Education Act,</emphasis> see section 79-1110.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>