
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id521">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id523" statutenumber="83-112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-112</statuteno><catchline id="id526">Department of
Health and Human Services; collection of information; encouragement of scientific
study; investigations.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Health
and Human Services shall gather information as to the expenditures of charitable
institutions in this and other countries and regarding the best and most successful
methods of caring for persons with an
intellectual disability and persons with a mental disorder.</para>
<para>(2) The Department of Health and Human Services shall encourage
scientific investigation of the treatment of mental problems, epilepsy, and
all other diseases and causes that contribute to mental disabilities by the
medical staffs of the state medical institutions. The department shall provide
forms for statistical returns to be made by the institutions. The department
shall make an investigation of the conditions, causes, prevention, and cure
of epilepsy, intellectual disability, and
mental disorders. The department shall give special attention to the methods
of care, treatment, education, and improvement of the persons served by the
institutions under its control and shall exercise a careful supervision of
the methods to the end that, so far as practicable, the best treatment and
care known to modern science shall be given to such persons and that the best
methods of teaching, improving, and educating such persons shall be used.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 179, &#167; 28, p. 547; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7206; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6857; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 83-128; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 83-112; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 231, &#167; 22, p. 728; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 563, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 545, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1177, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 901; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB23, &#167; 49.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>