<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id352"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-191.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-191.01</statuteno><catchline>Board of Parole; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that include:</para><para>(1) Clearly defined and easily understood written mission statements and strategic plans encompassing public safety and rehabilitation. The board shall align such statements and plans with those of the department;</para><para>(2) Procedures to ensure that victims are appropriately notified and given the opportunity to provide input in the rulemaking process;</para><para>(3) A requirement that board members receive initial and ongoing training on cultural competency, implicit bias, an understanding of the historical perspective of how and why parole was created, the powers and duties of the board, and ethics. Such training shall address current suggested best practices and enhance and strengthen members' decisionmaking skills;</para><para>(4) A requirement that board members receive initial and ongoing training on motivational interviewing using approaches and materials developed and approved by the National Institute of Corrections;</para><para>(5) A code of ethics for members of the board;</para><para>(6) Requirements and procedures for the board to incorporate evidence-based practices that reduce recidivism. This includes, but is not limited to, a requirement that the board measure performance outcomes and develop transparent, written criteria that shall be considered when making decisions on whether to grant or revoke parole and when setting the conditions of parole;</para><para>(7) Methods by which the board will enhance opportunities for the success of people released on parole by collaborating with partners within and outside of the criminal justice system, supporting the supervision of people released on parole in their communities, employing informal social controls, and enabling people released on parole to participate meaningfully in the supervision process; and</para><para>(8) Policies and standard practices that will assist in ensuring neutrality, impartiality, and objectivity as an integral part of the board's culture and practices.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 38. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>