<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions"  statutenumber="83-4,143"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>83-4,143</statuteno><catchline>Eligibility for incarceration work camp; court, Board of Parole, or Director of Correctional Services; considerations; duration.</catchline><para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that the court target the felony offender (a) who is eligible and by virtue of his or her criminogenic needs is suitable to be sentenced to intensive supervision probation with placement at the incarceration work camp, (b) for whom the court finds that other conditions of a sentence of intensive supervision probation, in and of themselves, are not suitable, and (c) who, without the existence of an incarceration work camp, would, in all likelihood, be sentenced to prison.</para><para>(2) When the court is of the opinion that imprisonment is appropriate, but that a brief and intensive period of regimented, structured, and disciplined programming within a secure facility may better serve the interests of society, the court may place an offender in an incarceration work camp for a period not to exceed one hundred eighty days as a condition of a sentence of intensive supervision probation. The court may consider such placement if the offender (a) is a male or female offender convicted of a felony offense in a district court, (b) is medically and mentally fit to participate, with allowances given for reasonable accommodation as determined by medical and mental health professionals, and (c) has not previously been incarcerated for a violent felony crime. Offenders convicted of a crime under sections 28-319 to 28-322.04 or of any capital crime are not eligible to be placed in an incarceration work camp.</para><para>(3) It is also the intent of the Legislature that the Board of Parole may recommend placement of felony offenders at the incarceration work camp. The offenders recommended by the board shall be offenders currently housed at other Department of Correctional Services adult correctional facilities and shall complete the incarceration work camp programming prior to release on parole.</para><para>(4) When the Board of Parole is of the opinion that a felony offender currently incarcerated in a Department of Correctional Services adult correctional facility may benefit from a brief and intensive period of regimented, structured, and disciplined programming immediately prior to release on parole, the board may direct placement of such an offender in an incarceration work camp for a period not to exceed one hundred eighty days as a condition of release on parole. The board may consider such placement if the felony offender (a) is medically and mentally fit to participate, with allowances given for reasonable accommodation as determined by medical and mental health professionals, and (b) has not previously been incarcerated for a violent felony crime. Offenders convicted of a crime under sections 28-319 to 28-322.04 or of any capital crime are not eligible to be placed in an incarceration work camp.</para><para>(5) The Director of Correctional Services may assign a felony offender to an incarceration work camp if he or she believes it is in the best interests of the felony offender and of society, except that offenders convicted of a crime under sections 28-319 to 28-321 or of any capital crime are not eligible to be assigned to an incarceration work camp pursuant to this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 882, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 288, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 538, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB83, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB97, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB274, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 33; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The changes made to section 83-4,143 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 33, have been omitted because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>