<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id00" statutenumber="83-192"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-192</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Board of Parole; chairperson; powers; duties.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The Board of Parole shall:</para><para id="id00">(a) Determine the time of release on parole of committed offenders eligible for such release;</para><para id="id00">(b) Fix the conditions of parole, revoke parole, issue or authorize the issuance of warrants for the arrest of parole violators, and impose other sanctions short of revocation for violation of conditions of parole;</para><para id="id00">(c) Determine the time of mandatory discharge from parole;</para><para id="id00">(d) Visit and inspect any facility, state or local, for the detention of persons charged with or convicted of an offense and for the safekeeping of such other persons as may be remanded to such facility in accordance with law;</para><para id="id00">(e) Within two years after July 1, 2006, implement the utilization of a validated risk and needs assessment in coordination with the Department of Correctional Services and the Division of Parole Supervision. The assessment shall be prepared and completed by the department or the division for use by the board in determining release on parole;</para><para id="id00">(f) Review the record of every parole-eligible committed offender annually when he or she is within three years of his or her earliest parole eligibility date.</para><para id="id00">The review schedule shall be based on court-imposed sentences or statutory minimum sentences, whichever are greater. The board is not required to review the record of a committed offender when the committed offender's parole eligibility date is within one month of his or her mandatory discharge date. Nothing in such schedule shall prohibit the board from reviewing a committed offender's case at any time;</para><para id="id00">(g) Appoint and remove all employees of the board as prescribed by the State Personnel System and delegate appropriate powers and duties to them;</para><para>(h) Carry out its duties under section 83-962 during a correctional system overcrowding emergency;</para><para id="id00">(i) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations; and</para><para id="id00">(j) Exercise all powers and perform all duties necessary and proper in carrying out its responsibilities under the Nebraska Treatment and Corrections Act.</para><para id="id00">(2) The chairperson of the board shall:</para><para id="id00">(a) Supervise the administration and operation of the board;</para><para id="id00">(b) Serve in an advisory capacity to the director in administering parole services within any facility;</para><para id="id00">(c) Interpret the parole program to the public with a view toward developing a broad base of public support;</para><para id="id00">(d) Conduct research for the purpose of evaluating and improving the effectiveness of the parole system;</para><para id="id00">(e) Recommend parole legislation to the Governor;</para><para id="id00">(f) Adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the administration and operation of the board;</para><para>(g) Take all actions necessary to assist the board in carrying out its duties under section 83-962 during a correctional system overcrowding emergency; and</para><para id="id00">(h) Exercise all other powers and perform all other duties necessary and proper in carrying out his or her responsibilities as chairperson.</para><para id="id00">(3) This section does not prohibit a committed offender from requesting that the board review his or her record. The board is not required to review a committed offender's record more than once a year, except as otherwise required by statute, including section 83-962.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 817, &#167; 23, p. 3085; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 322, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 545, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1241, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 13, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 677, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1113, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 29. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Personnel System,</emphasis> see sections 81-1301 to 81-1316.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>