<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id358">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id360" statutenumber="83-4,126">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>83-4,126</statuteno><catchline id="id363">Jail Standards
Board; powers and duties; enumerated.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section,
the Jail Standards Board shall have the authority and responsibility:</para>
<para>(a) To develop minimum standards
for the construction, maintenance, and operation of criminal detention facilities;</para>
<para>(b) To perform such other
duties as may be necessary to carry out the policy of the state regarding
such criminal detention facilities and juvenile detention facilities as stated
in sections 83-4,124 to 83-4,134; and</para>
<para>(c) Consistent with the purposes
and objectives of the Juvenile Services Act, to develop standards for juvenile
detention facilities, including, but not limited to, standards for physical
facilities, care, programs, and disciplinary procedures, and to develop guidelines
pertaining to the operation of such facilities.</para>
<para>(2) The Jail
Standards Board shall not have authority over or responsibility for correctional
facilities that are accredited by a nationally recognized correctional association.
A correctional facility that is accredited by a nationally recognized correctional
association shall show proof of accreditation annually to the Jail Standards
Board. For purposes of this subsection, nationally recognized correctional
association includes, but is not limited to, the American Correctional Association
or its successor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 417, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 212, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1980, &#167; 83-948; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 663, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1184, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB390, &#167; 27.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Juvenile Services Act,</emphasis> see section 43-2401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
