
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-104</statuteno><catchline>State institutions; annual physical review; report.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The office of Public Counsel shall conduct an annual physical review of the following state institutions:</para><para>(i) The Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Geneva;</para><para>(ii) The Youth Rehabilitation and Treatment Center-Kearney;</para><para>(iii) Any other facility operated and utilized as a youth rehabilitation and treatment center;</para><para>(iv) The Hastings Regional Center;</para><para>(v) The Lincoln Regional Center;</para><para>(vi) The Norfolk Regional Center; and</para><para>(vii) The Beatrice State Developmental Center.</para><para>(b) Such physical review may include a review of the condition of buildings and grounds and the physical wear and tear of buildings, fixtures, equipment, furniture, security systems, and any improvements to the facility.</para><para>(2) The office of Public Counsel shall report to the Legislature on the condition of such state institutions. The report shall be due on or before March 15, 2021, for the 2020 calendar year, and on or before December 15 of each year beginning in 2021, for the period beginning with December 1 of the prior year through November 30 of the then current year. Such report shall include, for each state institution listed in subdivision (1)(a) of this section:</para><para>(a) The findings and observations from the annual physical review;</para><para>(b) Recent inspection reports regarding the facility;</para><para>(c) Staffing information, listed separately for each state institution, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(i) The number of assaults on staff;</para><para>(ii) Staffing levels;</para><para>(iii) Staff retention rates; and</para><para>(iv) Staff turnover rates, including unfilled and vacant positions; and</para><para>(d) The number of reports received by the office of Public Counsel for each institution and any systemic issues identified as a result of such physical review.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1144, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB273, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>