
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" id="id6" statutenumber="83-305.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-305.05</statuteno><catchline>Hastings Correctional Behavioral
Health Treatment Center; feasibility study; program statement.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Legislature
finds that a need exists for additional behavioral health treatment beds for
inmates in the state correctional system. In order to follow an orderly and
reasonable process based upon defined and documented need and an analysis
of the utilization of existing facilities, the Legislature authorizes the
Division of Behavioral Health of the Department of Health and Human Services
to study the feasibility of the establishment of a Hastings Correctional Behavioral
Health Treatment Center at the Hastings Regional Center.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The Division
of Behavioral Health of the Department of Health and Human Services shall
prepare a complete program statement for the Hastings Correctional Behavioral
Health Treatment Center, prepared in accordance with the Procedural Manual
for Capital Construction Projects, as approved by the state building division
of the Department of Administrative Services. The state building division
shall assist the Department of Health and Human Services in the preparation
and submission of the program statement.</para><para>(b) The program statement shall plan for
the long-term needs of the mentally ill inmates in the correctional system
as well as inmates who have drug and alcohol addictions. The intent is to
provide a facility for up to two hundred inmates in one or more buildings
at the Hastings Regional Center renovated or constructed to meet the needs
of the program. The program statement shall identify the classification of
inmates to be placed in the center, the programs needed to provide mental
health and substance abuse treatment, and the capital cost of renovation needed
to fully support the program objectives. The program statement shall estimate
building renovation costs, staffing costs, and operational costs for the center
along with a proposed project schedule.</para><para>(c) The completed program statement shall
be submitted electronically to the Governor and Legislature by December 15,
2014.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB999, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>