<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id779"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1,100.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,100.02</statuteno><catchline>Person on parole; levels of supervision; department; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Levels of supervision means the determination of the following for each person on parole:</para><para>(i) Supervision contact requirements, including the frequency, location, methods, and nature of contact with the parole officer;</para><para>(ii) Substance abuse testing requirements and frequency;</para><para>(iii) Contact restrictions;</para><para>(iv) Curfew restrictions;</para><para>(v) Access to available programs and treatment, with priority given to moderate-risk and high-risk parolees; and</para><para>(vi) Severity of graduated responses to violations of supervision conditions;</para><para>(b) Responsivity factors means characteristics of a parolee that affect the parolee's ability to respond favorably or unfavorably to any treatment goals; and</para><para>(c) Risk and needs assessment means an actuarial tool that has been validated in Nebraska to determine the likelihood of the parolee engaging in future criminal behavior.</para><para>(2) The department shall establish an evidence-based process that utilizes a risk and needs assessment to measure criminal risk factors, specific individual needs, and responsivity factors.</para><para>(3) The risk and needs assessment shall be performed at the commencement of the parole term and every six months thereafter by department staff trained and certified in the use of the risk and needs assessment.</para><para>(4) The validity of the risk and needs assessment shall be tested at least every five years.</para><para>(5) Based on the results of the risk and needs assessment, the department shall target parolee criminal risk and need factors by focusing sanction, program, and treatment resources on moderate-risk and high-risk parolees.</para><para>(6) The department shall provide training to its parole officers on (a) use of a risk and needs assessment, (b) risk-based supervision strategies, (c) relationship skills, (d) cognitive behavioral interventions, (e) community-based resources, (f) criminal risk factors, (g) targeting criminal risk factors to reduce recidivism, (h) proper use of a matrix of administrative sanctions, custodial sanctions, and rewards developed pursuant to section 83-1,119, and (i) addressing responsivity factors. Each parole officer shall complete the training requirements set forth in this subsection within one year after his or her hire date or September 1, 2024, whichever is later.</para><para>(7) The department shall provide training for chief parole officers to become trainers so as to ensure long-term and self-sufficient training capacity in the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1094, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB841, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB50, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB150, &#167; 141. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>