<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1,100.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,100.03</statuteno><catchline>Board of Parole; rules and regulations relating to sentencing and supervision; duties; offenders released with no supervision; report; list for placement in community work release and reentry centers.</catchline><para>(1) The board, in consultation with the department, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to reduce the number of inmates under the custody of the department who serve their entire sentence in a correctional facility and are released without supervision. The rules and regulations shall establish clear guidelines and procedures to ensure that each parolee is subject to a minimum of nine months of supervision and shall place priority on providing supervision lengths that enable meaningful transition periods for all offenders. The rules and regulations shall ensure that each inmate eligible for parole is assessed for risk of reoffending using a validated risk and needs assessment provided by the department and shall incorporate into the release decision an inmate's assessed risk of reoffending, past criminal history, program completion, institutional conduct, and other individual characteristics related to the likelihood of reoffending into parole release decisions.</para><para>(2) By February 1 of each year, the board and the department shall submit a report to the Legislature, the Supreme Court, and the Governor that describes the percentage of offenders sentenced to the custody of the department who complete their entire sentence and are released with no supervision. The report shall document characteristics of the individuals released without supervision, including the highest felony class of conviction, offense type of conviction, most recent risk assessment, status of the individualized release or reentry plan, and reasons for the release without supervision. The report also shall provide recommendations from the department and board for changes to policy and practice to meet the goal of achieving a reduction in the number of inmates under the custody of the department who serve their entire sentence in a correctional facility and are released without supervision. The report to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(3) The department, in consultation with the board, shall maintain a list of individuals who are eligible for parole but are expected to complete their entire sentence in the custody of the department and be released with no supervision. This list shall be used to facilitate the placement of committed offenders in community work release and reentry centers under the Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB605, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 31. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community Work Release and Reentry Centers Act,</emphasis> see section 47-1101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>