<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-424"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-424</statuteno><catchline>Fees and expenses; transporting prisoners; mileage; paid by county where crime was committed; amounts.</catchline><para>The expenses and fees of sheriffs and other officers incurred in conveying convicted prisoners to any Department of Correctional Services adult facility shall be examined, adjusted, and approved by the county board and paid out of the treasury of the county in which the crime was committed. The county board shall allow expenses and fees at the following rates: (1) For the sheriff, six dollars per day for time actually necessary in conveying a prisoner to the facility and return; and (2) for each assistant or guard absolutely necessary, six dollars per day. No allowance for assistance shall be made when only one prisoner is conveyed to a facility. The county board shall allow the actual and necessary traveling expenses in going and coming. When the trip is made by automobile, mileage included in such expenses shall be computed at the rate provided in section 33-117 for county sheriffs and deputy county sheriffs for each mile actually and necessarily traveled by the most direct route.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1897, c. 75, &#167; 36, p. 341; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7341; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 138, &#167; 2, p. 304; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 7001; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 83-939; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 96, &#167; 21, p. 399; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 83-939; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 83-424; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 123, &#167; 3, p. 361; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 348, &#167; 1, p. 1124; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 70, &#167; 11, p. 303; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 84, &#167; 6, p. 389; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 162, &#167; 2, p. 492; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 566, &#167; 1, p. 1851; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 823, &#167; 1, p. 3130; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 625, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 691, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 615, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 207; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 31, &#167; 36. </para></source><annotation><para>Sheriff's per diem should be accounted for to county. Drexel v. Douglas County, 62 Neb. 862, 87 N.W. 1053 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>