<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1,122.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,122.02</statuteno><catchline>Technical parole violation residential housing program; pilot program; participants; placement; requirements; report.</catchline><para>(1) The Division of Parole Supervision shall create a pilot program to establish a technical parole violation residential housing program. The purpose of the program is to provide accountability and intensive support for individuals on parole who commit technical violations, without revoking them fully back to prison.</para><para>(2) The program shall provide a structured environment for selected individuals on parole who have committed technical violations. The program shall be based upon a therapeutic community model. Participants in the program shall, at a minimum, be required to take part in counseling, educational, and other programs as the Division of Parole Supervision deems appropriate, to provide community service, and to submit to drug and alcohol screening.</para><para>(3) An individual on parole shall not be placed in the pilot program until the Division of Parole Supervision has determined the individual is a suitable candidate in accordance with policies and guidelines developed by the division.</para><para>(4) On or before June 1, 2024, the Division of Parole Supervision shall electronically submit a report to the Judiciary Committee of the Legislature regarding the pilot program. The report shall evaluate effects of the pilot program on recidivism and make recommendations regarding expansion of or changes to the program.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, technical violation has the same meaning as in section 83-1,119.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB50, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 36. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>