<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id937"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1,107.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1,107.03</statuteno><catchline>Parole School; curriculum.</catchline><para>(1) The board shall conduct Parole School sessions in each facility on a regular and recurring basis to equip committed offenders with the knowledge, skills, and confidence needed to navigate the parole process successfully.</para><para>(2) Parole School curriculum shall include, but need not be limited to, the following areas:</para><para>(a) Understanding parole guidelines, including:</para><para>(i) Comprehensive instruction on the legal framework and regulations governing parole;</para><para>(ii) Explanation of eligibility criteria and conditions for parole release; and</para><para>(iii) Clarification on the role of the board in its decisionmaking process;</para><para>(b) Preparing for parole board hearings, including:</para><para>(i) Guidance on compiling a thorough parole packet, including personal statements, character references, and evidence of rehabilitation efforts;</para><para>(ii) Workshops on effective communication and presentation skills for the parole board hearing; and</para><para>(iii) Mock parole board hearings to simulate real-life scenarios and receive constructive feedback;</para><para>(c) Factors considered by the board, including:</para><para>(i) Factors considered under section 83-1,114;</para><para>(ii) Insight into the importance of demonstrating remorse, accountability, and rehabilitation efforts; and</para><para>(iii) Strategies for addressing past mistakes and highlighting personal growth and positive change; and</para><para>(d) Interacting with parole board and parole officers, including:</para><para>(i) Training on respectful and professional communication with board members and parole officers;</para><para>(ii) Role-playing exercises to practice answering difficult questions and addressing concerns raised by the board; and</para><para>(iii) Guidance on complying with parole conditions and navigating the reintegration process post-release.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB631, &#167; 41. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>