
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id656"><amendatorysection statutenumber="83-1227" chaptername="State Institutions"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1227</statuteno><catchline>Department; prepare comprehensive plan for Beatrice State Developmental Center and Bridges program; contents; assessment of facilities; public hearing; report.</catchline><para>(1) Within the framework of the best interests of persons with developmental disabilities, the department shall prepare a comprehensive plan for the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program in Hastings, Nebraska. The plan shall include, but not be limited to:</para><para>(a) An analysis of residents of the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program in Hastings, Nebraska, on April 8, 2016, and their needs and the ability to serve them in the community;</para><para>(b) The role of the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program in the continuum of services offered to persons with developmental disabilities in Nebraska;</para><para>(c) The preferences of residents of the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program and their families;</para><para>(d) Nationwide trends in facilities like the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program;</para><para>(e) The cost efficiency of services provided at the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program;</para><para>(f) An analysis of the facilities at the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program on April 8, 2016, and the long-term structural needs of the facilities;</para><para>(g) Census trends and future needs for services at the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program; and</para><para>(h) The level of community integration for residents of the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program.</para><para>(2) The department shall prepare an assessment of the long-term viability of the facilities used to provide services at the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the facilities used to provide services through the Bridges program in Hastings, Nebraska.</para><para>(3) The department shall analyze the United States Supreme Court’s decision in Olmstead v. L.C., 527 U.S. 581 (1999), and provide an analysis of Nebraska's compliance with the decision.</para><para>(4) The department shall hold a public hearing to receive input from the public on the Beatrice State Developmental Center and the Bridges program.</para><para>(5) The department shall prepare a report including the plan, assessment, analysis, and results of the hearing required by subsections (1) through (4) of this section. The department shall submit the report electronically to the Legislature on or before June 1, 2017.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB895, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>