<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id227">
<sectno id="id228" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 44.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id229" statutenumber="83-1217.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id231">83-1217.02</statuteno><catchline id="id232">Employees
subject to criminal history record information check; fingerprints; confidentiality.</catchline>
<para>Each employee subject to the criminal history record information
check requirements of subdivision (9) of section 83-1217 and section 83-1217.01
shall file a complete set of his or her legible fingerprints with the department.
The department shall transmit such fingerprints to the Nebraska State Patrol
which shall transmit a copy of the applicant's fingerprints to the Identification
Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history
record information check.</para>
<para>The national criminal history record information check shall
include information concerning the employee from federal repositories of such
information and repositories of such information in other states if authorized
by federal law. The division shall issue a report containing the results of
the national criminal history record information check to the department.</para>
<para>The Nebraska State Patrol shall undertake a search for Nebraska
criminal history record information concerning the employee. The Nebraska
State Patrol shall issue a report to the department which contains the results
of the criminal history record information check conducted by the Nebraska
State Patrol.</para>
<para>The department shall issue copies of the reports to the
employer listed by the employee.</para>
<para>Criminal history record information subject to federal confidentiality
requirements shall remain confidential and may be released only upon the written
authorization by the employee.</para>
<para>The department, in cooperation with the Nebraska State Patrol,
shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.
Such rules and regulations shall provide that the decision to initiate, continue,
or terminate the employment of the employee is and shall remain that of the
employer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 852, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 722, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 44.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>