<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1216"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1216</statuteno><catchline>Department; duties; services; legislative intent; priorities.</catchline><para>(1) The department shall administer the medicaid home and community-based services waivers upon application approval by the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services. Beginning July 1, 2019, persons determined to be eligible for specialized services who on or after September 6, 1993, graduate from high school, reach the age of twenty-one years, or are currently receiving services shall receive services in accordance with the Developmental Disabilities Services Act. The amount of funding for any person receiving services shall be determined using an objective assessment process developed by the department and approved by the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</para><para>(2) The department shall provide directly or by contract service coordination to Nebraska residents found to be eligible for specialized services.</para><para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature that the department take all possible steps to maximize federal funding. All Nebraska residents eligible for funding for specialized services through the department shall apply for and accept any federal medicaid benefits for which they may be eligible and benefits from other funding sources within the department, the State Department of Education, specifically including the Division of Rehabilitation Services, and other agencies to the maximum extent possible.</para><para>(4) The priorities for funding the medicaid home and community-based services waivers under this section are as follows:</para><para>(a) The first funding priority of the state shall be responding to the needs of persons with developmental disabilities in immediate crisis due to caregiver death, homelessness, or a threat to the life and safety of the person;</para><para>(b) The second funding priority of the state in responding to the needs of persons with developmental disabilities shall be for persons that have resided in an institutional setting for a period of at least twelve consecutive months and who are requesting community-based services;</para><para>(c) The third funding priority of the state in responding to the needs of persons with developmental disabilities shall be for serving wards of the department or persons placed under the supervision of the Office of Probation Administration by the Nebraska court system who are transitioning upon age nineteen with no other alternatives as determined by the department to support residential services necessary to pursue economic self-sufficiency;</para><para>(d) The fourth funding priority of the state in responding to the needs of persons with developmental disabilities shall be for serving persons transitioning from the education system upon attaining twenty-one years of age to maintain skills and receive the day services necessary to pursue economic self-sufficiency; and</para><para>(e) The fifth funding priority of the state in responding to the needs of persons with developmental disabilities shall be for serving all other persons by date of application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 830, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 4, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1136, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 975; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 297, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 809; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB333, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>