<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id458"><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1230"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1230</statuteno><catchline>Developmental Disabilities Provider Capital and Equipment Maintenance Cash Fund; provider; grants.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Department means the Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(b) Eligible purpose means any upgrade, modernization, renovation, maintenance, or new purchase of the following that are used by a provider to provide any developmental disability service:</para><para>(i) The transportation fleet that is used to provide support to or to transport any individual with a developmental disability;</para><para>(ii) Any physical infrastructure or safety feature, including any feature that is used to reinforce any space that is used to provide any developmental disability service, safety glass, any perimeter security feature, and any other physical improvement that is meant to protect any client or staff member of a provider;</para><para>(iii) Any technology or remote-support infrastructure that is used to support or monitor any client, staff member, or facility infrastructure of a provider. Such technology or remote-support infrastructure includes any sensor, smart-home automation feature, and broadband infrastructure; and</para><para>(iv) Any facility to increase capacity for clients or optimize space that is available for clients or the provision of any developmental disability service, including any facility floorplan efficiency improvement and installation of any amenity or restroom; and</para><para>(c) Provider means any entity that is under contract with the department to provide any specialized or assisted service under section 83-1217.</para><para>(2) A provider may apply to the department for a grant under this section. The department shall prescribe the form for the application.</para><para>(3) The department may award a grant to any qualified applicant who applies under this section for an eligible purpose.</para><para>(4) No later than January 1, 2027, the department shall prescribe the form for grant applications under this section.</para><para>(5) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB972, &#167; 83. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>