<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id339">
<sectno id="id340" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 30.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id341" statutenumber="83-1217"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id343">83-1217</statuteno><catchline id="id344">Department;
contract for specialized services; certification and accreditation requirements;
assisted services; method of reimbursement.</catchline><para>The
department shall contract for specialized services and shall only contract
with specialized programs which meet certification and accreditation requirements.
Assisted services provided under this section through community-based developmental
disability programs shall be reimbursed on a daily rate basis, including such
services provided to eligible recipients under the medical assistance program
established in section 68-903 upon approval for such reimbursement from the
federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services. The department shall apply
to the federal Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services for approval of
any necessary waiver amendments to permit such reimbursement and shall begin
reimbursing such services on a daily rate basis no later than March 1, 2011. In order to
be certified, each specialized program shall:</para>
<para>(1) Have an internal quality assurance process;</para>
<para>(2) Have a program evaluation component;</para>
<para>(3) Have a complaint mechanism for persons with developmental
disabilities and their families;</para>
<para>(4) Have a process to ensure direct and open communication
with the department;</para>
<para>(5) Develop, implement, and regularly evaluate a plan to
ensure retention of quality employees and prevent staff turnover;</para>
<para>(6) Have measures to enhance staff training and development;</para>
<para>(7) Be governed by a local governing board or have an advisory
committee, the membership of which consists of (a) persons with developmental
disabilities, (b) family members or legal guardians of persons
with developmental disabilities,
and (c) persons who are interested community members;</para>
<para>(8) Meet accreditation standards developed by the department;</para>
<para>(9) Require a criminal history record information check of
all employees hired on or after September 13, 1997, who work directly with
clients receiving services and who are not licensed or certified as members
of their profession; and</para>
<para>(10) Meet any other certification requirements developed
by the department to further the purposes of the Developmental Disabilities
Services Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 830, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 852, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 297, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB288, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB849, &#167; 30.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>