<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="State Institutions" statutenumber="83-1212.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1212.01</statuteno><catchline>Advisory Committee on Developmental Disabilities; created; members; expenses; duties.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created the Advisory Committee on Developmental Disabilities. The advisory committee shall consist of a representative of a statewide advocacy organization for persons with developmental disabilities and their families and not more than fifteen additional members, at least one-third of whom shall be persons with developmental disabilities, at least one-third of whom shall be families of persons with developmental disabilities, and no more than one-third of whom shall be elected officials or interested community persons.</para><para>(2) The members shall be appointed by the Governor for staggered terms of three years. Any vacancy shall be filled by the Governor for the remainder of the term. One of the members shall be designated as chairperson by the Governor. Members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(3) The advisory committee shall advise the department regarding all aspects of the funding and delivery of services to persons with developmental disabilities.</para><para>(4) The advisory committee shall provide sufficient oversight to ensure that persons placed in the custody of the department under the Developmental Disabilities Court-Ordered Custody Act are receiving the least restrictive treatment and services necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1136, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 206, &#167; 35. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Developmental Disabilities Court-Ordered Custody Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1101.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>