
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="State Institutions" id="id5" statutenumber="83-1217.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>83-1217.01</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Employees; criminal
history record information check;
fingerprints; Nebraska State Patrol; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Each employee of state-operated
services and facilities providing developmental disabilities services shall
be subject to the criminal history record information check requirements of
subdivision (9) of section 83-1217 and shall
file a complete set of his or her legible fingerprints with the department.
The department shall transmit such fingerprints to the Nebraska State Patrol
which shall transmit a copy of the applicant's fingerprints to the Identification
Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation for a national criminal history
record information check.</para>
<para>(2) The national
criminal history record information check shall include information concerning
the employee from federal repositories of such information and repositories
of such information in other states if authorized by federal law for use by
the department.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska State Patrol shall undertake a search for Nebraska
criminal history record information concerning the employee. The Nebraska
State Patrol shall issue a report to the department which contains the results
of the criminal history record information check conducted by the Nebraska
State Patrol.</para><para>(4) Criminal history record information subject to federal confidentiality
requirements shall remain confidential and may be released only upon the written
authorization of the employee.</para><para>(5) The department, in cooperation with
the Nebraska State Patrol, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 852, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB728, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>