<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-115"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-115</statuteno><catchline>Subsequent elections.</catchline><para>Fifteen days before any election held under the provisions of sections 46-101 to 46-1,111, subsequent to the organization of the district, the secretary of the board of directors shall cause notice to be posted in three public places in each election precinct, of the time and place of holding the election, and shall also post a general notice of the same in the office of the board, which shall be established and kept at some fixed place to be determined by the board, specifying the polling places of each precinct. Prior to the time for posting the notices the board must appoint from each precinct, from the electors thereof, one clerk and two judges, who shall constitute a board of election for such precinct. If the board fails to appoint a board of election, or the members appointed do not attend at the opening of the polls on the morning of election, the electors of the precinct present at that hour may appoint the board, or supply the place of an absent member thereof. The board of directors must, in its order appointing the board of election, designate the hour and place in the precinct where the election must be held. All provisions of law authorizing voting by mail shall apply to all irrigation district elections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 5, p. 274; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3461; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2861; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-115; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 148, &#167; 2, p. 596. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Voting by mail,</emphasis> absentee voters, see sections 32-938 to 32-951.</para><para><emphasis>Voting by mail,</emphasis> special election procedures, see sections 32-952 to 32-959.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 