<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-125</statuteno><catchline>Surveys; acquisition of property; eminent domain; procedure; construction; powers of board.</catchline><para>The board, its agents, and employees shall have the right to enter upon any land within the district to make surveys, and may locate the line of any canal or canals and the necessary branches of such location. The board shall have the right to acquire, either by purchase or condemnation, all lands and waters and other property necessary for the construction, use, maintenance, repair, and improvement of any canal, canals, power plants of any kind or nature, and lands for reservoirs for the storage of water and all necessary appurtenances. The board shall have the right to acquire by purchase or condemnation any irrigation works, power plant, ditches, canals, or reservoirs already constructed for the use of the district. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724. In case of purchase, the bonds of the district hereinafter provided for may be used at their par value in payment. The board may also construct the necessary dams, reservoirs, and works for the collection of water for the district, and do any lawful act necessary to be done that sufficient water may be furnished to each landowner in the district for irrigation purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 10, p. 277; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 619; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 166, &#167; 1, p. 651; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 157, &#167; 1, p. 567; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 159, &#167; 1, p. 528; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 226, &#167; 1, p. 657; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3466; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 3, p. 174; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2866; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-110; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-125; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 89, p. 485. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For construction requirements and exclusions,</emphasis> see Safety of Dams and Reservoirs Act, see section 46-1601 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Irrigation district may acquire fee simple title under eminent domain. Burnett v. Central Neb. P. P. &amp; I. Dist., 147 Neb. 458, 23 N.W.2d 661 (1946).</para><para>Mandamus is proper to compel district directors to provide landowners just share of water and supervise distribution. State ex rel. Clarke v. Gering Irr. Dist., 109 Neb. 642, 192 N.W. 212 (1923).</para><para>Board may acquire by purchase or condemnation all lands necessary for construction, use, maintenance, repair and improvement of its canals. Andrews v. Lillian Irr. Dist., 66 Neb. 458, 92 N.W. 612 (1902), 97 N.W. 336 (1903).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 