<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-110"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-110</statuteno><catchline>District; organization and officers; election; notice; voters; eligibility.</catchline><para>The county board shall then give notice of an election to be held in such proposed district, for the purpose of determining whether or not the same shall be organized under the provisions of sections 46-101 to 46-128. Such notice shall describe the boundaries as established and shall designate a name for such proposed district. The notice shall be published for at least three weeks prior to such election in a newspaper in the county; and if any portion of such proposed district lies within another county or counties, then the notice shall be published in a newspaper published within each of such counties. The notice shall require the electors to cast ballots which shall contain the words Irrigation district ...... Yes, or Irrigation district ...... No, or words equivalent thereto; and also the names of persons to be voted for to fill various elective offices hereinafter prescribed. No person shall be entitled to vote at any election held under the provisions of sections 46-101 to 46-1,111 unless he shall be a qualified elector.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 2, p. 271; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 617; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 155, &#167; 1, p. 560; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3458; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 81, &#167; 1, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2858; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-102; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 357; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 46-102; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-110.</para></source></law></legaldoc> 