<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id118">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" id="id120" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="46-755"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>46-755</statuteno><catchline>Basin-wide plan; development and adoption;
extension; stated goals and objectives; plan contents; department and natural
resources districts; duties; public meeting; report; public hearing.</catchline>
<para>This section
shall apply notwithstanding any other provision of the Nebraska Ground Water
Management and Protection Act.</para>
<para>(1) If a river
basin as described in subdivision (2)(a) of section 2-1504 includes three
or more natural resources districts that, pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of
section 46-715, have been or are required to develop an integrated management
plan for all or substantially all (eighty-five percent) of the district, such
natural resources districts shall, jointly with the department and the natural
resources districts within the same basin, develop and adopt a basin-wide
plan for the areas of a basin, subbasin, or reach determined by the department
to have hydrologically connected water supplies, except that any natural resources
district that has developed and implemented a basin-wide plan pursuant to
subsection (5) of section 46-715 shall not be affected by this section. If
deemed appropriate by the department and the affected natural resources districts,
the basin-wide plan may combine two or more river basins.</para>
<para>(2) An integrated
management plan developed under subdivision (1)(a) or (b) of section 46-715
shall ensure such integrated management plan is consistent with any basin-wide
plan developed pursuant to this section. However, an integrated management
plan may implement additional incentive programs or controls pursuant to section
46-739 if the programs and controls are consistent with the basin-wide plan.</para>
<para>(3) A basin-wide
plan shall be completed, adopted, and take effect within three years after
April 17, 2014, unless the department and the natural resources districts
jointly agree to an extension of not more than an additional two years.</para>
<para>(4) A basin-wide
plan shall (a) have clear goals and objectives with a purpose of sustaining
a balance between water uses and water supplies so that the economic viability,
social and environmental health, safety, and welfare of the river basin, subbasin,
or reach can be achieved and maintained for both the near term and the long
term, (b) ensure that compliance with any interstate compact or decree or
other formal state contract or agreement or applicable state or federal law
is maintained, and (c) set forth a timeline to meet the goals and objectives
as required under this subdivision, but in no case shall a timeline exceed
thirty years after April 17, 2014.</para><para>(5)(a) A basin-wide plan developed under
this section shall utilize the best generally-accepted methodologies and available
information, data, and science to evaluate the effect of existing uses of
hydrologically connected water on existing surface water and ground water
users. The plan shall include a process to gather and evaluate data, information,
and methodologies to increase understanding of the surface water and hydrologically
connected ground water system within the basin, subbasin, or reach and test
the validity of the conclusions, information, and assumptions upon which the
plan is based.</para><para>(b) A basin-wide plan developed under this section shall include
a schedule indicating the end date by which the stated goals and objectives
are to be achieved and the management actions to be taken to achieve the goals
and objectives. To ensure that reasonable progress is being made toward achieving
the final goals and objectives of the plan, the schedule shall also include
measurable hydrologic objectives and intermediate dates by which the objectives
are expected to be met and monitoring plans to measure the extent to which
the objectives are being achieved. Such intermediate objectives shall be established
in a manner that, if achieved on schedule, will provide a reasonable expectation
that the goals of the plan will be achieved by the established end date.</para>
<para>(c) A basin-wide
plan shall be developed using a consultation and collaboration process involving
representatives from irrigation districts, reclamation districts, public power
and irrigation districts, mutual irrigation companies, canal companies, ground
water users, range livestock owners, the Game and Parks Commission, and municipalities
that rely on water from within the affected area and that, after being notified
of the commencement of the plan development process, indicate in writing their
desire to become an official participant in such process. The department and
affected natural resources districts shall involve official participants in
formulating, evaluating, and recommending plans and management actions and
work to reach an agreement among all official participants involved in a basin-wide
plan. In addition, the department or the affected natural resources districts
may include designated representatives of other stakeholders. If agreement
is reached by all parties involved in such consultation and collaboration
process, the department and the affected natural resources districts shall
adopt the agreed-upon basin-wide plan. If agreement cannot be reached by all
parties involved, the basin-wide plan shall be developed and adopted by the
department and the affected natural resources districts or by the Interrelated
Water Review Board pursuant to section 46-719.</para><para>(d) Within five years after
the adoption of the basin-wide plan, and every five years thereafter, the
department and affected natural resources districts shall conduct a technical
analysis of the actions taken in a river basin to determine the progress towards
meeting the goals and objectives of the plan. The analysis shall include an
examination of (i) available supplies, current uses, and changes in long-term
water availability, (ii) the effects of conservation practices and natural
causes, including, but not limited to, drought, and (iii) the effects of the
plan in meeting the goal of sustaining a balance between water uses and water
supplies. The analysis shall determine if changes or modifications to the
basin-wide plan are needed to meet the goals and objectives pursuant to subdivision
(4)(a) of this section. The department and affected natural resources districts
shall present the results of the analysis and any recommended modifications
to the plan at a public meeting and shall provide for at least a thirty-day
public comment period before holding a public hearing on the recommended modifications.
The department shall submit a report to the Legislature of the results of
this analysis and the progress made under the basin-wide plan. The report
shall be submitted electronically. Any official participant or stakeholder
may submit comments to the department and affected natural resources districts
on the final basin-wide plan adopted by the department and affected natural
resources districts, which shall be made a part of the report to the Legislature.</para>
<para>(e) Before adoption
of a basin-wide plan, the department and affected natural resources districts
shall schedule at least one public hearing to take testimony on the proposed
plan. Any such hearings shall be held in reasonable proximity to the area
affected by the plan. Notice of hearings shall be published as provided in
section 46-743. All interested persons may appear at any hearings and present
testimony or provide other evidence relevant to the issues under consideration.
Within sixty days after the final hearing, the department and affected natural
resources districts shall jointly determine whether to adopt the plan.</para>
<para>(f) The department
and the affected natural resources districts may utilize, when necessary,
the Interrelated Water Review Board process provided in section 46-719 for
disputes arising from developing, implementing, and enforcing a basin-wide
plan developed under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB1098, &#167; 15.</para><operativedate>April 17, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>