<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-2,132"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-2,132</statuteno><catchline>Water Policy Task Force; members.</catchline><para>(1) The members of the Water Policy Task Force shall include: (a) Twenty irrigators, with at least one irrigator from each of the state's thirteen river basins, giving consideration to maintaining a balance between surface water users and ground water users. Three irrigators shall be selected from the Republican River Basin, two irrigators shall be selected from the North Platte River Basin, two irrigators shall be selected from the middle Platte River Basin, two irrigators shall be selected from the Loup River Basin, two irrigators shall be selected from the Elkhorn River Basin, two irrigators shall be selected from the Big Blue River Basin, one irrigator shall be selected from the South Platte River Basin, one irrigator shall be selected from the lower Platte River Basin, one irrigator shall be selected from the Little Blue River Basin, one irrigator shall be selected from the Nemaha River Basin, one irrigator shall be selected from the Niobrara River Basin, one irrigator shall be selected from the White Hat River Basin, and one irrigator shall be selected from the Missouri tributaries basin; (b) three representatives from differing agricultural organizations; (c) three representatives from differing environmental organizations; (d) two representatives from differing recreational organizations; (e) three representatives to represent the state at large; (f) five representatives suggested for the Governor's consideration by the Nebraska Association of Resources Districts; (g) four representatives suggested for the Governor's consideration by the Nebraska Power Association; (h) five representatives suggested for the Governor's consideration by the League of Nebraska Municipalities, with consideration given to maintaining a balance between larger and smaller municipalities; and (i) such other members as the Governor deems appropriate to provide the task force with adequate and balanced representation. The Governor shall notify the Legislature upon completion of the appointments.</para><para>(2) Additional members of the task force shall be: (a) One representative from the Department of Natural Resources to coordinate as appropriate with other state agencies; (b) one representative from the Attorney General's office; (c) the chairperson of the Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature; and (d) the vice chairperson of the Natural Resources Committee of the Legislature. Other members of the Legislature may participate as desired.</para><para>(3) If any member of the task force is unable to serve for any reason, the Governor shall appoint a successor to such member. The successor shall represent the same constituency as the member such successor replaces.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1003, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 31. </para><terminationdate>December 31, 2009</terminationdate></source></law></legaldoc> 