<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1,145" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1,145</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Contract for water supply; election required, when; notice; procedure; effect of affirmative vote.</catchline><para>If such contract provides for payments to be made extending for a period of more than one year from the date of making the contract, the board of directors of such irrigation district shall submit the contract to the electors of the district at any general election or at a special election called therefor for the approval or disapproval of the contract. The ballots at the election shall have printed thereon For approval of contract for water supply, and Against approval of contract for water supply. The notice of the election need not give the entire contract but shall be sufficient if it states in a general way the substance of the proposed contract. The election shall otherwise be conducted in accordance with sections 46-115 to 46-118. If a majority of the electors that vote on the proposition vote for approval of the contract, the board of directors shall enter into the contract and shall thereafter, at the time the other taxes of the district are levied, levy a tax on the taxable property of the district sufficient to pay the amount due and to become due on the contract before the next annual levy in the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 205, &#167; 3, p. 442; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2946; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-203; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-1,145; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB561, &#167; 12. </para></source><annotation><para>A contract for a supply of water which provides for payment to be made by an irrigation district for a period of more than one year from the date of making the contract must be approved by the legal voters of the district. Twin Loups Reclamation &amp; Irr. District v. Blessing, 202 Neb. 513, 276 N.W.2d 185 (1979).</para><para>Where sale of existing irrigation works was contemplated, notice in general of substance of contract was sufficient. Frenchman Valley Irr. Dist. v. Smith, 167 Neb. 78, 91 N.W.2d 415 (1958).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>