<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" id="id5" statutenumber="46-241">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>46-241</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Application for
water; storage reservoirs; facility for underground water storage; eminent
domain; procedure; duties and liabilities of owner.</catchline><para>(1)
Every person intending to construct and operate a storage reservoir for irrigation
or any other beneficial purpose or intending to construct and operate a facility
for intentional underground water storage and recovery shall, except as provided
in subsections (2) and (3) of this section and section 46-243, make an application
to the department upon the prescribed form and provide such plans, drawings,
and specifications as are necessary to comply with the Safety of Dams and
Reservoirs Act. Such application shall be filed and proceedings had thereunder
in the same manner and under the same rules and regulations as other applications.
Upon the approval of such application under this section and any approval
required by the act, the applicant shall have the right to construct and impound
in such reservoir, or store in and recover from such underground water storage
facility, all water not otherwise appropriated and any appropriated water
not needed for immediate use, to construct and operate necessary ditches for
the purpose of conducting water to such storage reservoir or facility, and
to condemn land for such reservoir, ditches, or other facility. The procedure
to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections
76-704 to 76-724.</para>
<para>(2) Any person intending to construct an on-channel reservoir
with a water storage impounding capacity of less than fifteen acre-feet measured
below the crest of the lowest open outlet or overflow shall be exempt from
subsection (1) of this section as long as there will be (a) no diversion or
withdrawal of water from the reservoir for any purpose other than for watering
range livestock and (b) no release from the reservoir to provide water for
a downstream diversion or withdrawal for any purpose other than for watering
range livestock. This subsection does not exempt any person from the requirements
of the Safety of Dams and Reservoirs Act or section 54-2425.</para>
<para>(3) Any person intending to construct a reservoir, holding
pond, or lagoon for the sole purpose of holding, managing, or disposing of
animal or human waste shall be exempt from subsection (1) of this section.
This subsection does not exempt any person from any requirements of the Safety
of Dams and Reservoirs Act or section 46-233 or 54-2425.</para>
<para>(4) Every person intending to modify or rehabilitate an existing
storage reservoir so that its impounding capacity is to be increased shall
comply with subsection (1) of this section.</para>
<para>(5) The owner of a storage reservoir or facility shall be
liable for all damages arising from leakage or overflow of the water therefrom
or from the breaking of the embankment of such reservoir. The owner or possessor
of a reservoir or intentional underground water storage facility does not
have the right to store water in such reservoir or facility during the time
that such water is required downstream in
ditches for direct irrigation or for any reservoir or facility holding a senior
right. Every person who owns, controls, or operates a reservoir or intentional
underground water storage facility, except political subdivisions of this
state, shall be required to pass through the outlets of such reservoir or
facility, whether presently existing or hereafter constructed, a portion of
the measured inflows to furnish water for livestock in such amounts and at
such times as directed by the department to meet the requirements for such
purposes as determined by the department, except that a reservoir or facility
owner shall not be required to release water for this purpose which has been
legally stored. Any dam shall be constructed in accordance with the Safety
of Dams and Reservoirs Act, and the outlet works shall be installed so that
water may be released in compliance with this section. The requirement for
outlet works may be waived by the department upon a showing of good cause.
Whenever any person diverts water from a public stream and returns it into
the same stream, he or she may take out the same amount of water, less a reasonable
deduction for losses in transit, to be determined by the department, if no
prior appropriator for beneficial use is prejudiced by such diversion.</para>
<para>(6) An application for storage and recovery of water intentionally
stored underground may be made only by an appropriator of record who shows,
by documentary evidence, sufficient interest in the underground water storage
facility to entitle the applicant to the water requested.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. VII, art. V, div. 3, &#167; 17, p. 852; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8467; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-617; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-241; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 91, p. 487; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 183, &#167; 2, p. 515; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 823, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 186, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 198, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 103, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 488, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 309, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 115; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 619, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 916, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 335, &#167; 74; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1098, &#167; 12.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Safety of Dams and Reservoirs Act,</emphasis> see section 46-1601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>There is no statutory or regulatory requirement that the design of a dam exempt from the permit requirement of subsection (1) of this section by virtue of its impoundment capacity must include a passthrough device. Koch v. Aupperle, 274 Neb. 52, 737 N.W.2d 869 (2007).</para><para>Pondage, captured by reservoir during nonirrigation season, or from waters during irrigation season which are not subject to appropriation, is entitled to be held by a public power district for use in operation and maintenance of its power works. Platte Valley Irr. Dist. v. Tilley, 142 Neb. 122, 5 N.W.2d 252 (1942).</para><para>Damages recoverable in a condemnation proceeding must be based upon the value of the land in the condition it was at the time of the condemnation. In re Platte Valley Public Power &amp; Irr. Dist., 137 Neb. 313, 289 N.W. 383 (1939).</para><para>Legislature contemplated the payment for, and not abatement of, damage from seepage arising from construction of permanent reserves. Applegate v. Platte Valley Public Power &amp; Irr. Dist., 136 Neb. 280, 285 N.W. 585 (1939).</para><para>Defendant district was entitled to condemn right-of-way for transmission lines across plaintiffs' lands irrespective of boundary lines. Johnson v. Platte Valley Public Power &amp; Irr. Dist., 133 Neb. 97, 274 N.W. 386 (1937).</para><para>Public power and irrigation districts are not authorized to take private property for public use without just compensation. State ex rel. Loseke v. Fricke, 126 Neb. 736, 254 N.W. 409 (1934).</para><para>Right of eminent domain, provided for in this section, cannot be exercised where purpose of proposed condemnation is to take part of one person's land, against his will, as site for reservoir from which to irrigate land of another, for his sole benefit. Vetter v. Broadhurst, 100 Neb. 356, 160 N.W. 109 (1916).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>