<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-1,164"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1,164</statuteno><catchline>Surface Water Irrigation Infrastructure Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>There is hereby created the Surface Water Irrigation Infrastructure Fund to be administered by the Department of Water, Energy, and Environment. The fund shall be used to provide grants in accordance with section 46-1,165 to irrigation districts. There shall be a one-time transfer of fifty million dollars from the Cash Reserve Fund to the Surface Water Irrigation Infrastructure Fund to carry out the purposes of section 46-1,165. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Surface Water Irrigation Infrastructure Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. Beginning July 1, 2025, through June 30, 2027, any investment earnings from investment of money in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund. Beginning July 1, 2027, any investment earnings from investment of money in the Surface Water Irrigation Infrastructure Fund shall be credited to the fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 132; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 68.</para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB264, section 132, with LB317, section 68, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB264 became operative May 22, 2025. Changes made by LB317 became operative July 1, 2025.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>