<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-124"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-124</statuteno><catchline>Board of directors; meetings; quorum; open records.</catchline><para>The board of directors shall hold regular meetings in its office each month and such special meetings as may be required for the proper transaction of business. All special meetings shall be ordered by the president of the board. The order must be entered of record and notice thereof must be given to each member. The order must specify the business to be transacted, and no other than that specified shall be transacted at such special meeting. All meetings of the board must be publicized. Two members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business, and upon all questions requiring a vote there shall be a concurrence of at least two members. All records of the board must be open to the inspection of any elector during business hours, and the board shall cause to be published at the close of each regular or special meeting a brief statement of the proceedings thereof in one newspaper in general circulation in the district, if the same can be done at an expense not exceeding one-third of the legal rate for advertising notices.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 10, p. 276; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 618; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 166, &#167; 1, p. 650; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 157, &#167; 1, p. 567; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 159, &#167; 1, p. 527; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 226, &#167; 1, p. 656; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3466; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 3, p. 173; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2866; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-110; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-124; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 578, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Legal rate for advertising notices,</emphasis> see section 33-141.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 