<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-151"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-151</statuteno><catchline>Cost of construction; when payable in bonds; issuance of additional bonds; additional levy.</catchline><para>The cost and expense of purchasing and acquiring property and constructing the works and improvements herein provided for, shall be wholly paid out of the construction fund, or in the bonds of such district at their par value, after having first advertised the same for sale as provided in section 46-1,100, and having received no bids therefor of ninety-five percent or upwards of their face value. In case such bonds or the money raised by their sale is insufficient for the purposes for which the bonds were issued, additional bonds may be issued, after submission of the question at a general or special election to the qualified voters of the district. In case of the issuance of additional bonds, the lien for taxes for the payment of the interest and principal of such issue shall be a subsequent lien to any prior bond issue. However, the provisions of this section shall not apply where the cost and expense of purchasing and acquiring property and constructing the works and improvements herein provided for are covered by contract between the district and the United States. In lieu of the issuance of additional bonds, the board of directors may provide for the completion of the irrigation system of the district by the levy of an assessment therefor in the same manner in which levy of an assessment is made for the other purposes provided in sections 46-101 to 46-1,111.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 24, p. 287; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 78, &#167; 2, p. 334; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 37, &#167; 1, p. 131; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3482; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 8, p. 179; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2882; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-127; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-151.</para></source><annotation><para>Expense of engineer for survey and plans is preliminary and payable out of construction fund. Willow Springs Irr. Dist. v. Wilson, 74 Neb. 269, 104 N.W. 165 (1905).</para><para>Construction fund must be provided before indebtedness incurred for construction. Lincoln &amp; Dawson County Irr. Dist. v. McNeal, 60 Neb. 613, 83 N.W. 847 (1900).</para><para>Amendment of 1899 was valid. Baltes v. Farmers Irr. Dist., 60 Neb. 310, 83 N.W. 83 (1900).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 