<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="46-715"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-715</statuteno><catchline>River basin, subbasin, or reach; integrated
management plan; considerations; contents; amendment; technical analysis;
forecast of water available from streamflow.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Whenever
the Department of Natural Resources has designated a river basin, subbasin,
or reach as overappropriated or has made a final determination that a river
basin, subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated, the natural resources districts
encompassing such river basin, subbasin, or reach and the department shall
jointly develop an integrated management plan for such river basin, subbasin,
or reach. The plan shall be completed, adopted, and take effect within three
years after such designation or final determination unless the department
and the natural resources districts jointly agree to an extension of not more
than two additional years.</para>
<para>(b) A natural resources
district encompassing a river basin, subbasin, or reach that has not been
designated as overappropriated or has not been finally determined to be fully
appropriated may, jointly with the department, develop an integrated management
plan for such river basin, subbasin, or reach located within the district.
The district shall notify the department of its intention to develop an integrated
management plan which shall be developed and adopted according to sections
46-715 to 46-717 and subsections (1) and (2) of section 46-718. The objective
of an integrated management plan under this subdivision is to manage such
river basin, subbasin, or reach to achieve and sustain a balance between water
uses and water supplies for the long term. If a district develops an integrated
management plan under this subdivision and the department subsequently determines
the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach to be fully appropriated, the
department and the affected natural resources district may amend the integrated
management plan.</para><para>(2) In developing an integrated management
plan, the effects of existing and potential new water uses on existing surface
water appropriators and ground water users shall be considered. An integrated
management plan shall include the following: (a) Clear goals and objectives
with a purpose of sustaining a balance between water uses and water supplies
so that the economic viability, social and environmental health, safety, and
welfare of the river basin, subbasin, or reach can be achieved and maintained
for both the near term and the long term; (b) a map clearly delineating the
geographic area subject to the integrated management plan; (c) one or more
of the ground water controls authorized for adoption by natural resources
districts pursuant to section 46-739; (d) one or more of the surface water
controls authorized for adoption by the department pursuant to section 46-716;
and (e) a plan to gather and evaluate data, information, and methodologies
that could be used to implement sections 46-715 to 46-717, increase understanding
of the surface water and hydrologically connected ground water system, and
test the validity of the conclusions and information upon which the integrated
management plan is based. The plan may also provide for utilization of any
applicable incentive programs authorized by law. Nothing in the integrated
management plan for a fully appropriated river basin, subbasin, or reach shall
require a natural resources district to regulate ground water uses in place
at the time of the department's preliminary determination that the river basin,
subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated, but a natural resources district
may voluntarily adopt such regulations. The applicable natural resources district
may decide to include all water users within the district boundary in an integrated
management plan.</para>
<para>(3) In order to provide a process for economic development opportunities
and economic sustainability within a river basin, subbasin, or reach, the
integrated management plan shall include clear and transparent procedures
to track depletions and gains to streamflows resulting from new, retired,
or other changes to uses within the river basin, subbasin, or reach. The procedures
shall:</para>
<para>(a) Utilize generally accepted methodologies based on the best available
information, data, and science;</para>
<para>(b) Include a generally accepted methodology to be utilized to estimate
depletions and gains to streamflows, which methodology includes location,
amount, and time regarding gains to streamflows as offsets to new uses;</para>
<para>(c) Identify means to be utilized so that new uses will not have more
than a de minimis effect upon existing surface water users or ground water
users;</para>
<para>(d) Identify procedures the natural resources district and the department
will use to report, consult, and otherwise share information on new uses,
changes in uses, or other activities affecting water use in the river basin,
subbasin, or reach;</para>
<para>(e) Identify, to the extent feasible, potential water available to mitigate
new uses, including, but not limited to, water rights leases, interference
agreements, augmentation projects, conjunctive use management, and use retirement;</para>
<para>(f) Develop, to the extent feasible, an outline of plans after consultation
with and an opportunity to provide input from irrigation districts, public
power and irrigation districts, reclamation districts, municipalities, other
political subdivisions, and other water users to make water available for
offset to enhance and encourage economic development opportunities and economic
sustainability in the river basin, subbasin, or reach; and</para>
<para>(g) Clearly identify procedures that applicants for new uses shall take
to apply for approval of a new water use and corresponding offset.</para>
<para>Nothing in this subsection shall require revision or amendment of an
integrated management plan approved on or before August 30, 2009.</para>
<para>(4) The ground water and surface water controls proposed for adoption
in the integrated management plan pursuant to subsection (1) of this section
shall, when considered together and with any applicable incentive programs,
(a) be consistent with the goals and objectives of the plan, (b) be sufficient
to ensure that the state will remain in compliance with applicable state and
federal laws and with any applicable interstate water compact or decree or
other formal state contract or agreement pertaining to surface water or ground
water use or supplies, and (c) protect the ground water users whose water
wells are dependent on recharge from the river or stream involved and the
surface water appropriators on such river or stream from streamflow depletion
caused by surface water uses and ground water uses begun, in the case of a river basin, subbasin, or
reach designated
as overappropriated or preliminarily
determined to be fully appropriated in accordance with section 46-713, after the date of such designation or
preliminary determination.</para>
<para>(5)(a) In any river basin, subbasin, or reach that is designated as
overappropriated, when the designated area lies within two or more natural
resources districts, the department and the affected natural resources districts
shall jointly develop a basin-wide plan for the area designated as overappropriated.
Such plan shall be developed using the consultation and collaboration process
described in subdivision (b) of this subsection, shall be developed concurrently
with the development of the integrated management plan required pursuant to
subsections (1) through (4) of this section, and shall be designed to achieve,
in the incremental manner described in subdivision (d) of this subsection,
the goals and objectives described in subsection (2) of this section. The
basin-wide plan shall be adopted after hearings by the department and the
affected natural resources districts.</para>
<para>(b) In any river basin, subbasin, or reach designated as overappropriated
and subject to this subsection, the department and each natural resources
district encompassing such river basin, subbasin, or reach shall jointly develop
an integrated management plan for such river basin, subbasin, or reach pursuant
to subsections (1) through (4) of this section. Each integrated management
plan for a river basin, subbasin, or reach subject to this subsection shall
be consistent with any basin-wide plan developed pursuant to subdivision (a)
of this subsection. Such integrated management plan shall be developed after
consultation and collaboration with irrigation districts, reclamation districts,
public power and irrigation districts, mutual irrigation companies, canal
companies, and municipalities that rely on water from within the affected
area and that, after being notified of the commencement of the plan development
process, indicate in writing their desire to participate in such process.
In addition, the department or the affected natural resources districts may
include designated representatives of other stakeholders. If agreement is
reached by all parties involved in such consultation and collaboration process,
the department and each natural resources district shall adopt the agreed-upon
integrated management plan. If agreement cannot be reached by all parties
involved, the integrated management plan shall be developed and adopted by
the department and the affected natural resources district pursuant to sections
46-715 to 46-718 or by the Interrelated Water Review Board pursuant to section
46-719.</para>
<para>(c) Any integrated management plan developed under this subsection shall
identify the overall difference between the current and fully appropriated
levels of development. Such determination shall take into account cyclical
supply, including drought, identify the portion of the overall difference
between the current and fully appropriated levels of development that is due
to conservation measures, and identify the portions of the overall difference
between the current and fully appropriated levels of development that are
due to water use initiated prior to July 1, 1997, and to water use initiated
on or after such date.</para>
<para>(d) Any integrated management plan developed under this subsection shall
adopt an incremental approach to achieve the goals and objectives identified
under subdivision (2)(a) of this section using the following steps:</para>
<para>(i) The first incremental goals shall be to address the impact of streamflow
depletions to (A) surface water appropriations and (B) water wells constructed
in aquifers dependent upon recharge from streamflow, to the extent those depletions
are due to water use initiated after July 1, 1997, and, unless an interstate
cooperative agreement for such river basin, subbasin, or reach is no longer
in effect, to prevent streamflow depletions that would cause noncompliance
by Nebraska with such interstate cooperative agreement. During the first increment,
the department and the affected natural resources districts shall also pursue
voluntary efforts, subject to the availability of funds, to offset any increase
in streamflow depletive effects that occur after July 1, 1997, but are caused
by ground water uses initiated prior to such date. The department and the
affected natural resources districts may also use other appropriate and authorized
measures for such purpose;</para>
<para>(ii) The department and the affected natural resources districts may
amend an integrated management plan subject to this subsection (5) as necessary
based on an annual review of the progress being made toward achieving the
goals for that increment;</para>
<para>(iii) During the ten years following adoption of an integrated management
plan developed under this subsection (5) or during the ten years after the
adoption of any subsequent increment of the integrated management plan pursuant
to subdivision (d)(iv) of this subsection, the department and the affected
natural resources district shall conduct a technical analysis of the actions
taken in such increment to determine the progress towards meeting the goals
and objectives adopted pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. The analysis
shall include an examination of (A) available supplies and changes in long-term
availability, (B) the effects of conservation practices and natural causes,
including, but not limited to, drought, and (C) the effects of the plan on
reducing the overall difference between the current and fully appropriated
levels of development identified in subdivision (5)(c) of this section. The
analysis shall determine whether a subsequent increment is necessary in the
integrated management plan to meet the goals and objectives adopted pursuant
to subsection (2) of this section and reduce the overall difference between
the current and fully appropriated levels of development identified in subdivision
(5)(c) of this section;</para>
<para>(iv) Based on the determination made in subdivision (d)(iii) of this
subsection, the department and the affected natural resources districts, utilizing
the consultative and collaborative process described in subdivision (b) of
this subsection, shall if necessary identify goals for a subsequent increment
of the integrated management plan. Subsequent increments shall be completed,
adopted, and take effect not more than ten years after adoption of the previous
increment; and</para>
<para>(v) If necessary, the steps described in subdivisions (d)(ii) through
(iv) of this subsection shall be repeated until the department and the affected
natural resources districts agree that the goals and objectives identified
pursuant to subsection (2) of this section have been met and the overall difference
between the current and fully appropriated levels of development identified
in subdivision (5)(c) of this section has been addressed so that the river
basin, subbasin, or reach has returned to a fully appropriated condition.</para>
<para>(6) In any river basin, subbasin, or reach that is designated as fully
appropriated or overappropriated and whenever necessary to ensure that the
state is in compliance with an interstate compact or decree or a formal state
contract or agreement, the department, in consultation with the affected districts,
shall forecast on an annual basis the maximum amount of water that may be
available from streamflow for beneficial use in the short term and long term
in order to comply with the requirement of subdivision (4)(b) of this section.
This forecast shall be made by January 1, 2008, and each January 1 thereafter.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1226, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB54, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB764, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>