<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-190"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-190</statuteno><catchline>Discontinuance of district; assets of district used to pay debts; procedure; unused funds; distribution.</catchline><para>After a sale of the property and franchises of the district, the board of directors shall, with the amount realized from such sale, together with such other funds as such district may have, make settlement, payment, and redemption, if possible, of all outstanding bonded and other indebtedness of the district, but shall in no case pay more than the market value of such outstanding bonds with interest up to the time of payment. In cases when bonds not yet due cannot be redeemed by reason of the refusal of the owner thereof to surrender them before due, the board may invest the surplus money of the district, after paying all debts that can be paid, in state, county, or other safe bonds, bearing the same or greater rate of interest, if possible, than the district bonds thus outstanding, for the purpose of paying such outstanding bonds of the district when due. In case the amount realized from the sale of such district property, together with other money of the district, is insufficient for the payment of all the indebtedness of the district, assessments shall continue to be made against the lands included in the district in the manner provided by law for assessments to pay bonds and other indebtedness of irrigation districts until a sufficient amount is raised to fully pay all obligations of such district.</para><para>Any balance of funds remaining after the sale or disposition of all property belonging to the district and after all obligations and indebtedness of the district have been paid or discharged shall be distributed by the county treasurer to all assessment payers of the district of record as of the date of the filing in the office of the Department of Natural Resources of the report referred to in section 46-192. Such distribution shall be made pro rata in accordance with the number of acres of irrigable land owned within the district as of the date of the last assessment against such land for the district prior to the date of the filing of such report.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 628; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3521; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2921; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-166; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-190; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 66, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 88. </para></source><annotation><para>In tax sale foreclosure, property remains liable for payment of future assessments by irrigation district to discharge irrigation bonds. County of Garden v. Schaaf, 145 Neb. 676, 17 N.W.2d 874 (1945).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 