<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-236"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>46-236</statuteno><catchline>Application for water power; lease
from state required; fee; renewal; cancellation; grounds.</catchline><para>An application for appropriation of water
for water power shall meet the requirements of section 46-234 and subsection
(1) of section 46-235 to be approved. Within six months after
the approval of an application for water power and before
placing water to any beneficial use, the applicant shall enter into a contract
with the State of Nebraska, through the department, for leasing the use of
all water so appropriated. Such lease shall be upon forms prepared by the
department, and the time of such lease shall not run for a greater period
than fifty years; and for the use of water for power purposes the applicant
shall pay into the state treasury on or before January 1 each year fifteen
dollars for each one hundred horsepower for all water so appropriated. Upon
application of the lessee or its assigns, the department shall renew the lease
so as to continue it and the water appropriation in full force and effect
for an additional period of fifty years.</para>
<para>Upon the failure of the applicant to comply with any of the provisions
of such lease and the failure to pay any of such fees, the department shall
notify the lessee that the required fees have not been paid to the department
or that the lessee is not otherwise in compliance with the provisions of the
lease. If the lessee has not come into compliance with all provisions of the
lease or has not paid to the department all required fees within fifteen calendar
days after the date of such notice, the department shall issue an order denying
the applicant the right to divert or otherwise use the water appropriation
for power production. The department shall rescind the order denying use of
the water appropriation at such time as the lessee has come into compliance
with all provisions of the lease and has paid all required fees to the department.
If after forty-five calendar days from the date of issuance of the order the
lessee is not in compliance with all provisions of the lease or required fees
have not been paid to the department, such lease and water appropriation shall
be canceled by the department.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 291, &#167; 1, p. 942; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8437; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 81-6318; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-236; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1306, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 140, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 111; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB27, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>State may lease use of public waters for power purposes. Hickman v. Loup River P. P. Dist., 176 Neb. 416, 126 N.W.2d 404 (1964).</para><para>Applicant for use of water for power purposes may make lease with state. Hickman v. Loup River P. P. Dist., 173 Neb. 428, 113 N.W.2d 617 (1962).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
