<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-253"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-253</statuteno><catchline>Ditches; changing line; flow maintained; liability.</catchline><para>No owner of any ditch or canal shall change the line of the ditch or canal so as to interfere with the use of water by anyone, who, prior to the proposed change, had used water for irrigation purposes from such ditch or canal, and the owner of such ditch or canal shall keep the same in good repair so as to permit the water to flow in a quantity sufficient to furnish the statutory amount to the lands entitled thereto at all reasonable times. The majority of the water users under any ditch may designate such reasonable time for the use of water as such majority may determine upon, upon a written notice signed by such majority to the persons in control of such ditch or canal. The owners, or those in control, may limit the flow of water in the canal in accordance with such notice, between April 1 and May 1, and October 1 and November 15. No ditch shall be closed between May 1 and October 1. For a failure to cause the water to flow as aforesaid, the owners, or those in control, of any such ditch or canal shall be liable to anyone for any damage resulting from such failure, unavoidable accidents and shortage in the source of supply excepted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 69, &#167; 46, p. 261; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3436; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 65, &#167; 1, p. 164; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 190, tit. VII, art. V, div. 3, &#167; 9, p. 849; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8459; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 132, &#167; 1, p. 347; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 143, &#167; 1, p. 387; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-609; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 104, &#167; 1, p. 363; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 46-609; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-253.</para></source><annotation><para>Action to enjoin district from using waters of stream, brought after close of irrigation season, in county other than that where principal place of business of district is located, making parties defendant certain public officers whose terms expire before beginning of next irrigation season in order to confer jurisdiction in court, will be dismissed for want of jurisdiction. Platte Valley Irr. Dist. v. Bryan, 130 Neb. 657, 266 N.W. 73 (1936).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 