<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water"  statutenumber="46-602.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-602.01</statuteno><catchline>Water well in management area; duties; prohibited acts; penalty.</catchline><para>Prior to commencing construction of or installation of a pump in a water well in a management area or completing a notice of modification and change of use in lieu of decommissioning of a water well as part of a water well replacement procedure, a licensed water well contractor as defined in section 46-1213 or a licensed pump installation contractor as defined in section 46-1209 shall take those steps necessary to satisfy himself or herself that the person for whom the well is to be constructed, the modification and change of use is to be completed, or the pump installed has obtained a permit as required by the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act. The permit issued by the natural resources district as required by the act may (1) further define a replacement water well in accordance with the act so long as any further definition is not inconsistent with section 46-602, (2) impose restrictions on consumptive use, or (3) impose additional restrictions based on historic consumptive use.</para><para>Any person who commences or causes construction of or installation of a pump in a water well for which the required permit has not been obtained or who knowingly furnishes false information regarding such permit shall be guilty of an offense punishable as provided in section 46-613.02.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 325, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 131, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 508, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1141.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 46-701.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>