<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-112</statuteno><catchline>District officers; election; terms.</catchline><para>The officers elected in compliance with section 46-110, upon qualifying as provided in section 46-113, shall hold their respective offices until the next general election for the irrigation district when their successors shall be elected. At such general election the member of the board of directors having the highest number of votes shall hold his or her respective office for a term of three years, the member of the board of directors having the next highest number of votes shall be declared to be elected for a term of two years, and the member of the board of directors having the least number of votes shall be elected for a term of one year. Each year thereafter, one member of the board of directors shall be elected for a term of three years. Each member of the board of directors shall be nominated and elected by a majority vote of the electors of the division in the irrigation district and shall be an elector of the division for which he or she is to serve as such director. If, after the election, it appears that any two or more persons have an equal and the highest number of votes for the same office, the county board shall, in the presence of the candidates or their representatives, determine by lot which of the candidates shall be elected.</para><para>An automatic recount shall be held in accordance with sections 32-1119 to 32-1122. The regular election of the district shall be held on the first Tuesday in February.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1905, c. 166, &#167; 1, p. 649; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 142, &#167; 2, p. 344; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3460; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 1, p. 170; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2860; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 97, &#167; 1, p. 245; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-104; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 106, &#167; 1, p. 341; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 46-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-112; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 421, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 555; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 99, &#167; 12. </para></source></law></legaldoc>