<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-691.03" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-691.03</statuteno><catchline>Transfer off overlying land for environmental or recreational benefits; when allowed; application; fee; natural resources district; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person intending to withdraw ground water from any water well located in the State of Nebraska, transport that water off the overlying land, and use it to augment water supplies in any Nebraska wetland or natural stream for the purpose of benefiting fish or wildlife or producing other environmental or recreational benefits may do so only if the natural resources district in which the water well is or would be located allows withdrawals and transport for such purposes and only after applying for and obtaining a permit from such natural resources district. An application for any such permit shall be accompanied by a nonrefundable fee of fifty dollars payable to such district. Such permit shall be in addition to any permit required pursuant to section 46-252 or 46-735 or subdivision (1)(k) of section 46-739.</para><para>(2) Prior to taking action on an application pursuant to this section, the district shall provide an opportunity for public comment on such application at a regular or special board meeting for which advance published notice of the meeting and the agenda therefor have been given consistent with the Open Meetings Act.</para><para>(3) In determining whether to grant a permit under this section, the board of directors for the natural resources district shall consider:</para><para>(a) Whether the proposed use is a beneficial use of ground water;</para><para>(b) The availability to the applicant of alternative sources of surface water or ground water for the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use;</para><para>(c) Any negative effect of the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use on ground water supplies needed to meet present or reasonable future demands for water in the area of the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use, to comply with any interstate compact or decree, or to fulfill the provisions of any other formal state contract or agreement;</para><para>(d) Any negative effect of the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use on surface water supplies needed to meet present or reasonable future demands for water within the state, to comply with any interstate compact or decree, or to fulfill the provisions of any other formal state contract or agreement;</para><para>(e) Any adverse environmental effect of the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use of the ground water;</para><para>(f) The cumulative effects of the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use relative to the matters listed in subdivisions (3)(c) through (e) of this section when considered in conjunction with all other withdrawals, transports, and uses subject to this section;</para><para>(g) Whether the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use is consistent with the district's ground water quantity and quality management plan and with any integrated management plan previously adopted or being considered for adoption in accordance with sections 46-713 to 46-719; and</para><para>(h) Any other factors consistent with the purposes of this section which the board of directors deems relevant to protect the interests of the state and its citizens.</para><para>(4) Issuance of a permit shall be conditioned on the applicant's compliance with the rules and regulations of the natural resources district from which the water is to be withdrawn and, if the location where the water is to be used to produce the intended benefits is in a different natural resources district, with the rules and regulations of that natural resources district. The board of directors may include such reasonable conditions on the proposed withdrawal, transport, and use as it deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this section.</para><para>(5) The applicant shall be required to provide access to his or her property at reasonable times for purposes of inspection by officials of any district where the water is to be withdrawn or to be used.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 97; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1226, &#167; 18.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>