<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-104</statuteno><catchline>Petition; map; requirements.</catchline><para>The petitioners must accompany the petition with a map of the proposed district. The map shall show the location of the proposed canal or the works by means of which it is intended to irrigate the proposed district, and of all the canals situated within the boundaries of the proposed district; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> canals that only pass through such lands, and which do not in fact irrigate any of the same, need not be shown. If the water supply be from natural streams, the flow of such stream or streams shall be stated in cubic feet per second. If the water supply for the district is to be gathered by storage reservoirs, the map shall show the location of the proposed reservoirs and shall give their capacity in acre-feet. The map shall be drawn to a scale of two inches to the mile. Cross sections of the proposed canal, and all canals existing within the boundaries of the proposed district and shown on the map, and all proposed dams and embankments, shall be given in sufficient number to show the contemplated mode of construction, and the capacity shall be given in cubic feet per second of the proposed and such existing canals. Such cross sections shall be drawn to a scale of ten feet to the inch, and the map and cross sections shall be certified to by a competent irrigation engineer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 155, &#167; 1, p. 558; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3458; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 81, &#167; 1, p. 191; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2858; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-102; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 355; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 46-102; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-104.</para></source></law></legaldoc> 