<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-305"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-305</statuteno><catchline>Electric light and power system; construction or acquisition; election required; procedure; vote required; effect of affirmative vote.</catchline><para>Upon the filing of the data and certificates with the board of directors of the district, the board of directors and the other proper officers of the district shall submit the proposed plan and project to the qualified electors of the district for their approval or rejection, at a general election or at a special election called for that purpose, the submission of proposition and all matters pertaining to such election to conform, including notice of election, as nearly as may be, and except as otherwise expressly provided in sections 46-301 to 46-315, to the provisions of law governing elections upon propositions for the issuance of bonds of the district. The report of the Department of Natural Resources and all other data and information on file with the board of directors or the officers of the district shall be subject to inspection at all reasonable business hours by any elector of the district, or other interested persons, for the entire period during which notice of the election shall be published. Such question and proposition shall be thus submitted by ballots upon which shall appear, in a clear, fair, and concise manner, a statement of the nature and description of the proposed project, and, if such proposition includes the issuance of bonds of the district, there shall also appear upon the ballots a general description of such bonds, including principal amount, rate of interest and when payable, date of issuance, and date of maturity. At the bottom of the ballots substantially the following form shall appear:</para><para>FOR the adoption of the foregoing plan and project (and issuance of bonds of the district).</para><para>AGAINST the adoption of the foregoing plan and project (and the issuance of bonds of the district).</para><para>If a majority of the ballots cast on such proposition are in favor thereof, the board of directors shall declare the same adopted, and the board of directors of the district shall proceed forthwith to put such plan and project into effect, including the issuance of bonds of the district if included in the proposition submitted at the election, the levy and collection of taxes and assessments to pay such bonds and interest thereon, and the execution of all contracts proper or incident to the consummation of such plan and project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1931, c. 91, &#167; 5, p. 254; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 46-705; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-305; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 534, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 163. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Issuance of bonds,</emphasis> election, see section 46-194.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 