<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-742"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-742</statuteno><catchline>Transport of ground water; prohibited; when.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever the drilling of new wells has been stayed pursuant to section 46-714, ground water withdrawn outside the affected area shall not be transported for use inside such area unless (a) such withdrawal and transport began before the stay took effect, (b) the water is used solely for domestic purposes, or (c) such withdrawal and transport is approved in advance by the district in which the stay is in effect and, if the water is withdrawn in another natural resources district, by the other district.</para><para>(2) Whenever a natural resources district pursuant to subdivision (1)(m) of section 46-739 has closed all or part of the district to the issuance of additional well permits, ground water withdrawn outside the affected area shall not be transported for use inside such area unless (a) such withdrawal and transport began before the affected area was closed to the issuance of additional well permits, (b) the water is used solely for domestic purposes, or (c) such withdrawal and transport is approved in advance by the district that closed the affected area to additional well permits and, if the water is withdrawn in another natural resources district, by the other district.</para><para>(3) If a proposed withdrawal and transport of water under subsection (1) or (2) of this section is intended for municipal purposes, the natural resources district shall approve the withdrawal and transport of ground water into the affected area when a public water supplier providing water for municipal purposes receives a permit from the Department of Natural Resources pursuant to the Municipal and Rural Domestic Ground Water Transfers Permit Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 619, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2003, &#167; 46-656.24; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 82. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Municipal and Rural Domestic Ground Water Transfers Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 46-650.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>