<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-752"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-752</statuteno><catchline>Interrelated Water Management Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Interrelated Water Management Fund is created. The State Treasurer shall credit to the fund, for the purpose of conducting studies to determine the cause of current or potential conflicts between ground water users and surface water appropriators, disputes over interstate compacts or decrees, or difficulties fulfilling the provisions of other formal state contracts and agreements, such money as is specifically appropriated and such funds, fees, donations, gifts, or services or devises or bequests of real or personal property received by the Department of Natural Resources from any federal, state, public, or private source, to be used by the department for the purpose of funding studies as described in this section. The department may use its budget authority to request appropriations specifically for the purpose of funding studies described in this section. The department shall allocate money from the fund for use by the department, by any state agency, board, or commission, or by any political subdivision of the state, by agreement, or by private organizations or firms as may be contracted with by the department. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 108, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 219; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 46-656.67; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 92. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 