<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-718"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-718</statuteno><catchline>Integrated management plan; hearings; implementation order; dispute; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) If the Department of Natural Resources and the affected natural resources districts preparing an integrated management plan reach agreement on (a) the proposed goals and objectives of the plan for the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach, (b) the proposed geographic area to be subject to controls, and (c) the surface water and ground water controls and any incentive programs that are proposed for adoption and implementation in the river basin, subbasin, or reach, they shall schedule one or more public hearings to take testimony on the proposed integrated management plan and the proposed controls. Such hearings shall be held within forty-five days after reaching agreement and within or in reasonable proximity to the area to be affected by implementation of the integrated management plan. Notice of such hearings shall be published as provided in section 46-743. The costs of publishing the notice shall be shared between the department and the affected natural resources districts. All interested persons may appear at the hearings and present testimony or provide other evidence relevant to the issues being considered.</para><para>(2) Within sixty days after the final hearing under this section, the department and the affected natural resources districts shall jointly decide whether to implement the plan proposed, with or without modifications, and whether to adopt and implement the surface water and ground water controls and incentive programs proposed in the plan. If the department and the natural resources districts agree to implement the plan and to adopt and implement the proposed controls, the natural resources districts shall by order designate a ground water management area for integrated management or, if the geographic area subject to the integrated management plan is already in a ground water management area, the order shall designate an integrated management subarea for that area. The order shall include a geographic and stratigraphic definition of the ground water management area or integrated management subarea and shall adopt the controls in the integrated management plan that are authorized for adoption by the natural resources district pursuant to section 46-739. The department shall by order adopt the controls in the integrated management plan that are authorized for adoption by the department pursuant to section 46-716. Neither the controls adopted by the district nor those adopted by the department shall include controls substantially different from those set forth in the notice of hearing. The area designated as a ground water management area or an integrated management subarea by the natural resources district shall not include any area that was not identified in the notice of the hearing as within the area proposed to be subject to the controls in the plan. The department and the natural resources district shall each cause a copy of its order to be published in the manner provided in section 46-744.</para><para>(3) If at any time during the development of a basin-wide plan or an integrated management plan either the department or the affected natural resources districts conclude that the parties will be unable to reach a timely agreement on the basin-wide plan or on (a) the goals and objectives of the integrated management plan for the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach, (b) the geographic area to be subject to controls, or (c) the surface water or ground water controls or any incentive programs to be proposed for adoption and implementation in the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach, the Governor shall be notified and the dispute shall be submitted to the Interrelated Water Review Board as provided in subsection (2) of section 46-719.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 58. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 