<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-233.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-233.01</statuteno><catchline>Permit to appropriate water for use in another state; application; considerations; determination.</catchline><para>(1) Application may be made to the department for a permit to appropriate any of the public surface waters of the State of Nebraska to be diverted or stored in Nebraska for use in any other state.</para><para>(2) In determining whether to grant such application, the director shall consider the following factors:</para><para>(a) Whether unappropriated water exists in the source of supply named in the application;</para><para>(b) Whether such application and appropriation when perfected are not otherwise detrimental to the public welfare;</para><para>(c) Whether denial of the application is demanded by the public interest; and</para><para>(d) Whether the proposed use is a beneficial use of water.</para><para>(3) When determining whether denial of such application is demanded by the public interest, the director shall consider the following factors:</para><para>(a) The economic, environmental, and other benefits of the proposed use;</para><para>(b) Any adverse economic, environmental, and other impacts of the proposed use;</para><para>(c) Any current beneficial uses being made of the unappropriated water;</para><para>(d) The economic, environmental, and other benefits of not allowing the appropriation and preserving the water supply for beneficial uses within the state;</para><para>(e) Alternative sources of water supply available to the applicant; and</para><para>(f) Any other factors consistent with the purposes of this section that the director deems relevant to protecting the interests of the state and its citizens.</para><para>The application shall be deemed in the public interest if the overall benefits to Nebraska are greater than the adverse impacts to Nebraska. The director's order granting or denying an application shall specify the reasons for such action, including a discussion of the required factors for consideration, and shall document such decision by reference to the hearing record, if any, and to any other sources used by the director in making the decision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 161, &#167; 1, p. 504; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 146, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 105. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 