<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-110" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>46-110</statuteno><catchline id="id00">District; organization and officers; election; notice; voters; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) After dividing the proposed irrigation district into divisions, the county board shall give notice of an election to be held in such proposed district, for the purpose of determining whether or not the same shall be organized under the Irrigation District Act. Such notice shall describe the boundaries as established and shall designate a name for such proposed district. The notice shall be published for at least three weeks prior to such election in a newspaper of general circulation in the county; and if any portion of such proposed district lies within another county or counties, then the notice shall be published in a newspaper of general circulation within each of such counties. The notice shall include the contents of the ballots to be cast and the date, time, place, and manner of the election, with instructions and deadlines to request and cast a ballot by mail. The ballot shall contain the words Irrigation district ...... Yes, or Irrigation district ...... No, or words equivalent thereto; and also the names of persons to be voted for to fill various elective offices prescribed in the Irrigation District Act.</para><para>(2) No person shall be entitled to vote at any election held under the Irrigation District Act unless he or she is qualified as an elector as provided in section 46-102. For any election under the Irrigation District Act, status as an elector shall be established by a record date designated by the election commissioner or county clerk for initial organization of the irrigation district or designated by the secretary of the board of directors for all other elections. The record date shall not be more than thirty days prior to the election. After such record date, a person may be allowed to vote when such person establishes his or her status as an elector to the satisfaction of the election commissioner or county clerk for initial organization of the district or to the satisfaction of the secretary of the board of directors for all other elections. The determination of the election commissioner, county clerk, or secretary of the board of directors, as the case may be, shall be conclusive.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 2, p. 271; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 617; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 155, &#167; 1, p. 560; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3458; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 81, &#167; 1, p. 193; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2858; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-102; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 357; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 46-102; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-110; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB561, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>