<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" id="id5" statutenumber="46-294"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>46-294</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Applications; approval;
requirements; conditions; burden of proof.</catchline><para>(1) Except
for applications approved in accordance with subsection (1) of section 46-291,
the Director of Natural Resources shall approve an application filed pursuant
to section 46-290 only if the application and the proposed transfer or change
meet the following requirements:</para>
<para>(a) The application is complete and all other information
requested pursuant to section 46-293 has been provided;</para>
<para>(b) The proposed use of water after the transfer or change
will be a beneficial use of water;</para>
<para>(c)(i) Any requested transfer in the location of use is within
the same river basin as defined in section 46-288 or (ii) the river basin
from which the appropriation is to be transferred is tributary to the river
basin to which the appropriation is to be transferred;</para>
<para>(d) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this
section, the proposed transfer or change, alone or when combined with any
new or increased use of any other source of water at the original location
or within the same irrigation district, reclamation district, public power
and irrigation district, or mutual irrigation or canal company for the original
or other purposes, will not diminish the supply of water available for or
otherwise adversely affect any other water appropriator and will not significantly
adversely affect any riparian water user who files an objection in writing
pursuant to section 46-291;</para>
<para>(e) The quantity of water that is transferred for diversion
or other use at the new location will not exceed the historic consumptive
use under the appropriation or portion thereof being transferred, except that
this subdivision does not apply to (i) a
transfer in the location of use if both the current use and the proposed use
are for irrigation, the number of acres to be irrigated will not increase
after the transfer, and the location of the diversion from the stream will
not change or (ii) a transfer
or change in the purpose of use of a surface water irrigation appropriation
as provided for in subsection (3), (5), or (6) of section 46-290 if the transfer
or change in purpose will not diminish the supply of water available or otherwise
adversely affect any other water appropriator, adversely affect Nebraska's
ability to meet its obligations under a multistate agreement, or result in
administration of the prior appropriation system by the Department of Natural
Resources, which would not have otherwise occurred;</para>
<para>(f) The appropriation, prior to the transfer or change, is
not subject to termination or cancellation pursuant to sections 46-229 to
46-229.04;</para>
<para>(g) If a proposed transfer or change is of an appropriation
that has been used for irrigation and is in the name of an irrigation district,
reclamation district, public power and irrigation district, or mutual irrigation
or canal company or is dependent upon any such district's or company's facilities
for water delivery, such district or company has approved the transfer or
change;</para>
<para>(h) If the proposed transfer or change is of a storage-use
appropriation and if the owner of that appropriation is different from the
owner of the associated storage appropriation, the owner of the storage appropriation
has approved the transfer or change;</para>
<para>(i) If the proposed transfer or change is to be permanent,
either (i) the purpose for which the water is to be used before the transfer
or change is in the same preference category established by section 46-204
as the purpose for which the water is to be used after the transfer or change
or (ii) the purpose for which the water is to be used before the transfer
or change and the purpose for which the water is to be used after the transfer
or change are both purposes for which no preferences are established by section
46-204;</para>
<para>(j) If the proposed transfer or change is to be temporary,
it will be for a duration of no less than one year and, except as provided
in section 46-294.02, no more than thirty years;</para>
<para>(k) The transfer or change will not be inconsistent with any
applicable state or federal law and will not jeopardize the state's compliance
with any applicable interstate water compact or decree or cause difficulty
in fulfilling the provisions of any other formal state contract or agreement;
and</para>
<para>(l) The proposed transfer or change is in the public interest.
The director's considerations relative to the public interest shall include,
but not be limited to, (i) the economic, social, and environmental impacts
of the proposed transfer or change and (ii) whether and under what conditions
other sources of water are available for the uses to be made of the appropriation
after the proposed transfer or change. The Department of Natural Resources
shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to govern the director's
determination of whether a proposed transfer or change is in the public interest.</para>
<para>(2) The applicant has the burden of proving that the proposed
transfer or change will comply with subdivisions (1)(a) through (l) of this
section, except that (a) the burden is on a riparian user to demonstrate his
or her riparian status and to demonstrate a significant adverse effect on
his or her use in order to prevent approval of an application and (b) if both
the current use and the proposed use after a transfer are for irrigation,
the number of acres to be irrigated will not increase after the transfer,
and the location of the diversion from the stream will not change, there is
a rebuttable presumption that the transfer will be consistent with subdivision
(1)(d) of this section.</para>
<para>(3) In approving an application, the director may impose any
reasonable conditions deemed necessary to protect the public interest, to
ensure consistency with any of the other criteria in subsection (1) of this
section, or to provide the department with information needed to properly
and efficiently administer the appropriation while the transfer or change
remains in effect. If necessary to prevent diminution of supply for any other
appropriator, the conditions imposed by the director shall require that historic
return flows be maintained or replaced in quantity, timing, and location.
After approval of any such transfer or change, the appropriation shall be
subject to all water use restrictions and requirements in effect at any new
location of use and, if applicable, at any new diversion location. An appropriation
for which a transfer or change has been approved shall retain the same priority
date as that of the original appropriation. If an approved transfer or change
is temporary, the location of use, purpose of use, or type of appropriation
shall revert to the location of use, purpose of use, or type of appropriation
prior to the transfer or change.</para>
<para>(4) In approving an application for a transfer, the director
may also authorize the overlying of water appropriations on the same lands,
except that if any such overlying of appropriations would result in either
the authorized diversion rate or the authorized aggregate annual quantity
that could be diverted to be greater than is otherwise permitted by section
46-231, the director shall limit the total diversion rate or aggregate annual
quantity for the appropriations overlain to the rate or quantity that he or
she determines is necessary, in the exercise of good husbandry, for the production
of crops on the land involved. The director may also authorize a greater number
of acres to be irrigated if the amount and rate of water approved under the
original appropriation is not increased by the change of location. An increase
in the number of acres to be irrigated shall be approved only if (a) such
an increase will not diminish the supply of water available to or otherwise
adversely affect another water appropriator or (b) the transfer would not
adversely affect the water supply for any river basin, subbasin, or reach
that has been designated as overappropriated pursuant to section 46-713 or
determined to be fully appropriated pursuant to section 46-714 and (i) the
number of acres authorized under the appropriation when originally approved
has not been increased previously, (ii) the increase in the number of acres
irrigated will not exceed five percent of the number of acres being irrigated
under the permit before the proposed transfer or a total of ten acres, whichever
acreage is less, and (iii) all the use will be either on the quarter section
to which the appropriation was appurtenant before the transfer or on an adjacent
quarter section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 21, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 818, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 789, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 135; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB526, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>