  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-145"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-145</statuteno><catchline>Construction of works; notice; bond of contractor; bids; letting.</catchline><para>After adopting a plan of such canal or canals, storage reservoirs, and works, the board of directors shall give notice, by publication thereof not less than twenty days in one newspaper published in each of the counties composing the district, provided a newspaper is published therein, and in such other newspapers as it may deem advisable, calling for bids for the construction of the work or any portion thereof, and if less than the whole work is advertised, then the portion so advertised must be particularly described in such notice. The notice shall set forth that plans and specifications can be seen at the office of the board, and that the board will receive sealed proposals therefor, and that the contract will be let to the lowest responsible bidder, stating the time and place for opening the proposals, which at the time and place shall be opened in public. As soon as convenient thereafter the board shall let such work, either in part or as a whole, to the lowest responsible bidder, or it may reject any or all bids and readvertise for proposals, or may proceed to construct the work under its own superintendence with the labor of the residents of the district. Contracts for the purchase of material shall be awarded to the lowest responsible bidder. The person or persons to whom a contract may be awarded shall enter into a bond with good and sufficient sureties, to be approved by the board payable to such district for its use, to an amount equal to twenty-five percent of the contract price, for the faithful performance of the contract; <emphasis type="italic">Provided, however,</emphasis> in case twenty-five percent of the contract price shall exceed the sum of fifty thousand dollars, then such bond shall be in the sum of fifty thousand dollars. The work shall be done under the direction and to the satisfaction of the engineer and be approved by the board. The provisions of this section shall not apply in the case of any contract between the district and the United States.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 22, p. 285; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 161, &#167; 1, p. 533; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3480; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 7, p. 179; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2880; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-145.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For other provisions for letting of contracts,</emphasis> see Chapter 73.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Provisions must be complied with before board is authorized to proceed with construction. Reasonable value of services, not exceeding contract price, can be recovered under authorized contract of directors, even though same is illegal, where district has received benefit. Lincoln &amp; Dawson County Irr. Dist. v. McNeal, 60 Neb. 613, 83 N.W. 847 (1900).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 