<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-185" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>46-185</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Discontinuance of district; petition; special election; notice; procedure.</catchline><para>Whenever a majority of the assessment payers, representing a majority of the number of acres of irrigable land within any irrigation district, petition the board of directors to call a special election for the purpose of submitting to the electors of such irrigation district a proposition to vote on the discontinuance of such irrigation district and a settlement of its bonded and other indebtedness, the board of directors shall call an election, setting forth the object of the same, and cause a notice of such election to be published in some newspaper of general circulation in each of the counties in which the district is located, for a period of thirty days prior to such election, setting forth the time and place for holding such election in each of the voting precincts in the district, and shall also cause a written or printed notice of such election to be posted in some conspicuous place in each of the voting precincts. The board of directors shall provide ballots to be used at such election on which shall be written or printed the words For discontinuance ..... Yes, and For discontinuance ..... No. The election shall otherwise be conducted in accordance with sections 46-115 to 46-118.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1897, c. 91, &#167;&#167; 1, 2, p. 372; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 625; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3521; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2921; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-166; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-185; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB561, &#167; 11. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>