<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-735"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-735</statuteno><catchline>Construct water well in a management area; permit required; application; form; fee; contents; late permit application; fee.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who intends to construct a water well in a management area in this state on land which he or she owns or controls shall, before commencing construction, apply with the district in which the water well will be located for a permit on forms provided by the district, except that (a) no permit shall be required for test holes or dewatering wells with an intended use of ninety days or less, (b) no permit shall be required for a single water well designed and constructed to pump fifty gallons per minute or less, and (c) a district may provide by rule and regulation that a permit need not be obtained for water wells defined by the district to be replacement water wells. A district may require a permit for a water well designed and constructed to pump fifty gallons per minute or less if such water well is commingled, combined, clustered, or joined with any other water well or wells or other water source, other than a water source used to water range livestock. Such wells shall be considered one water well and the combined capacity shall be used as the rated capacity. A district may by rule and regulation require that a permit be obtained for each water well or for one or more categories of water wells designed and constructed to pump fifty gallons per minute or less, other than a water source required for human needs as it relates to health, fire control, and sanitation or used to water range livestock, in ground water management areas in which regulations have been imposed to control declining ground water levels. Forms shall be made available at each district in which a management area is located, in whole or in part, and at such other places as may be deemed appropriate. The district shall review such application and issue or deny the permit within thirty days after the application is filed.</para><para>(2) A person shall apply for a permit under this section before he or she modifies a water well for which a permit was not required under subsection (1) of this section into one for which a permit would otherwise be required under such subsection.</para><para>(3) The application shall be accompanied by a fifty-dollar filing fee payable to the district and shall contain (a) the name and post office address of the applicant or applicants, (b) the nature of the proposed use, (c) the intended location of the proposed water well or other means of obtaining ground water, (d) the intended size, type, and description of the proposed water well and the estimated depth, if known, (e) the estimated capacity in gallons per minute, (f) the acreage and location by legal description of the land involved if the water is to be used for irrigation, (g) a description of the proposed use if other than for irrigation purposes, (h) the registration number of the water well being replaced if applicable, and (i) such other information as the district requires.</para><para>(4) Any person who has failed or in the future fails to obtain a permit required by subsection (1) or (2) of this section shall make application for a late permit on forms provided by the district.</para><para>(5) The application for a late permit shall be accompanied by a two-hundred-fifty-dollar fee payable to the district and shall contain the same information required in subsection (3) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 577, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 643, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 325, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 375, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 23, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1071, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 894, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 131, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 981, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 145, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1994, &#167; 46-659; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 108, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 870, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 34, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2003, &#167; 46-656.29; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 75. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 