<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-136"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-136</statuteno><catchline>District taxes; collection; payment; medium; fee.</catchline><para>The general fund tax mentioned in section 46-135, shall be collected by the county treasurer at the same time, and in the same manner as all other taxes are collected in this state; <emphasis type="italic">Provided, however,</emphasis> such county treasurer shall receive in payment of the general fund tax, above mentioned, for the year in which such tax is levied, warrants drawn against such general fund, the same as so much lawful money of the United States, if such warrants do not exceed the amount of general fund tax which the person tendering the same owes; and he shall accept payment of the district bond fund tax and issue receipt therefor whenever the same may be tendered, and shall receive in payment of the district bond fund tax, for the year in which such taxes were levied, interest coupons past due issued by such irrigation district the same as so much lawful money of the United States, if such interest coupons do not exceed the amount of the district bond fund which the person tendering the same owes. The county treasurer shall be entitled to a collection fee of one-half of one percent on all money collected, to be deducted from the bond interest fund of the district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1897, c. 86, &#167; 4, p. 362; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 78, &#167; 1, p. 332; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 77, &#167; 1, p. 468; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 142, &#167; 3, p. 346; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3475; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 68, &#167; 1, p. 169; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 5, p. 176; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 110, &#167; 1, p. 270; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2875; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-120; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-136.</para></source><annotation><para>This section provides for the collection of taxes for the general fund of the irrigation district in the same manner as other taxes are collected. Loup County v. Rumbaugh, 151 Neb. 563, 38 N.W.2d 745 (1949).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 