<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-731" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-731</statuteno><catchline>Management area; action plan; director specify controls; when; powers and duties; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The power to specify controls authorized by section 46-739 shall vest in the Director of Environment and Energy if (a) at the end of one hundred eighty days following the designation of a management area or the requiring of an action plan for a management area pursuant to section 46-725, a district encompassed in whole or in part by the management area has not completed and adopted an action plan, (b) a district does not submit a revised action plan within sixty days after denial of its original action plan, or (c) the district submits a revised action plan which is not approved by the director.</para><para>(2) If the power to specify controls in such a management area is vested in the Director of Environment and Energy, he or she shall within ninety days adopt and promulgate by rule and regulation such measures as he or she deems necessary for carrying out the intent of the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act. He or she shall conduct one or more public hearings prior to the adoption of controls. Notice of any such additional hearings shall be given in the manner provided in section 46-743. The enforcement of controls adopted pursuant to this section shall be the responsibility of the Department of Environment and Energy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 894, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 51, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 22; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1993), &#167; 46-674.12; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 108, &#167; 51; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1998), &#167; 46-656.45; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 39. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>