<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-115" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>46-115</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Subsequent elections; manner; notice.</catchline><para>(1) Fifteen days before any election which is not held by mail under the Irrigation District Act subsequent to the organization of the irrigation district, the secretary of the board of directors shall cause notice to be published in a newspaper of general circulation in each county in which the irrigation district lies. The notice shall include the date, time, place, and manner of holding the election. The secretary shall also post a general notice of the same in the office of the board, which shall be established and kept at some fixed place to be determined by the board, specifying the polling places, if any, of each precinct of the irrigation district.</para><para>(2) Each year the board of directors of an irrigation district shall determine whether to hold the subsequent regular election of the irrigation district by mail. The board of directors may determine to hold any other election by mail under the Irrigation District Act if the decision to hold the election by mail is made at least forty-five days prior to the date set for such election. The secretary of the board of directors shall, at least thirty days prior to the date set for the election, mail to the last-known post office address of each elector a ballot which lists the names of the candidates and gives instructions and the deadlines to return the ballot. The secretary shall publish notice of the election by mail in a newspaper of general circulation in each county in which the irrigation district lies. The notice shall include instructions and the deadlines for requesting a ballot and instructions and the deadlines for casting ballots by mail. The notice shall also include the time and place designated for processing and counting the ballots cast by mail.</para><para>(3) Prior to the time for posting the notices, the board of directors shall appoint three residents from each precinct, one clerk and two judges, who shall constitute a board of election for such precinct. If the board of directors fails to appoint a board of election or the members appointed do not attend at the opening of the polls on the morning of election or at the time and place for processing and counting the ballots cast by mail, as the case may be, the electors of the precinct present at that hour may appoint the board. The board of directors must, in its order appointing the board of election, designate the hour and place in the precinct where the election must be held or the time and place for processing and counting the ballots cast by mail, as the case may be.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 5, p. 274; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3461; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2861; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-115; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 148, &#167; 2, p. 596; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB561, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Voting by mail,</emphasis> absentee voters, see sections 32-938 to 32-951.</para><para><emphasis>Voting by mail,</emphasis> special election procedures, see sections 32-952 to 32-959.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>