<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id65">
<sectno id="id66">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" id="id67" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="46-714"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id69">46-714</statuteno><catchline id="id70">River basin, subbasin,
or reach; stay on new appropriations; notifications required; hearing; natural
resources district; duties;
status change; department; natural resources district; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Whenever the Department of Natural Resources makes a preliminary
determination that a river basin, subbasin, or reach not previously designated
as overappropriated and not previously determined to be fully appropriated
has become fully appropriated, the department shall place an immediate stay
on the issuance of any new natural-flow, storage, or storage-use appropriations
in such river basin, subbasin, or reach. The department shall also provide
prompt notice of such preliminary determination to all licensed water well
contractors in the state and to each natural resources district that encompasses
any of the geographic area involved. Such notice to natural resources districts
shall be by certified mail. The notice shall be addressed to the manager of
the natural resources district or his or her designee and shall include the
signature of the Director of Natural Resources. Immediately upon receipt of
such notice by the natural resources district, there shall be a stay on issuance
of water well construction permits in the geographic area preliminarily determined
by the department to include hydrologically connected surface water and ground
water in such river basin, subbasin, or reach. The department shall also notify
the public of the preliminary determination that the river basin, subbasin,
or reach is fully appropriated and of the affected geographic area. Such notice
shall be provided by publication once each week for three consecutive weeks
in at least one newspaper of statewide circulation and in such other newspaper
or newspapers as are deemed appropriate by the department to provide general
circulation in the river basin, subbasin, or reach.</para>
<para>(2) If the department preliminarily determines a river basin,
subbasin, or reach to be fully appropriated and has identified the existence
of hydrologically connected surface water and ground water in such river basin,
subbasin, or reach, stays shall also be imposed:</para>
<para>(a) On the construction of any new water well in the area
covered by the determination unless a permit with conditions imposed by the
natural resources district has been issued prior to the determination. Such
conditions shall meet the objectives of subsection (4) of
section 46-715 and may include, but are not limited to, conditions in accordance
with subsection (6) of section 46-739. Any well constructed pursuant to such
permit shall be completed in accordance with section 46-738; and</para>
<para>(b) On the use of an existing water well or an existing surface
water appropriation in the affected area to increase the number of acres historically
irrigated.</para>
<para>Such additional stays shall begin ten days after the first
publication, in a newspaper of statewide circulation, of the notice of the
preliminary determination that the river basin, subbasin, or reach is fully
appropriated.</para>
<para>(3) Exceptions to the stays imposed pursuant to subsection
(1), (2), (8), or (9) of this section
shall exist for (a) test holes, (b) dewatering wells with an intended use
of one year or less, (c) monitoring wells, (d) wells constructed pursuant
to a ground water remediation plan under the Environmental Protection Act,
(e) water wells designed and constructed to pump fifty gallons per minute
or less, except that no two or more water wells that each pump fifty gallons
per minute or less may be connected or otherwise combined to serve a single
project such that the collective pumping would exceed fifty gallons per minute,
(f) water wells for range livestock, (g) new surface water uses or water wells
that are necessary to alleviate an emergency situation involving the provision
of water for human consumption or public health and safety, (h) water wells
defined by the applicable natural resources district as replacement water
wells, but the consumptive use of any such replacement water well can be no
greater than the historic consumptive use of the water well it is to replace
or, if applicable, the historic consumptive use of the surface water use it
is to replace, (i) new surface water uses and water wells to which a right
or permit is transferred in accordance with state law, but the consumptive
use of any such new use can be no greater than the historic consumptive use
of the surface water use or water well from which the right or permit is being
transferred, (j) water wells and increases in ground water irrigated acres
for which a variance is granted by the applicable natural resources district
for good cause shown, (k) subject to any conditions imposed by the applicable
natural resources district, to the extent permitted by the applicable natural
resources district, increases in ground water irrigated acres that result
from the use of water wells that were permitted prior to the effective date
of the determination made in subsection (1) of this section and completed
in accordance with section 46-738 but were not used for irrigation prior to
that effective date, (l) to the extent permitted by the applicable natural
resources district, increases in ground water irrigated acres that result
from the use of water wells that are constructed after the effective date
of the stay in accordance with a permit granted by that natural resources
district prior to the effective date of the stay, (m) surface water uses for
which temporary public-use construction permits are issued pursuant to subsection
(8) of section 46-233, (n) surface water uses and increases in surface water
irrigated acres for which a variance is granted by the department for good
cause shown, and (o) water wells for which permits have been approved by the
Department of Natural Resources pursuant to the Municipal and Rural Domestic
Ground Water Transfers Permit Act prior to the effective date of the stay.</para>
<para>(4) Except as otherwise provided in this section, any stay
imposed pursuant to subsections (1) and (2) of this section shall remain in
effect for the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach until the department
has made a final determination regarding whether the river basin, subbasin,
or reach is fully appropriated and, if the department's final determination
is that the river basin, subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated, shall remain
in effect as provided in subsection (11) of this section. Within
the time period between the dates of the preliminary and final determinations,
the department and the affected natural resources districts shall consult
with any irrigation district, reclamation district, public power and irrigation
district, mutual irrigation company, canal company, or municipality that relies
on water from the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach and with other
water users and stakeholders as deemed appropriate by the department or the
natural resources districts. The department shall also hold one or more public
hearings not more than ninety days after the first publication of the notice
required by subsection (1) of this section. Notice of the hearings shall be
provided in the same manner as the notice required by such subsection. Any
interested person may appear at such hearing and present written or oral testimony
and evidence concerning the appropriation status of the river basin, subbasin,
or reach, the department's preliminary conclusions about the extent of the
area within which the surface water and ground water supplies for the river
basin, subbasin, or reach are determined to be hydrologically connected, and
whether the stays on new uses should be terminated.</para>
<para>(5) Within thirty days after the final hearing under subsection
(4) of this section, the department shall notify the appropriate natural resources
districts of the department's final determination with respect to the appropriation
status of the river basin, subbasin, or reach. If the final determination
is that the river basin, subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated, the department,
at the same time, shall (a) decide whether to continue or to terminate the
stays on new surface water uses and on increases in the number of surface
water irrigated acres and (b) designate the geographic area within which the
department considers surface water and ground water to be hydrologically connected
in the river basin, subbasin, or reach and describe the methods and criteria
used in making that determination. The department shall provide notice of
its decision to continue or terminate the stays in the same manner as the
notice required by subsection (1) of this section.</para>
<para>(6) Within ninety days after a final determination
by the department that a river basin, subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated,
an affected natural resources district may hold one or more public hearings
on the question of whether the stays on the issuance of new water well permits,
on the construction of new water wells, or on increases in ground water irrigated
acres should be terminated. Notice of the hearings shall be published as provided
in section 46-743.</para>
<para>(7) Within forty-five days
after a natural resources district's final hearing pursuant to subsection (6) of this section, the natural resources district
shall decide (a) whether to terminate the stay on new water wells in all or
part of the natural resources district subject to the stay and (b) whether
to terminate the stay on increases in ground water irrigated acres. If the
natural resources district decides not to terminate the stay on new water
wells in any geographic area, it shall also decide whether to exempt from
such stay the construction of water wells for which permits were issued prior
to the issuance of the stay but for which construction had not begun prior
to issuance of the stay. If construction of water wells for which permits
were issued prior to the stay is allowed, all permits that were valid when
the stay went into effect shall be extended by a time period equal to the
length of the stay.</para>
<para>(8) Whenever the department
designates a river basin, subbasin, or reach as overappropriated, each previously
declared moratorium on the issuance of new surface water appropriations in
the river basin, subbasin, or reach shall continue in effect. The department
shall also provide prompt notice of such designation to all licensed water
well contractors in the state and to each natural resources district that
encompasses any of the geographic area involved. Immediately upon receipt
of such notice by a natural resources district, there shall be a stay on the
issuance of new water well construction permits in any portion of such natural
resources district that is within the hydrologically connected area designated
by the department. The department shall also notify the public of its designation
of such river basin, subbasin, or reach as overappropriated and of the geographic
area involved in such designation. Such notice shall be published once each
week for three consecutive weeks in at least one newspaper of statewide circulation
and in such other newspapers as are deemed appropriate by the department to
provide general notice in the river basin, subbasin, or reach.</para>
<para>(9) Beginning ten days after
the first publication of notice under subsection (8) of
this section in a newspaper of statewide circulation, there shall also be
stays (a) on the construction of any new water well in the hydrologically
connected area if such construction has not commenced prior to such date and
if no permit for construction of the water well has been issued previously
by either the department or the natural resources district, (b) on the use
of an existing water well in the hydrologically connected area to increase
the number of acres historically irrigated, and (c) on the use of an existing
surface water appropriation to increase the number of acres historically irrigated
in the affected area.</para>
<para>(10) Within ninety days after
a designation by the department of a river basin, subbasin, or reach as overappropriated,
a natural resources district that encompasses any of the hydrologically connected
area designated by the department may hold one or more public hearings on
the question of whether to terminate the stays on (a) the construction of
new water wells within all or part of its portion of the hydrologically connected
area, (b) the issuance of new water well construction permits in such area,
or (c) the increase in ground water irrigated acres in such area. Notice of
any hearing for such purpose shall be provided pursuant to section 46-743.
Prior to the scheduling of a natural resources district hearing on the question
of whether to terminate any such stay, the department and the affected natural
resources district shall consult with any irrigation district, reclamation
district, public power and irrigation district, mutual irrigation company,
canal company, or municipality that relies on water from the affected river
basin, subbasin, or reach and with other water users and stakeholders as deemed
appropriate by the department or the natural resources district.</para>
<para>(11) Any stay issued pursuant
to this section shall remain in effect until (a) the stay has been terminated
pursuant to subsection (5), (7),
or (10) of this section, (b) an integrated management plan for
the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach has been adopted by the department
and the affected natural resources districts and has taken effect, (c) an
integrated management plan for the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach
has been adopted by the Interrelated Water Review Board and has taken effect,
(d) the department has completed a reevaluation pursuant to subsection (2)
of section 46-713 and has determined that the affected river basin, subbasin,
or reach is not fully appropriated or overappropriated, or (e) the stay expires
pursuant to this subsection. Such stay may be imposed initially for not more
than three years following the department's designation of the river basin,
subbasin, or reach as overappropriated or the department's final determination
that a river basin, subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated and may be extended
thereafter on an annual basis by agreement of the department and the affected
natural resources district for not more than two additional years if necessary
to allow the development, adoption, and implementation of an integrated management
plan pursuant to sections 46-715 to 46-719.</para>
<para>(12)(a) For purposes
of this subsection, (i) a status change occurs when a preliminary or final
determination that a river basin, subbasin, or reach is fully appropriated
is reversed by the department or by judicial determination and such river
basin, subbasin, or reach is determined not to be fully appropriated and (ii)
the hydrologically connected area means the geographic area within which the
department considers surface water and ground water in such river basin, subbasin,
or reach to be hydrologically connected.</para><para>(b) If a status change occurs, any stays previously
in force by the department or affected natural resources districts shall remain
in force until the stays imposed under this subsection are in place and the
department shall place an immediate stay on the issuance of any new natural-flow,
storage, or storage-use appropriations in the river basin, subbasin, or reach.
The department shall also provide prompt notice of the status change in accordance
with subsection (1) of this section. Immediately upon receipt of the notice
by the affected natural resources district, there shall be stays imposed as
set forth in subsections (1) and (2) of this section, subject to the exceptions
set forth in subsection (3) of this section. The stays imposed pursuant to
this subsection shall remain in effect within each affected natural resources
district until such district adopts rules and regulations in accordance with
subdivision (c), (d), or (e) of this subsection.</para><para>(c) Upon receipt of notice of a
status change, each affected natural resources district shall adopt rules
and regulations within one hundred twenty days after receipt of such notice
for the prioritization and granting of water well permits within the hydrologically
connected area for the four-year period following the status change. Nothing
in this subsection shall be construed to supersede the authority provided
to natural resources districts under subsection (2) of section 46-707 and
subdivisions (1)(f) and (1)(m) of section 46-739.</para><para>(d) The rules and regulations adopted
by each affected natural resources district in accordance with subdivision
(c) of this subsection shall (i) allow a limited number of total new ground
water irrigated acres annually, (ii) be created with the purpose of maintaining
the status of not fully appropriated based on the most recent basin determination,
(iii) be for a term of not less than four years, and (iv) limit the number
of new permits so that total new ground water irrigated acres do not exceed
the number set in the rules and regulations. The department shall approve
the proposed new number of ground water irrigated acres within sixty days
after approval by the natural resources district if such district meets the
conditions set forth in subdivision (d)(ii) of this subsection, based on the
most recent basin determination.</para><para>(e) If the proposed new number of acres is not approved
by the department within the applicable time period as provided in subdivision
(d) of this subsection, the affected natural resources districts shall adopt
rules and regulations that allow water well permits to be issued that will
result in no more than two thousand five hundred irrigated acres or that will
result in an increase of not more than twenty percent of all historically
irrigated acres within the hydrologically connected area of each natural resources
district within the affected river basin, subbasin, or reach, whichever is
less, for each calendar year of the four-year period following the date of
the determination described in this subsection. Each affected natural resources
district may, after the initial four-year period has expired, annually determine
whether water well permit limitations should continue and may enforce such
limitations.</para><para>(f)
During the four-year period following the status change, the department shall
ensure that any new appropriation granted will not cause the basin, subbasin,
or reach to be fully appropriated based on the most recent basin determination.
The department, pursuant to its rules and regulations, shall not issue new
natural flow surface water appropriations for irrigation, within the river
basin, subbasin, or reach affected by the status change, that will result
in a net increase of more than eight hundred thirty-four irrigated acres in
each natural resources district during each calendar year of the four-year
period following the date of the determination described in this subsection.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1226, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB54, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB483, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Environmental Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1532.</para><para><emphasis>Municipal and Rural Domestic Ground Water Transfers Permit Act,</emphasis> see section 46-650.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>