<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="46-2,140"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>46-2,140</statuteno><catchline>Republican River Basin Water Sustainability
Task Force; created; members; meetings; duties; report.</catchline><para>(1)
The Republican River Basin Water Sustainability Task Force is created. The
task force shall consist of twenty-two voting members, and except for the
state agency representatives, the members shall be residents representing
a cross-section of the Republican River basin. The Governor shall appoint
two representatives from each natural resources district in the basin; four
representatives from the irrigation districts in the basin; one representative
each from the University of Nebraska Institute of Agriculture and Natural
Resources, the Game and Parks Commission, the Department of Agriculture, and
the Department of Natural Resources; one representative each from a school
district, a city, a county, and a public power district in the basin; and
two representatives from agriculture-related businesses in the Republican
River basin. The chairperson of the Executive Board of the Legislative Council
shall appoint five ex officio, nonvoting
members from the Legislature, two of whom are residents of the basin, two of whom have a portion of his or her legislative
district in the basin, and one who is the chairperson of the Natural Resources
Committee of the Legislature. For administrative and budgetary purposes only,
the task force shall be housed within the Department of Natural Resources.
Additional advisory support may be requested from appropriate federal and
state agencies. Members of the task force who are not state employees shall
be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in carrying
out their duties as members as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para>
<para>(2) The task force shall meet no less than quarterly and shall hire
a trained facilitator to conduct its meetings. The purposes of the task force
are to define water sustainability for the Republican River basin, develop
and recommend a plan to help reach water sustainability in the basin, and
develop and recommend a plan to help avoid a water-short year in the basin.
The task force shall convene within thirty days after appointment of the members
is completed to elect a chairperson and conduct such other business as deemed
necessary.</para>
<para>(3) The task force shall present a preliminary report to the Governor
and the Legislature on or before May 15, 2011, and a final report before May
15, 2012. This section terminates on June 30, 2012.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1057, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB243, &#167; 1.</para><terminationdate>June 30, 2012</terminationdate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>