<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1,122"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1,122</statuteno><catchline>Bonds issued to discharge judgments or procure surrender of bonds, notes, and warrants; special election required; notice; form and contents; effect of affirmative vote.</catchline><para>The board of directors shall then call a special election. Notice of such election shall be given by posting notice in three public places in each election precinct in the district for at least twenty days and also by publication of such notice in some newspaper published in the county where the office of the board of directors of such district is required to be kept, once a week for at least three successive weeks. Such notice must specify the time of holding the election and that the purpose of the election is to decide for or against the approval of a resolution of the board of directors providing for the issuance of bonds, stating the principal amount, in place of existing indebtedness of the district. The election must be held and the result thereof determined and declared in all respects as nearly as practicable in conformity with the provisions of sections 46-109 to 46-115 governing the election of officers; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> no informalities in conducting such election shall invalidate the same if the election shall have been otherwise fairly conducted. At such election the ballot shall contain the words Bond Resolution ........... Yes, and Bond Resolution ............ No, or words equivalent thereto. If a majority of the votes cast are Bond Resolution ............ Yes, the resolution adopted by the board of directors shall become effective, and the board shall then be authorized to pass such supplemental resolutions and do such acts and things not inconsistent with this section and the resolution as may be necessary or convenient to carry out the provisions of the resolution.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 128, &#167; 9, p. 338; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-186; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-1,122.</para></source></law></legaldoc> 