<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-692"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-692</statuteno><catchline>Wells; measuring devices; cost-share assistance.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Measuring device means any accurate method used to measure total volume of water pumped or diverted annually; and</para><para>(b) Well means a water well to be used for other than domestic purposes which is capable of pumping more than fifty gallons per minute and which is located in the alluvial aquifer of the Republican River Basin as determined and delineated on a map provided by the Department of Natural Resources.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate five hundred thousand dollars each year for FY1998-99, FY1999-00, and FY2000-01 for a cost-share program to install measuring devices on wells in the alluvial aquifer of the Republican River Basin and on surface water diversion works from the Republican River and its tributaries. The money shall be appropriated to a separate account within the Nebraska Soil and Water Conservation Fund for cost sharing on the purchase and installation of measuring devices if every natural resources district covering any portion of the alluvial aquifer of the Republican River Basin has established by October 1, 1998, a program requiring the installation of measuring devices on a minimum of ninety percent of active eligible wells by June 1, 2001, and adopts and promulgates rules and regulations within a reasonable time governing the program.</para><para>(3) To be eligible for cost-share assistance under this section, a surface water diversion works must have a valid surface water appropriation and a well must meet the definition of a well in subsection (1) of this section and the measuring device shall be purchased, installed, and operational by June 1, 2001. If eligible for cost sharing under this section, fifty percent of the cost of purchase and installation of the measuring device, up to a maximum state share of six hundred dollars per well or diversion works, may be provided through the cost-share program.</para><para>(4) Any owner or operator of a well upon which cost-share funds are expended under this section shall be responsible for reporting water use to the natural resources district in which the well is located in a manner prescribed by the natural resources district. Any owner or operator of a surface water diversion works upon which cost-share funds are expended under this section shall be responsible for reporting water use to the Department of Natural Resources in a manner prescribed by the department.</para><para>(5) If the requirements of subsections (2) and (3) of this section have not been met by June 1, 2001, the natural resources district shall remit to the state an amount equal to the cost-share assistance provided to the natural resources district under such subsections. Any owner or operator of a well upon which cost-share funds are expended shall not be responsible for any repayment requirements under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 224. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 