<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="46-2,139"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>46-2,139</statuteno><catchline>Storm Water Management Plan Program;
created; assistance to cities and counties; grants; Department of Environmental
Quality; duties.</catchline><para>The Storm Water Management Plan Program
is created. The purpose of the program is to facilitate and fund the duties
of cities and counties under the federal Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. 1251 et
seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2006, regarding storm water runoff
under the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System requirements. The
Storm Water Management Plan Program shall function as a grant program administered
by the Department of Environmental Quality, using funds appropriated for the
program. The department shall deduct from funds appropriated amounts sufficient
to reimburse itself for its costs of administration of the grant program.
Any city or county when applying for a grant under the program shall have
a storm water management plan approved by the department which meets the requirements
of the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System. Grant applications
shall be made to the department on forms prescribed by the department. Grant
funds shall be distributed by the department as follows:</para>
<para>(1) Not less than eighty percent of the funds available for grants under
this section shall be provided to cities and counties in urbanized areas,
as identified in 77
Federal Register 18652-18669, that apply for grants and meet the
requirements of this section. Grants made pursuant to this subdivision shall
be distributed proportionately based on the population of applicants within
such category, as determined by the most recent federal census update or recount
certified by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census.
For the purpose of distributing grant funds to a county pursuant to this subdivision,
the proportion shall be based on the county population, less the population
of city applicants within that county. Any funds available for grants under
this subdivision and not awarded by the end of a calendar year shall be available
for grants in the following year; and</para>
<para>(2) Not more than twenty percent of the funds available for grants under
this section shall be provided to cities and counties outside of urbanized
areas, as identified in 77
Federal Register 18652-18669, with populations greater than ten
thousand inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal census update
or recount certified by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of
the Census, that apply for grants and meet the requirements of this section.
Grants under this subdivision shall be distributed proportionately based on
the population of applicants within this category as determined by the most
recent federal census update or recount certified by the United States Department
of Commerce, Bureau of the Census. For the purpose of distributing grant funds
to a county pursuant to this subdivision, the proportion shall be based on
the county population, less the population of city applicants within that
county. Any funds available for grants pursuant to this subdivision which
have not been awarded at the end of each calendar year shall be available
for awarding grants pursuant to subdivision (1) of this section.</para>
<para>Any city or county receiving a grant under subdivision (1) or (2) of
this section shall contribute matching funds equal to twenty percent of the
grant amount.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1226, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB530, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB683, &#167; 1.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>