<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-119"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-119</statuteno><catchline>Board; organization; officers; bonds; payment of premiums.</catchline><para>On the first Wednesday following their election, the board of directors shall meet and organize as a board, elect a president from their number and appoint a secretary, treasurer, and assessor. All such offices may be held by one person. When the offices of secretary and treasurer are held by one person he shall give a penal bond in the sum of not less than fifty percent of the general fund levy for the current year, but when the offices of secretary and treasurer are held by separate individuals, then the treasurer shall be required to give bond in the sum of not less than twenty percent of the levy for general fund purposes for the current year. The secretary shall be required to give a penal bond in a sum of not less than thirty percent of the general fund levy for the current year, but the board of directors may increase the amount of either or both of such bonds in such an amount as it may think necessary. All of such bonds shall be approved by the directors of the district; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that the district shall pay the cost of such bonds.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 9, p. 276; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 156, &#167; 1, p. 565; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 158, &#167; 1, p. 524; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3465; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 69, &#167; 2, p. 172; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 82, &#167; 1, p. 194; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2865; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 97, &#167; 2, p. 246; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 142, &#167; 1, p. 385; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-109; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-119.</para></source></law></legaldoc> 