<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-116" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>46-116</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Election officers; powers and duties; hours of election.</catchline><para>(1) One of the judges shall be chairperson of the board of election and may (a) administer all oaths required in the progress of an election under the Irrigation District Act and (b) appoint judges and clerks, if during the progress of the election or processing and counting ballots cast by mail, as the case may be, any judge or clerk ceases to act. Any member of the board of election, or any clerk thereof, may administer and certify oaths required to be administered during the progress of an election or the processing and counting of ballots cast by mail, as the case may be. Before opening the polls or processing and counting ballots cast by mail, each member of the board of election must take and subscribe to an oath to faithfully perform the duties imposed upon him or her by law. Any elector of the precinct may administer and certify such oath.</para><para>(2) For elections other than those conducted by mail, the polls must be opened at 8 a.m. on the morning of the election and be kept open until 6 p.m. of the same day, except that in districts embracing twelve thousand acres or less, the polls may, by direction of the board of directors, be opened at 1 p.m. and be kept open until 5:30 p.m. of the same day.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 70, &#167; 6, p. 274; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 22, &#167; 1, p. 94; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3462; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2862; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 46-106; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 46-116; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB561, &#167; 7. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>