<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-691"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-691</statuteno><catchline>Transfer off overlying land; when allowed; objection; procedure; natural resources district; powers and duties; Director of Natural Resources; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person who withdraws ground water for agricultural purposes, or for any purpose pursuant to a ground water remediation plan as required under the Environmental Protection Act, including the providing of water for domestic purposes, from aquifers located within the State of Nebraska may transfer the use of the ground water off the overlying land if the ground water is put to a reasonable and beneficial use within the State of Nebraska and is used for an agricultural purpose, or for any purpose pursuant to a ground water remediation plan as required under the Environmental Protection Act, including the providing of water for domestic purposes, after transfer, and if such withdrawal, transfer, and use (a) will not significantly adversely affect any other water user, (b) is consistent with all applicable statutes and rules and regulations, and (c) is in the public interest. The determination made by a natural resources district under subsection (2) of this section or the Director of Natural Resources under subsection (3) of this section shall include consideration of the factors set forth in subdivisions (1) through (7) of section 46-613.01. For purposes of this section, domestic has the same meaning as in section 46-613.</para><para>(2) Any affected party may object to the transfer of ground water by filing written objections, specifically stating the grounds for such objection, in the office of the natural resources district containing the land from which the ground water is withdrawn. Upon the filing of such objections or on its own initiative, the natural resources district shall conduct a preliminary investigation to determine if the withdrawal, transfer, and use of ground water is consistent with the requirements of subsection (1) of this section. Following the preliminary investigation, if the district has reason to believe that the withdrawal, transfer, or use may not comply with any rule or regulation of the district, it may utilize its authority under the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act to prohibit such withdrawal, transfer, or use. If the district has reason to believe that the withdrawal, transfer, and use is consistent with all rules and regulations of the district but may not comply with one or more other requirements of subsection (1) of this section, the district shall request that the Department of Natural Resources hold a hearing on such transfer.</para><para>(3) At the hearing, all interested persons may appear and present testimony. Agencies or political subdivisions of this state and the appropriate natural resources districts shall offer as evidence any information in their possession which they deem relevant to the purposes of the hearing. After the hearing, if the Director of Natural Resources finds that the withdrawal, transfer, or use of ground water is contrary to the requirements of subsection (1) of this section, he or she shall issue a cease and desist order prohibiting the withdrawal and transfer.</para><para>(4) The director may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 251, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 223; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 619, &#167; 14. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Environmental Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1532.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 46-701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Only parties who are affected by the transfer of ground water off overlying land for agricultural purposes or pursuant to a water remediation plan, as required under the Environmental Protection Act, may object to such transfer by the procedures outlined in subsection (2) of this section. Upon an objection to the transfer of ground water pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, a natural resources district shall conduct an investigation to determine whether the transfer of water complained of by the objector, which objectionable transfer must be for agricultural purposes or pursuant to a water remediation plan as required under the Environmental Protection Act, is consistent with the requirements of subsection (1) of this section that the transfer (a) will not significantly adversely affect any other water user, (b) is consistent with all applicable statutes and rules and regulations, and (c) is in the public interest. In re Referral of Lower Platte South NRD, 261 Neb. 90, 621 N.W.2d 299 (2001).</para><para>The Legislature's purpose in enacting this section was to carve out two exceptions from Nebraska's common-law prohibition against transfers of water off overlying land: (1) for agricultural purposes and (2) pursuant to a remediation plan under the Environmental Protection Act. In re Referral of Lower Platte South NRD, 261 Neb. 90, 621 N.W.2d 299 (2001).</para><para>According to the legislative history of LB 251, later codified as this section, the Legislature manifested an intent to validate agreements made before the bill's passage to transfer ground water off overlying land for agricultural purposes by failing to void such preexisting transfers. Springer v. Kuhns, 6 Neb. App. 115, 571 N.W.2d 323 (1997).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 