
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1217"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1217</statuteno><catchline>Water Well Standards and Contractors' Licensing Board; created; members; qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) There is hereby created a Water Well Standards and Contractors' Licensing Board. The board shall be composed of ten members, six of whom shall be appointed by the Governor as follows: (a) A licensed water well contractor representing irrigation water well contractors, (b) a licensed water well contractor representing domestic water well contractors, (c) a licensed water well contractor representing municipal and industrial water well contractors, (d) a licensed pump installation contractor, (e) a manufacturer or supplier of water well or pumping equipment, and (f) a holder of a license issued under the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act employed by a natural resources district. The chief executive officer of the Department of Health and Human Services or his or her designated representative, the Director of Environment and Energy or his or her designated representative, the Director of Natural Resources or his or her designated representative, and the director of the Conservation and Survey Division of the University of Nebraska or his or her designated representative shall also serve as members of the board.</para><para>(2) Each member shall be a resident of the state. Each industry representative shall have had at least five years of experience in the business of his or her category prior to appointment and shall be actively engaged in such business at the time of appointment and while serving on the board. Each member representing a category subject to licensing under the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act shall be licensed by the department pursuant to such act. In making appointments, the Governor may consider recommendations made by the trade associations of each category.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 310, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 131, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 266; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 235; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 508, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1155; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 48. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Provisions regarding Water Well Standards and Contractors' Licensing Board,</emphasis> see sections 38-151, 38-155, and 38-158 to 38-174.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>