<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1662"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1662</statuteno><catchline>Periodic inspections; when; Chief Water Officer; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) During the construction, reconstruction, enlargement, alteration, breach, removal, or abandonment of any dam, the Chief Water Officer may make periodic inspections for the purpose of ascertaining compliance with the approved plans and specifications. The Chief Water Officer shall require the owner to direct the design engineer to provide adequate supervision during construction, reconstruction, enlargement, alteration, breach, removal, or abandonment and to provide sufficient information to enable the Chief Water Officer to determine that conformity with the approved plans and specifications is being attained.</para><para>(2) If, after any inspection or investigation, during the construction, reconstruction, enlargement, alteration, breach, removal, or abandonment of a dam or at any time prior to issuance of an approval to operate, it is found by the Chief Water Officer that modifications or changes are necessary to ensure the safety of the dam, the Chief Water Officer shall order the owner to revise his or her plans and specifications. The owner may, pursuant to section 46-1645, request an independent consulting board to review the order of the Chief Water Officer.</para><para>(3) If at any time during construction, reconstruction, enlargement, alteration, breach, removal, or abandonment of any dam, the Chief Water Officer finds that the work is not being done in accordance with the approved plans and specifications, the Chief Water Officer shall deliver a written notice of noncompliance to the owner. The notice shall be delivered by registered mail or by personal service to the owner, shall state the particulars in which the approved plans and specifications are not being or have not been complied with, and shall order immediate compliance with the approved plans and specifications. The Chief Water Officer may order that no further work be done until such compliance has been effected and approved by the department.</para><para>(4) Failure to comply with the notice delivered under subsection (3) of this section may cause revocation of application approval by the Chief Water Officer. If compliance with the notice has not occurred within sixty days after the date of the notice, the Chief Water Officer shall order the incomplete structure removed sufficiently to eliminate any safety hazard to life.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 335, &#167; 62; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB317, &#167; 300. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>