<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id30">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" id="id32" statutenumber="46-1121"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1121</statuteno><catchline id="id35">Fees; Chemigation
Costs Fund; created; investment; annual permits; renewal.</catchline><para>(1)
To aid in defraying the cost of administration of the Nebraska Chemigation
Act, the district shall collect an initial application fee for a permit, a
special permit fee, an annual renewal fee, and an emergency permit fee. The
fees shall be established by the district and shall be sufficient to cover
the ongoing administrative costs and the costs of annual inspection programs
by the district and department. The fees collected pursuant to this section
shall be established by the district in the amount necessary to pay reasonable
costs of administering the permit program pursuant to the act. The fee for
a permit and special permit shall not exceed one hundred fifty dollars. The
fee for a renewal permit shall not exceed one hundred dollars. The fees for
an emergency permit under section 46-1119 shall not exceed five hundred dollars.
The district shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations establishing
a fee schedule to be paid to the district by a person or persons applying
for a permit to operate a chemigation system.</para><para>(2) The fee for initial application
for a permit or special permit shall be payable to the district. For each
permit, five dollars shall be paid by the district to the department.</para>
<para>(3) The annual fee for
renewal of a permit or special permit shall be payable to the district. For
each permit, two dollars of the annual fee shall be paid by the district to
the department.</para><para>(4) All fees shall be used by the district and
the department to administer the Nebraska Chemigation Act. The department's
fee shall be credited to the Chemigation Costs Fund which is hereby created.
All fees collected by the department pursuant to the act shall be remitted
to the State Treasurer for credit to the fund. Transfers may be made from
the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money
in the Chemigation Costs Fund available for investment shall be invested by
the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act
and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(5) All permits issued pursuant
to sections 46-1117 and 46-1117.01 shall be annual permits and shall expire
each year on June 1. A permit may be renewed each year upon payment of the
annual renewal fee and completion of a form provided by the district which
lists the names of all chemicals used in chemigation the previous year. Once
a permit has expired, it shall not be reinstated without meeting all of the
requirements for a new permit including an inspection and payment of the initial
application fee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 284, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 146, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1046, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB272, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>