<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1667"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1667</statuteno><catchline>Notice of violation; orders; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) If the department has reason to believe that an owner or other person is violating or has violated the Safety of Dams and Reservoirs Act, an application approval, an approval to operate, a rule, a regulation, an order, or a requirement of the department issued or adopted pursuant to the act, the department shall give the owner or person written notice by certified mail that the owner or person appears to be in violation of the act. The owner or other person shall have thirty days from the mailing of such notice to respond or to request a hearing before the department as to why the owner or other person should not be ordered to cease and desist from the violation. The notice shall inform the owner or other person how to request the hearing and the consequences of failure to request a hearing.</para><para>(2) If the department finds that an owner or person is constructing, reconstructing, enlarging, altering, breaching, removing, or abandoning a dam without having first obtained the required application approval, the department shall issue a temporary order for the owner or person to cease and desist the construction, reconstruction, enlargement, alteration, breach, removal, or abandonment pending final action by the department pursuant to subsection (3) of this section. The temporary order shall include written notice by certified mail to the owner or person of the time and date set by the department for a hearing to show cause why the temporary order should be vacated.</para><para>(3) After a response to a notice or a hearing pursuant to subsection (1) or (2) of this section or after the expiration of time to request a hearing, the department shall issue a decision and final order. The decision and final order may take such form as the department determines to be reasonable and appropriate and may include a determination of violation, a cease and desist order, the recommendation of a civil penalty, and an order directing that positive steps be taken to abate or ameliorate any harm or damage arising from the violation. The owner or person affected may appeal the hearing decision as provided in section 61-207.</para><para>(4) If the owner or person continues the violation after the department has issued a final decision and order pursuant to subsection (3) of this section or a temporary order pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the department may apply for a temporary restraining order or preliminary or permanent injunction from a court of competent jurisdiction. A decision to seek injunctive relief does not preclude other forms of relief or enforcement against the violator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 335, &#167; 67. </para></source></law></legaldoc>