  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1138"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1138</statuteno><catchline>Violation of act; procedures for compliance; prosecuting attorney; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any person found by the district to be in violation of the Nebraska Chemigation Act or any rules and regulations issued pursuant to the act shall be notified by the district of such violation. Each person so notified by the district shall have ten days in which to comply. The district shall make every reasonable effort to obtain voluntary compliance. Voluntary compliance shall not preclude the district, department, Attorney General, or county attorney from pursuing penalties in the proper court of law based on violations of the act or the rules and regulations. If after such ten-day period the violation has not been corrected, the district shall notify the department of the violation. The department shall make a preliminary investigation. If after such investigation the department determines that there is a violation of the act or rules and regulations, the district or the department shall either revoke the person's chemigation permit until such time as there is satisfactory compliance or issue an order suspending operation of the chemigation system until the required permit is obtained.</para><para>(2) The district or department may apply for a restraining order, a temporary or permanent injunction, or a mandatory injunction against the person or persons violating or threatening to violate the Nebraska Chemigation Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under such act to the district court of the county where the violation is occurring or is about to occur. The court shall have jurisdiction to grant such relief upon good cause shown. Relief may be granted notwithstanding the existence of any other remedy at law and shall be granted without bond.</para><para>(3) If the violation of the Nebraska Chemigation Act occurs with respect to a permitted system, a schedule for compliance may be established by the district in lieu of the ten-day compliance requirement.</para><para>(4) It shall be the duty of the Attorney General or the county attorney of the county in which such violation occurs or is about to occur, when notified of such violation or threatened violation, to cause appropriate proceedings under this section to be instituted and pursued without delay.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 284, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 619, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 