<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1229"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1229</statuteno><catchline>License required; application; qualifications; existing rules, regulations, licenses, forms of approval, suits, other proceedings; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) Any person desiring to engage in the construction of water wells, the installation of pumps and pumping equipment, or the decommissioning of water wells shall make initial application for a license to the department in accordance with rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act. A license to engage in the construction or decommissioning of water wells or the installation of pumps and pumping equipment shall be issued to every applicant who demonstrates professional competence by successfully passing the examination prescribed in section 46-1223 and otherwise complies with the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act and all standards, rules, and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act. Applicants shall receive licenses for any category or combination of categories for which they have successfully passed the required examination.</para><para>(2) The department, with the approval of the board, shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing application for and issuance and renewal of licenses required pursuant to this section and fees pursuant to section 46-1224.</para><para>(3) All rules and regulations adopted prior to July 1, 2021, under the Uniform Credentialing Act and the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act shall continue to be effective to the extent not in conflict with the changes made by Laws 2021, LB148.</para><para>(4) All licenses or other forms of approval issued prior to July 1, 2021, in accordance with the Uniform Credentialing Act and the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act shall remain valid as issued for purposes of the changes made by Laws 2021, LB148, unless revoked or otherwise terminated by law.</para><para>(5) Any suit, action, or other proceeding, judicial or administrative, which was lawfully commenced prior to July 1, 2021, under the Uniform Credentialing Act and the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act shall be subject to the provisions of the acts as they existed prior to July 1, 2021.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 310, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 122; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 242, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1164; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB148, &#167; 64. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>