<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1233"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1233</statuteno><catchline>Water well construction or decommissioning; equipment installation or repair; supervision required.</catchline><para>(1) Any person constructing a water well, installing or repairing pumps onsite, or decommissioning a water well shall do such work in accordance with the rules and regulations developed under the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act.</para><para>(2) A water well shall be constructed, pumps and pumping equipment shall be installed and repaired onsite, and water wells shall be decommissioned by a licensed contractor or supervisor or a person working directly under the supervision of a licensed contractor or supervisor, except that an individual may construct a water well or install and repair pumps and pumping equipment onsite on land owned by him or her and used by him or her for farming, ranching, or agricultural purposes or as his or her place of abode. No water well shall be opened or the seal broken by any person other than an owner of the water well unless (a) the opening or breaking of the seal is carried out by a licensed water well monitoring technician or a licensed natural resources ground water technician, (b) the opening or breaking of the seal is carried out by a licensed operator of a public water system in the course of his or her employment or someone under his or her supervision, or (c) a state electrical inspector in the course of his or her employment.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, supervision means the ready availability of the person licensed pursuant to the Water Well Standards and Contractors' Practice Act for consultation and direction of the activities of any person not licensed who assists in the construction of a water well, the installation of pumps and pumping equipment, or decommissioning of a water well. Contact with the licensed contractor or supervisor by telecommunication shall be sufficient to show ready availability.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 310, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1241, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 667, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1167.</para></source></law></legaldoc>