
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1117</statuteno><catchline>Permit required; exception; application.</catchline>
<para>No person
shall apply or authorize the application of chemicals to land or crops through
the use of chemigation unless such person obtains a permit from the district
in which the well or diversion is located, except that nothing in this section
shall require a person to obtain a chemigation permit to pump or divert water
to or through an open discharge system. Any person
who intends to engage in chemigation shall, before commencing, file with the
district an application for a chemigation permit for each injection location
on forms provided by the department or
by the district. Upon request, forms shall
be made available by the department to each district office and at such other
places as may be deemed appropriate. Except as provided in section 46-1119, the district shall
review each application, conduct an inspection, and approve or deny the application
within forty-five days after the application is filed. An application shall
be approved and a permit issued by the district if the irrigation distribution
system complies with the equipment requirements of section 46-1127 and the
applicator has been certified as a chemigation applicator under sections 46-1128
and 46-1129. A copy of each approved application or the information contained in the application
shall be maintained by the district and provided to the department upon request.
This section shall not be construed to prevent the use of portable chemigation
equipment if such equipment meets the requirements of section 46-1127.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 284, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB2, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB28, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
