<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1652"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1652</statuteno><catchline>Construction or enlargement of dam; application for approval; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Construction of any new dam or the enlargement of any dam shall not commence until the owner has applied for and obtained from the department written application approval of plans and specifications.</para><para>(2) A separate application for each dam shall be filed with the department upon forms provided by the department. Plans and specifications signed and sealed by the design engineer shall accompany the application.</para><para>(3) The application shall provide the following information:</para><para>(a) The name and address of the owner;</para><para>(b) The name and address of the applicant, if different from the owner;</para><para>(c) The name and address of the operator or other person to be contacted regarding arrangements for inspections or other matters associated with the dam;</para><para>(d) The location, type, size, purpose, and height of the proposed dam;</para><para>(e) The reservoir surface areas and associated storage capacity at elevation intervals not exceeding two feet;</para><para>(f) Plans for proposed permanent instrument installations in the dam;</para><para>(g) The area of the drainage basin, rainfall records, streamflow records, and flood flow records and estimates, if available;</para><para>(h) Maps and design drawings showing plans, elevations, and sections of all principal structures and appurtenant works with other features of the project in sufficient detail, including design analyses, to determine safety, adequacy, and suitability of design;</para><para>(i) The estimated construction cost of the dam; and</para><para>(j) Such other pertinent information as the department requires.</para><para>(4) The department may, when in its judgment it is necessary, also require the following:</para><para>(a) Data concerning subsoil and rock foundation conditions and the materials involved in the construction of the dam;</para><para>(b) Investigations of, and reports on, subsurface conditions, exploratory pits, trenches and adits, drilling, coring, and geophysical tests to measure in place and in the laboratory the properties and behavior of foundation materials at the dam site;</para><para>(c) Investigations and reports on the geology of the dam site, possible geologic hazards, seismic activity, faults, weak seams and joints, availability and quality of construction materials, and other pertinent features; and</para><para>(d) Other appropriate information.</para><para>(5) If an application is incomplete or defective, it shall be returned to the applicant to complete or to correct the defects. The application shall be corrected and returned to the department within ninety days after it is returned to the applicant or within such additional time as may be allowed by the department. If the application is returned to the department after expiration of such time period, it shall be dismissed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 335, &#167; 52. </para></source></law></legaldoc>