<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation and Regulation of Water" statutenumber="46-1404" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1404</statuteno><catchline>Water Well Decommissioning Fund; allocation; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>The Water Well Decommissioning Fund shall be allocated by contractual agreement with natural resources districts for the purpose of accelerating the decommissioning of illegal water wells throughout the state. The allocations each fiscal year shall be made by the Department of Natural Resources to natural resources districts in a proportion based on the number of illegal water wells decommissioned in each district in the previous fiscal year which were part of the district's cost-share program to the total number of illegal water wells decommissioned in the state in the previous fiscal year which were part of a district cost-share program. Subsequent allocations for any district which has had a cost-share program for three or more consecutive years shall be based upon the previous three-year average. The allocations may be adjusted on or after March 1 of any year if the Director of Natural Resources determines that one or more districts cannot reasonably be expected to use their full allocation for that fiscal year. Actual disbursement to each district shall be on a reimbursement basis and shall not exceed the amount expended by the district consistent with sections 46-1401 to 46-1405. The Nebraska Natural Resources Commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out such sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 981, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 239; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 508, &#167; 9.</para></source></law></legaldoc>