<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1126"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1126</statuteno><catchline>Permit denial, suspension, or revocation; procedures; suspend operation; when.</catchline><para>(1) Before a district denies, refuses to renew, suspends, or revokes a permit, it shall send to the applicant or permitholder a notice setting forth the specific reasons for the proposed action. The denial, refusal to renew, suspension, or revocation shall become final ten calendar days after mailing of the notice unless such person, within such ten-day period, gives the district written notice of a request for a hearing. If such request is made, the applicant or permitholder shall be given an opportunity for a hearing before the board of directors of the district and shall have the right to present evidence on his or her own behalf. On the basis of the evidence presented, the proposed action shall be affirmed or set aside. A copy of such decision setting forth the findings of fact and the specific reasons upon which it is based shall be sent to the applicant or permitholder.</para><para>(2) If the district or department concludes that there is or may be an actual or imminent threat of danger to persons or the environment by the operation of a chemigation system, the district or department shall immediately order suspension of the operation of the system. Any aggrieved person may, within ten days of receipt of an order of suspension pursuant to this section, request a hearing on such order. The hearing shall be held within ten days of receipt of the request. The district or department shall give written notice of the hearing by certified or registered mail or by personal service to the permitholder, applicator, or person responsible for the operation of the chemigation system. The district or department shall issue an order addressing the matters raised at the hearing within ten days after the hearing.</para><para>If the district or department concludes that the suspension should be continued, the district or department may, if necessary, apply for a restraining order or a temporary or permanent injunction against the permitholder, applicator, or person responsible for the operation of the chemigation system pursuant to the procedure prescribed by section 46-1138.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 284, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 619, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 