  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Irrigation And Regulation Of Water" statutenumber="46-1506"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>46-1506</statuteno><catchline>Boundaries of wellhead protection area; designation; procedure.</catchline><para>Within sixty days after the last time for public comment under section 46-1505, the controlling entity shall make a final designation of the boundaries of the wellhead protection area and the controls necessary to protect the water in the wellhead protection area and shall submit them to the director for approval or disapproval. Such approval shall be based on whether the boundaries of the wellhead protection area are reasonably defined, the controls are reasonably related to the purpose of ground water protection in the area, and such approval is in the public interest. The director shall act on the proposed designation of boundaries and proposed controls within ninety days after the date the proposals are received by him or her.</para><para>If the director approves the proposed boundaries and controls, he or she shall so notify the controlling entity, but the boundaries and controls shall not be deemed effective until the controlling entity has adopted such boundaries and controls by ordinance or resolution. If the director disapproves either or both of the proposals, he or she shall return the proposals to the controlling entity with an explanation of the reasons for such disapproval. The controlling entity may revise such proposed designation of boundaries and proposed controls and, after notice and hearing as provided for in the original proposed designation of boundaries and proposed controls, submit the revised proposed designation of boundaries and proposed controls to the director for approval or disapproval.</para><para>If the director does not act on either the original or revised proposed designation of boundaries and proposed controls within ninety days after submission by the controlling entity, the proposed designation of boundaries and proposed controls shall be deemed approved by the director.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 1161, &#167; 7. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 