<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id928" statutenumber="86-127"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>86-127</statuteno><catchline id="id931">Nebraska Competitive Telephone Marketplace Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) One of the goals of the federal Telecommunications Act of 1996, as such act existed on January 1, 2002, is to foster competition among telephone companies. Section 271 of the federal act (a) establishes specific incentives, procedures, and requirements for regional Bell operating companies to offer inter-LATA interexchange service and (b) requires the Public Service Commission to monitor the competitive performance of a regional Bell operating company and to consult with the Federal Communications Commission regarding such activities.</para><para>(2) The Nebraska Competitive Telephone Marketplace Fund is created. The Public Service Commission may accept, and the fund shall consist of, any voluntary performance payments received from a regional Bell operating company. The fund shall be used by the commission for expenses related to the monitoring of compliance with section 271 of the federal act. If money in the fund exceeds thirty thousand dollars, the commission shall remit such excess money to the State Treasurer for credit to the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund, except that transfers may be made from the Nebraska Competitive Telephone Marketplace Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Nebraska Competitive Telephone Marketplace Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1211, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB755, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB992, &#167; 11. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Certificates for inter-LATA interexchange services,</emphasis> see section 86-129.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>