<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-514"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-514</statuteno><catchline>University of Nebraska; Legislature; exemptions.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that the University of Nebraska, as the state's only public university, has unique needs and requirements in the area of information technology relating to the university's academic research mission. Accordingly, the Legislature intends that sections 86-512 to 86-524 shall not limit the authority of the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska to make decisions about policies, purchases, and uses of information technology related to its academic research mission. For purposes of this section, academic research mission means those specific activities or programs of the university which are undertaken as a part of sponsored or grant-supported activities, organized research projects, or other similar activities intended to produce one or more research outcomes and conducted by employees of the university or other entities, including, but not limited to, research divisions, bureaus, institutes, and experimental stations. Academic research mission does not include the administrative activities of the university, instruction of students, or services provided by the university to communities when not conducted in the context of research outcomes.</para><para>(2) The Legislature finds that, as a separate branch of government, the Legislature must perform its functions independently of other branches. Accordingly, the Legislature shall not be limited by the provisions and requirements of sections 86-512 to 86-524. However the Legislature reserves the right to use the resources established by such sections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1503; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 284. </para></source></law></legaldoc>