<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id191">
<sectno id="id192" opdate="April 15, 2010">Sec. 41.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id193" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-520"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id195">86-520</statuteno><catchline id="id196">Chief Information
Officer; duties.</catchline><para>The Chief Information Officer
shall:</para>
<para>(1) Maintain, in cooperation with the Department of Administrative
Services, an inventory of noneducation state government technology assets,
including hardware, applications, and data bases;</para>
<para>(2) Recommend policies and guidelines for acceptable and
cost-effective use of information technology in noneducation state government;</para>
<para>(3) Advise the Governor and Legislature on policy issues
affecting noneducation state government related to information technology;</para>
<para>(4) Coordinate efforts among other noneducation state government
technology agencies and coordinating bodies;</para>
<para>(5) Implement a strategic, tactical, and project planning
process for noneducation state government information technology that is linked
to the budget process;</para>
<para>(6) Assist the budget division of the Department of Administrative
Services and Legislative Fiscal Analyst in evaluating technology-related budget
requests;</para>
<para>(7) Work with each governmental department and noneducation
state agency to evaluate and act upon opportunities to more efficiently and
effectively deliver government services through the use of information technology;</para>
<para>(8) Recommend to the Governor and Legislature methods for
improving the organization and management of data by noneducation agencies
to achieve the goals of making information sharable and reusable, eliminating
redundancy of data and programs, improving the quality and usefulness of data,
and improving access to data, and implement such recommendations as the Governor
or Legislature may direct;</para>
<para>(9) Monitor the status of major noneducation state government
technology projects;</para>
<para>(10) Establish and maintain Network Nebraska pursuant to
section 86-5,100;</para>
<para>(11) Apply in aggregate for
reimbursements from the federal Universal Service Fund pursuant to section
254 of the Telecommunications Act of 1996, 47 U.S.C. 254, as such section
existed on January 1, 2006, on behalf of school districts requesting to be
included in such aggregated application;</para>
<para>(12) Administer such funds
as may be appropriated to the Chief Information Officer by the Legislature;</para>
<para>(13) Monitor the status of
information technology projects that are enterprise projects;</para>
<para>(14) Collect information from
state agencies, boards, and commissions as provided in section 86-524.01;
and</para>
<para>(15) Complete other tasks
as assigned by the Governor.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1510; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 290; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 41.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>