<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id72"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id74"  statutenumber="86-527"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id76">86-527</statuteno><catchline id="id77">Information Technology Infrastructure Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Information Technology Infrastructure Fund is hereby created. The fund shall contain revenue from the special privilege tax as provided in section 77-2602, gifts, grants, and such other money as is appropriated or transferred by the Legislature. The fund shall be used to attain the goals and priorities identified in the statewide technology plan. The fund shall be administered by the office of Chief Information Officer. Expenditures shall be made from the fund to finance the operations of the Information Technology Infrastructure Act in accordance with the appropriations made by the Legislature. Transfers from the fund to the General Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Information Technology Infrastructure Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1190, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1349, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2000, &#167; 81-1195; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 297; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 408, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 921, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc>
