<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id00" statutenumber="86-324"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-324</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund; created; use; investment; commission; powers and duties; administrative fine.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) The Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund is hereby created. The fund shall provide the assistance necessary to make universal access to telecommunications services available to all persons in the state consistent with the policies set forth in the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act. Only eligible telecommunications companies designated by the commission shall be eligible to receive support to serve high-cost areas from the fund. A telecommunications company that receives such support shall use that support only for the provision, maintenance, and upgrading of facilities and services for which the support is intended. Any such support should be explicit and sufficient to achieve the purpose of the act.</para><para id="id00">(2) Notwithstanding the provisions of section 86-124, in addition to other provisions of the act, and to the extent not prohibited by federal law, the commission:</para><para id="id00">(a) Shall have authority and power to subject eligible telecommunications companies to service quality, customer service, and billing regulations. Such regulations shall apply only to the extent of any telecommunications services or offerings made by an eligible telecommunications company which are eligible for support by the fund. The commission shall be reimbursed from the fund for all costs related to drafting, implementing, and enforcing the regulations and any other services provided on behalf of customers pursuant to this subdivision;</para><para id="id00">(b) Shall have authority and power to issue orders carrying out its responsibilities and to review the compliance of any eligible telecommunications company receiving support for continued compliance with any such orders or regulations adopted pursuant to the act;</para><para id="id00">(c) May withhold all or a portion of the funds to be distributed from any telecommunications company failing to continue compliance with the commission's orders or regulations;</para><para>(d) Shall withhold support distributed from the fund from any telecommunications company using or providing any communications equipment or service deemed to pose a threat to national security identified on the Covered List developed pursuant to 47 C.F.R. 1.50002, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2023, and published by the Public Safety and Homeland Security Bureau of the Federal Communications Commission pursuant to the federal Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019, 47 U.S.C. 1601 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2023, and the rules adopted pursuant to such act by the Federal Communications Commission on November 11, 2022, in its Report and Order FCC 22-84. Any telecommunications company that removes, discontinues, or replaces any communications equipment or service identified on the Covered List described in this subdivision in compliance with federal law shall not be required to obtain any additional permits from any state agency or political subdivision in the removal, discontinuance, or replacement of such communications equipment or service as long as the state agency or political subdivision is properly notified of the necessary replacements and the replacement of any communications equipment is similar to the existing communications equipment;</para><para id="id00">(e) Shall require every telecommunications company to contribute to any universal service mechanism established by the commission pursuant to state law. The commission shall require, as reasonably necessary, an annual audit of any telecommunications company to be performed by a third-party certified public accountant to insure the billing, collection, and remittance of a surcharge for universal service. The costs of any audit required pursuant to this subdivision shall be paid by the telecommunications company being audited;</para><para id="id00">(f) Shall require an audit of information provided by a telecommunications company to be performed by a third-party certified public accountant for purposes of calculating universal service fund payments to such telecommunications company. The costs of any audit required pursuant to this subdivision shall be paid by the telecommunications company being audited; and</para><para id="id00">(g) May administratively fine pursuant to section 75-156 any person who violates the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(4)(a) Transfers may be made from earnings on the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund to the 211 Cash Fund or the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature.</para><para>(b) The State Treasurer shall transfer one million two hundred seventy-five thousand dollars on July 1, 2023, from the earnings on the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund to the 211 Cash Fund. The State Treasurer shall transfer one million four hundred fifty-five thousand dollars on July 1, 2024, from the earnings on the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund to the 211 Cash Fund.</para><para>(c) On June 30, 2025, the State Treasurer shall transfer all earnings on the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund, less any transfers made to the 211 Cash Fund in such fiscal year, to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 686, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 514, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1285, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 389, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-1405; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 202; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1211, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 37, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB331, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB384, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1012, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB683, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB818, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1413, &#167; 59. </para><effectivedate>April 2, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act is not an unconstitutional delegation of authority to the Public Service Commission. Schumacher v. Johanns, 272 Neb. 346, 722 N.W.2d 37 (2006).</para><para>The surcharge assessed by the Public Service Commission based on the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act is not a tax. Schumacher v. Johanns, 272 Neb. 346, 722 N.W.2d 37 (2006).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>