<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-329"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-329</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Telephone Assistance Program; commission; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall establish the Nebraska Telephone Assistance Program. The purpose of the Nebraska Telephone Assistance Program is to promote the provision of universal service to low-income households by local exchange carriers. Support provided by the program shall be specifically targeted to maintain affordable rates for residential basic local exchange services supported by federal and state universal service mechanisms. The commission shall establish means-tested eligibility guidelines and standards for the provision of support from the program which are consistent with the Telecommunications Act of 1996 and 47 C.F.R. 54.400 through 54.409, as such act and regulations existed on January 1, 2002.</para><para>(2) Any local exchange carrier receiving state universal service support shall be prohibited from disconnecting the basic local exchange service of any customer receiving low-income support from the program for the nonpayment of any interexchange toll service charges. The commission may grant limited waivers of this requirement in a manner consistent with 47 C.F.R. 54.400 through 54.409, as such regulations existed on January 1, 2002.</para><para>(3) Any person receiving low-income support from the program shall be exempt from the payment of any surcharge established by the commission pursuant to the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 686, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 514, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1410; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 207; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1004, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>