<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id00" statutenumber="86-579"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>86-579</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Nebraska Internet Enhancement Fund; created; use; investment; termination.</catchline><para id="id00">The Nebraska Internet Enhancement Fund is created. The fund shall be used to provide financial assistance to install and deliver broadband or other advanced telecommunications infrastructure and service throughout the state. It is the intent of the Legislature that two hundred fifty thousand dollars shall be appropriated to the fund to be used for startup costs and seed money for FY2001-02. The Public Service Commission may receive gifts, contributions, property, and equipment from public and private sources for purposes of the fund. The fund shall consist of money appropriated by the Legislature, any money transferred pursuant to section 86-127, and gifts, grants, or bequests from any source including any other federal, state, public, and private sources. Transfers from the fund to the General Fund may be made at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Nebraska Internet Enhancement Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. The fund terminates on June 30, 2021, and the State Treasurer shall transfer any unencumbered money in the fund on such date to the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund.</para><para id="id00">The State Treasurer shall transfer one hundred thousand dollars from the Nebraska Internet Enhancement Fund to the General Fund on or before July 15, 2003.</para><para>The State Treasurer shall transfer fifty thousand dollars from the Nebraska Internet Enhancement Fund to the Rural Broadband Task Force Fund on or before July 15, 2018.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 827, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2306; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 349; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1211, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 408, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB994, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB992, &#167; 13. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>