<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id219" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-5,100"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-5,100</statuteno><catchline id="id222">Network Nebraska;
development and maintenance; access; Chief Information Officer; duties; cost;
report.</catchline><para>The Chief Information Officer, in partnership with
the University of Nebraska, shall develop and maintain a statewide, multipurpose,
high capacity, scalable telecommunications network to be called Network Nebraska.
The network shall consist of contractual arrangements with providers to meet
the demand of state agencies, local governments, and educational entities
as defined in section 79-1201.01. Such network shall provide access to a reliable
and affordable infrastructure capable of carrying a spectrum of services and
applications, including distance education, across the state. The Chief Information
Officer shall provide access to each school district, each educational service
unit, each community college, each state college, and the University of Nebraska
at the earliest feasible date and no later than July 1, 2012. Access may be
provided through educational service units or other aggregation points. Participation
in Network Nebraska shall not be required for any educational entity. The
Chief Information Officer shall aggregate demand for those state agencies
and educational entities choosing to participate and shall reduce costs for
participants whenever feasible. The Chief Information Officer shall establish
a cost structure based on actual costs, including necessary administrative
expenses but not including administrative travel or conference expenses, and
shall charge participants according to such cost structure. The Chief Information
Officer shall annually provide a detailed report of such costs to each participant
and to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The
report submitted to the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall be submitted electronically.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 248.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>