<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id45"><sectno id="id46" opdate="January 1, 2009">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id47" statutenumber="86-250"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id49">86-250</statuteno><catchline id="id50">Permit required; procedure; liability; filing required.</catchline><para>(1) A person shall not connect or operate an automatic dialing-announcing device for the purpose of making telephone solicitations on any telephone line unless the person has a current permit from the commission for the device. An applicant for a permit shall make a written application to the commission. The application shall be in a form prescribed by the commission and shall require information about the type of device proposed for connection and operation, the time of day telephone solicitations will be made using the device, the anticipated number of calls proposed to be placed during the specified calling period, the average length of a completed call, or such alternative or additional information as the commission may require. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. The applicant shall remit a fee of five hundred dollars for each device with the application.</para><para>(2) Upon receiving an application for a permit, the commission may grant, grant as modified, or deny the application. The commission may modify or deny the permit if the commission determines that (a) the applicant is unwilling or unable to meet the requirements placed on such operations by law, rule, or regulation or has failed to comply with the requirements in the past, (b) the connection or operation of the device will result in a significant decline in the quality of service or access to service for other telephone users, (c) the applicant's equipment is unable to meet the requirements of law, rule, or regulation, or (d) the application does not contain adequate information.</para><para>(3) If a permit is granted, the permit shall remain in force for two years from the date of issuance, and each application for the renewal of a permit shall be treated as a new application.</para><para>(4) After receiving a permit but prior to connecting or operating an automatic dialing-announcing device on any telephone line, the permitholder shall notify the telephone company of the telephone line on which the device is proposed to be connected or operated. The telephone line shall be considered a business telephone line. The telephone company shall release to the commission the identity of any person connecting or operating an automatic dialing-announcing device when requested to do so by the commission pursuant to an investigation.</para><para>(5) A person contracting with a third party to connect or operate an automatic dialing-announcing device for the purpose of making telephone solicitations on any telephone line shall be jointly and severally liable with the third party for connecting and operating the automatic dialing-announcing device in violation of the Automatic Dialing-Announcing Devices Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.</para><para>(6) A person contracting with a third party to connect or operate an automatic dialing-announcing device for the purpose of making telephone solicitations shall file with the commission the message to be used to comply with the requirements of section 86-247. Such person shall file any subsequent change to the message with the commission within five days after the change.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 305, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 231; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1214; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB720, &#167; 4.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2009</operativedate></source>  </law></legaldoc>
