<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-2,111"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-2,111</statuteno><catchline>Interception; grand jury procedure.</catchline><para>(1) If the Attorney General or any county attorney reasonably determines that the testimony of any witness or the production of books, papers, or other evidence by any witness is necessary to the public interest in any proceeding before the grand jury of the district court of the State of Nebraska involving any violation or conspiracy to violate the provisions of subsection (1) of section 86-290 or involving the offenses enumerated in section 86-291, the Attorney General or county attorney, upon the approval of the Attorney General, shall make application to the court that the witness be instructed to testify or produce evidence subject to the provisions of this section. Upon an order of the court, such witness shall not be excused from testifying or from producing books, papers, or other evidence on the grounds that the testimony or evidence required by him or her may incriminate him or her or subject him or her to a penalty or forfeiture. Nothing in this section shall be construed to suspend or otherwise interfere with the operation of the provisions of the Free Flow of Information Act or sections 27-503 to 27-506 and 27-605.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this section, no such witness shall be prosecuted or subjected to any penalty or forfeiture for or on account of any transaction, matter, or thing concerning which the witness is compelled, after having claimed the privilege against self-incrimination, to testify or produce evidence, nor shall testimony so compelled be used as evidence in any criminal proceeding against the witness in any court. No witness shall be exempt under this section from prosecution for perjury or contempt committed while giving testimony or producing evidence under compulsion pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 583, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 13, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-708; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 173. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Free Flow of Information Act,</emphasis> see section 20-147.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>