<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-143"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>86-143</statuteno><catchline>Local competition determination; rate list filing requirements.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) Except as provided
in subdivision (b) of this subsection, in  an exchange in which local competition exists,
telecommunications companies shall file rate lists for each telecommunications
service which shall be effective after ten days' notice to the commission.</para>
<para>(b) Notwithstanding any
other provision of Chapter 86, a telecommunications company shall not be required
to file rate lists, tariffs, or contracts for any telecommunications service,
including local exchange and interexchange services, provided as a business
service. Upon written notice to the commission, a telecommunications company
may withdraw any rate list, tariff, or contract not required to be filed under
this subdivision if the telecommunications company posts the rates, terms,
and conditions of its telecommunications service on the company's web site.</para>
<para>(2) Local competition shall be deemed to exist in an exchange if a telecommunications
company files an application with the commission requesting a determination
as to whether local competition exists in one or more exchanges specified
in the application and the commission enters an order after public notice
and a hearing which determines that local competition exists in such exchange
or exchanges. Notwithstanding any other provision of the Nebraska Telecommunications
Regulation Act, the commission may consider any wireless telecommunications
service provided in the exchange or exchanges when determining whether local
competition exists.</para>
<para>(3) The notice of the hearing on the telecommunications company's application
shall be given once each week for two consecutive weeks in a newspaper of
general circulation in the affected area and shall state that a determination
of local competition may result in the freeing of the telecommunications company
from rate regulation by the commission. The notice of the hearing on the commission's
motion shall be sent to the telecommunications company by certified mail,
return receipt requested, and notice of such hearing shall be published in
a newspaper of general circulation in the exchange area. The hearing on the
commission's motion shall be held no sooner than ten days after the receipt
of notice by the telecommunications company.</para>
<para>(4) The commission may, on its own motion at any time after a determination
as to whether local competition exists, reexamine and redetermine the determination
after notice and a hearing on the issue.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB257, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
