<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id945" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-463"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>86-463</statuteno><catchline id="id948">Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund is created. The fund shall consist of the surcharges credited to the fund, any money appropriated by the Legislature, any federal funds received for wireless emergency communication except as otherwise provided in section 86-1028, and any other funds designated for credit to the fund. Money in the fund shall be used for the costs of administering the fund and the purposes specified in section 86-465 unless otherwise directed by federal law with respect to any federal funds. Money shall be transferred from the fund to the 911 Service System Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Within five days after April 19, 2016, the State Treasurer shall transfer two million one hundred thirty-eight thousand three hundred thirty-seven dollars from the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund to the 911 Service System Fund. On or before July 5, 2017, the State Treasurer shall transfer one million nine hundred eighty-eight thousand seven hundred ninety dollars from the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund to the 911 Service System Fund. The costs of administering the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund shall be kept to a minimum. The money in the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund shall not be subject to any fiscal-year limitation or lapse provision of unexpended balance at the end of any fiscal year or biennium. Any money in the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 585, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2208; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 264; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1222, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 98; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB938, &#167; 33. </para><effectivedate>April 19, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>