
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-461"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-461</statuteno><catchline>Enhanced Wireless 911 Advisory Board; created; members; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Enhanced Wireless 911 Advisory Board is created to advise the commission concerning the implementation, development, administration, coordination, evaluation, and maintenance of enhanced wireless 911 service. The advisory board shall be composed of nine individuals appointed by the Governor, including:</para><para>(a) One sheriff;</para><para>(b) Two county officials or employees;</para><para>(c) Two municipal officials or employees;</para><para>(d) One representative from the state's wireless telecommunications industry;</para><para>(e) One manager of a public safety answering point not employed by a sheriff;</para><para>(f) One representative of the state's local exchange telecommunications service industry; and</para><para>(g) One member of the public.</para><para>(2) The advisory board shall also include two ex officio members: </para><para>(a) One commissioner from the Public Service Commission or his or her designee; and </para><para>(b) The Chief Information Officer or his or her designee.</para><para>(3) Members of the board as described in subdivisions (1)(a) through (1)(g) of this section shall be appointed for a term of three years. Each succeeding member of the board shall be appointed for a term of three years. The board shall meet as often as necessary to carry out its duties. Members of the board shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 585, &#167; 6; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2206; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 262; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 921, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB661, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 141. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>