<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id29">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id31" statutenumber="86-136"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-136</statuteno><catchline id="id34">Commission; application approval.</catchline>
<para>Upon the completion of the hearing on such an application
made pursuant to section 86-135, if a hearing is required, the commission
may grant the application, in whole or in part, if the evidence establishes the following:</para>
<para>(1) That such applicant is not receiving, and will not within
a reasonable time receive, reasonable
advanced telecommunications capability service from the telecommunications
company which furnishes telecommunications service
in the local exchange area in which the
applicant resides;</para>
<para>(2) That the revision of the exchange
service area required to grant the application is
economically sound, will
not impair the capability of any telecommunications company affected to serve
the remaining subscribers in any affected exchanges, and will not impose an undue and unreasonable technological
or engineering burden on any affected telecommunications company; and</para>
<para>(3)
That the applicant is willing and, unless waived by the affected telecommunications company, will pay such construction
and other costs and rates as are fair and equitable and will reimburse the
affected telecommunications company for any undepreciated investment
in existing property as determined by the commission. The amount of any payment by the applicant for construction
and other costs associated with providing service to the applicant may be
negotiated between the applicant and the affected telecommunications company.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 601, &#167; 2, p. 2457; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 229, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 414, &#167; 109; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 75-613; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB715, &#167; 5.</para></source><annotation><para>Applicants are required, irrespective of whether phone company currently providing service participates, to present evidence to establish their case. Public Service Commission may consider, in determining the adequacy of service the applicant receives, the evidence that toll charges deter others in the applicant's community of interest from calling him. In re Application of Jantzen, 245 Neb. 81, 511 N.W.2d 504 (1994).</para><para>A toll charge as contemplated in subsection (1) of this statute (formerly section 75-613) is a charge for a single long-distance call, not a monthly flat fee for service. In re Application of George Farm Co., 233 Neb. 23, 443 N.W.2d 285 (1989).</para><para>The determination of what is economically sound under this section (formerly section 75-613) is peculiarly within the discretion and expertise of the Public Service Commission. Where the evidence is in conflict, the weight of the evidence is for the determination of the commission and not the appellate court. Reis v. Glenwood Telephone Membership Corp., 207 Neb. 575, 299 N.W.2d 771 (1980).</para><para>Terminology of this section (formerly section 75-613) has acquired new meanings requiring case-by-case evaluation. Hartman v. Glenwood Tel. Membership Corp., 197 Neb. 359, 249 N.W.2d 468 (1977).</para><para>An applicant may obtain authority from the State Railway Commission for telephone service furnished in adjacent service area without proving inadequacy of service or unfairness of rates in the tradition of public utility law. Schoen v. American Communication Co., Inc., 189 Neb. 78, 199 N.W.2d 716 (1972).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>