<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-2,112"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>86-2,112</statuteno><catchline>Attorney General or county attorney; discovery; additional order limiting notification.</catchline><para>(1) The Attorney General or any county attorney may administer oaths and affirmations, subpoena witnesses and compel their attendance, take evidence, and require the production of records including books, papers, documents, and tangible things which constitute or contain evidence relevant or material to the investigation or enforcement of the laws of this state when it reasonably appears that such action is necessary and proper. The attendance of witnesses and the production of records shall be required from any place within the State of Nebraska, and service of subpoenas may be made upon any publicly or privately held corporation, partnership, or other legal entity located within or outside the State of Nebraska. Witnesses summoned by the Attorney General or a county attorney shall be paid the same fees that are paid witnesses in the courts of the State of Nebraska and mileage at the rate provided in section 81-1176.</para><para>(2) The Attorney General or a county attorney may apply to a court for an order commanding the person or entity to which a subpoena is directed not to notify any other person of the existence of the subpoena. The court shall enter such an order if it determines that there is reason to believe that notification of the existence of the subpoena will result in an adverse result, as such term is defined in section 86-2,108.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 583, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 221; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-709; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB952, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB294, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>