<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id715"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id717" statutenumber="86-2,107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id719">86-2,107</statuteno><catchline id="id720">Remote computing service; court order for government access.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A governmental entity acting under subsection (2) of section 86-2,106 may include in its subpoena or court order a requirement that the provider to whom the request is directed create a backup copy of the contents of the electronic communications sought in order to preserve those communications. Without notifying the subscriber or customer of such subpoena or court order, such provider shall create such backup copy as soon as practicable consistent with its regular business practices and shall confirm to the governmental entity that such backup copy has been made. Such backup copy shall be created within two business days after receipt by the provider of the subpoena or court order.</para><para>(b) Notice to the subscriber or customer shall be made by the governmental entity within three days after receipt of such confirmation unless such notice is delayed pursuant to section 86-2,108.</para><para>(c) The provider shall not destroy such backup copy until the later of (i) the delivery of the information or (ii) the resolution of any proceedings including appeals of any proceeding concerning the subpoena or court order.</para><para>(d) The provider shall release such backup copy to the requesting governmental entity no sooner than fourteen days after the governmental entity's notice to the subscriber or customer if such provider (i) has not received notice from the subscriber or customer that the subscriber or customer has challenged the governmental entity's request and (ii) has not initiated proceedings to challenge the request of the governmental entity.</para><para>(e) A governmental entity may seek to require the creation of a backup copy under subdivision (a) of this subsection if in its sole discretion such entity determines that there is reason to believe that notification under this section and section 86-2,106 of the existence of the subpoena or court order may result in destruction of or tampering with evidence. This determination shall not be subject to challenge by the subscriber, customer, or provider.</para><para>(2)(a) Within fourteen days after notice by the governmental entity to the subscriber or customer under subdivision (1)(b) of this section, such subscriber or customer may file a motion to quash such subpoena or vacate such court order, with copies served upon the governmental entity and with written notice of such challenge to the provider. A motion to vacate a court order shall be filed in the court which issued such order. A motion to quash a subpoena shall be filed in the appropriate court. Such motion or application shall contain an affidavit or sworn statement (i) stating that the applicant is a subscriber to or customer of the service from which the contents of electronic communications maintained for him or her have been sought and (ii) stating the applicant's reasons for believing that the records sought are not relevant to a legitimate law enforcement inquiry or that there has not been substantial compliance with sections 86-2,104 to 86-2,110 in some other respect.</para><para>(b) Service shall be made under this section upon a governmental entity by delivering or mailing by registered or certified mail a copy of the papers to the person, office, or department specified in the notice which the subscriber or customer has received pursuant to sections 86-2,106 to 86-2,108. For purposes of this section, delivery means (i) handing a copy to the attorney or to the party or (ii) leaving a copy at the attorney's or party's office with a clerk or other person in charge of the office, or if the office is closed or the attorney or party to be served has no office, leaving it at the attorney's or the party's dwelling house or usual place of abode with some person of suitable age and discretion then residing therein.</para><para>(c) If the court finds that the subscriber or customer has complied with subdivisions (a) and (b) of this subsection, the court shall order the governmental entity to file a sworn response, which may be filed in camera if the governmental entity includes in its response the reasons which make in camera review appropriate. If the court is unable to determine the motion or application on the basis of the parties' initial allegations and response, the court may conduct such additional proceedings as it deems appropriate. All such proceedings shall be completed and the motion or application decided as soon as practicable after the filing of the governmental entity's response.</para><para>(d) If the court finds that the applicant is not the subscriber or customer for whom the communications sought by the governmental entity are maintained or that there is reason to believe that the law enforcement inquiry is legitimate and that the communications sought are relevant to that inquiry, it shall deny the motion or application and order such process enforced. If the court finds that the applicant is the subscriber or customer for whom the communications sought by the governmental entity are maintained and that there is not reason to believe that the communications sought are relevant to a legitimate law enforcement inquiry or that there has not been substantial compliance with sections 86-2,104 to 86-2,110, it shall order the process quashed.</para><para>(e) A court order denying a motion or application under this section shall not be deemed a final order and no interlocutory appeal may be taken therefrom by the subscriber or customer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 899, &#167; 18; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-707.12; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 169; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 70.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
