<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id174" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-516"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-516</statuteno><catchline id="id177">Commission;
duties.</catchline><para>The commission shall:</para>
<para>(1) Annually by July 1, adopt policies and procedures used to develop,
review, and annually update a statewide technology plan;</para>
<para>(2) Create an information technology clearinghouse to identify and share
best practices and new developments, as well as identify existing problems
and deficiencies;</para>
<para>(3) Review and adopt policies to provide incentives for investments
in information technology infrastructure services;</para>
<para>(4) Determine a broad strategy and objectives for developing and sustaining
information technology development in Nebraska, including long-range funding
strategies, research and development investment, support and maintenance requirements,
and system usage and assessment guidelines;</para>
<para>(5) Adopt guidelines regarding project planning and management and administrative
and technical review procedures involving state-owned or state-supported technology
and infrastructure. Governmental entities, state agencies, and noneducation
political subdivisions shall submit all projects which use any combination
of general funds, federal funds, or cash funds for information technology
purposes to the process established by sections 86-512 to 86-524. The commission
may adopt policies that establish the format and minimum requirements for
project submissions. The commission may monitor the progress of any such project
and may require progress reports;</para>
<para>(6) Adopt minimum technical standards, guidelines, and architectures
upon recommendation by the technical panel. Such standards and guidelines
shall not unnecessarily restrict the use of new technologies or prevent commercial
competition, including competition with Network Nebraska;</para>
<para>(7) Establish ad hoc technical advisory groups to study and make recommendations
on specific topics, including workgroups to establish, coordinate, and prioritize
needs for education, local communities, intergovernmental data communications,
and state agencies;</para>
<para>(8) By November 15 of each even-numbered year, make recommendations
on technology investments to the Governor and the Legislature, including a
prioritized list of projects, reviewed by the technical panel pursuant to
section 86-521. The recommendations
submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(9) Approve grants from the Community Technology Fund and Government
Technology Collaboration Fund;</para>
<para>(10) Adopt schedules and procedures for reporting needs, priorities,
and recommended projects;</para>
<para>(11) Assist the Chief Information Officer in developing and maintaining
Network Nebraska pursuant to section 86-5,100; and</para>
<para>(12) Determine the format that state agencies, boards, and commissions
shall use to report their information technology plans under section 86-524.01.
The commission shall include an analysis of such plans in the statewide technology
plan.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 446, &#167; 12; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1506; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 286; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 343, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1071, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 244.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>