<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-254"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-254</statuteno><catchline>Seizure of automatic dialing-announcing devices; when; destruction; liability.</catchline><para>The commission, its agents or employees, or any peace officer of this state at the direction of the commission may, at any place in the state, seize without a warrant any automatic dialing-announcing device the operation of which does not conform in all respects to requirements imposed by subdivisions (1) and (2) of section 86-244 or any rules or regulations. The seized device shall constitute contraband. The commission may, upon satisfactory proof, direct return of a seized device when the evidence establishes the owner did not willfully or intentionally fail to comply with the applicable law, rules, or regulations. The commission may, upon finding that the owner of a seized device has willfully or intentionally failed to comply with the applicable law, rules, or regulations, confiscate the device. Any device so confiscated may be destroyed. Destruction of a device shall not occur before all statutory appeal periods available to the owner have been exhausted. The seizure and destruction of an automatic dialing-announcing device shall not relieve any person from a fine, imprisonment, or other penalty for violation of the applicable law, rules, or regulations. The commission, its agents and employees, or any peace officer of this state shall not be liable for negligence for the seizure, confiscation, or destruction of any contraband pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 305, &#167; 18; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1218; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 116. </para></source></law></legaldoc>