<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id39"  statutenumber="86-465"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>86-465</statuteno><catchline id="id42">Commission; advisory board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The commission shall, in consultation with the advisory board:</para><para>(a) Determine the costs to implement wireless automatic location identification;</para><para>(b) Determine the level of funding needed to trigger disbursements pursuant to the Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act;</para><para>(c) Determine the percentage of the 911 Service System Fund to be allocated to each funding purpose, including the percentage that shall be designated for funding 911 service under subdivision (2)(c) of this section; </para><para>(d) Determine how the funds distributed under subdivisions (2)(a) and (2)(c) of this section are to be allocated among the wireless carriers and the public safety answering points; and </para><para>(e) Establish a mechanism for determining the level of funding available to each public safety answering point and wireless carrier for costs determined to be eligible by the commission under subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(2) The commission shall, in consultation with the advisory board, establish eligibility standards and criteria for applications for disbursements from the 911 Service System Fund and standards and criteria concerning the level of fund disbursement for each application. In establishing such criteria and standards, the following purposes may be eligible for funding:</para><para>(a) Costs incurred or to be incurred by wireless carriers to implement enhanced wireless 911 service pursuant to a service agreement with a public safety answering point or pursuant to a request for service from a public safety answering point. Such costs may include, but not be limited to, the portion of the costs for new equipment used for providing enhanced wireless 911 service, costs to lease another vendor's equipment or services to provide enhanced wireless 911 service, costs to create or maintain any database or database elements used solely for enhanced wireless 911 service, and other costs of establishing enhanced wireless 911 service. The portion of the costs of equipment or services used in the wireless carrier's main infrastructure resulting in revenue to the wireless carrier is not eligible for funding;</para><para>(b) Costs incurred or to be incurred by public safety answering points to implement enhanced wireless 911 service may include, but not be limited to, purchases of new equipment, costs of upgrades, modification and personnel training used solely to process the data elements of enhanced wireless 911 service, and maintenance costs and license fees for new equipment;</para><para>(c) Costs incurred or to be incurred by public safety answering points for the purchase, installation, maintenance, and operation of telecommunications equipment and telecommunications services required for the provision of enhanced wireless 911 service; and</para><para>(d) Expenses incurred by members of the advisory board while performing duties required by the Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act.</para><para>(3) A wireless carrier receiving funds from the 911 Service System Fund shall not directly assess any of the costs associated with the implementation or provision of enhanced wireless 911 service to any public safety answering point, county, or municipality without the express consent of the commission.</para><para>(4) The commission shall have any powers necessary to carry out the intent and purposes of the Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 585, &#167; 10; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2210; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 266; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1222, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB755, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB595, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB993, &#167; 5. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>