<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id13"><sectno id="id14" opdate="January 1, 2009">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id15" statutenumber="86-256"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id17">86-256</statuteno><catchline id="id18">Automatic dialing-announcing device; registration required; when; message requirements; liability; filing required.</catchline><para>(1) Any person using an automatic dialing-announcing device other than for telephone solicitations shall register the device with the commission pursuant to the application process, without a fee, and shall include with the application a detailed explanation of the use planned and the message to be used.</para><para>(2) All telephone messages transmitted by an automatic dialing-announcing device other than telephone solicitations shall:</para><para>(a) At the beginning of the message, state clearly the identity of the person on whose behalf the message is being transmitted;</para><para>(b) During or after the message, state clearly the telephone number, other than that of the device which made the call, or address of the person operating the device; and</para><para>(c) Transmit messages only between the hours of 8 a.m. and 9 p.m. at the location of the person receiving the message.</para><para>(3) This section does not apply to (a) a message from any elementary, secondary, or postsecondary educational institution to any of its students, parents, or employees, (b) a message to a person with whom the person placing the call or the person on whose behalf the message is being transmitted has an established business or personal relationship, (c) a message from an employer advising any of its employees of work schedules, or (d) a message from a political subdivision as defined in section 13-903.</para><para>(4) A person contracting with a third party to connect or operate an automatic dialing-announcing device for other than telephone solicitations shall be jointly and severally liable with the third party for connecting and operating the automatic dialing-announcing device in violation of the Automatic Dialing-Announcing Devices Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under the act.</para><para>(5) A person contracting with a third party to connect or operate an automatic dialing-announcing device for other than telephone solicitations shall file with the commission the message to be used within twenty-four hours after the message is transmitted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 305, &#167; 21; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1221; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 118; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB720, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>
