<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-313"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>86-313</statuteno><catchline>Surcharge; amount; hearing; commission;
powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Each telephone company in Nebraska
shall collect from each of the telephone subscribers a surcharge not to exceed
twenty cents per month on each telephone number or functional equivalent in
Nebraska, including wireless service as defined in section 86-456.01. Except
for wireless service, the surcharge shall only be collected on the first one
hundred telephone numbers or functional equivalents per subscriber. The companies
shall add the surcharge to each subscriber's bill.</para>
<para>(b) The telephone companies are not liable for any surcharge not paid
by a subscriber.</para>
<para>(2) Before April 1 of each year, the commission shall hold a public
hearing to determine the amount of surcharge necessary to carry out the Telecommunications
Relay System Act. After the hearing, the commission shall set the surcharge
at the level necessary to fund the statewide telecommunications relay system
and the specialized telecommunications equipment program for the following
year plus a reasonable reserve. The surcharge shall become effective on July
1 following the change.</para>
<para>(3) In an emergency the commission may adjust the amount of the surcharge
to become effective before such date but only after a public hearing for such
purpose.</para>
<para>(4) Each telephone company shall remit the proceeds
from the surcharge to the commission. The commission shall remit the funds to the
State Treasurer for credit to the fund.</para>
<para>(5) The commission may require an audit of any company collecting the
surcharge pursuant to the act.</para>
<para>(6) This section shall not apply to subscribers who have no access to
relay service.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1990, LB 240, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1992, &#167; 86-904; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 305, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 146, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1305; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 191; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB661, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB723, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Prepaid Wireless Surcharge Act,</emphasis> see section 86-901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>