<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-457"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-457</statuteno><catchline>Surcharge; commission; duties; applicability of section.</catchline><para>(1) Each wireless carrier shall collect:</para><para>(a) A surcharge of up to seventy cents, except as provided in subdivision (1)(b) of this subsection and as otherwise provided in this section with respect to prepaid wireless service, on all active telephone numbers or functional equivalents every month from users of wireless service and shall remit the surcharge in accordance with section 86-459; or</para><para>(b) A surcharge of up to fifty cents, except as otherwise provided in this section with respect to prepaid wireless service, on all active telephone numbers or functional equivalents every month from users of wireless service whose primary place of use is in a county containing a city of the metropolitan class and shall remit the surcharge in accordance with section 86-459.</para><para>The wireless carrier is not liable for any surcharge not paid by a customer.</para><para>(2) Except as otherwise provided in this section, the wireless carrier shall add the surcharge to each user's billing statement. The surcharge shall appear as a separate line-item charge on the user's billing statement and shall be labeled as "Enhanced Wireless 911 Surcharge" or a reasonable abbreviation of such phrase.</para><para>(3) If a wireless carrier, except as otherwise provided in this section, resells its service through other entities, each reseller shall collect the surcharge from its customers and shall remit the surcharge in accordance with section 86-459.</para><para>(4) It is the intent of the Legislature that, effective July 1, 2007, all users of prepaid wireless services pay an amount comparable to the amount paid by users of wireless services that are not prepaid in support of statewide wireless enhanced 911 service. It is also the intent of the Legislature that whenever possible such amounts be collected from the users of such prepaid wireless services.</para><para>(5) The commission shall establish surcharges comparable to the surcharge assessed on other users of wireless services and shall develop methods for collection and remittance of such surcharges from wireless carriers offering prepaid wireless services.</para><para>(6) The duty to remit any surcharges established pursuant to subsection (5) of this section is the responsibility of the wireless carrier.</para><para>(7) This section shall not apply to users who have no 911 service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 585, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2202; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 258; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 187, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1222, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB661, &#167; 23.</para></source><annotation><para>Subsections (1) through (3) of this section exclusively apply to postpaid wireless services, while subsections (4) through (6) apply to prepaid wireless services. TracFone Wireless v. Nebraska Pub. Serv. Comm., 279 Neb. 426, 778 N.W.2d 452 (2010).</para><para>The plain language of subsection (5) of this section permits the Public Service Commission to require compliance with the surcharges and methods for collection and remittance that it establishes. TracFone Wireless v. Nebraska Pub. Serv. Comm., 279 Neb. 426, 778 N.W.2d 452 (2010).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>