<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id645"><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-330"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>86-330</statuteno><catchline>Unserved or underserved exchanges; reverse auction program; funding to providers; Public Service Commission; powers and duties.</catchline><para>Based on consumer complaints or upon its own motion, the Public Service Commission may open a docket to consider the implementation and operation of a reverse auction program that awards funding to broadband Internet service providers to support high-speed Internet infrastructure deployment projects in unserved or underserved exchanges within the State of Nebraska. The commission may, in its discretion, withhold funding from the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund to any telecommunications company that has not served, to the commission's satisfaction, those areas with service that meets the criteria for successful investment of funding from the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund.</para><para>The commission shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that establish standards governing the withholding of funding from the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund from any recipient, including the provision of notice and the right to a hearing prior to the issuance of an order withdrawing such funding. If the commission withdraws funding from the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund from any telecommunications company, the commission may use the funding that is withdrawn to implement and operate a reverse auction program, except that any funding that is withdrawn shall be utilized in the exchange area for which the funding was originally granted. The commission shall have wide discretion in the design, implementation, and operation of a reverse auction program but may use as a guide the program designed by the Federal Communications Commission in its Connect America Fund Phase II Auction process.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2018, LB994, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2018</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>