<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id00" statutenumber="86-2,108"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-2,108</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Electronic communication service; remote computing service; notification requirements.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A governmental entity acting under subsection (2) of section 86-2,106 shall (i) when a court order is sought, include in the application a request, which the court shall grant, for an order delaying the notification required under such subsection for a period not to exceed ninety days if the court determines that there is reason to believe that notification of the existence of the court order may have an adverse result or (ii) when an administrative subpoena is obtained, delay the notification required under such subsection for a period not to exceed ninety days upon the execution of a written certification of a supervisory official that there is reason to believe that notification of the existence of the subpoena may have an adverse result.</para><para>(b) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(i) Adverse result means:</para><para>(A) Endangering the life or physical safety of an individual;</para><para>(B) Flight from prosecution;</para><para>(C) Destruction of or tampering with evidence;</para><para>(D) Intimidation of potential witnesses; or</para><para>(E) Otherwise seriously jeopardizing an investigation or unduly delaying a trial; and</para><para>(ii) Supervisory official means the investigative agent in charge, the assistant investigative agent in charge, an equivalent of an investigating agency's headquarters or regional office, the chief prosecuting attorney, the first assistant prosecuting attorney, or an equivalent of a prosecuting attorney's headquarters or regional office.</para><para>(c) The governmental entity shall maintain a true copy of certification under subdivision (a)(ii) of this subsection.</para><para>(d) Extensions of the delay of notification provided in sections 86-2,106 and 86-2,107 of up to ninety days each may be granted by the court upon application, or by certification by a governmental entity, but only in accordance with subsection (2) of this section.</para><para>(e) Upon expiration of the period of delay of notification under subdivision (a) or (d) of this subsection, the governmental entity shall serve upon or deliver by registered or first-class mail to the customer or subscriber a copy of the process or request together with notice that:</para><para>(i) States with reasonable specificity the nature of the law enforcement inquiry; and</para><para>(ii) Informs such customer or subscriber:</para><para>(A) That information maintained for such customer or subscriber by the provider named in such process or request was supplied to or requested by that governmental entity and the date on which the supplying or request took place;</para><para>(B) That notification of such customer or subscriber was delayed;</para><para>(C) What governmental entity or court made the certification or determination pursuant to which that delay was made; and</para><para>(D) Which provision of sections 86-2,104 to 86-2,109 allowed such delay.</para><para>(2) A governmental entity acting under section 86-2,106, except as provided in subsection (1) of this section, may apply to a court for an order commanding a provider of electronic communication service or remote computing service to whom a warrant, subpoena, or court order is directed, for such period as the court deems appropriate, not to notify any other person of the existence of the warrant, subpoena, or court order. The court shall enter such an order if it determines that there is reason to believe that notification of the existence of the warrant, subpoena, or court order will result in an adverse result.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 899, &#167; 19; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-707.13; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 170; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB294, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>