<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id55"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id57" statutenumber="86-569"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id59">86-569</statuteno><catchline id="id60">Findings and intent.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that Geographic Information Systems are a computer-based technology that captures, stores, analyzes, and displays information about the earth's surface from geographically referenced systems, that an interest in the systems is rapidly increasing at all levels of government, and that an institutional mechanism is needed to encourage initiatives, coordinate efforts, avoid duplication, seek efficiencies, develop guidelines, policies, and standards for operations and management, promote education and training, and make recommendations so that such technology will benefit the entire state and endure as an analysis tool for decisionmakers.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature that a Geographic Information Systems Council be created with statewide responsibilities to take an active role in implementing Geographic Information Systems. Such council would help facilitate acquisition of such technology at all levels of government and make recommendations to the Legislature for program initiatives and funding and the fostering of communication, training, and education.</para><para>(3) It is the intent of the Legislature that the Geographic Information Systems Council serve as an advisory council to the Nebraska Information Technology Commission and assist the commission in its overall information technology planning and oversight and provide technical advice and recommendations related to the specialized needs of Geographic Information Systems.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 639, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 81-2601; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 339; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>