<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id18"><sectno id="id19">Sec. 14.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id20" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-563"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id22">86-563</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Division; duties and powers.</catchline><para>In establishing and maintaining the system:</para><para>(1) The division:</para><para>(a) Shall provide the computer network and services for the system with assistance from the division of communications of the office;</para><para>(b) Shall, within available resources, assist local, state, and federal collaborative efforts to encourage coordination of information systems and data sharing;</para><para>(c) Shall coordinate its activities and responsibilities with the functions of the division of communications to minimize overlap and duplication of technical services between the divisions in supporting the system, its applications, and application development; and</para><para>(d) May undertake and coordinate planning studies to determine the feasibility, benefits, costs, requirements, and options for the intergovernmental transfer of data;</para><para>(2) The officer:</para><para>(a) Shall approve and coordinate the design, development, installation, training, and maintenance of applications by state agencies for use on the system. Any agency proposing to add an application to the system shall submit an evaluation to the officer that examines the cost-effectiveness, technical feasibility, and potential use of the proposed application; that identifies the total costs of the application, including design, development, testing, installation, operation, and any changes to the computer network that are necessary for its operation; and that provides a schedule that shows the estimated completion dates for design, development, testing, installation, training, and full operational status. The officer shall not approve an application by a state agency for use on the system unless his or her review shows that the application is cost effective and technically feasible, that funding is available, and that the proposed schedule is reasonable and feasible;</para><para>(b) Shall approve changes in the design of applications by state agencies for use on the system. The officer may require such information from the agency as necessary to determine that the proposed change in design is cost effective and technically feasible, that funding is available, and that the proposed schedule for implementation is reasonable and feasible;</para><para>(c) May contract with other governmental entities or private vendors in carrying out the duties relating to the intergovernmental data services program;</para><para>(d) Shall establish a rate schedule that reflects the rates adopted by the division of communications and the information management services division, plus any additional costs of the system. Such fees may reflect a base cost for access to the system, costs for actual usage of the system, costs for special equipment or services, or a combination of these factors. The officer may charge for the costs of changes to the system that are requested by or are necessary to accommodate a request by a user. All fees shall be set to recover all costs of operation;</para><para>(e) May enter into agreements with other state and local governments, the federal government, or private-sector entities for the purpose of sale, lease, or licensing for third-party resale of applications and system design. Proceeds from such agreements shall be deposited to the Data Systems Cash Fund;</para><para>(f) Shall determine whether a local application shall be a component of the system. No local application shall be resident or operational in any component of the system without explicit authorization of the officer; and</para><para>(g) Shall approve or disapprove the attachment of any peripheral device to the system and may prescribe standards and specifications that such devices must meet;</para><para>(3) The officer shall be responsible for the proper operation of the system, applications, and peripheral devices purchased or developed by the expenditure of state funds. The ownership of such system, applications, and peripheral devices shall be vested with the state; and</para><para>(4) All communications and telecommunications services for the intergovernmental data services program and the system shall be secured from the division of communications. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 543, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 104; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 34; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2000, &#167; 81-1120.38; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 333; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 921, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167;  14.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2008</effectivedate></source>  </law></legaldoc>
