<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-402</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(1) During emergencies the resources of the state and its political subdivisions must be effectively directed to save lives, to protect property, and to meet the needs of its citizens;</para><para>(2) Public safety agencies fulfill this unique and essential role;</para><para>(3) Public safety agencies are only as effective as their ability to communicate. To adequately ensure public safety, such agencies require efficient, reliable communication systems which account for their unique role and the specialized needs that accompany such role;</para><para>(4) There are presently radio communication systems used by public safety agencies during daily operations and emergencies that are deficient. Many of Nebraska's systems rely on inadequate equipment, are susceptible to communication interference, have limited coverage areas, operate under the constraints of a limited number of radio frequency channels, and lack coordination and the ability to interoperate among city, county, and other local users, state users, and federal users. Additionally, such systems presently do not allow for secure transmissions which are necessary for the protection and integrity of public safety communications;</para><para>(5) Recent changes and advances in communication technology would increase the capability of public safety agencies to provide efficient and effective public safety services;</para><para>(6) Investment in the public safety communication infrastructure is required to ensure the effectiveness of Nebraska's public safety agencies;</para><para>(7) Regional approaches to communications planning and preparedness and the adoption of regional response structures should be used to develop and sustain interoperable communications. Local and state public safety agencies shall develop a comprehensive interoperable communications plan before receiving any state or federal funding to build, upgrade, enhance, or replace communication systems; and</para><para>(8) A network of regional communication systems should balance the need for multiple simultaneous users while maintaining autonomy for the internal use of individual agencies. The objectives of such a network should include maximizing resources and reducing duplication among public safety agencies as well as encouraging cooperation, coordination, consolidation, sharing, and partnerships between public agencies and private entities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 446, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1804; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 209; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1211, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 343, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>