<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-125</statuteno><catchline>Communications provider; registration; requirements; administrative fine.</catchline><para>Notwithstanding the provisions of section 86-124:</para><para>(1) Any communications provider providing service in Nebraska shall file a registration form with and pay a registration fee to the Public Service Commission. Any communications provider shall register with the commission prior to providing service. The commission shall prescribe the registration form to be filed pursuant to this section;</para><para>(2) A communications provider providing the services described in subdivision (7)(a) of this section shall provide the commission with the name, address, telephone number, and email address of a contact person concerning:</para><para>(a) The Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act and related surcharges, if applicable;</para><para>(b) The Telecommunications Relay System Act and related surcharges, if applicable;</para><para>(c) The Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act and related surcharges, if applicable; and</para><para>(d) Consumer complaints and inquiries;</para><para>(3) A communications provider providing the services described in subdivision (7)(b) of this section shall provide the commission with the name, address, telephone number, and email address of a person with managerial responsibility for Nebraska operations;</para><para>(4) A communications provider shall:</para><para>(a) Submit a registration fee at the time of submission of the registration form. The commission shall set the fee in an amount sufficient to cover the costs of administering the registration process but not to exceed fifty dollars;</para><para>(b) Keep the information required by this section current and notify the commission of any changes to such information within sixty days after the change; and</para><para>(c) Certify to the commission by January 1 each year that such communications provider does not use or provide any communications equipment or service deemed to pose a threat to national security identified on the Covered List developed pursuant to 47 C.F.R. 1.50002, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2023, and published by the Public Safety and Homeland Security Bureau of the Federal Communications Commission pursuant to the federal Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019, 47 U.S.C. 1601 et seq., as such act existed on January 1, 2023, and the rules adopted pursuant to such act by the Federal Communications Commission on November 11, 2022, in its Report and Order FCC 22-84;</para><para>(5) The commission may, pursuant to section 75-156, administratively fine any communications provider which violates this section;</para><para>(6) This section applies to all communications providers providing service in Nebraska except for those communications providers otherwise regulated under the Nebraska Telecommunications Regulation Act; and </para><para>(7) For purposes of this section, communications provider means any entity that:</para><para>(a) Uses telephone numbers or Internet protocol addresses or their functional equivalents or successors to provide information of a user's choosing by aid of wire, cable, wireless, satellite, or other like connection, whether part of a bundle of services or offered separately, (i) which provides or enables real-time or interactive voice communications and (ii) in which the voice component is the primary function; or</para><para>(b) Provides any service, whether part of a bundle of services or offered separately, used for transmission of information of a user's choosing regardless of the transmission medium or technology employed, that connects to a network that permits the end user to engage in electronic communications, including, but not limited to, service provided directly (i) to the public or (ii) to such classes of users as to be effectively available directly to the public.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 1211, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB661, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB683, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Enhanced Wireless 911 Services Act,</emphasis> see section 86-442.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund Act,</emphasis> see section 86-316.</para><para><emphasis>Telecommunications Relay System Act,</emphasis> see section 86-301.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>