<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-515"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>86-515</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska Information Technology Commission; created; members; expenses; executive director.</catchline><para>(1) The Nebraska Information Technology Commission is created. The commission shall consist of (a) one member representing elementary and secondary education, (b) one member representing postsecondary education, (c) the Governor or his or her designee, (d) one member representing communities, and (e) five members representing the general public who have experience in developing strategic plans and making high-level business decisions. A member of the Transportation and Telecommunications Committee of the Legislature shall be appointed by the Executive Board of the Legislative Council to serve as an ex officio, nonvoting member of the commission. The Executive Board shall make the initial appointment of such member after January 5, 2011, and shall appoint a member every two years after the initial appointment. At any time that there is not a member of the Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council serving on the Nebraska Information Technology Commission, the technical panel established pursuant to section 86-521, or any working groups established pursuant to sections 86-512 to 86-524 that establish, coordinate, or prioritize needs for education, the Governor shall appoint to the commission one member who serves on the Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council.</para><para>(2) The Governor or a designee of the Governor shall serve as chairperson of the commission.</para><para>(3) The members of the commission other than the legislative member shall be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature. Members of the commission shall serve for terms of four years, except that two members initially appointed to represent the general public shall be appointed for a term of two years and any member appointed to represent the Educational Service Unit Coordinating Council shall be appointed for a term of one year. Members shall be limited to two consecutive terms. The Governor or his or her designee shall serve on the commission for his or her term. The legislative member of the commission shall serve until he or she is reappointed or a successor is appointed. Each member shall serve until the appointment and qualification of his or her successor. In case of a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of the term of a member, the appointment shall be made only for the remainder of the term.</para><para>(4) Members shall be reimbursed for expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para><para>(5) The commission may employ or designate an executive director to provide administrative and operational support for the commission. The Department of Administrative Services and Nebraska Educational Telecommunications Commission shall assist with administrative and operational support for the Nebraska Information Technology Commission as necessary to carry out its duties.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 5; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1505; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 285; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1208, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB603, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB787, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB381, &#167; 142. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>