<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id943">
<sectno id="id944">Sec. 98.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id945" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-463">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id947">86-463</statuteno><catchline id="id948">Enhanced Wireless
911 Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>The Enhanced
Wireless 911 Fund is created. The fund shall consist of the surcharges credited
to the fund, any money appropriated by the Legislature, any federal funds
received for wireless emergency communication, and any other funds designated
for credit to the fund. Money in the fund shall be used for the costs of administering
the fund and the purposes specified in section 86-465 unless otherwise directed
by federal law with respect to any federal funds. The costs of administering
the fund shall be kept to a minimum. The money in the fund shall not be subject
to any fiscal-year limitation or lapse provision of unexpended balance at
the end of any fiscal year or biennium. Interest
accruing to the fund from invested fund balances may be transferred to the
General Fund at the direction of the Legislature through June 30, 2010. Any
money in the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund available
for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant
to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 585, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2208; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 264; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1222, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 98.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>