<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id893"><amendatorysection statutenumber="86-2,117" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>86-2,117</statuteno><catchline>Telecommunications service or IP-enabled voice service; prohibited acts; penalty; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) This section shall be known and may be cited as the Neighbor Spoofing Protection Act.</para><para>(2) No person shall, in connection with any telecommunications service or IP-enabled voice service, cause any caller identification service to knowingly transmit misleading or inaccurate caller identification information with the intent to defraud, cause harm, or wrongfully obtain anything of value.</para><para>(3) Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent or restrict any person from blocking the capability of any caller identification service to transmit caller identification information.</para><para>(4) This section shall not apply:</para><para>(a) To any authorized activity of a law enforcement agency;</para><para>(b) When a court order specifically authorizes the use of caller identification manipulation; or</para><para>(c) To any provider of telecommunications services, broadband services, or Internet services, as those terms are defined in section 86-593, if such provider is acting in a manner that is authorized or required by federal law.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in this section, local exchange carriers and telecommunications carriers shall not be responsible for enforcement of this section.</para><para>(6)(a) Notwithstanding section 75-156, the Public Service Commission may, after hearing, impose an administrative penalty for a violation of this section. The penalty for a violation shall not exceed two thousand dollars. Every violation associated with a specific telephone number within the state shall be considered a separate and distinct violation.</para><para>(b) The amount of an administrative penalty shall be based on:</para><para>(i) The nature, circumstances, extent, and gravity of a prohibited act;</para><para>(ii) The history of previous violations;</para><para>(iii) The amount necessary to deter future violations; and</para><para>(iv) Any efforts to correct the violation.</para><para>(c) The commission shall remit any administrative penalty collected under this section to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska.</para><para>(d) Any administrative penalty may be appealed. The appeal shall be in accordance with section 75-136.</para><para>(7) Notwithstanding subsection (6) of this section, a violation of this section shall be considered a violation of section 59-1602 and be subject to the Consumer Protection Act and any other law which provides for the implementation and enforcement of section 59-1602. A violation of this section does not give rise to a private cause of action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB693, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>