<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id64"><sectno id="id65">Sec. 18.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" id="id66" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-570"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id68">86-570</statuteno><catchline id="id69">Geographic Information Systems Council; created; members; appointment; terms; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) The Geographic Information Systems Council is hereby created and shall consist of:</para><para>(a) The Chief Information Officer or his or her designee, the chief executive officer or designee of the Department of Health and Human Services, and the director or designee of the Department of Environmental Quality, the Conservation and Survey Division of the University of Nebraska, the Department of Natural Resources, and the Governor's Policy Research Office;</para><para>(b) The Director-State Engineer or designee;</para><para>(c) The State Surveyor or designee;</para><para>(d) The Clerk of the Legislature or designee;</para><para>(e) The secretary of the Game and Parks Commission or designee;</para><para>(f) The Property Tax Administrator or designee;</para><para>(g) One representative of federal agencies appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(h) One representative of the natural resources districts nominated by the Nebraska Association of Resources Districts and appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(i) One representative of the public power districts appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(j) Two representatives of the counties nominated by the Nebraska Association of County Officials and appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(k) One representative of the municipalities nominated by the League of Nebraska Municipalities and appointed by the Governor;</para><para>(l) Two members at large appointed by the Governor; and</para><para>(m) Such other members as nominated by the Nebraska Information Technology Commission and appointed by the Governor.</para><para>(2) The appointed members shall serve terms as determined by the Nebraska Information Technology Commission.</para><para>(3) The members shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 639, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 594, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 250; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2000, &#167; 81-2602; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 340; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 921, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 812; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB797, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
