<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id97" statutenumber="86-572"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>86-572</statuteno><catchline id="id100">Council; duties.</catchline>
<para>The Geographic Information Systems Council shall:</para>
<para>(1) Make recommendations to the Legislature and the Nebraska Information
Technology Commission for program initiatives and funding. The recommendations submitted to the Legislature shall
be submitted electronically;</para>
<para>(2) Establish guidelines and policies for statewide Geographic Information
Systems operations and management to include:</para>
<para>(a) The acquisition, development, maintenance, quality assurance such
as standards, access, ownership, cost recovery, and priorities of data bases;</para>
<para>(b) The compatibility, acquisition, and communications of hardware and
software;</para>
<para>(c) The assessment of needs, identification of scope, setting of standards,
and determination of an appropriate enforcement mechanism;</para>
<para>(d) The fostering of training programs and promoting education and information
about Geographic Information Systems; and</para>
<para>(e) The promoting of Geographic Information Systems development in the
State of Nebraska and providing or coordinating additional support to address
Geographic Information Systems issues as such issues arise;</para>
<para>(3) Report to, assist, and advise the Chief Information Officer in setting
information technology policy; and</para>
<para>(4) Provide assistance as requested by the commission and support the
technical panel created in section 86-521.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 639, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 924, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 446, &#167; 11; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 81-2604; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 342; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 343, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB823, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 247.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>