<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-577"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-577</statuteno><catchline>Agency or political subdivision; dark fiber; lease.</catchline><para>Any agency or political subdivision of the state may lease its dark fiber if:</para><para>(1) The lessee is a certificated telecommunications common carrier or a permitted telecommunications contract carrier pursuant to section 86-128 or an Internet service provider;</para><para>(2) The lease price and profit distribution is approved by the Public Service Commission as follows:</para><para>(a) The commission shall not approve any lease price which is less than the market rate for leasing such fiber as determined by the commission. The market rate is the price associated with similar unbundled network elements that may be available from the incumbent local exchange carrier or the price of any other private entity leasing dark fiber optic facilities serving the same or similar territory where the leased equipment is located. Before entering into a lease, each agency or political subdivision shall file a request with the commission for a competitive price comparison to determine the market rate. When conducting a competitive price comparison, the commission in its discretion shall use rate schedules, interconnection agreements, or other documents within its regulatory oversight and shall gather other market rate information as deemed necessary;</para><para>(b) The commission shall not approve any lease price which is agreed upon by the agency or political subdivision and the lessee unless the lease requires that the agency or political subdivision be solely responsible for the maintenance of its dark fiber and that the lessee be responsible, on a pro rata basis, for any such maintenance costs; and</para><para>(c) The commission shall not approve any lease unless fifty percent of the profit earned by the agency or political subdivision under the lease is remitted to the Nebraska Internet Enhancement Fund. Profit earned by the agency or political subdivision is the lease price less the cost of infrastructure overbuilding. Before entering into a lease, each agency or political subdivision shall file a request with the commission to determine the cost of overbuilding its fiber optic infrastructure. For purposes of this subdivision, cost of infrastructure overbuilding means the cost of each leased optic fiber, including the cost, on a pro rata basis, associated with the agency's or political subdivision's installation of such fiber;</para><para>(3) Any interconnection agreement subject to section 86-122 is approved by the commission; and</para><para>(4) The lessee makes every reasonable effort to activate the maximum amount of the leased fiber as is possible, within one year after entering into the lease, unless good cause is shown.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 827, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2001, &#167; 86-2304; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 347. </para></source></law></legaldoc>