<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" id="id12" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="86-164"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>86-164</statuteno><catchline>Telecommunications carrier; placement
of line, wire, or cable across railroad right-of-way; application; petition;
hearing; order; standard crossing fee; expenses; agreement.</catchline><para>(1)
Any telecommunications carrier that intends to place a line, wire, or cable
across a railroad right-of-way shall request permission for such placement
from the railroad carrier. The request shall be in the form of a completed
crossing application, including engineering specifications. Upon receipt of
such application, the railroad carrier and the telecommunications carrier
may enter into a binding wire-crossing agreement. If the railroad carrier
and the telecommunications carrier are unable to negotiate a binding wire-crossing
agreement within sixty days after receipt of the crossing application by the
railroad carrier, either party may submit a petition to the commission for
a hearing on the disputed terms and conditions of the purported wire-crossing
agreement.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Unless otherwise agreed to by all parties, the commission shall,
after providing proper notice, hold and complete such hearing within sixty
days after receipt of the petition. The commission shall issue an order of
its decision within thirty days after the hearing. In rendering its decision,
the commission shall consider whether the terms and conditions at issue are
unreasonable or against the public interest, taking into account safety, engineering,
and access requirements of the railroad carrier as such requirements are prescribed
by the Federal Railroad Administration and established rail industry standards.</para>
<para>(b) Upon issuance of an order by the commission under subdivision (a)
of this subsection, the railroad carrier and the telecommunications carrier
shall have fifteen days after the date of issuance to file a conforming wire-crossing
agreement with the commission. The commission shall have fifteen days after
the date of such filing to approve or reject the agreement. If the commission
does not issue an approval or rejection of such agreement within the fifteen-day
requirement, the agreement shall be deemed approved. The commission may reject
a wire-crossing agreement if it finds that the agreement does not conform
to the order issued by the commission. If the commission enters such a finding,
the parties shall revise the agreement to comply with the commission's order
and shall refile the agreement to the commission for further review. If the
commission does not approve or reject the revised agreement within fifteen
days after the date of refiling, the agreement shall be deemed approved.</para>
<para>(3)(a) Except as provided in subsection (4) of this section or as otherwise
agreed to by all parties, if a telecommunications carrier places a line, wire,
or cable across a railroad right-of-way pursuant to this section, it shall
pay the railroad carrier, owner,
manager, agent, or representative of the railroad carrier a one-time
standard crossing fee of one thousand two hundred fifty dollars for each applicable
crossing. In addition to the standard crossing fee, the telecommunications
carrier shall reimburse the railroad carrier for any actual flagging expenses
associated with the placement of the line, wire, or cable.</para>
<para>(b) The standard crossing fee shall be in lieu of any license fee or
any other fees or charges to reimburse the railroad carrier for any direct
expense incurred as a result of the placement of the line, wire, or cable.</para>
<para>(4) If a railroad carrier or telecommunications carrier believes a special
circumstance exists for the placement of a line, wire, or cable across a railroad
right-of-way, the railroad carrier or telecommunications carrier may petition
the commission for additional requirements or for modification of the standard
crossing fee in its initial petition to the commission pursuant to subsection
(1) of this section. If the petition is filed with the request for additional
requirements or modification, the commission shall determine if a special
circumstance exists that necessitates additional requirements for such placement
or a modification of the standard crossing fee.</para>
<para>(5) This section applies to any telecommunications carrier certified
by the commission pursuant to section 86-128. This section does not apply
to any longitudinal encumbrance or any line, wire, or cable within any public
right-of-way and does not change, modify, or supersede any rights or obligations
created pursuant to sections 86-701 to 86-707.</para>
<para>(6)(a) A wire-crossing agreement between a railroad carrier and a telecommunications
carrier that includes a provision, clause, covenant, or agreement contained
in, collateral to, or affecting such wire-crossing agreement that purports
to indemnify, defend, or hold harmless the railroad carrier from any liability
for loss or damage resulting from the negligence or willful and wanton misconduct
of the carrier or its agents, employees, or independent contractors who are
directly responsible to such carrier or has the effect of indemnifying, defending,
or holding harmless such carrier from the negligence or willful and wanton
misconduct of the carrier or its agents, employees, or independent contractors
who are directly responsible to the carrier is against the public policy of
this state and is unenforceable.</para>
<para>(b) Nothing in this section shall affect a provision, clause, covenant,
or agreement in which the telecommunications carrier indemnifies, defends,
or holds harmless a railroad carrier against liability for loss or damage
to the extent that the loss or damage results from the negligence or willful
and wanton misconduct of the telecommunications carrier or its agents, employees,
or independent contractors who are directly responsible to the telecommunications
carrier.</para>
<para>(7) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Railroad carrier has the same meaning as in section 75-402; and</para>
<para>(b) Telecommunications carrier means a telecommunications common carrier
as defined in section 86-118 or a telecommunications contract carrier as defined
in section 86-120.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB181, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB47, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>