<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications And Technology" statutenumber="86-323"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-323</statuteno><catchline>Legislature; declaration of policy.</catchline><para>The Legislature declares that it is the policy of the state to preserve and advance universal service based on the following principles:</para><para>(1) Quality telecommunications and information services should be available at just, reasonable, and affordable rates;</para><para>(2) Access to advanced telecommunications and information services should be provided in all regions of the state;</para><para>(3) Consumers in all regions of the state, including low-income consumers and those in rural and high-cost areas, should have access to telecommunications and information services, including interexchange services and advanced telecommunications and information services, that are reasonably comparable to those services provided in urban areas and that are available at rates that are reasonably comparable to rates charged for similar services in urban areas;</para><para>(4) All providers of telecommunications should make an equitable and nondiscriminatory contribution to the preservation and advancement of universal service;</para><para>(5) There should be specific, predictable, sufficient, and competitively neutral mechanisms to preserve and advance universal service. Funds for the support of high-cost service areas will be available only to the designated eligible telecommunications companies providing service to such areas. Funds for the support of low-income customers, schools, libraries, and providers of health care to rural areas will be available to any entity providing telecommunications services, maintenance, and upgrading of facilities. The distribution of universal service funds should encourage the continued development and maintenance of telecommunications infrastructure;</para><para>(6) Elementary and secondary schools, libraries, and providers of health care to rural areas should have access to advanced telecommunications services as described in the Telecommunications Act of 1996. To promote the efficient use of facilities in rural areas, universal service rules should not preclude the sharing of facilities supported by universal service funds with other local users, if such ineligible users pay appropriate retail usage rates to the telecommunications company;</para><para>(7) The implicit support mechanisms in intrastate access rates throughout the state may be replaced while ensuring that local service rates in all areas of the state remain affordable; and</para><para>(8) The costs of administration of the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund should be kept to a minimum.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 686, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1999), &#167; 86-1404; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 201; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB661, &#167; 8.</para></source></law></legaldoc>