<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id986"><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications relay services" statutenumber="86-1029.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1029.04</statuteno><catchline>911 calls; transmission to next-generation 911 network; requirements; agreements; required; report.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, originating service provider means the telecommunications service provider, whether by wireline or wireless service, or the voice over Internet protocol service provider providing the capability for customers to originate 911 calls.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(c) of this section, or unless otherwise required by the Federal Communications Commission, no later than January 1, 2026, an originating service provider and the next-generation 911 service contractor shall cause:</para><para>(i) All 911 calls to be transmitted to the next-generation 911 network that allows 911 calls to be answered; and</para><para>(ii) All translation and routing to be completed to deliver all 911 calls, including associated location information in the requested Internet protocol-enabled service format, to the next-generation 911 network that allows 911 calls to be answered.</para><para>(b) No later than ten months prior to the date set forth in subdivision (2)(a) of this section, an originating service provider and the next-generation 911 service contractor shall enter into an agreement to cause the requirements of such subdivision to be met. If the originating service provider and the next-generation 911 service contractor have not entered into an agreement by such date, the originating service provider and the next-generation 911 service contractor shall notify the Public Service Commission to seek resolution of any unresolved issues in accordance with the commission's policies relating to interconnection arbitration and mediation.</para><para>(c) An originating service provider may enter into an agreement with the commission to establish an alternative timeframe for meeting the requirements of subdivision (2)(a) of this section. The originating service provider shall notify the commission of the dates and terms of the alternative timeframe within thirty days after entering into such agreement.</para><para>(3)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (3)(c) of this section, or unless otherwise required by the Federal Communications Commission, no later than January 1, 2026, a provider of telecommunications relay services and the next-generation 911 service contractor shall cause:</para><para>(i) All 911 calls to be transmitted to the next-generation 911 network that allows 911 calls to be answered; and</para><para>(ii) All translation and routing to be completed to deliver all 911 calls, including associated location information if received from the originating service provider in the requested Internet protocol-enabled service format, to the next-generation 911 network that allows 911 calls to be answered.</para><para>(b) No later than ten months prior to the date set forth in subdivision (3)(a) of this section, a provider of telecommunications relay services and the next-generation 911 service contractor shall enter into an agreement to cause the requirements of such subdivision to be met. If the provider of telecommunications relay services and the next-generation 911 service contractor have not entered into an agreement by such date, the provider of telecommunications relay services and the next-generation 911 service contractor shall notify the Public Service Commission to seek resolution of any unresolved issues in accordance with the commission's policies relating to interconnection arbitration and mediation.</para><para>(c) A provider of telecommunications relay services may enter into an agreement with the commission to establish an alternative timeframe for meeting the requirements of subdivision (3)(a) of this section. The telecommunications relay provider shall notify the commission of the dates and terms of the alternative timeframe within thirty days after entering into such agreement.</para><para>(4) No later than November 15, 2024, and no later than November 15 of each year thereafter, the next-generation 911 service contractor shall submit an annual report electronically to the Transportation and Telecommunications Committee of the Legislature and to the commission on the capabilities and redundancies of the next-generation 911 service network.</para><para>(5) Nothing in this section shall be construed to modify or change any requirement for an originating service provider to file a report with state and federal entities, including with public safety answering points and local governing bodies, in accordance with applicable local, state, or federal regulations and policies, regarding any impediment to transmitting and delivering 911 calls to the next-generation 911 network.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1031, &#167; 11. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>