<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id660"><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-1605"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1605</statuteno><catchline>Deregulated carrier; effects of deregulation.</catchline><para>(1) A deregulated carrier is not required to:</para><para>(a) Fulfill the obligations of a carrier of last resort;</para><para>(b) Comply with standards or reporting requirements related to quality of retail service;</para><para>(c) Comply with restrictions on rates for retail telecommunications services, including advanced telecommunications services, unless the restrictions are a condition of receiving grant funds administered by the commission or imposed for compliance with sections 86-139 to 86-157; or</para><para>(d) File an earnings report with the commission.</para><para>(2) The commission shall not provide a deregulated carrier with any funds from the Nebraska Telecommunications Universal Service Fund.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding any other provisions of Chapter 86, the commission shall have only the authority over a deregulated carrier provided under the Telecommunications Exchange Deregulation Act. If there is a conflict between the Telecommunications Exchange Deregulation Act and the other applicable provisions of Chapter 86, the Telecommunications Exchange Deregulation Act shall control.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section affects the continuing applicability of sections 86-122 to 86-124.</para><para>(5) The commission may receive, mediate, and hear complaints filed by any retail or wholesale customers against a deregulated carrier that are in the scope of the commission's authority provided under Chapter 86.</para><para>(6) A telecommunications company or communications provider shall not be required to fulfill the obligations of a carrier of last resort in an exchange that has been deregulated, unless such telecommunications company or communications provider consents to fulfilling such obligations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB311, &#167; 5. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>