<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id591"><amendatorysection statutenumber="86-1803" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1803</statuteno><catchline>Operator; requirements related to minor account holders.</catchline><para>(1) An operator shall clearly and conspicuously disclose to each minor account holder that such minor account holder is interacting with artificial intelligence:</para><para>(a) As a persistent visible disclaimer; or</para><para>(b) Both:</para><para>(i) At the beginning of each session; and</para><para>(ii) Appearing at least every three hours in a continuous conversational artificial intelligence service interaction.</para><para>(2) An operator shall not provide a minor account holder with points or similar rewards at unpredictable intervals with the intent to encourage increased engagement with the conversational artificial intelligence service.</para><para>(3) An operator shall, for minor account holders, institute reasonable measures to prevent the conversational artificial intelligence service from:</para><para>(a) Producing visual depictions of sexually explicit conduct;</para><para>(b) Generating direct statements that the account holder should engage in sexually explicit conduct; or</para><para>(c) Generating statements that sexually objectify the account holder.</para><para>(4) For minor account holders, the operator shall institute reasonable measures to prevent the conversational artificial intelligence service from generating statements that would lead a reasonable person to believe that they are interacting with a human, including:</para><para>(a) Explicit claims that the conversational artificial intelligence service is sentient or human;</para><para>(b) Statements that simulate emotional dependence;</para><para>(c) Statements that simulate romantic or sexual innuendos; or</para><para>(d) Role-playing of adult-minor romantic relationships.</para><para>(5) An operator shall offer tools for minor account holders, and, when such account holders are younger than thirteen years of age, their parents or guardians, to manage the account holders' privacy and account settings. An operator shall also offer related tools to the parents or guardians of minor account holders thirteen years of age and older, as appropriate based on relevant risks.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB525, &#167; 14. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2027</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>