<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id878"><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-1702"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1702</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Parental Rights in Social Media Act:</para><para>(1) Account holder means a person who, on or after July 1, 2026, creates an account or profile on a social media platform;</para><para>(2) Content includes a text, an image, or a video;</para><para>(3) Digitized identification card means a data file that contains all of the data elements visible on the face and back of a government-issued operator's license or government-issued identification document and displays the current status of the license or document;</para><para>(4)(a) Interactive computer service means an information service as defined in 47 U.S.C. 153, an information system, or an information access software that:</para><para>(i) Provides or enables access by multiple users to a computer server; and</para><para>(ii) Provides access to the Internet.</para><para>(b) An interactive computer service includes an Internet service, an Internet system, an Internet application, an Internet portal, and a website;</para><para>(5) Minor means an individual who is:</para><para>(a) Known or reasonably believed by a social media platform to be under eighteen years of age;</para><para>(b) Not emancipated; and</para><para>(c) A resident of this state;</para><para>(6) Parent means the parent or legal guardian of a minor;</para><para>(7) Person means an individual or entity;</para><para>(8) Post means content that an account holder makes available on a social media platform for other account holders and users to view;</para><para>(9) Reasonable age verification method includes requiring presentation of a digitized identification card or any commercially reasonable age verification method to confirm an individual's age;</para><para>(10) Social media company means a person that is an interactive computer service and that provides a social media platform;</para><para>(11)(a) Social media platform means a website or Internet application that:</para><para>(i) Allows a person to create an account; and</para><para>(ii) Enables an account holder to communicate with other account holders and users through posts.</para><para>(b) Social media platform does not include:</para><para>(i) A broadband Internet access service, as defined in 47 C.F.R. 8.1(b);</para><para>(ii) An email service;</para><para>(iii) An Internet service, Internet application, or website:</para><para>(A) That consists primarily of content that is not generated by account holders, but rather is preselected by the service, application, or website provider; and</para><para>(B) For which interactive functionality is incidental to, directly related to, or dependent upon, such preselected content;</para><para>(iv) Online shopping, if the interaction with other account holders or users is predominantly limited to the ability to (A) send, receive, request, or settle funds, (B) comment on transactions, (C) display goods for sale, (D) engage as consumers about products and reviews, or (E) post a wish list;</para><para>(v) An Internet service, Internet application, or website that primarily provides career development opportunities;</para><para>(vi) A cloud storage or cloud computing service;</para><para>(vii) An online service, application, or website in which interaction between users is predominately (A) used for technical support or (B) limited to reviewing products offered for sale by means of electronic commerce or commenting on such reviews posted by other users; or</para><para>(viii) Peer-to-peer payment platforms, if the interaction with other users or account holders is generally limited to the ability to send, receive, or request funds and to like or comment on such transactions, or other functions that are focused on sending, receiving, requesting, or settling payments between users or account holders; and</para><para>(12) User means a person who consumes posts on a social media platform but who is not an account holder.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB383, &#167; 27. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>