<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id464"><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-1703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1703</statuteno><catchline>Social media company; social media platform; account holder; minors; restrictions; age verification; parental consent.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, a social media company shall not permit a minor to become an account holder. A social media platform shall use a reasonable age verification method to verify the age of an individual seeking to become an account holder on the company's social media platform. A social media company may use a third-party vendor to perform such verification.</para><para>(b) A social media company or third-party vendor conducting such verification shall not retain any identifying information of an individual after verification is complete.</para><para>(2) A social media company may allow a minor to become an account holder if the parent of such minor provides express parental consent authorizing such minor to become an account holder. A social media company or third-party vendor shall verify the express parental consent which shall include:</para><para>(a) Age verification of the parent through a reasonable age verification method; and</para><para>(b) An oath, affirmation, or form signed by the parent and returned to the social media company or third-party vendor by common carrier, facsimile, or electronic scan stating that the consenting adult is the minor user's parent and authorizes such minor to become an account holder.</para><para>(3)(a) Once age and parental consent, if applicable, are verified, the social media company may permit the minor to become an account holder. Reverification of an account holder is not required unless parental consent is revoked by a parent.</para><para>(b) A social media company shall develop a method for a parent to revoke consent for a minor to be an account holder. If consent is revoked, a social media company shall remove the account of such parent's minor and prohibit such minor from becoming an account holder until additional express parental consent is provided.</para><para>(4) A social media company shall provide a parent of a minor account holder with methods for the parent to supervise the minor's account. Such methods shall include options for the parent to:</para><para>(a) View all posts the minor account holder makes under the social media platform account;</para><para>(b) View all responses and messages sent to or by the minor account holder in the social media platform account;</para><para>(c) Control the minor's privacy and account settings; and</para><para>(d) Monitor and limit the amount of time the minor account holder spends using the social media platform.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB383, &#167; 28. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>