<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-1028"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1028</statuteno><catchline>911 Service System Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The 911 Service System Fund is created. The fund shall consist of surcharges collected pursuant to sections 86-457 and 86-904, money transferred from the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund, any federal funds received for implementation and development of 911 service, and any other money designated for credit to the 911 Service System Fund. The fund shall be used for the costs of administering the fund, for the purposes specified in section 86-465 unless otherwise directed by federal law with respect to any federal funds, and for the purposes specified in the 911 Service System Act. The costs of administering the 911 Service System Fund shall be kept to a minimum.</para><para>(2) The fund shall not be subject to any fiscal-year limitation or lapse provision of unexpended balance at the end of any fiscal year or biennium. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act, and for the period July 1, 2017, through June 30, 2019, any interest earned by the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para><para>(3) Money in the 911 Service System Fund may be used to pay for costs incurred by or on behalf of governing bodies or public safety answering points to provide 911 service that are determined by the commission to be eligible for funding. The commission is not required to provide funding from the 911 Service System Fund to more than one public safety answering point in any county. Each entity that receives disbursements from the fund under this subsection shall make a full accounting of the money in a manner and form prescribed by the commission.</para><para>(4) The State Treasurer shall transfer any money in the Enhanced Wireless 911 Fund on July 1, 2018, to the 911 Service System Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB938, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB993, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>