<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id445"><amendatorysection chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-1069" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1069</statuteno><catchline>911 service outage; reports; required; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Communications service provider means a cable operator as defined in 47 U.S.C. 522, a provider of information service as defined in 47 U.S.C. 153, or a telecommunications carrier as defined in 47 U.S.C. 153, but does not include a wireless provider; and</para><para>(b) Outage has the same meaning as described in 47 C.F.R. 4.5(e).</para><para>(2) A communications service provider that is required to file reports with the Federal Communications Commission regarding a 911 service outage pursuant to 47 C.F.R. 4.9(h) shall also file copies of such reports with the Public Service Commission. The reports filed with the Public Service Commission shall follow the same timelines and provide the same information as outlined in 47 C.F.R. 4.9 and 4.11. Reports filed pursuant to this section shall be deemed confidential and shall not be subject to public disclosure pursuant to sections 84-712 to 84-712.09.</para><para>(3)(a) The Public Service Commission shall hold a public hearing no later than ninety days after receipt of the first report filed by a communications service provider pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. The commission may delay the hearing for good cause shown, but such delay shall be extended no longer than thirty days. The commission may hold subsequent hearings as it deems necessary.</para><para>(b) This subsection shall not apply if:</para><para>(i) The communications service provider has, in good faith, withdrawn the first report filed pursuant to subsection (2) of this section; or</para><para>(ii) The Public Service Commission has waived the requirements of this subsection by a majority vote of the commission.</para><para>(4) The Public Service Commission may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para><para>(5) This section shall only apply to 911 service outages in Nebraska.</para><para>(6) Nothing in this section shall be construed to authorize the Public Service Commission to regulate any activities prohibited by section 86-124.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1031, &#167; 13; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2024), &#167; 86-1031; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB362, &#167; 51. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law></legaldoc>