<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id744"><amendatorysection statutenumber="86-1802" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1802</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Conversational Artificial Intelligence Safety Act:</para><para>(1) Account holder means an individual who has, or opens, an account or profile to use a conversational artificial intelligence service;</para><para>(2)(a) Conversational artificial intelligence service means an artificial intelligence software application, web interface, or computer program that is accessible to the general public and that primarily simulates human conversation and interaction through textual, visual, or aural communications.</para><para>(b) Conversational artificial intelligence service does not include an application, web interface, or computer program that is any of the following:</para><para>(i) Primarily designed and marketed for use by developers or researchers;</para><para>(ii) A feature within another software application, web interface, or computer program that is not a conversational artificial intelligence service;</para><para>(iii) Designed to provide outputs relating to a narrow and discrete topic;</para><para>(iv) Primarily designed and marketed for commercial use by business entities;</para><para>(v) Functions as a speaker and voice command interface or voice-activated virtual assistant for a consumer electronic device;</para><para>(vi) Used by a business solely for internal purposes; or</para><para>(vii) Used by a business solely for customer service or strictly to provide users with information about available commercial services or products provided by the business, customer service account information, or other information strictly related to the business's customer service;</para><para>(3) Individual means a natural person;</para><para>(4) Minor means an individual that, based upon the circumstance, the operator has actual knowledge or reasonable certainty is younger than eighteen years of age;</para><para>(5) Minor account holder means an account holder who is a minor;</para><para>(6)(a) Operator means a person who makes available a conversational artificial intelligence service to the public.</para><para>(b) Operator does not include mobile application stores or search engines solely because they provide access to a conversational artificial intelligence service;</para><para>(7) Person means a natural person or legal entity; and</para><para>(8) Sexually explicit conduct and visual depiction have the same meanings as in 18 U.S.C. 2256.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB525, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2027</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>