<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id377"><amendatorysection statutenumber="86-1807" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1807</statuteno><catchline>Attorney General; enforcement authority; liability limitation.</catchline><para>(1) The Attorney General may enforce the Conversational Artificial Intelligence Safety Act.</para><para>(2)(a) The Attorney General may bring a civil action for appropriate relief against an operator for a violation of the Conversational Artificial Intelligence Safety Act, on behalf of the State of Nebraska or on behalf of any person aggrieved by a violation of the act.</para><para>(b) In an action under this section, appropriate relief includes:</para><para>(i) Such preliminary and other equitable or declaratory relief as may be appropriate;</para><para>(ii) An award of actual damages;</para><para>(iii) Civil penalties of at least one thousand dollars per violation, but in no event more than five hundred thousand dollars per operator. Any such civil penalty that is recovered shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska; and</para><para>(iv) Reasonable expenses incurred in bringing the civil action, including court costs, reasonable attorney's fees, investigative costs, witness fees, and deposition costs.</para><para>(3) Nothing in the Conversational Artificial Intelligence Safety Act shall be interpreted as creating a private right of action.</para><para>(4) The Conversational Artificial Intelligence Act shall not create liability for the developer of an artificial intelligence model for any violation of the act by a conversational artificial intelligence system developed by a third-party operator to provide a conversational artificial intelligence service for such developer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB525, &#167; 18. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2027</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>