<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Telecommunications and Technology" statutenumber="86-1027"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>86-1027</statuteno><catchline>Plan for 911 service system; contents; public hearings; report.</catchline><para>(1) The commission and the state 911 director shall develop and prepare a plan for a 911 service system, to be approved by the commission, and to be implemented by the commission and the state 911 director on or after July 1, 2018. The commission shall hold at least two public hearings on the plan: One hearing at least ninety days prior to the adoption of the plan; and one hearing at least thirty days prior to the adoption of the plan. The commission shall present the adopted plan to the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Transportation and Telecommunications Committee of the Legislature no later than December 1, 2017. The state 911 director, with the approval of the commission, shall prepare and provide a report to the Appropriations Committee and the Transportation and Telecommunications Committee on the progress of the development of the plan no later than February 1, 2017. The report shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(2) The plan adopted by the commission shall, at a minimum, detail the following:</para><para>(a) The costs associated with the implementation and estimated ongoing operation and maintenance of the 911 service system. The discussion of costs shall detail which costs the commission determines should be paid from the 911 Service System Fund, which costs would be the obligation of local governing bodies, and how the proposed costs represent a cost-effective plan;</para><para>(b) Recommendations to the Legislature for cost recovery for the implementation, operation, and maintenance of the 911 service system;</para><para>(c) The commission's proposal for carrying out its role as coordinator of the 911 service system;</para><para>(d) A recommendation of the number of public safety answering points that should be maintained in the state that are capable of next-generation 911 service; and</para><para>(e) Recommendations for any additional legislation required to implement the 911 service system.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB938, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB993, &#167; 17. </para><effectivedate>April 5, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>