<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="appendix"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Appendix" statutenumber="1-109"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-109</statuteno><catchline>CIVIL DEFENSE AND DISASTER COMPACT</catchline><para>AN ACT to ratify a civil defense and disaster compact on behalf of the State of Nebraska with any other state legally joining thereon; to provide for the prescribed duties of the Secretary of State as prescribed; and to provide the effect of the compact.</para><para>Be it enacted by the people of the State of Nebraska,</para><para>Section 1. The Legislature of this state hereby ratifies a Civil Defense and Disaster Compact, on behalf of the State of Nebraska, with any other state legally joining therein in the form substantially as follows:</para><para>"INTERSTATE CIVIL DEFENSE AND DISASTER COMPACT</para><para>The contracting states solemnly agree:</para><para>Article 1. The purpose of this compact is to provide mutual aid among the states in meeting any emergency or disaster from enemy attack or other cause (natural or otherwise) including sabotage and subversive acts and direct attacks by bombs, shellfire, and atomic, radiological, chemical, bacteriological means, and other weapons. The prompt, full and effective utilization of the resources of the respective states, including such resources as may be available from the United States government or any other source, are essential to the safety, care and welfare of the people thereof in the event of enemy action or other emergency, and any other resources, including personnel, equipment or supplies, shall be incorporated into a plan or plans of mutual aid to be developed among the Civil Defense agencies or similar bodies of the states that are parties hereto. The Directors of Civil Defense of all party states shall constitute a committee to formulate plans and take all necessary steps for the implementation of this compact.</para><para>Article 2. It shall be the duty of each party state to formulate civil defense plans and programs for application within such state. There shall be frequent consultation between the representatives of the states and with the United States government and the free exchange of information and plans, including inventories of any materials and equipment available for civil defense. In carrying out such defense plans and programs the party states shall so far as possible provide and follow uniform standards, practices and rules and regulations including:</para><para>(1) Insignia, arm bands and any other distinctive articles to designate and distinguish the different civil defense services;</para><para>(2) Black-outs and practice black-outs, air-raid drills, mobilization of civil defense forces and other tests and exercises;</para><para>(3) Warnings and signals for drills or attacks and the mechanical devices to be used in connection therewith;</para><para>(4) The effective screening or extinguishing of all lights and lighting devices and appliances;</para><para>(5) Shutting off water mains, gas mains, electric power connections and the suspension of all other utility services;</para><para>(6) All materials or equipment used or to be used for civil defense purposes in order to assure that such materials and equipment will be easily and freely interchangeable when used in or by any other party state;</para><para>(7) The conduct of civilians and the movement and cessation of movement of pedestrians and vehicular traffic, prior, during and subsequent to drills or attacks;</para><para>(8) The safety of public meetings or gatherings; and</para><para>(9) Mobile support units.</para><para>Article 3. Any party state requested to render mutual aid shall take such action as is necessary to provide and make available the resources covered by this compact in accordance with the terms hereof; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that it is understood that the state rendering aid may withhold resources to the extent necessary to provide reasonable protection for such state. Each party state shall extend to the civil defense forces of any other party state, while operating within its state limits under the terms and conditions of this compact, the same powers (except that of arrest unless specifically authorized by the receiving state), duties, rights, privileges and immunities as if they were performing their duties in the state in which normally employed or rendering services. Civil defense forces will continue under the command and control of their regular leaders but the organizational units will come under the operational control of the civil defense authorities of the state receiving assistance.</para><para>Article 4. Whenever any person holds a license, certificate or other permit issued by any state evidencing the meeting of qualifications for professional, mechanical or other skills, such person may render aid involving such skill in any party state to meet an emergency or disaster and such state shall give due recognition to such license, certificate or other permit as if issued in the state in which aid is rendered.</para><para>Article 5. No party state or its officers or employees rendering aid in another state pursuant to this compact shall be liable on account of any act or omission in good faith on the part of such forces while so engaged, or on account of the maintenance or use of any equipment or supplies in connection therewith.</para><para>Article 6. Inasmuch as it is probable that the pattern and detail of the machinery for mutual aid among two or more states may differ from that appropriate among other states party hereto, this instrument contains elements of a broad base common to all states, and nothing herein contained shall preclude any state from entering into supplementary agreements with another state or states. Such supplementary agreements may comprehend, but shall not be limited to, provisions for evacuation and reception of injured and other persons, and the exchange of medical, fire, police, public utility, reconnaissance, welfare, transportation and communications personnel, equipment and supplies.</para><para>Article 7. Each party state shall provide for the payment of compensation and death benefits to injured members of the civil defense forces of that state and the representatives of deceased members of such forces in case such members sustain injuries or are killed while rendering aid pursuant to this compact, in the same manner and on the same terms as if the injury or death were sustained within such state.</para><para>Article 8. Any party state rendering aid in another state pursuant to this compact shall be reimbursed by the party state receiving such aid for any loss or damage to, or expense incurred in the operation of any equipment answering a request for aid, and for the cost incurred in connection with such requests; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that any aiding party state may assume in whole or in part such loss, damage, expense, or other cost, or may loan such equipment or donate such services to the receiving party state without charge or cost; <emphasis type="italic">and provided further,</emphasis> that any two or more party states may enter into supplementary agreements establishing a different allocation of costs as among those states. The United States government may relieve the party state receiving aid from any liability and reimburse the party state supplying civil defense forces for the compensation paid to and the transportation, subsistence and maintenance expenses of such forces during the time of the rendition of such aid or assistance outside the state and may also pay fair and reasonable compensation for the use or utilization of the supplies, materials, equipment or facilities so utilized or consumed.</para><para>Article 9. Plans for the orderly evacuation and reception of the civilian population as the result of an emergency or disaster shall be worked out from time to time between representatives of the party states and the various local civil defense areas thereof. Such plans shall include the manner of transporting such evacuees, the number of evacuees to be received in different areas, the manner in which food, clothing, housing, and medical care will be provided, the registration of the evacuees, the providing of facilities for the notification of relatives or friends and the forwarding of such evacuees to other areas or the bringing in of additional materials, supplies, and all other relevant factors. Such plans shall provide that the party state receiving evacuees shall be reimbursed generally for the out-of-pocket expenses incurred in receiving and caring for such evacuees, for expenditures for transportation, food, clothing, medicines and medical care and like items. Such expenditures shall be reimbursed by the party state of which the evacuees are residents, or by the United States government under plans approved by it. After the termination of the emergency or disaster the party state of which the evacuees are resident shall assume the responsibility for the ultimate support or repatriation of such evacuees.</para><para>Article 10. This compact shall be available to any state, territory or possession of the United States, and the District of Columbia. The term "state" may also include any neighboring foreign country or province or state thereof.</para><para>Article 11. The committee established pursuant to Article 1 of this compact may request the Civil Defense Agency of the United States government to act as an informational and coordinating body under this compact, and representatives of such agency of the United States government may attend meetings of such committee.</para><para>Article 12. This compact shall become operative immediately upon its ratification by any state as between it and any other state or states so ratifying and shall be subject to approval by Congress unless prior Congressional approval has been given. Duly authenticated copies of this compact and of such supplementary agreements as may be entered into shall, at the time of their approval, be deposited with each of the party states and with the Civil Defense Agency and other appropriate agencies of the United States government.</para><para>Article 13. This compact shall continue in force and remain binding on each party state until the Legislature or the Governor of such party state takes action to withdraw therefrom. Such action shall be effective until thirty days after notice thereof has been sent by the Governor of the party state desiring to withdraw to the Governors of all other party states.</para><para>Article 14. This compact shall be construed to effectuate the purposes stated in Article 1 hereof. If any provision of this compact is declared unconstitutional, or the applicability thereof to any person or circumstance is held invalid, the constitutionality of the remainder of this compact and the applicability thereof to other persons and circumstances shall not be affected thereby."</para><para>Sec. 2. Duly authenticated copies of this act, upon its passage and approval, shall be transmitted by the Secretary of State to the Governor of each state, to the President of the Senate of the United States, to the Speaker of the United States House of Representatives, to the Federal Civil Defense Administration, or any successor agency, to the Secretary of State of the United States, and to the Council of State Governments.</para><para>Sec. 3. Nothing in this act shall be construed as a limitation of powers granted in any other act to enter into interstate compacts or other agreements relating to civil defense, or impairing in any respect the force and effect thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 202, p. 709.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
