<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="appendix">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Appendix" statutenumber="1-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-104</statuteno><catchline>IOWA-NEBRASKA BOUNDARY COMPACT</catchline><para><emphasis type="italic">(1) Ratification by Nebraska Legislature</emphasis></para><para>AN ACT to establish the boundary line between Iowa and Nebraska by agreement; to cede to Iowa and to relinquish jurisdiction over lands now in Nebraska but lying easterly of said boundary line and contiguous to lands in Iowa; to provide that the provisions of this act shall become effective upon the approval of and consent of the Congress of the United States of America to the compact effected by this act and House File 437 of the 1943 Session of the Iowa Legislature; to repeal Chapter 121, Session Laws of Nebraska, 1941; and to declare an emergency.</para><para>Be it enacted by the people of the State of Nebraska,</para><para>Section 1. That on and after the approval and consent of the Congress of the United States of America to this act and a similar and reciprocal act enacted by the Legislature of the State of Iowa, as hereinafter provided, the boundary line between the States of Iowa and Nebraska shall be described as follows:</para><para>Commencing at a point on the south line of section 20, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian, produced 861 1/2 feet west of the S.E. corner of said section, and running thence northwesterly to a point on the south line of lot 4 of section 10, in township 15 N., of range 13 E. of the sixth principal meridian, 2,275 feet east of the S.W. corner of the N.W. 1/4 of the S.E. 1/4 of said section 10; thence northerly, to a point on the north line of lot 4 aforesaid, 2,068 feet east of the center line of said section 10; thence north, to a point on the north line of section 10, 2,068 feet east of the quarter section corner on the north line of said section 10; thence northerly, to a point 312 feet WEST OF THE S.E. corner of lot 1, in section 3, township 15 N., range 13 E., aforesaid; thence northerly, to a point on the section line between sections 2 and 3, 358 feet south of the quarter section corner on said line; thence northeasterly, to the center of the S.E. 1/4 of the N.W. 1/4 of section 2 aforesaid; thence east, to the center of the W. 1/2 of lot 5, otherwise described as the S.W. 1/4 of the N.W. 1/4 of section 1, in township 15, range 13, aforesaid; thence southeasterly, to a point on the south line of lot 5 aforesaid, 1,540 feet west of the center of section 1, last aforesaid; thence south 2,050 feet, to a point 1,540 feet west of the north and south open line through said section 1; thence southwesterly, to the S.W. corner of the N.E. 1/4 of the S.W. 1/4 of section 21, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian; thence southeasterly, to a point 660 feet south of the N.E. corner of the N.W. 1/4 of the N.E. 1/4 of section 28, in township 75 N., range 44 W., aforesaid; and said line produced to the center of the channel of the Missouri river; thence up the middle of the main channel of the Missouri river to a point opposite the middle of the main channel of the Big Sioux river.</para>
<para>Commencing again at the point of beginning first named, namely, a point on the south line of section 20, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian, produced 861 1/2 feet west of S.E. corner of said section, and running thence southeasterly to a point 660 feet east of the S.W. corner of the N.W. 1/4 of the N.W. 1/4 of section 28, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian, and said line produced to the center of the channel of the Missouri river; thence down the middle of the main channel of the Missouri river to the northern boundary of the State of Missouri.</para>
<para>The said middle of the main channel of the Missouri river referred to in this act shall be the center line of the proposed stabilized channel of the Missouri river as established by the United States engineers' office, Omaha, Nebraska, and shown on the alluvial plain maps of the Missouri river from Sioux City, Iowa, to Rulo, Nebraska, and identified by file numbers AP-1 to 4 inclusive, dated January 30, 1940, and file numbers AP-5 to 10 inclusive, dated March 29, 1940, which maps are now on file in the United States engineers' office at Omaha, Nebraska, and copies of which maps are now on file with the Secretary of State of the State of Iowa and with the Secretary of State of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>Sec. 2. The State of Nebraska hereby cedes to the State of Iowa and relinquishes jurisdiction over all lands now in Nebraska but lying easterly of said boundary line and contiguous to lands in Iowa.</para><para>Sec. 3. Titles, mortgages, and other liens good in Iowa shall be good in Nebraska as to any lands Iowa may cede to Nebraska, and any pending suits or actions concerning said lands may be prosecuted to final judgment in Iowa and such judgment shall be accorded full force and effect in Nebraska.</para><para>Sec. 4. Taxes for the current year may be levied and collected by Iowa, or its authorized governmental subdivisions and agencies, on lands ceded to Nebraska and any liens or other rights accrued or accruing, including the right of collection, shall be fully recognized and the county treasurers of the counties affected shall act as agents in carrying out the provisions of this section; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that all liens or other rights accrued or accruing, as aforesaid, shall be claimed or asserted within five years after this act becomes effective, and if not so claimed or asserted, shall be forever barred.</para><para>Sec. 5. The provisions of this act shall become effective only upon the approval and consent of the Congress of the United States of America to the compact effected by this act and the similar and reciprocal act enacted by the 1943 Session of the Legislature of Iowa as House File 437 of that body.</para><para>Sec. 6. That Chapter 121, Session Laws of Nebraska, 1941, is repealed.</para><para>Sec. 7. Since an emergency exists, this act shall be in full force and take effect, from and after its passage and approval, according to law.</para><para>Approved May 7, 1943.</para><para><emphasis type="italic">(2) Ratification by Iowa Legislature</emphasis></para><para>AN ACT</para><para>TO ESTABLISH THE BOUNDARY LINE BETWEEN IOWA AND NEBRASKA BY AGREEMENT; TO CEDE TO NEBRASKA AND TO RELINQUISH JURISDICTION OVER LANDS NOW IN IOWA BUT LYING WESTERLY OF SAID BOUNDARY LINE AND CONTIGUOUS TO LANDS IN NEBRASKA; TO PROVIDE THAT THE PROVISIONS OF THE ACT BECOME EFFECTIVE UPON THE ENACTMENT OF A SIMILAR AND RECIPROCAL LAW BY NEBRASKA AND THE APPROVAL OF AND CONSENT TO THE COMPACT THEREBY EFFECTED BY THE CONGRESS OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO DECLARE AN EMERGENCY.</para><para><emphasis type="italic">BE IT ENACTED BY THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF THE STATE OF IOWA:</emphasis></para><para>Section 1. That on and after the enactment of a similar and reciprocal law by the State of Nebraska, and the approval and consent of the Congress of the United States of America, as hereinafter provided, the boundary line between the States of Iowa and Nebraska shall be described as follows:</para>
<para>Commencing at a point on the south line of section 20, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian, produced 861 1/2 feet west of the S.E. corner of said section, and running thence northwesterly to a point on the south line of lot 4 of section 10, in township 15 N., of range 13 E. of the sixth principal meridian, 2,275 feet east of the S.W. corner of the N.W. 1/4 of the S.E. 1/4 of said section 10; thence northerly, to a point on the north line of lot 4 aforesaid, 2,068 feet east of the center line of said section 10; thence north, to a point on the north line of section 10, 2,068 feet east of the quarter section corner on the north line of said section 10; thence northerly, to a point 312 feet west of the S.E. corner of lot 1, in section 3, township 15 N., range 13 E., aforesaid; thence, northerly, to a point on the section line between sections 2 and 3, 358 feet south of the quarter section corner on said line; thence northeasterly, to the center of the S.E. 1/4 of the N.W. 1/4 of section 2 aforesaid; thence east, to the center of the W. 1/2 of lot 5, otherwise described as the S.W. 1/4 of the N.W. 1/4 of section 1, in township 15, range 13, aforesaid; thence southeasterly, to a point on the south line of lot 5 aforesaid, 1,540 feet west of the center of section 1, last aforesaid; thence south 2,050 feet, to a point 1,540 feet west of the north and south open line through said section 1; thence southwesterly, to the S.W. corner of the N.E. 1/4 of the S.W. 1/4 of section 21, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian; thence southeasterly, to a point 660 feet south of the N.E. corner of the N.W. 1/4 of the N.E. 1/4 of section 28, in township 75 N., range 44 W., aforesaid; and said line produced to the center of the channel of the Missouri river; thence up the middle of the main channel of the Missouri river to a point opposite the middle of the main channel of the Big Sioux river.</para><para>Commencing again at the point of beginning first named, namely, a point on the south line of section 20, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian, produced 861 1/2 feet west of S.E. corner of said section, and running thence southeasterly to a point 660 feet east of the S.W. corner of the N.W. 1/4 of the N.W. 1/4 of section 28, in township 75 N., range 44 W. of the fifth principal meridian, and said line produced to the center of the channel of the Missouri river; thence down the middle of the main channel of the Missouri river to the northern boundary of the State of Missouri.</para><para>The said middle of the main channel of the Missouri river referred to in this act shall be the center line of the proposed stabilized channel of the Missouri river as established by the United States engineers' office, Omaha, Nebraska, and shown on the alluvial plain maps of the Missouri river from Sioux City, Iowa, to Rulo, Nebraska, and identified by file numbers AP-1 to 4 inclusive, dated January 30, 1940, and file numbers AP-5 to 10 inclusive, dated March 29, 1940, which maps are now on file in the United States engineers' office at Omaha, Nebraska, and copies of which maps are now on file with the secretary of state of the State of Iowa and with the secretary of state of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>Sec. 2. The State of Iowa hereby cedes to the State of Nebraska and relinquishes jurisdiction over all lands now in Iowa but lying westerly of said boundary line and contiguous to lands in Nebraska.</para><para>Sec. 3. Titles, mortgages, and other liens good in Nebraska shall be good in Iowa as to any lands Nebraska may cede to Iowa and any pending suits or actions concerning said lands may be prosecuted to final judgment in Nebraska and such judgments shall be accorded full force and effect in Iowa.</para><para>Sec. 4. Taxes for the current year may be levied and collected by Nebraska or its authorized governmental subdivisions and agencies on lands ceded to Iowa and any liens or other rights accrued or accruing, including the right of collection, shall be fully recognized and the county treasurers of the counties affected shall act as agents in carrying out the provisions of this section: <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that all liens or other rights accrued or accruing, as aforesaid, shall be claimed or asserted within five years after this act becomes effective, and if not so claimed or asserted, shall be forever barred.</para><para>Sec. 5. The provisions of this act shall become effective only upon the enactment of a similar and reciprocal law by the State of Nebraska and the approval of and consent to the compact thereby effected by the Congress of the United States of America. Said similar and reciprocal law shall contain provisions identical with those contained herein for the cession to Iowa of all lands now in Nebraska but lying easterly of said boundary line described in section 1 of this act and contiguous to lands in Iowa and also contain provisions identical with those contained in sections 3 and 4 of this act but applying to lands ceded to Nebraska.</para><para>Sec. 6. Whereas an emergency exists, this act shall be in full force and effect, subject to conditions as hereinabove expressed from and after its publication in the Sioux City Journal, a newspaper published at Sioux City, Iowa, and in the Nonpareil, a newspaper published at Council Bluffs, Iowa.</para><para>(Signed) Henry W. Burma</para><para>Speaker of the House</para><para>(Signed) Robert D. Blue</para><para>President of the Senate</para><para>I hereby certify that this Bill originated in the House and is known as House File 437, Fiftieth General Assembly.</para>
<para>(Signed) A.C. Gustafson</para><para>Chief Clerk of the House.</para><para>Approved April 15th, 1943.</para><para>(Signed) Bourke B. Hickenlooper</para><para>Governor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Nebraska: Laws 1943, c. 130, p. 434; </para><para>Iowa: Laws 1943, p. 797.</para></source><annotation><para>Where a river changes its main channel by flowing around intervening land as by deepening a smaller channel until it becomes the main channel, the boundary which was fixed as the main channel remains there, and title to riparian lands runs to the thread of the contiguous stream. Valder v. Wallis, 196 Neb. 222, 242 N.W.2d 112 (1976).</para><para>The word cedes as used herein covers all area formed before Compact date, whose titles, mortgages, and liens were at date of Compact good in the ceding state, and private titles to riparian lands good in Nebraska shall be good in Iowa. State of Nebraska v. State of Iowa, 406 U.S. 117 (1972).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
