<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN"
 "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="appendix">
<section><sectno></sectno>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Appendix" statutenumber="1-115">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo>
<statuteno>1-115</statuteno>
<catchline>BLUE RIVER BASIN COMPACT</catchline>
<para>A BILL</para>
<para>FOR AN ACT to ratify the compact entered into by the States of Kansas
and Nebraska on January 25, 1971, relating to the waters of the basins of
the Big Blue River and the Little Blue River; and to provide duties for the
Revisor of Statutes as prescribed.</para>
<para>Be it enacted by the people of the State of Nebraska,</para>
<para>Section 1. The compact respecting the waters of the Big Blue River Basin
entered into on January 25, 1971, by the States of Kansas and Nebraska, a
copy of which was filed in the office of the Secretary of State on January
28, 1971, and in the negotiation of which compact a representative of the
President of the United States participated, is ratified and approved in all
respects.</para>
<para>Sec. 2. After the effective date of this act, in any future edition
of a supplement to the Revised Statutes of Nebraska, 1943, or in any reissue
of permanent volume 2A of the Revised Statutes of Nebraska, the Revisor of
Statutes is authorized and directed to print the entire compact referred to
in section 1 of this act.</para>
<para>KANSAS-NEBRASKA BIG BLUE RIVER COMPACT</para>
<para>PREAMBLE</para>
<para>The State of Kansas and the State of Nebraska, acting through their
duly authorized Compact representatives, Keith S. Krause for the State of
Kansas and Dan S. Jones, Jr., for the State of Nebraska, after negotiations
participated in by Elmo W. McClendon, appointed by the President as the representative
of the United States of America, and in accordance with the consent to such
negotiations granted by an Act of Congress of the United States of America,
approved June 3, 1960, Public Law 489, 86th Congress, 2nd Session, have agreed
that the major purposes of this Compact concerning the waters of the Big Blue
River and its tributaries are:</para>
<para>A. To promote interstate comity between the States of Nebraska and Kansas;</para>
<para>B. To achieve an equitable apportionment of the waters of the Big Blue
River Basin between the two States and to promote orderly development thereof;
and</para>
<para>C. To encourage continuation of the active pollution-abatement programs
in each of the two States and to seek further reduction in both natural and
man-made pollution of the waters of the Big Blue River Basin.</para>
<para>To accomplish these purposes, the said States have agreed as set forth
in the following Articles.</para>
<para>Article I&#8212;DEFINITIONS</para>
<para>As used in this Compact:</para>
<para>1.1 The term "State" shall mean either State signatory hereto, and it
shall be construed to include any person, entity, or agency of either State
who, by reason of official responsibility or by designation of the Governor
of the State, is acting as an official representative of the State;</para>
<para>1.2 The term "Kansas-Nebraska Big Blue River Compact Administration,"
or the term "Administration," means the agency created by this Compact for
the administration thereof;</para>
<para>1.3 The term "Big Blue River Basin" means all of the drainage basin
of the Big Blue and Little Blue Rivers in Nebraska and Kansas downstream to
the confluence of the Big Blue River with the Kansas River near Manhattan,
Kansas;</para>
<para>1.4 The term "Big Blue River Basin in Nebraska" means all of the drainage
basin of the Big Blue River in Nebraska and is exclusive of the drainage basin
of the Little Blue River in Nebraska;</para>
<para>1.5 The term "minimum mean daily flow" means the minimum mean flow for
any one calendar day;</para>
<para>1.6 The term "pollution" means contamination or other undesirable alteration
of any of the physical, chemical, biological, radiological, or thermal properties
of the waters of the basin, or the discharge into the waters of the basin
of any liquid, gaseous, or solid substances that create or are likely to result
in a nuisance, or that render or are likely to render the waters into which
they are discharged harmful, detrimental, or injurious to public health, safety,
or welfare, or that are harmful, detrimental, or injurious to beneficial uses
of the water;</para>
<para>1.7 The term "water project" means any physical structure of any man-made
changes which affect the quantity or quality of natural water supplies or
natural streamflows and which are designed to bring about greater beneficial
use of the water resources of an area;</para>
<para>1.8 The term "natural flow" means that portion of the flow in a natural
stream that consists of direct runoff from precipitation on the land surface,
ground-water infiltration to the stream, return flows to the natural stream
from municipal, agricultural, or other uses, and releases from storage for
no designated beneficial use;</para>
<para>1.9 The term "inactive water appropriation" means a water right that
is subject to cancellation or termination for non-use.</para>
<para>Article II&#8212;DESCRIPTION OF THE BASIN</para>
<para>2.1 The Big Blue River, a tributary of the Kansas River, drains an area
of 9,696 square miles in south central Nebraska and north central Kansas.
About 75 percent of the Big Blue River Basin is in Nebraska, and the remainder
is in Kansas. The Big Blue River and its principal tributary, the Little Blue
River, join near Blue Rapids, Kansas. From there, the Big Blue River flows
generally southward to join the Kansas River near Manhattan, Kansas, as shown
on Exhibit A.</para>
<para>2.2 Much of the upper portion of the basin in Nebraska is underlain
with sands and gravels that supply large quantities of water to irrigation
wells. The lower portion of the basin in Nebraska and that portion of the
basin in Kansas lack significant groundwater supplies except within the major
stream valleys.</para>
<para>Article III&#8212;ORGANIZATION OF COMPACT ADMINISTRATION</para>
<para>3.1 Administration Agency. There is hereby established an interstate
administrative agency, to be known as the "Kansas-Nebraska Big Blue River
Compact Administration," to administer the Compact.</para>
<para>3.2 Administration Membership. The Administration shall be composed
of one ex officio member and one advisory member from each State, plus a Federal
member to be appointed by the President if he so desires. The ex officio member
from each State shall be the official charged with the duty of administering
the laws of his State pertaining to water rights. Said official shall designate
a representative who may serve in his place at meetings of the Administration.
All actions taken by the designated representative in the transaction of the
business of the Administration shall be in the name of the official he represents
and shall be binding on that official. The advisory member from each State
may serve in any capacity within the Administration. He shall reside in the
Big Blue River Basin portion of the State he represents.</para><para>The Governor of each
State shall appoint the advisory member from that state for a term of 4 years.
This appointment shall be made within 90 days after the effective date of
this Compact.</para>
<para>3.3 Administration Government. The Administration shall hold its first
meeting within 120 days after the effective date of this Compact, and it shall
meet at least annually thereafter. The Federal member, if one be designated,
shall serve as Chairman, without vote. If no Federal representative is appointed,
the Administration shall select a Chairman, in addition to such officers as
may be provided for in the rules and regulations, to serve at the will of
the Administration. A meeting quorum shall consist of the ex officio members
from both States, or their designated representatives. Each State shall have
but one vote, cast by the ex officio member or his representative. All actions
must be approved by both ex officio members or their representatives. Minutes
of each meeting shall be kept, and they shall be available for public inspection.</para>
<para>3.4 Administration Powers and Duties. The Administration shall have
the power to adopt rules and regulations consistent with the provisions of
this Compact, to enforce such rules and regulations, and to otherwise carry
out its responsibilities. It may institute action in its own name in courts
of competent jurisdiction to compel compliance with the provisions of this
Compact and with the rules and regulations it adopts.</para><para>The Administration is hereby authorized to employ the technical and
clerical staff necessary to carry out its functions, and to maintain the office
and appurtenances necessary to conduct its business. It may employ attorneys,
engineers, or other consultants. It may purchase equipment and services necessary
to its functions.</para>
<para>The Administration shall publish an annual report including a review
of its activities and financial status. It may also prepare and publish such
other reports and publications as it deems necessary.</para>
<para>In order to provide a sound basis for carrying out the apportionment
provisions of this Compact, the Administration shall cause to be established
such stream-gaging stations, ground-water observation wells, and other data-collection
facilities as are necessary for administering this Compact; and it shall install
such other equipment and collect such data therefrom, for a period of not
less than 5 years, as are necessary or desirable for evaluating the effects
of pumping of wells on the flows of the Big Blue and Little Blue Rivers at
the Kansas-Nebraska state line. The well area to be considered is described
in Article V, paragraph 5.2.</para><para>The Administration shall have authority to accept funds from local,
State, and Federal sources. It may enter into cooperative agreements and contribute
funds to support such data-collection and analysis programs as are necessary
for administration of the Compact.</para>
<para>Article IV&#8212;RESPONSIBILITY OF EACH STATE</para>
<para>4.1 Expenses of Administration. Each State and Federal member of the
Administration shall receive such compensation and such reimbursement for
travel and subsistence as are provided by the government he represents, and
he shall be paid by that government.</para>
<para>4.2 Budget. Each year, the Administration shall prepare a properly documented
budget covering the anticipated expenditures of the Administration for the
following fiscal period. Each State shall make provision in its budget for
funds to pay its share of the expenses of the Administration, which shall
be divided equally between the States of Kansas and Nebraska. The Administration
shall establish a fund to which each State shall contribute equally and from
which the expenses of the Administration shall be paid.</para>
<para>4.3 Records and Information. The State of Kansas and the State of Nebraska
shall cooperate with the Administration and furnish to it such records, information,
plans, data, and assistance as may be reasonably available; and they shall
keep the Administration advised of Federal activities in connection with planning,
design, construction, operation, and maintenance of water-resource projects
in the Big Blue River Basin. Any local, public, or private agency collecting
water data or planning, designing, constructing, operating, or maintaining
any water project or facility in the Big Blue River Basin shall keep the Administration
advised of its investigations and of any proposed changes and additions to
existing projects and facilities, and it shall submit plans for new projects
to the Administration for review of those project aspects affecting surface-water
flowage and quality.</para>
<para>Article V&#8212;APPORTIONMENT OF WATERS OF THE BIG BLUE RIVER BASIN</para>
<para>5.1 Principles of Apportionment. The physical and other conditions peculiar
to the Big Blue River Basin constitute the basis for this apportionment, and
neither of the signatory States hereby, nor the Congress of the United States
by its consent hereto, concedes that this apportionment establishes any general
principle with respect to any other interstate stream.</para><para>The States of Kansas
and Nebraska subscribe to the principle of including storage capacity for
low-flow regulation in reservoirs constructed by the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation
and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, and to the principle of such administration
as is required to assure that water released from storage for low-flow regulation
shall remain available in the stream to accomplish its intended purpose.</para>
<para>5.2 Nebraska Apportionment. The State of Nebraska shall have free and
unrestricted use of the waters of the Little Blue and Big Blue River Basins
in Nebraska, such use to be in accordance with the laws of the State of Nebraska,
subject to the limitations set forth below.</para><para>(a) Water appropriations of record
in the Little Blue and Big Blue River Basins in Nebraska on November 1, 1968,
that were then inactive, shall be cancelled by due process of laws in effect
in that State.</para><para>(b) During the period, May 1-September 30, the State of Nebraska
shall regulate diversions from natural flow of streams in the Little Blue
and Big Blue River Basins by water appropriators junior to November 1, 1968,
in order to maintain minimum mean daily flows at the state-line gaging stations
(which are now located at Fairbury and Barneston, respectively, but which
may be relocated at such other places as may be designated state-line gaging
stations by the Administration) during each month as follows:</para>
<para><table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4">
<?PubTbl tgroup clmarg="0.00pt" crmarg="0.00pt" ctmarg="0.00pt" cbmarg="2.10pt"?>
<colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1.04*"/><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.10*"/>
<colspec colname="col3" colwidth="0.93*"/><colspec colname="col4" colwidth="0.93*"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="right"><?Pub _font Underline="yes"?>Little
Blue River<?Pub /_font?></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="right"><?Pub _font Underline="yes"?>Big
Blue River<?Pub /_font?></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">May</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">45 cfs</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">May</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">45 cfs</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">June</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">45 cfs</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">June</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">45 cfs</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">July<?Pub Caret?></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">75 cfs</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">July</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">80 cfs</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">August</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">80 cfs</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">August</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">90 cfs</entry>
</row>
<row>
<?PubTbl row rht="0.31in"?>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">September</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">60 cfs</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">September</entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">65 cfs</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></para>
<para>When such action is necessary to maintain the above schedule of flows,
the State of Nebraska shall:</para><para>(1) Limit diversions by natural-flow appropriators
in Nebraska in accordance with their water appropriations;</para>
<para>(2) Close, in reverse order of priority, natural-flow appropriations
with priority dates subsequent to November 1, 1968, including rights to store
water in the conservation-storage zones of reservoirs;</para>
<para>(3) Enjoin all persons not holding valid natural-flow appropriations
from taking water during periods when the exercise of junior natural-flow
appropriations is being restricted;</para>
<para>(4) Regulate, in the same manner that diversion of natural flows is
regulated, withdrawals of water from irrigation wells installed after November
1, 1968, except equivalent wells drilled to replace wells installed before
that date, in the alluvium and valley side terrace deposits within one mile
from the thread of the river and between the mouth of Walnut Creek and the
Kansas-Nebraska state line on the Little Blue River and between the mouth
of Turkey Creek and the Kansas-Nebraska state line on the Big Blue River (as
delineated on Exhibits A and B of Supplement No. 1 to the Report of the Engineering
Committee) provided that, if the regulation of such wells fails to yield any
measurable increases in flows at the state-line gaging stations as determined
by the investigations to be undertaken under Article III, paragraph 3.4, the
regulation of such wells shall be discontinued. Determination of the effect
on streamflow of the pumping of such wells shall rest with the Administration.</para>
<para>Delivery of water under the terms of this article shall be deemed to
be in compliance with its provisions when the amounts passing the state-line
gaging stations are substantially equivalent to the scheduled amounts. Minor
irregularities in flow shall be disregarded.</para>
<para>(c) The storage capacity provided in reservoirs in the Little Blue River
Basin in Nebraska shall be limited to a total of 200,000 acre-feet. Similarly,
the storage capacity in reservoirs in the Big Blue River Basin in Nebraska
shall be limited to 500,000 acre-feet. These limitations are exclusive of
storage capacity that may be found necessary for regulation and use of waters
imported into these basins in Nebraska; exclusive of storage capacity in small
reservoir projects where the storage of water for subsequent use is less than
200 acre-feet; exclusive of storage capacity allocated to sedimentation and
flood control; and exclusive of storage capacity allocated to, and from which
water is released to accomplish, low-flow augmentation for improvement of
water quality, for fishery, wildlife, or recreation purposes, or for meeting
the flow schedules at the Kansas-Nebraska state line as set out in Article
V, paragraph 5.2.</para>
<para>5.3 Kansas Apportionment. The State of Kansas shall have free and unrestricted
use of all waters of the Big Blue River Basin flowing into Kansas from Nebraska
in accordance with this Compact, and of all waters of the basin originating
in Kansas, excepting such waters as may, in the future, flow from Kansas into
Nebraska.</para>
<para>5.4 Transbasin Diversion. In the event of any importation of water into
the Big Blue River Basin by either State, the State making the importation
shall have exclusive use of such imported water, including identifiable return
flows therefrom. Neither State shall authorize the exportation from the Big
Blue River of water originating within that basin without the approval of
the Administration.</para>
<para>Article VI&#8212;WATER QUALITY CONTROL</para>
<para>6.1 The States of Kansas and Nebraska mutually agree to the principle
of individual State efforts to control natural and man-made water pollution
within each State and to the continuing support of both States in active water
pollution control programs.</para>
<para>6.2 The two States agree to cooperate, through their appropriate State
agencies, in the investigation, abatement, and control of sources of alleged
interstate pollution within the Big Blue River Basin whenever such sources
are called to their attention by the Administration.</para>
<para>6.3 The two States agree to cooperate in maintaining the quality of
the waters of the Big Blue River Basin at or above such water quality standards
as may be adopted, now or hereafter, by the water pollution control agencies
of the respective States in compliance with the provisions of the Federal
Water Quality Act of 1965, and amendments thereto.</para>
<para>6.4 The two States agree to the principle that neither State may require
the other to provide water for the purpose of water quality control as a substitute
for adequate waste treatment.</para>
<para>Article VII&#8212;GENERAL PROVISIONS</para>
<para>7.1 Right to Store Water in Upper State. The right of the State of Kansas
or of any person, corporation, local agency, or entity in Kansas to construct
or participate in the future construction and use of any storage reservoir
or diversion works in the Big Blue and Little Blue Basins of Nebraska for
the purpose of regulating water to be used in Kansas shall never be denied;
provided, that such right is subject to the laws of the State of Nebraska
and that any such storage for use by Kansas shall be excluded from the limitations
on storage under Article V, paragraph 5.2(c).</para><para>Releases of water from storage
provided by Kansas interests in the State of Nebraska shall not be counted
toward meeting the minimum flow requirements at the State line under the provisions
of paragraph 5.2(b).</para>
<para>7.2 Disclaimer. Nothing contained in this Compact shall be deemed:</para>
<para>1. To impair, extend, or otherwise affect any right or power of the United States,
its agencies, or its instrumentalities involved herein;</para><para>2. To subject to the
laws of the States of Kansas and Nebraska any property or rights of the United
States that were not subject to the laws of those States prior to the date
of this Compact;</para><para>3. To interfere with or impair the right or power of either
signatory State to regulate within its boundaries the appropriation, use,
and control of waters within that State consistent with its obligations under
this Compact.</para>
<para>7.3 Invalidity in Part. Should a court of competent jurisdiction hold
any part of this Compact to be contrary to the constitution of either signatory
State or to the Constitution of the United States, all other severable provisions
of this Compact shall continue in full force and effect.</para>
<para>7.4 Future Review. After the expiration of 5 years following the effective
date of this Compact, the Administration may review any provisions hereof;
and it shall meet for such review whenever a member of the Administration
from either State requests such review. All provisions hereof shall remain
in full force and effect until changed and amended within the intent of the
Compact by unanimous action of the Administration, and until such changes
in this Compact are ratified by the Legislatures of the respective States
and are consented to by the Congress of the United States, in the same manner
that this Compact is required to be ratified and consented to before it becomes
effective.</para>
<para>7.5 Termination. This Compact may be terminated at any time by appropriate
action of the Legislatures of both signatory States. In the event of amendment
or termination of the Compact, the water-resource developments made in compliance
with, and reliant upon, this Compact shall continue unimpaired.</para>
<para>Article VIII&#8212;RATIFICATION</para>
<para>8.1 This Compact shall become binding and obligatory when it shall have
been ratified by the Legislature of each State and consented to by the Congress
of the United States and when the Congressional act consenting to this Compact
includes the consent of Congress to name and join the United States as a party
in any litigation in the United States Supreme Court, if the United States
is an indispensable party and if the litigation arises out of this Compact
or its application, and if a signatory State is a party thereto.</para>
<para>8.2 Notice of ratification by the Legislature of each State shall be
given by the Governor of that State to the Governor of the other State and
to the President of the United States, and the President is hereby requested
to give notice to the Governor of each State of the consent by the Congress
of the United States.</para>
<para>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the authorized representatives have executed three
counterparts hereof, each of which shall be and constitute an original, one
of which shall be deposited with the Administrator of General Services of
the United States, and one of which shall be forwarded to the Governor of
each State.</para>
<para>Done at Lincoln, Nebraska, this 25th day of January 1971.</para><para>/S/ KEITH
S. KRAUSE</para><para>Commissioner for the State of Kansas</para><para>/S/ DAN S. JONES, Jr.</para><para>Commissioner
for the State of Nebraska</para>
<para>APPROVED:</para>
<para>/S/ ELMO W. McCLENDON</para><para>Representative of the United States of America</para>
</amendatorysection></section>
<source>
<para>Laws 1971, LB 609.</para></source></law></legaldoc>
