<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="appendix"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Appendix" statutenumber="1-118"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-118</statuteno><catchline>MISSOURI RIVER BARGE TRAFFIC COMPACT</catchline><para>A BILL</para><para>FOR AN ACT to direct the Governor to enter into a compact with Iowa, Missouri, Kansas, and other states having an interest in the promotion of barge traffic on the Missouri River; to develop the Missouri River for more barge traffic and to promote the use of barges on the Missouri River.</para><para>Be it enacted by the people of the State of Nebraska,</para><para>Source: Laws 1980, LB 759, title; Laws 1981, LB 118, &#167; 2.</para><para>Section 1. The Governor of Nebraska is hereby authorized and directed to execute a compact on behalf of the State of Nebraska with the States of Iowa, Missouri, Kansas, and other states having an interest in the promotion of barge traffic on the Missouri River legally joining therein, in form substantially as follows:</para><para>ARTICLE I</para><para>The purposes of this compact are to provide for the most efficient use of the waters of the Missouri River; to increase the amount of barge traffic on the Missouri River which flows along or through the compact states; to take necessary steps to develop the Missouri River and its banks to handle more barge traffic than is presently handled; to encourage the use of barges on the Missouri River for transporting bulk goods, especially farm commodities; and to promote joint action between the compact parties to accomplish the above purposes.</para><para>ARTICLE II</para><para>It shall be the responsibility of the compact states to accomplish the purposes in Article I through the official in each state who is now or may hereafter be charged with the duty of administering the public waters and to collect and correlate through such officials the data necessary for the proper administration of the compact. Such officials may, by unanimous action, adopt rules and regulations to accomplish the purposes of this compact. To render advice and make recommendations to the Nebraska official charged with administration of this compact, the Governor of Nebraska shall appoint an advisory committee to be composed of three individuals with a demonstrated interest in barge transportation. Members of the advisory committee shall serve terms of three years and may be reappointed. Members shall receive no compensation, but shall be reimbursed for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in performing their official duties as provided in sections 81-1174 to 81-1177 for state employees.</para><para>ARTICLE III</para><para>The states of Iowa, Missouri, Kansas, Nebraska, and other states having an interest in the promotion of barge traffic on the Missouri River agree that within a reasonable time they shall fulfill the obligations of this compact and that each shall authorize the proper official or agency in its state to take the necessary steps to promote the use of barges and develop the Missouri River for greater amounts of barge traffic.</para><para>ARTICLE IV</para><para>Nothing in this act shall be construed to limit the powers granted in any other act to enter into interstate or other agreements relating to the Missouri River, nor alter the relations between the respective internal responsibilities of the government of a party state and its subdivisions; or impair or affect any rights, powers, or jurisdiction of the United States, or those acting by or under its authority, in, over, and to the waters of the Missouri River.</para><para>ARTICLE V</para><para>Unless this compact is entered into on or before July 1, 1984, the Governor shall take no further action to execute the compact.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 759, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 118, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>
