<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd">
<legaldoc><law type="appendix">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Appendix" statutenumber="1-103"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>1-103</statuteno>
<catchline>RESOLUTION FOR JEFFERSON DAY</catchline>
<para>WHEREAS, Thomas Jefferson was born on the thirteenth day of April 1743, and was a signer of the Declaration of Independence, and</para>
<para>WHEREAS, he is known as the great believer of democracy and maintained that "Those who labor in the earth are the chosen people of God, if ever he had a chosen people, whose breasts he has made his peculiar deposit for substantial and genuine virtue," and</para>
<para>WHEREAS, he was a great statesman and scholar holding the various positions, among others, of Governor of Virginia, Minister to France, Secretary of State, Vice President, and President, and</para>
<para>WHEREAS, it is fitting that the recurring anniversary of this day be commemorated with appropriate patriotic and public exercises in observing and commemorating the birth of this great American statesman, NOW THEREFORE <emphasis type="italic">Be it Resolved by the House of Representatives of the State of Nebraska, the Senate Concurring:</emphasis></para>
<para>Section 1. That the Governor of the State of Nebraska is authorized and directed to issue a proclamation calling upon the officials of the state government and the various subdivisions thereof in local communities to display the flag of the United States on all public buildings on April thirteenth of each year and inviting the people of the state of Nebraska to observe the day in schools and other suitable places, with appropriate ceremonies in commemoration of the birth of Thomas Jefferson.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source>
<para>Laws 1935, c. 124, p. 445.</para>
</source>
</law></legaldoc>
