<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id20">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id22" statutenumber="77-202.12"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-202.12</statuteno><catchline id="id25">Public property;
taxation status; county assessor; duties; appeal.</catchline><para>(1)
On or before March 1, the county assessor shall send notice to the state or
to any governmental subdivision if it has property not being used for a public
purpose upon which a payment in lieu of taxes is not made. Such notice shall
inform the state or governmental subdivision that the property will be subject
to taxation for property tax purposes. The written notice shall contain the
legal description of the property and be given by first-class mail addressed
to the state's or governmental subdivision's last-known address. If the property
is leased by the state or the governmental subdivision to another entity and
the lessor does not intend to pay the taxes for the lessee as allowed under
subsection (4) of section 77-202.11, the lessor shall immediately forward
the notice to the lessee.</para>
<para>(2) The state, governmental subdivision, or lessee may protest
the determination of the county assessor that the property is not used for
a public purpose to the county board of equalization on or before April 1.
The county board of equalization shall issue its decision on the protest on
or before May 1.</para>
<para>(3) The decision of the county board of equalization may be
appealed to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission on or before June 1.
The Tax Commissioner in his or her discretion may intervene in an appeal pursuant
to this section within thirty
days after notice by the Tax Equalization and Review Commission that an appeal
has been filed pursuant to this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 271, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 263, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
