<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id19"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-377.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>77-377.02</statuteno><catchline>Delinquent tax collection; collection agency; fees; remit funds.</catchline><para>(1) Fees for services, reimbursements, or other remuneration to such collection agency shall be based on the amount of tax, penalty, and interest actually collected and shall not be subject to the requirements of section 73-203 or 73-204. Each contract entered into between the Tax Commissioner and the collection agency shall provide for the payment of fees for such services, reimbursements, or other remuneration not in excess of fifty percent of the total amount of delinquent taxes, penalties, and interest actually collected.</para><para>(2) If, at the time a delinquent tax claim is assigned to a collection agency, any collection fees or costs were added to the tax liability pursuant to subsections (1) and (2) of section 77-371, then a portion of such fees and costs, up to fifty percent of the balance of the delinquent tax claim, shall be added to the amount owed and collected from the taxpayer along with the fees for the collection agency's services as provided in the contract. The collection fees and costs added to the amount owed and collected from the taxpayer pursuant to this subsection shall be remitted and deposited in the same manner as the taxes being collected. For purposes of this subsection, delinquent tax claim shall have the same meaning as in section 77-377.01.</para><para>(3) All funds collected, less the fees for the collection agency's services as provided in the contract, shall be remitted to the Tax Commissioner within forty-five days from the date of collection from a taxpayer. Forms to be used for such remittances shall be prescribed by the Tax Commissioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 170, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB901, &#167; 17. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2026</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>