<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id58"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3,114"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3,114</statuteno><catchline>Tax or other incentive programs; foreign adversarial company; ineligible.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Company means any corporation, partnership, association, organization, or other combination of persons;</para><para>(b) Foreign adversary means those countries listed in 15 C.F.R. 791.4, as such regulation existed on April 1, 2025;</para><para>(c) Foreign adversarial company means a company that:</para><para>(i) Is organized under the laws of a foreign adversary;</para><para>(ii) Has its principal place of business within a foreign adversary;</para><para>(iii) Is owned in whole or in part, operated, or controlled by the government of a foreign adversary; or</para><para>(iv) Is a subsidiary or parent of any company otherwise described in subdivision (1)(c) of this section; and</para><para>(d) Government of a foreign adversary means any person or group of persons exercising sovereign de facto or de jure political jurisdiction over any foreign adversary, or over any part of such country, and includes any subdivision of any such group and any group or agency to which such sovereign de facto or de jure authority or functions are directly or indirectly delegated. Such term shall include any faction or body of insurgents within a country assuming to exercise governmental authority whether such faction or body of insurgents has or has not been recognized by the United States.</para><para>(2) A foreign adversarial company shall be ineligible to receive any benefits under an incentive program of the State of Nebraska, including under:</para><para>(a) The Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act;</para><para>(b) The ImagiNE Nebraska Act;</para><para>(c) The Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act;</para><para>(d) The Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act;</para><para>(e) The Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act;</para><para>(f) The Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act;</para><para>(g) The New Markets Job Growth Investment Act;</para><para>(h) The Urban Redevelopment Act; and</para><para>(i) Any other tax or other incentive program created by legislative or executive action for the purpose of recruitment or retention of businesses in Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB644, &#167; 31. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5201.
    </para><para><emphasis>ImagiNE Nebraska Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act
    </emphasis> see section 77-5801.
    </para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act,
    </emphasis> see section 77-27,187.
    </para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act,
    </emphasis> see section 77-2901.
    </para><para><emphasis>New Markets Job Growth Investment Act,
    </emphasis> see section 77-1101.
    </para><para><emphasis>Urban Redevelopment Act,
    </emphasis> see section 77-6901.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>