<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-366"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-366</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; officers and employees; deputies; bond or insurance; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall appoint or employ deputies, investigators, inspectors, agents, security personnel, and other persons as he or she deems necessary to administer and effectively enforce all provisions of the revenue and property tax laws of this state. The appointed personnel shall hold office at the pleasure of the Tax Commissioner. Any appointed or employed personnel shall perform the duties assigned by the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(2) All personnel appointed or employed by the Tax Commissioner shall be bonded or insured as required by section 11-201. As specified by the Tax Commissioner, certain personnel shall be vested with the authority and power of a law enforcement officer to carry out the laws of this state administered by the Tax Commissioner or the Department of Revenue and to enforce sections 28-1101 to 28-1117 relating to possession of a gambling device pursuant to the limitations in section 9-1,101. Such personnel shall be empowered to arrest with or without a warrant, file and serve any lien, seize property, serve and return a summons, warrant, or subpoena issued by the Tax Commissioner, collect taxes, and bring an offender before any court with jurisdiction in this state, except that such personnel shall not be authorized to carry weapons or enforce any laws other than laws administered by the Tax Commissioner or the Department of Revenue and sections 28-1101 to 28-1117 relating to possession of a gambling device pursuant to the limitations in section 9-1,101.</para><para>(3) Subsection (2) of this section shall not be construed to restrict any other law enforcement officer of this state from enforcing any state law, revenue or otherwise.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 834, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 821, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 36, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 884, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB638, &#167; 19.</para></source></law></legaldoc>