<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id71"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id73" statutenumber="77-373.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id75">77-373.01</statuteno><catchline id="id76">Department of Labor and Department of Revenue; statistical compilation; confidentiality; disclosure authorized.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Labor and the Department of Revenue shall use the codes under the North American Industry Classification System for the compilation and publication of statistics rather than codes under the Standard Industrial Classification System.</para> <para>For the sole purpose of determining or updating the proper code under the appropriate industrial classification system, the Department of Labor and the Department of Revenue may disclose to the other department identification information about taxpayers conducting a business in this state. The information disclosed shall be strictly limited to the name, address, and federal employer identification number or numbers of the taxpayer and the code under the industrial classification system.</para> <para>(2) Notwithstanding sections 77-2711 and 77-27,119 and for the sole purpose of administration of the Contractor Registration Act and the contractor data base provisions of section 48-2117, the Department of Labor and the Department of Revenue may disclose to the other department identification information about taxpayers conducting a business in this state. The information disclosed shall be limited to the name, address, and federal employer identification number or numbers of the taxpayer.</para><para>(3) The disclosures allowed under this section may be made notwithstanding any other provision of law of this state regarding disclosure of information by either department. Any information received by either department under this section shall be considered confidential by the receiving department, and any employee who discloses such information other than as specifically allowed by this section or other laws of this state shall be subject to the penalties normally imposed on employees who improperly disclose information.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 875, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB162, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Contractor Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 48-2101.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>