<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id399">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id401" statutenumber="77-3,116"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3,116</statuteno><catchline id="id404">Study; cooperation
with Department of Labor and other state agencies; contracts authorized; reports;
department; duty.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Revenue and the Department
of Labor shall cooperate and participate in the collection of data for the
study described in section
77-3,115. Other state agencies, including the University of Nebraska,
shall assist in the study or the update as requested by the Department of
Revenue and as any necessary funds are available. Any agency may contract
with the Department of Revenue to provide such assistance. The Department
of Revenue may also contract with an independent entity for the entity to
conduct or assist in conducting such study or update. The department, other
state agency, or independent entity preparing the material or study shall
utilize and consider, along with other information, the results of any available
study relating to the items listed in section 77-3,115 and conducted or contracted
for by the Legislature in the year prior to April 16, 1992.</para>
<para>(2) A
preliminary report of the initial study's models and initial findings shall
be reported by the Department of Revenue to the chairpersons of the Appropriations
Committee and Revenue Committee of the Legislature, the Clerk of the Legislature,
and the Governor by December 1, 1992. The initial study shall be completed
and the department shall report its findings to the same entities by December
1, 1993. The study shall be updated and the update shall be reported to the
same entities on December 1, 2013, and every two years thereafter. The
study submitted to the Appropriations Committee and Revenue Committee of the
Legislature and the Clerk of the Legislature pursuant to this subsection shall
be submitted electronically.</para>
<para>(3) Any
models developed for the initial study or update shall be electronically shared with the Legislative Fiscal
Analyst. The Department of Revenue shall include in its budget request for
every other biennium following the 1991-93 biennium sufficient appropriation
authority to conduct or contract for the required update.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 218; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 137.</para><operativedate>July 19, 2012</operativedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB727, section 29, with LB782, section 137, to reflect all amendments.</note></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>