<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-684"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-684</statuteno><catchline>Tax rate; determination; collection; appeal; distribution.</catchline><para>The Property Tax Administrator shall, on or before January 15 each year, establish a tax rate for purposes of taxation against the taxable value as provided in sections 77-682 and 77-683 at a rate which shall be equal to the total property taxes levied in the state divided by the total taxable value of all taxable property in the state as certified pursuant to section 77-1613.01. The date when such tax rate is determined shall be deemed to be the levy date for the property. The Property Tax Administrator shall send to each car line company a statement showing the taxable value, the tax rate, and the amount of the tax and a statement that such tax is due and payable to the Property Tax Administrator on January 31 next following the levy thereof. If a car line company feels aggrieved, such company may, on or before February 15, file an appeal with the Tax Commissioner. The Tax Commissioner shall act upon the appeal and shall issue a written order mailed to the company within seven days after the date of the order. The order may be appealed within thirty days after the date of the order to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission in accordance with section 77-5013. The Property Tax Administrator shall remit the tax collected, less a three-percent collection fee, to the State Treasurer for distribution among the taxing subdivisions in proportion to all railroad taxes levied by taxing subdivisions. The collection fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the Department of Revenue Property Assessment Division Cash Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 210; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 36, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 37.</para></source></law></legaldoc>