<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id5" statutenumber="77-105">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-105</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Tangible personal
property, intangible personal property, defined.</catchline><para>The
term tangible personal property includes all personal property possessing
a physical existence, excluding money. The term tangible personal property
also includes trade fixtures, which means machinery and equipment, regardless
of the degree of attachment to real property, used directly in commercial,
manufacturing, or processing activities conducted on real property, regardless
of whether the real property is owned or leased, and all depreciable
tangible personal property described in subsection (9) of section 77-202 used
in the generation of electricity using wind as the fuel source. The
term intangible personal property includes all other personal property, including
money.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 133, art. I, &#167; 4, p. 545; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5811; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-104; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 156, &#167; 2, p. 592; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-105; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 829, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB360, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Electricity is not tangible personal property for tax purposes. Omaha Pub. Power Dist. v. Nebraska Dept. of Revenue, 248 Neb 518, 537 N.W.2d 312 (1995).</para><para>Cited in discussion of taxability of intangible property of foreign corporation. International Harvester Co. v. County of Douglas, 146 Neb. 555, 20 N.W.2d 620 (1945).</para><para>In view of change in legislative definition of intangible property, corporation is taxable where it has its principal office or place of business. Joyce Lumber Co. v. Anderson, 125 Neb. 886, 252 N.W. 394 (1934).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>