<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3,116"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3,116</statuteno><catchline>Study; cooperation with Department of Labor and other state agencies; contracts authorized; reports; department; duty.</catchline><para>The Department of Revenue and the Department of Labor shall cooperate and participate in the collection of data for the study. Other state agencies, including the University of Nebraska, shall assist in the study or the update as requested by the Department of Revenue and as any necessary funds are available. Any agency may contract with the Department of Revenue to provide such assistance. The Department of Revenue may also contract with an independent entity for the entity to conduct or assist in conducting such study or update. The department, other state agency, or independent entity preparing the material or study shall utilize and consider, along with other information, the results of any available study relating to the items listed in section 77-3,115 and conducted or contracted for by the Legislature in the year prior to April 16, 1992.</para><para>A preliminary report of the initial study's models and initial findings shall be reported by the Department of Revenue to the chairpersons of the Appropriations Committee and Revenue Committee of the Legislature, the Clerk of the Legislature, and the Governor by December 1, 1992. The initial study shall be completed and the department shall report its findings to the same entities by December 1, 1993. The study shall be updated and the update shall be reported to the same entities (1) on December 1, 1994, and every four years thereafter or (2) more often if determined appropriate by the Tax Commissioner and if the data or economic circumstances reported in the previous report have changed to such a degree as to vary the conclusions in the previous report or update.</para><para>Any models developed for the initial study or update shall be shared with the Legislative Fiscal Analyst. The Department of Revenue shall include in its budget request for every other biennium following the 1991-93 biennium sufficient appropriation authority to conduct or contract for the required update.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 218. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 