<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id54">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id56" statutenumber="77-1311">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1311</statuteno><catchline id="id59">County assessor;
duties.</catchline><para>The county assessor shall have general
supervision over and direction of the assessment of all property in his or
her county. In addition to the other duties provided by law, the county assessor
shall:</para>
<para>(1) Annually revise the real property assessment for the correction
of errors;</para>
<para>(2) When a parcel has been assessed and thereafter part or
parts are transferred to a different ownership, set off and apportion to each
its just and equitable portion of the assessment;</para>
<para>(3) Obey all rules and regulations made under Chapter 77 and
the instructions and orders sent out by the Tax Commissioner and the Tax Equalization
and Review Commission;</para>
<para>(4) Examine the records in the office of the register of deeds
and county clerk for the purpose of ascertaining whether the property described
in producing mineral leases, contracts, and bills of sale, have been fully
and correctly listed and add to the assessment roll any property which has
been omitted;</para>
<para>(5) Prepare the assessment roll as defined in section 77-129
and described in section 77-1303;
and</para>
<para>(6) Beginning
January 1, 2014, in any county with a population of at least one hundred fifty
thousand inhabitants according to the most recent federal decennial census,
provide, between January 15 and March 1 of each year, the opportunity to real
property owners to meet in person with the county assessor or the county assessor's
designated representative. If the real property owner does not notify the
county assessor or the county assessor's designated representative by February
1 of the real property owner's intent to meet in person, the real property
owner waives the opportunity to meet in person with the county assessor or
the county assessor's designated representative. During such meetings, the
county assessor or the county assessor's designated representative shall provide
a basis for the property valuation contained in the notice of preliminary
valuation sent pursuant to section 77-1301 and accept any information the
property owner provides relevant to the property value. </para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 113, p. 425; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 111, &#167; 3, p. 512; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 111, &#167; 1, p. 442; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 104, &#167; 12, p. 377; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6428; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 137, &#167; 1, p. 602; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5963; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-1609; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 133, &#167; 4, p. 481; </para><para>Laws 1935, Spec. Sess., c. 14, &#167; 5, p. 91; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 17, p. 155; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-1609; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1311; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 250, &#167; 24, p. 796; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 257, &#167; 2, p. 882; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 370, &#167; 2, p. 1303; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1069, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 205; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1177, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 821, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 165; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1275, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 121; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 292, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 263, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 8.</para><operativedate>August 27, 2011</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Under this section, the county assessor has authority to correct valuations which have become erroneous by reason of a judicial declaration of invalidity of an increase ordered by the State Board of Equalization and Assessment. Hansen v. County of Lincoln, 188 Neb. 461, 197 N.W.2d 651 (1972).</para><para>County assessor has the duty of assessing real estate. LeDioyt v. County of Keith, 161 Neb. 615, 74 N.W.2d 455 (1956).</para><para>County assessor is given direct charge and full control over assessment of property in county, and is competent witness to value of real estate. Beebe &amp; Runyan Furniture Co. v. Board of Equalization, 139 Neb. 158, 296 N.W. 764 (1941).</para><para>County assessor, upon due notice to taxpayer, is authorized to change schedule of a taxpayer by adding thereto taxable property omitted. Bankers Life Ins. Co. v. Bd. of Equalization of Lancaster County, 89 Neb. 469, 131 N.W. 1034 (1911).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
