<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1913"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1913</statuteno><catchline>Foreclosure proceedings; examination by court; order for sheriff's deed; certificate of tax sale for subsequent taxes.</catchline><para>The court shall, after the expiration of the time provided in section 77-1903 and on the motion of the plaintiff, examine the proceedings and, if they are found to be correct and if the subsequent taxes have been paid to date, in case the purchaser is not a land reutilization authority or a governmental subdivision of the state, a municipal corporation or an irrigation or drainage district interested in the distribution of the proceeds of the foreclosure sale, make and enter an order of confirmation of the sale, shall direct the disposition of the proceeds of the sale and order the sheriff to make and deliver to the purchasers, without further cost to them, a sheriff's deed for any real estate not redeemed; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> if a private purchaser at any sale held by the sheriff in tax foreclosure proceedings shall fail to pay the subsequent taxes levied and assessed against the property under foreclosure, any governmental subdivision of the state, municipal corporation or drainage or irrigation district, interested in the distribution of the proceeds of the foreclosure sale, may apply for and have issued to it a certificate of tax sale covering such subsequent taxes in the manner provided by sections 77-1809 and 77-1810, and, upon production of such certificate in the court conducting said foreclosure proceedings, such court may thereupon order confirmation of such foreclosure sale, notwithstanding the private purchaser has failed to pay the subsequent taxes levied and assessed against the property.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 176, &#167; 13, p. 617; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1913; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 630, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Subsequent taxes that a purchaser at a sheriff's sale in the foreclosure of a tax certificate is required to pay before confirmation of the sale are limited to those levied and assessed on the property under foreclosure, i.e., taxes assessed and levied after commencement of the foreclosure proceeding. "Subsequent taxes" within the meaning of this section do not include taxes, whether general taxes or special assessments, that were assessed and levied prior to the commencement of the foreclosure proceeding. INA Group v. Young, 271 Neb. 956, 716 N.W.2d 733 (2006).</para><para>When there is no evidence that others are willing to pay more, a judicial sale will not be set aside on account of mere inadequacy of price, unless such inadequacy is so gross as to make it appear that it was the result of fraud or mistake, or to shock the conscience of the court. The district court must determine by unrestricted means whether at the sheriff's sale the price bid is adequate or whether at a subsequent sale more would be realized, and this court will not overturn its determination absent an abuse of discretion. County of Dakota v. Mallett, 235 Neb. 82, 453 N.W.2d 594 (1990).</para><para>Substantially increased offers made in open court before confirmation of sale are sufficient to authorize district court to deny confirmation and order a new sale. County of Gage v. Beatrice Neb. Water Co., 147 Neb. 236, 22 N.W.2d 696 (1946).</para><para>Title to land acquired by tax foreclosure in Nebraska was subject to attack in Missouri federal district court on jurisdictional grounds. Duke v. Durfee, 308 F.2d 209 (8th Cir. 1962).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 