<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1301.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1301.01</statuteno><catchline>Appraisal; standards; establishment by Tax Commissioner; contracts; approval.</catchline><para>The Tax Commissioner shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to establish standards for the appraisal of classes or subclasses of real property in a county. The standards established shall require that the appraisal shall be based upon the use of manuals developed pursuant to section 77-1330 and shall arrive at a determination of taxable value on a consistent basis in accordance with the methods prescribed in sections 77-112 and 77-201. The Tax Commissioner shall also establish standards for appraisal contracts which shall, among other provisions, require that all such contracts shall require the use of manuals developed pursuant to section 77-1330. No appraisal contract shall be valid until approved in writing by the Tax Commissioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 450, &#167; 2, p. 1474; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 672, &#167; 1, p. 2594; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 159, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 30, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 817, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 361, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 320, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 115; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 62.</para></source><annotation><para>Application of Department of Revenue guidelines for allowance of economic depreciation raises a presumption that the resulting assessment is correct; however, the guidelines must give way to evidence showing that such application will violate the constitutional requirement of uniform and proportionate taxation or the statutory requirement of taxation at actual value. Farmers Co-op Assn. v. Boone County, 213 Neb. 763, 332 N.W.2d 32 (1983).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>