<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1388"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1388</statuteno><catchline>Historically significant real property; preliminary certificate of rehabilitation; filing with State Historic Preservation Officer.</catchline><para>(1) The owner of historically significant real property described in section 77-1385 may apply for a preliminary certificate of rehabilitation on a form prescribed by the State Historic Preservation Officer. The application shall be filed with the State Historic Preservation Officer prior to beginning rehabilitation. The application shall contain at least the following information:</para><para>(a) The address or location of the historically significant real property;</para><para>(b) Documentation of the cost of the rehabilitation, including estimated cost of architectural fees if applicable;</para><para>(c) A certification from the county assessor stating the assessed valuation of the historically significant real property that was last certified by the county assessor pursuant to section 13-509 or as finally determined if appealed;</para><para>(d) A description of the historic condition of the historically significant real property, when possible, and condition of the historically significant real property immediately prior to the rehabilitation; and</para><para>(e) A detailed description of the proposed rehabilitation work, including plans and specifications, if applicable.</para><para>(2) Within thirty days after receipt of an application for a preliminary certificate of rehabilitation, the State Historic Preservation Officer shall issue a preliminary certificate of rehabilitation to the applicant and transmit a copy to the county assessor if he or she determines that:</para><para>(a) The proposed work meets the Standards for Rehabilitation as described in 36 C.F.R. 67.7, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2005; and</para><para>(b) The work is a substantial rehabilitation.</para><para>(3) The State Historic Preservation Officer may extend the deadline up to an additional forty-five days if he or she determines that a site inspection is necessary. The State Historic Preservation Officer shall determine the length of the rehabilitation period, which shall not exceed two years unless the State Historic Preservation Officer finds (a) it is economically infeasible to complete the rehabilitation in two years or (b) the magnitude of the project is such that a good faith attempt to complete the rehabilitation in two years would not succeed. The certificate shall identify the rehabilitation period.</para><para>(4) The State Historic Preservation Officer shall issue a preliminary certificate of rehabilitation to the owner if (a) the property was determined to be qualified for historic preservation valuation pursuant to subsection (2) of section 77-1387, (b) the proposed rehabilitation meets the Standards for Rehabilitation as described in 36 C.F.R. 67.7, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2005, and (c) the proposed rehabilitation is a substantial rehabilitation. The State Historic Preservation Officer shall transmit a copy of the preliminary certificate of rehabilitation to the county assessor within seven days after issuance of the certificate to the owner.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, substantial rehabilitation means interior or exterior rehabilitation work that preserves the historically significant real property in a manner that significantly improves its condition and that costs an amount equal to or greater than twenty-five percent of the assessed valuation certified by the county assessor and contained in the application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 66, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>