<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1318.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1318.01</statuteno><catchline>Improvements to real property; information statement filed with county assessor; forms; contents.</catchline><para>(1) In order that improvements to real property are properly assessed for property tax purposes, no building amounting to a value of two thousand five hundred dollars or more shall hereafter be erected, or structurally altered or repaired, and no electrical, heating, plumbing, or other installation or connection, or other improvement to real property, amounting to a value of two thousand five hundred dollars or more, shall hereafter be made until an information statement has been filed with the county assessor in the county in which the improvement is to be made. Common carriers and public utilities regulated either by the State of Nebraska or the federal government, or owned, operated, or leased by a political subdivision thereof, shall not be required to file an information statement for the structural alteration, or repair of a building, or for the electrical, heating, plumbing, or other installation or connection, or other improvement to real property owned by it or pursuant to a contract or a service agreement. Any building permit required and issued by a county or municipal officer shall fulfill the requirements of this section if it contains the information required by this section and if a copy is provided to the county assessor by the officer.</para><para>(2) If the county or municipality does not require a permit under its zoning laws, the information statement shall be filed with the county assessor. The form for the information statement shall be provided by the county assessor and shall be filed on or before December 31 of the year of construction, repair, alteration, or improvement.</para><para>(3) The information statement shall show the following: (a) Name and address of the owner of the property; (b) name and address of the applicant, if different than owner; (c) name of prime contractor for the project, if there is one; (d) location of the property, size, nature, intended use, and approximate material cost of the improvement; and (e) the estimated period of construction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 624, &#167; 1, p. 2522; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 994, &#167; 13. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 