<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1838" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1838</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Real property taxes; issuance of treasurer's tax deed; execution, acknowledgment, and recording; effect; lien for special assessments.</catchline><para>The deed made by the county treasurer shall be under the official seal of office and acknowledged by the county treasurer before some officer authorized to take the acknowledgment of deeds. When so executed and acknowledged, it shall be recorded in the same manner as other conveyances of real estate. When recorded it shall vest in the grantee and his or her heirs and assigns the title of the property described in the deed, subject to any lien on real estate for special assessments levied by a sanitary and improvement district which special assessments have not been previously offered for sale by the county treasurer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 218, p. 469; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6546; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6074; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2026; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1838; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB277, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Formal requirements</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Formal requirements</emphasis></para><para>Affixing of county treasurer's official seal necessary to validity of tax deed. County of Lincoln v. Evans, 185 Neb. 19, 173 N.W.2d 365 (1969).</para><para>When the statute under which land is sold for taxes directs an act to be done, such as recording a tax deed, such statute must be strictly, if not literally, complied with. Saffer v. Saffer, 133 Neb. 528, 274 N.W. 479 (1937).</para><para>Tax deed issued on private sale was void for failure to recite that land was not sold at public sale for want of bidders. Sherlock v. Gillis, 108 Neb. 72, 187 N.W. 812 (1922).</para><para>Deed need not be witnessed. Sanford v. Scott, 105 Neb. 479, 181 N.W. 148 (1920).</para><para>If deed is invalid by reason of formal defects, purchaser has lien for amount of taxes paid with interest. Merriam v. Rauen, 23 Neb. 217, 36 N.W. 489 (1888).</para><para>A tax deed to be valid must have official seal of treasurer attached. Bendexen v. Fenton, 21 Neb. 184, 31 N.W. 685 (1887); Baldwin v. Merriam, 16 Neb. 199, 20 N.W. 250 (1884).</para><para>A deed which does not recite that sale was had at place designated by statute is invalid. Shelley v. Towle, 16 Neb. 194, 20 N.W. 251 (1884); Haller v. Blaco, 10 Neb. 36, 4 N.W. 362 (1880).</para><para>A scroll to represent a seal is not sufficient. Sullivan v. Merriam, 16 Neb. 157, 20 N.W. 118 (1884).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Where deed conforms to statute then in force, it is valid on its face within meaning of special statute of limitations. Opp v. Smith, 102 Neb. 152, 166 N.W. 265 (1918).</para><para>Two distinct tracts may be included in deed. Towle v. Holt, 14 Neb. 221, 15 N.W. 203 (1883).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>