<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id102"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id104" statutenumber="77-1233.06"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id106">77-1233.06</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Taxable tangible personal property tax valuation or penalty; appeal; procedure; collection procedures.</catchline><para>For purposes of section 77-1233.04:</para><para>(1) The county assessor shall notify the taxpayer, on a form prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, of the action taken, the penalty, and the rate of interest. The notice shall also state the taxpayer's appeal rights and the appeal procedures. Such notice shall be given by first-class mail addressed to such taxpayer's last-known address. The entire penalty and interest shall be waived if the omission or failure to report any item of taxable tangible personal property was for the reason that the property was timely reported in the wrong tax district;</para><para>(2) The taxpayer may appeal the action of the county assessor, either as to the valuation or the penalties imposed, to the county board of equalization within thirty days after the date of notice. The taxpayer shall preserve his or her appeal by filing a written appeal with the county clerk in the same manner as prescribed for protests in section 77-1502. The action of the county assessor shall become final unless a written appeal is filed within the time prescribed;</para><para>(3) The action of the county board of equalization, in an appeal of the penalties imposed, shall be limited to correcting penalties which were wrongly imposed or incorrectly calculated. The county board of equalization shall have no authority to waive or reduce any penalty which was correctly imposed and calculated. The entire penalty and interest on the penalty shall be waived if the omission or failure to report any item of taxable tangible personal property was for the reason that the property was timely reported in the wrong tax district;</para><para>(4) Upon ten days' notice to the taxpayer, the county board of equalization shall set a date for hearing the appeal of the taxpayer. The county board of equalization shall make its determination on the appeal within thirty days after the date of hearing. The county clerk shall, within seven days after the determination of the county board, send notice to the taxpayer and the county assessor, on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, of the action of the county board. Appeal may be taken within thirty days after the decision of the county board of equalization to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission; and</para><para>(5) Taxes and penalties assessed for the current year, if not delinquent, shall be certified to the county treasurer and collected as if the property had been properly reported for taxation, except that separate tax statements may be mailed. Taxes and penalties assessed for the current year, if delinquent, and taxes and penalties assessed for prior years shall be certified to the county treasurer, and the taxes, penalties, and interest thereon shall be due and collectible immediately upon certification. Collection procedures shall be started immediately regardless of the provisions of any other statute to the contrary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>Section 77-1233.04 and this section control a taxpayer's appeal from a decision of a county board of equalization to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission when a county assessor changes a taxpayer's reported valuation of personal property to conform to net book value. Prime Alliance Bank v. Lincoln Cty. Bd. of Equal., 283 Neb. 732, 811 N.W.2d 690 (2012).</para><para>The assignee of certain interests in ethanol manufacturing equipment had 30 days from the date of the decision under subsection (4) of this section, and not until the August 24 deadline under section 77-1510, to appeal to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission from a county board of equalization's decision in a case where the assignor had filed a personal property return with the value of zero dollars for the equipment and had not filed a protest of the valuation. Republic Bank v. Lincoln Cty. Bd. of Equal., 283 Neb. 721, 811 N.W.2d 682 (2012).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc> 