<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id603"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1309"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1309</statuteno><catchline>Destroyed real property; county board of equalization; adjust assessed valuation; notice; protests; filing; decision; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) If the county board of equalization receives a report of destroyed real property pursuant to section 77-1308, the county board of equalization shall adjust the assessed value of the destroyed real property to its assessed value on the date it suffers significant property damage.</para><para>(2) The county board of equalization may meet on or after June 1 and on or before July 25, or on or before August 10 if the board has adopted a resolution to extend the deadline for hearing protests under section 77-1502, for the purpose of considering the assessed value of destroyed real property pursuant to this section. Any action of the county board of equalization which changes the assessed value of destroyed real property pursuant to this section shall be for the current assessment year only.</para><para>(3) The county board of equalization shall give notice of the assessed value of the destroyed real property to the record owner or agent at his or her last-known address. Protests of the assessed value proposed for destroyed real property pursuant to this section shall be filed with the county board of equalization within thirty days after the mailing of the notice. All provisions of section 77-1502 except dates for filing a protest, the period for hearing protests, and the date for mailing notice of the county board of equalization's decision are applicable to any protest filed pursuant to this section. The county board of equalization shall issue its decision on the protest within thirty days after the filing of the protest. Within seven days after the county board of equalization's final decision, the county clerk shall mail to the protester written notice of the decision. The notice shall contain a statement advising the protester that a report of the decision is available at the county clerk's or county assessor's office, whichever is appropriate.</para><para>(4) The action of the county board of equalization upon a protest filed pursuant to this section may be appealed to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission within thirty days after the board's final decision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 17. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>