<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1934"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1934</statuteno><catchline>Tax certificate foreclosure proceedings under old law; defective procedure; confirmation of sale not yet obtained; action to cure defects.</catchline><para>Where any county, city, village, school district, drainage district, or irrigation district shall have commenced proceedings under the provisions of either section 77-2040 or 77-2041, C.S.Supp.,1941, to foreclose tax sale certificates, and the sale or sales held by the sheriff in such proceedings has not been confirmed as of March 24, 1947, but more than two years shall have elapsed, either between the time of issuance of tax sale certificate and the time of instituting the tax foreclosure proceedings, or from and after the time of holding sheriff's sale, then such purchaser of the tax sale certificate or certificates shall be entitled upon motion to have the sale or sales confirmed and a deed or deeds issued to such purchaser, and any person, persons, firm, corporation, or governmental body, which shall have or has had any interest whatsoever in the real estate, lien thereon, or interest in the taxes foreclosed, shall have one year and no more, under any circumstances whatever, from the date of the issuance of the deed or deeds, within which to bring any action whatsoever to attack such proceedings, any of the steps taken thereunder, the method of purchasing or the power of the county, municipality or other governmental subdivision mentioned above to bring said proceedings, to purchase the property in its name as trustee, or to receive deed. In the event no such action shall be brought within the period of limitation fixed by this section, the title of the purchaser shall be valid and absolute against any such person, persons, firm, corporation, or governmental body.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 264, &#167; 2, p. 855. </para></source><annotation><para>Failure to bring action did not bar claim of easement. Jurgensen v. Ainscow, 155 Neb. 701, 53 N.W.2d 196 (1952).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>