<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id199">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id201" statutenumber="77-1736.06"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1736.06</statuteno><catchline id="id204">Property
tax refund; procedure.</catchline><para>The following procedure
shall apply when making a property tax refund:</para>
<para>(1) Within thirty days of the entry of a final nonappealable
order, an unprotested determination of a county assessor, an unappealed decision
of a county board of equalization, or other final action requiring a refund
of real or personal property taxes paid or, for property valued by the state,
within thirty days of a recertification of value by the Property Tax Administrator
pursuant to section 77-1775 or 77-1775.01, the county assessor shall determine
the amount of refund due the person entitled to the refund, certify that amount
to the county treasurer, and send a copy of such certification to the person
entitled to the refund. Within thirty days from the date the county assessor
certifies the amount of the refund, the county treasurer shall notify each
political subdivision, including any school district receiving a distribution
pursuant to section 79-1073 or 79-1073.01 and
any land bank receiving real property taxes pursuant to subdivision (3)(a)
of section 19-5211, of its respective share of the refund, except
that for any political subdivision whose share of the refund is two hundred
dollars or less, the county board may waive this notice requirement. Notification
shall be by first-class mail, postage prepaid, to the last-known address of
record of the political subdivision. The county treasurer shall pay the refund
from funds in his or her possession belonging to any political subdivision,
including any school district receiving a distribution pursuant to section
79-1073 or 79-1073.01 and any
land bank receiving real property taxes pursuant to subdivision (3)(a) of
section 19-5211, which received any part of the tax or penalty
being refunded. If sufficient funds are not available or the political subdivision,
within thirty days of the mailing of the notice by the county treasurer if
applicable, certifies to the county treasurer that a hardship would result
and create a serious interference with its governmental functions if the refund
of the tax or penalty is paid, the county treasurer shall register the refund
or portion thereof which remains unpaid as a claim against such political
subdivision and shall issue the person entitled to the refund a receipt for
the registration of the claim. The certification by a political subdivision
declaring a hardship shall be binding upon the county treasurer;</para>
<para>(2) The refund of a tax or penalty or the receipt for the
registration of a claim made or issued pursuant to this section shall be satisfied
in full as soon as practicable and in no event later than five years from
the date the final order or other action approving a refund is entered. The
governing body of the political subdivision shall make provisions in its budget
for the amount of any refund or claim to be satisfied pursuant to this section.
If a receipt for the registration of a claim is given:</para>
<para>(a) Such receipt shall be applied to satisfy any tax levied
or assessed by that political subdivision next falling due from the person
holding the receipt after the sixth next succeeding levy is made on behalf
of the political subdivision following the final order or other action approving
the refund; and</para>
<para>(b) To the extent the amount of such receipt exceeds the
amount of such tax liability, the unsatisfied balance of the receipt shall
be paid and satisfied within the five-year period prescribed in this subdivision
from a combination of a credit against taxes anticipated to be due to the
political subdivision during such period and cash payment from any funds expected
to accrue to the political subdivision pursuant to a written plan to be filed
by the political subdivision with the county treasurer no later than thirty
days after the claim against the political subdivision is first reduced by
operation of a credit against taxes due to such political subdivision.</para>
<para>If a political subdivision fails to fully satisfy the refund
or claim prior to the sixth next succeeding levy following the entry of a
final nonappealable order or other action approving a refund, interest shall
accrue on the unpaid balance commencing on the sixth next succeeding levy
following such entry or action at the rate set forth in section 45-103;</para>
<para>(3) The county treasurer shall mail the refund or the receipt
by first-class mail, postage prepaid, to the last-known address of the person
entitled thereto. Multiple refunds to the same person may be combined into
one refund or credit. If a refund is not claimed by June 1 of the year following
the year of mailing, the refund shall be canceled and the resultant amount
credited to the various funds originally charged;</para>
<para>(4) When the refund involves property valued by the state,
the Tax Commissioner shall be authorized to negotiate a settlement of the
amount of the refund or claim due pursuant to this section on behalf of the
political subdivision from which such refund or claim is due. Any political
subdivision which does not agree with the settlement terms as negotiated may
reject such terms, and the refund or claim due from the political subdivision
then shall be satisfied as set forth in this section as if no such negotiation
had occurred;</para>
<para>(5) In the event that the Legislature appropriates state
funds to be disbursed for the purposes of satisfying all or any portion of
any refund or claim, the Tax Commissioner shall order the county treasurer
to disburse such refund amounts directly to the persons entitled to the refund
in partial or total satisfaction of such persons' claims. The county treasurer
shall disburse such amounts within forty-five days after receipt thereof;
and</para>
<para>(6) If all or any portion of the refund is reduced by way
of settlement or forgiveness by the person entitled to the refund, the proportionate
amount of the refund that was paid by an appropriation of state funds shall
be reimbursed by the county treasurer to the State Treasurer within forty-five
days after receipt of the settlement agreement or receipt of the forgiven
refund. The amount so reimbursed shall be credited to the General Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 829, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 138; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 111; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 555, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 167; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 19.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>