<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1917.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1917.01</statuteno><catchline>Delinquent special assessments; effect; foreclosure proceedings.</catchline><para>All cities, villages and sanitary and improvement districts in Nebraska shall have a lien upon real estate within their boundaries for all special assessments due thereon to the municipal corporation or district, which lien shall be inferior only to general taxes levied by the state and its political subdivisions. When such special assessments have become delinquent, without the real property against which they are assessed being first offered at tax sale by the tax sale certificate method or otherwise, the municipal corporation or district involved may itself as party plaintiff proceed in the district court of the county in which the real estate is situated to foreclose, in its own name, the lien for such delinquent special assessments in the same manner and with like effect as in the foreclosure of a real estate mortgage, except as otherwise specifically provided by sections 77-1903 to 77-1917, which shall govern when applicable. Final confirmation of sale in such foreclosure proceeding and issuance of deed to the plaintiff, or its assignee, cannot be had until two years have expired from the date of the sale held by the sheriff, and, after expiration of such two-year period, personal notice has been served on occupants of the real property. The remedy granted in this section to cities, villages and sanitary and improvement districts for the collection of delinquent special assessments shall be cumulative and in addition to other existing methods.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 387, &#167; 1, p. 1182; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 313, &#167; 13. </para></source><annotation><para>This section provides the subdivision of the government named therein an independent and complete remedy for the foreclosure of special assessment liens and is in addition to any other remedies provided by the law for the collection of special assessments. Sanitary &amp; Improvement Dist. #222 v. Metropolitan Life Ins. Co., 201 Neb. 10, 266 N.W.2d 73 (1978).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 