<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1306.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1306.01</statuteno><catchline>Lands adjacent to rivers and streams; survey; report.</catchline><para>In all counties where land ownership may from time to time be altered to add new lands to the tax rolls due to the activity of any river, stream, or other body of water along or bordering state lines, whether by accretion or avulsion, it shall be the duty of the county surveyor prior to June 1, 1960, and at least once within each five-year period thereafter either to cause to be surveyed any lands believed to have been altered in such manner or to certify in writing that it is his or her opinion that no alteration of ownership of any land in the county from that shown by the then current tax rolls has occurred due to the action of any river, stream, or other body of water along or bordering state lines. A report of such survey or surveys, showing the extent of any probable alteration of ownership due to the action of a river, stream, or other body of water along or bordering state lines, or a certificate of no change as provided shall be filed with the county assessor within the periods hereinbefore stated. In any county where there is no regularly elected or appointed county surveyor the county board shall appoint a qualified surveyor to carry out the provisions of this section. In the event of a failure of county officials to act as directed by this section, within the periods stated, the Property Tax Administrator may appoint a qualified surveyor to act as provided by this section, and all costs incurred shall be paid by the county. In all counties where land ownership may from time to time be altered due to the activity of any river, stream, or other body of water not along or bordering state lines, whether by accretion or avulsion, it shall be the duty of the county surveyor to cause to be surveyed any lands believed to have been altered when directed by the county board of equalization or when requested by the Property Tax Administrator. If such a survey is ordered by the county board of equalization or requested by the Property Tax Administrator, the county surveyor shall perform the same duties as when a river, stream, or other body of water is along or borders state lines.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 370, &#167; 5, p. 1305; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 120. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 