
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id13">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id15" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-1363"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id17">77-1363</statuteno><catchline id="id18">Agricultural
and horticultural land; classes and subclasses.</catchline><para>Agricultural
land and horticultural land shall be divided into classes and subclasses of
real property under section 77-103.01, including, but not limited to, irrigated
cropland, dryland cropland, grassland, wasteland, nurseries, feedlots, and
orchards, so that the categories reflect uses appropriate for the valuation
of such land according to law. Classes shall be inventoried by subclasses
of real property based on soil classification standards developed by the Natural
Resources Conservation Service of the United States Department of Agriculture
as converted into land capability groups by the Property Tax Administrator.
County assessors shall utilize soil surveys from
the Natural Resources Conservation Service of the United States Department
of Agriculture as directed
by the Property Tax Administrator. Nothing in this section shall
be construed to limit the classes and subclasses of real property that may
be used by county assessors or the Tax Equalization and Review Commission
to achieve more uniform and proportionate valuations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 271, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1207, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 361, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 320, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 902, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 139; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 403, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1115, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB877, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>A "market area" does not constitute a class or subclass of agricultural land as defined by this section. Bartlett v. Dawes Cty. Bd. of Equal., 259 Neb. 954, 613 N.W.2d 810 (2000).</para><para>Neb. Const. art. VIII requires uniform and proportionate assessment within the class of agricultural land; agricultural land is then divided into "categories" such as irrigated cropland, dry cropland, and grassland. Schmidt v. Thayer Cty. Bd. of Equal., 10 Neb. App. 10, 624 N.W.2d 63 (2001).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>