<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id846"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1395"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1395</statuteno><catchline>Sales-restricted house; assessment; application; county assessor; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(a) The provision of safe, decent, and affordable housing to all residents of the State of Nebraska is a matter of public concern and represents a legitimate and compelling state need, affecting the general welfare of all residents;</para><para>(b) Sales-restricted houses effectively provide safe, decent, and affordable housing to residents of Nebraska;</para><para>(c) Sales-restricted houses are restricted by tools such as deed restrictions, covenants, land-lease agreements, and other similar recorded instruments that establish a period of affordability for low-income persons; and</para><para>(d) These restrictions alter the value of the property by limiting an owner's ability to sell the property.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Charitable nonprofit housing organization means a charitable nonprofit organization whose primary purpose is the construction or renovation of residential housing for conveyance to low-income persons;</para><para>(b) Low-income person means a person with a household income of not more than one hundred twenty percent of the area median income, as determined by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development;</para><para>(c) Primary residence means the home or place in which an individual's habitation is fixed and to which the individual has a present intention of returning after an absence therefrom, regardless of the duration of the absence; and</para><para>(d) Sales-restricted house means a residential single-family property that is subject to restrictions, created pursuant to a deed restriction, covenant, land-lease agreement, or other similar recorded instrument, that:</para><para>(i) Limit the ability of the owner to sell the property in an arm's length transaction;</para><para>(ii) Are attached to the property for a minimum period of twenty years;</para><para>(iii) Require the property to be the primary residence of an owner of the property;</para><para>(iv) Restrict the owner from selling the property to any buyer who is not a low-income person or a charitable nonprofit housing organization; and</para><para>(v) Were placed on the property by a charitable nonprofit housing organization upon such organization's conveyance of the property to a low-income person.</para><para>(3) Any organization or individual that owns a sales-restricted house may file an application with the county assessor of the county in which the sales-restricted house is located for a property valuation under this section. Application shall be made on a form prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. The application shall include (a) information describing the location of the sales-restricted house and (b) details on the sales restriction.</para><para>(4) Upon receipt of the application, the county assessor shall determine: </para><para>(a) The value of the sales-restricted house at its unrestricted appraised value; and</para><para>(b) The maximum sales price allowed for the sales-restricted house under the applicable restrictions.</para><para>(5) The county assessor shall use the lesser of the two values described in subsection (4) of this section for purposes of determining the value of the property under section 77-201.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1317, &#167; 77. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>