<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id21"><sectno id="id22" opdate="April 15, 2008">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id23" statutenumber="77-1734.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id25">77-1734.01</statuteno><catchline id="id26">Refund of tax paid; claim; verification required; county board approval.</catchline><para>(1) In the case of an amended federal income tax return or whenever a person's return is changed or corrected by the Internal Revenue Service or other competent authority that decreases the Nebraska adjusted basis of the person's taxable tangible personal property, the county treasurer shall refund that portion of the tax paid that is in excess of the amount due after the amendment or correction.</para><para>(2) In case of payment made of any property taxes or any payments in lieu of taxes with respect to property as a result of a clerical error or honest mistake or misunderstanding, on the part of a county or other political subdivision of the state or any taxpayer, the county treasurer to whom the tax was paid shall refund that portion of the tax paid as a result of the clerical error or honest mistake or misunderstanding. A claim for a refund pursuant to this section shall be made in writing to the county treasurer to whom the tax was paid within three years after the date the tax was due or within ninety days after filing the amended return or the correction becomes final.</para><para>(3) Before the refund is made, the county treasurer shall receive verification from the county assessor or other taxing official that such error or mistake was made or the amended return was filed or the correction made, and the claim for refund shall be submitted to the county board. Upon verification, the county board shall approve the claim. The refund shall be made in the manner prescribed in section 77-1736.06. Such refund shall not have a dispositional effect on any similar refund for another taxpayer. This section may not be used to challenge the valuation of property, the equalization of property, or the constitutionality of a tax.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 336, &#167; 1, p. 1173; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 373, &#167; 1, p. 1312; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 385, &#167; 1, p. 1179; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 245, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 819, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 762, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 829, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 17.</para></source><annotation><para>A request for refund of invalid tax or one paid as a result of clerical error must be by a written claim upon which the county board acts quasi-judicially, and upon request for declaratory relief on ground resolution for refund was invalid, refusal thereof was within discretion of district court where there was no showing such claim had not been filed. Svoboda v. Hahn, 196 Neb. 21, 241 N.W.2d 499 (1976).</para><para>The term clerical error herein is not restricted to a clerical error made by a taxpayer on the face of a personal property tax return. School Dist. of Minatare v. County of Scotts Bluff, 189 Neb. 395, 202 N.W.2d 825 (1972).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc> 