<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1718"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1718</statuteno><catchline>Collection of taxes; notice; issuance of distress warrant; affidavit of poverty; interest.</catchline><para>On or before November 1 of each year, the county treasurer shall issue and deliver to the sheriff of the county distress warrants against all persons having delinquent personal tax or real estate tax on a mobile home, cabin trailer, manufactured home, or similar property assessed and taxed as improvements to leased land for that year (1) unless such a person shall have paid such delinquent taxes in full, on or before September 1, with interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, or (2) unless such person shall, on or before September 1, file with the treasurer an affidavit that he or she is unable by reason of poverty to pay any such tax, in which case a distress warrant shall not be issued until ordered by the county board. At least twenty days prior to the issuance of a distress warrant, the county treasurer shall mail a notice to the delinquent taxpayer that, unless payment of the delinquent tax is made within twenty days, a distress warrant will be issued. Each such distress warrant shall include all delinquent taxes of the person against whom issued. When distress warrants have been issued and turned over to the sheriff, the county treasurer shall report and certify to the county board the total number of distress warrants issued and the total amount of money involved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 136, &#167; 3, p. 518; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 167, &#167; 22, p. 654; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 98, &#167; 22, p. 441; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 157, &#167; 22, p. 625; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-1915; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 181, &#167; 1, p. 627; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1718; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 259, &#167; 1, p. 846; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 646, &#167; 2, p. 2564; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 689, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 817, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 66. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 