<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1322"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1322</statuteno><catchline>Assessment of property; Board of Equalization; special assessments; invalid assessments for want of adequate notice; reassessment and relevy authorized.</catchline><para>The governing body of all cities, including cities which have adopted or which hereafter adopt a home rule charter under and pursuant to sections 2 to 5, inclusive, of Article XI of the Constitution of this state, villages, public corporations, and political subdivisions of the State of Nebraska, sitting as a board of equalization and assessment shall have power in all cases where special assessments heretofore made or which may hereafter be made for any purpose have been or may be declared void or invalid, for want of adequate notice, to reassess and relevy a new assessment equal to the special benefits and not exceeding the cost of the improvement for which the assessment was made upon the property originally assessed, and such reassessment and relevy shall be made substantially in the manner provided for making original assessments of like nature, and when so made shall constitute a lien upon the property prior and superior to all other liens except liens for taxes or other special assessments, and taxes so reassessed shall be enforced and collected as other special taxes; and in making such reassessment the governing body sitting as a board of equalization and assessment shall take into consideration payments, if any, made on behalf of the property reassessed, under such prior void assessment; and if such prior payments exceed the special assessment on the given property as finally determined, the excess, with lawful interest thereon, shall be refunded to the party paying the same.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 332, &#167; 1, p. 1165. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 