<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-1359"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1359</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Agricultural and
horticultural land; legislative findings; terms, defined.</catchline><para>The Legislature finds and declares that agricultural land and horticultural
land shall be a separate and distinct class of real property for purposes
of assessment. The assessed value of agricultural land and horticultural land
shall not be uniform and proportionate with all other real property, but the
assessed value shall be uniform and proportionate within the class of agricultural
land and horticultural land.</para>
<para>For purposes of this
section and section 77-1363:</para>
<para>(1) Agricultural land and horticultural land means a parcel
of land, excluding land associated with a building or enclosed structure located on
the parcel, which is primarily used for agricultural or horticultural purposes,
including wasteland lying in or adjacent to and in common ownership or management
with other agricultural land and horticultural land;</para>
<para>(2) Agricultural or horticultural purposes means used for
the commercial production of any plant or animal product in a raw or unprocessed
state that is derived from the science and art of agriculture, aquaculture,
or horticulture. Agricultural or horticultural purposes includes the following
uses of land:</para>
<para>(a) Land retained or protected for future agricultural or
horticultural purposes under a conservation easement as provided in the Conservation
and Preservation Easements Act except when the parcel or a portion thereof
is being used for purposes other than agricultural or horticultural purposes;
and</para>
<para>(b) Land enrolled in a federal or state program in which payments
are received for removing such land from agricultural or horticultural production;</para>
<para>(3) Farm home site means land contiguous to a farm site which includes an
inhabitable residence and improvements used for residential purposes and which
is located outside of urban areas or outside a platted and zoned subdivision;
and</para>
<para>(4) Farm site means the portion of land contiguous to land
actively devoted to agriculture which includes improvements that are agricultural
or horticultural in nature, including any uninhabitable or unimproved farm
home site.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 271, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 817, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1207, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 361, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 320, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 934, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 419, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB777, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB750, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Conservation and Preservation Easements Act,</emphasis> see section 76-2,118.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The inclusion of the term "parcel" requires a county assessor to consider the use of an entire tract of land, including any homesite, to determine whether that property qualifies as agricultural. Agena v. Lancaster Cty. Bd. of Equal., 276 Neb. 851, 758 N.W.2d 363 (2008).</para><para>This section does not violate Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 1. Agena v. Lancaster Cty. Bd. of Equal., 276 Neb. 851, 758 N.W.2d 363 (2008).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>