<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1340.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1340.03</statuteno><catchline>Transfer of assessment function; transferred employee; leave and insurance rights.</catchline><para>(1) A county shall transfer all accrued sick leave of a transferred employee up to the maximum number of accumulated hours for sick leave allowed by the State Personnel System. The county shall reimburse the state for twenty-five percent of the value of the accrued sick leave hours based on the straight-time rate of pay for each employee. A county assessor who becomes a state employee and who does not have any accrued sick leave shall be granted one hundred sixty hours of sick leave. The county shall reimburse the state for twenty-five percent of the value of the sick leave hours based on the straight-time rate of pay for the county assessor.</para><para>(2) The transferred employee may transfer the maximum amount of accrued annual leave earned as an employee of the county allowed by the State Personnel System. The county shall reimburse the state for one hundred percent of the value of the hours of accrued annual leave transferred. A county assessor who becomes a state employee and who does not have any accrued annual leave shall be granted ninety-six hours of vacation leave. The county shall reimburse the state for one hundred percent of the value of the hours of annual leave based on the straight-time rate of pay for the county assessor.</para><para>(3) No transferred employee shall lose any accrual rate value of his or her sick leave and vacation leave as a result of becoming a state employee, and a transferred employee may credit years of service with the county toward the accrual rate for sick leave and vacation leave plans. When accrued sick leave and vacation leave for a transferred employee are at a greater rate value than allowed by the state's sick leave and vacation leave plans, the county shall pay the state the difference between the value of the benefits allowed by the county and the state based on, at the time of transfer, twenty-five percent of the employee's straight-time rate of pay for the sick leave and one hundred percent of the employee's straight-time rate of pay for vacation leave. A county shall reimburse the state not later than one year after the transfer is complete.</para><para>(4) The transferred employee shall not receive any additional accrual rate value for state benefits until the employee meets the qualifications for the increased accrual rates pursuant to the state's requirements.</para><para>(5) The transferred employee may participate in and be covered by the insurance program established by sections 84-1601 to 84-1615. The waiting period for medical insurance coverage of transferred employees shall be waived.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Employee means a county assessor and employees of the county assessor's office transferred to the state pursuant to section 77-1340; and</para><para>(b) Straight-time rate of pay means the rate of pay in effect at the time of adoption of the resolution by the county board authorizing the transfer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 40.</para><note>This section was repealed by Laws 2009, LB121, section 15, operative on July 1, 2013.</note></source></law></legaldoc> 
