<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-1345.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id8">77-1345.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Agricultural or horticultural lands; special valuation; approval or denial; protest; appeal; failure to give notice; effect.</catchline><para>(1) On or before July 15 in the year of application, the county assessor shall approve or deny the application for special valuation filed pursuant to section 77-1345. On or before July 22, the county assessor shall issue notice of approval or denial.</para> <para>(2) If the application is approved by the county assessor, the land shall be valued as provided in section 77-1344 and, on or before July 22, the county board of equalization shall send a property valuation notice for special value to the owner and, if not the same, the applicant. Within thirty days after the mailing of the notice, a written protest of the special value may be filed.</para> <para>(3)(a) If the application is denied by the assessor, a written protest of the denial of the application may be filed within thirty days after the mailing of the denial.</para> <para>(b) If the denial of an application for special valuation is reversed on appeal and the application is approved, the land shall be valued as provided in section 77-1344 and the county board of equalization shall send the property valuation notice for special value to the owner and, if not the same, the applicant or his or her successor in interest, within fourteen days after the date of the final order. Within thirty days after the mailing of the notice, a written protest of the special value may be filed.</para> <para>(4) If the county board of equalization takes action pursuant to section 77-1504 or 77-1507 and the applicant filed an application for special valuation pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-1345, the county assessor shall approve or deny the application within fifteen days after the filing of the application and issue notice of the approval or denial as prescribed in subsection (1) of this section. If the application is denied by the county assessor, a written protest of the denial may be filed within thirty days of the mailing of the denial.</para> <para>(5) The assessor shall mail notice of any action taken by him or her on an application to the owner and the applicant if different than the owner.</para> <para>(6) All provisions of section 77-1502 except dates for filing of a protest, the period for hearing protests, and the date for mailing notice of the county board of equalization's decision are applicable to any protest filed pursuant to this section.</para> <para>(7) The county board of equalization shall decide any protest filed pursuant to this section within thirty days after the filing of the protest.</para> <para>(8) The clerk shall mail a copy of any decision made by the county board of equalization on a protest filed pursuant to this section to the owner and the applicant if different than the owner within seven days after the board's decision.</para> <para>(9) Any decision of the county board of equalization may be appealed to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission, in accordance with section 77-5013, within thirty days after the date of the decision.</para> <para>(10) If a failure to give notice as prescribed by this section prevented timely filing of a protest or appeal provided for in this section, any applicant may petition the Tax Equalization and Review Commission in accordance with section 77-5013, on or before December 31 of each year, to determine whether the land will receive special valuation for that year or to determine special value for that year.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 15, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 263, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB166, &#167; 11.</para><effectivedate>February 27, 2009</effectivedate></source> </law> </legaldoc>