 <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1601.02" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1601.02</statuteno><catchline>Property tax request; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The property tax request for the prior year shall be the property tax request for the current year for purposes of the levy set by the county board of equalization in section 77-1601 unless the governing body of the county, municipality, school district, learning community, sanitary and improvement district, natural resources district, educational service unit, or community college passes by a majority vote a resolution or ordinance setting the tax request at a different amount. Such resolution or ordinance shall only be passed after a special public hearing called for such purpose is held and after notice is published in a newspaper of general circulation in the area of the political subdivision at least five days prior to the hearing. The hearing notice shall contain the following information: The dollar amount of the prior year's tax request and the property tax rate that was necessary to fund that tax request; the property tax rate that would be necessary to fund last year's tax request if applied to the current year's valuation; and the proposed dollar amount of the tax request for the current year and the property tax rate that will be necessary to fund that tax request. Any resolution setting a tax request under this section shall be certified and forwarded to the county clerk on or before October 13 of the year for which the tax request is to apply.</para><para>(2) Any levy which is not in compliance with this section and section 77-1601 shall be construed as an unauthorized levy under section 77-1606.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 693, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 797, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>