<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id00" statutenumber="77-1248"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1248</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Taxation of air carriers; taxable value; allocation; Property Tax Administrator; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The Property Tax Administrator shall ascertain from the reports made and from any other information obtained by him or her the taxable value of the flight equipment of air carriers and the proportion allocated to this state for the purposes of taxation as provided in section 77-1245.</para><para>(2)(a) In determining the taxable value of the flight equipment of air carriers pursuant to subsection (1) of this section, the Property Tax Administrator shall determine the following ratios:</para><para>(i) The ratio of the taxable value of all commercial and industrial depreciable tangible personal property in the state actually subjected to property tax to the market value of all commercial and industrial depreciable tangible personal property in the state; and</para><para>(ii) The ratio of the taxable value of flight equipment of air carriers to the market value of flight equipment of air carriers.</para><para>(b) If the ratio of the taxable value of flight equipment of air carriers exceeds the ratio of the taxable value of commercial and industrial depreciable tangible personal property by more than five percent, the Property Tax Administrator may adjust the value of such flight equipment of air carriers to the percentage of the taxable commercial and industrial depreciable tangible personal property pursuant to federal law applicable to air carrier transportation property or Nebraska federal court decisions applicable thereto.</para><para>(c) For purposes of this subsection, commercial and industrial depreciable tangible personal property means all personal property which is devoted to commercial or industrial use other than flight equipment of air carriers.</para><para>(3) The Property Tax Administrator shall multiply the valuation of each air carrier by the compensating exemption factor calculated in section 77-1238.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1949, c. 231, &#167; 2, p. 641; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 669, &#167; 1, p. 2591; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 82; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 101; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB259, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB261, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>