<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1613.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1613.02</statuteno><catchline>Tax list; corrections; prohibited acts; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>The county assessor or county clerk shall correct the assessment and tax rolls after action of the county board of equalization. Each correction shall be made in triplicate, each set of triplicate forms being consecutively numbered, and there shall be entered upon such form all data pertaining to the assessment which is to be corrected. The correction shall show all additions and reductions, the amount of tax added or reduced, with the reason therefor, and the page or pages of the tax rolls upon which such change is to be made. The original copy shall be delivered to the county treasurer, the duplicate copy to the county clerk, and the triplicate copy shall remain in the office of the county assessor. The county assessor or county clerk shall provide upon demand a listing showing each entry and sorted by tax year. The county treasurer shall thereupon correct the tax roll to conform to the correction copy and all changes shall be made in red ink, drawing a line through the original or erroneous figures, but not erasing the same. No county assessor shall reduce or increase the valuation of any property, real or personal, without the approval of the county board of equalization. Any county assessor who shall willfully reduce or increase the valuation of any property, without the approval of the county board of equalization, as provided in this section, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and shall, upon conviction thereof, be fined not less than twenty dollars nor more than one hundred dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 133, art. XI, &#167; 6, p. 592; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5903; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-1006; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 100, &#167; 1, p. 457; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-1006; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-519; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 250, &#167; 12, p. 791; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 261, &#167; 1, p. 887; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1986), &#167; 77-519; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 160; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB166, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>The purpose of this statute is to permit the county assessor to correct clerical errors in the tax list, not to correct alleged errors in valuation of property. Olson v. County of Dakota, 224 Neb. 516, 398 N.W.2d 727 (1987).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>