<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1245"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1245</statuteno><catchline>Taxation of air carriers; assessment; collection; disbursement; allocation to this state; petition to Property Tax Administrator, when.</catchline><para>Any tax upon or measured by the value of flight equipment of air carriers incorporated or doing business in this state shall be assessed, collected by the Property Tax Administrator, and disbursed as provided in section 77-1250. The proportion of flight equipment allocated to this state for purposes of taxation shall be the arithmetical average of the following three ratios: (1) The ratio which the aircraft arrivals and departures within this state scheduled by such air carrier during the preceding calendar year bears to the total aircraft arrivals and departures within and without this state scheduled by such carrier during the same period, except that in the case of nonscheduled operations all arrivals and departures shall be substituted for scheduled arrivals and departures; (2) the ratio which the revenue tons handled by such air carrier at airports within this state during the preceding calendar year bears to the total revenue tons handled by such carrier at airports within and without this state during the same period; and (3) the ratio which such air carrier's originating revenue within this state for the preceding calendar year bears to the total originating revenue of such carrier within and without this state for the same period.</para><para>If allocation in accordance with the provisions of this section does not fairly represent the proportion of flight equipment properly allocable to this state, the taxpayer may petition for, or the Property Tax Administrator may require, the inclusion of one or more additional ratios or the employment of any other method to effectuate an equitable allocation of the taxpayer's flight equipment for purposes of taxation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 266, &#167; 2, p. 859; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 478, &#167; 9, p. 1543; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 625, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 99. </para></source><annotation><para>Levy of tax on allocation basis was constitutional. Mid-Continent Airlines v. State Board of Equalization &amp; Assessment, 157 Neb. 425, 59 N.W.2d 746 (1953).</para><para>This section sets out basis of valuation upon which tax is laid. Mid-Continent Airlines v. Nebraska State Board of Equalization, 105 F.Supp. 188 (D. Neb. 1952).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 