<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1387"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1387</statuteno><catchline>Historically significant real property; application by property owner; approval.</catchline><para>(1) A property owner or the legally designated representative of the property owner may submit an application to the State Historic Preservation Officer for a determination of whether the property owner's real property is qualified to receive historic rehabilitation valuation authorized by section 77-1391 on a form prescribed by the State Historic Preservation Officer. The application shall contain at least the following information:</para><para>(a) The address and location of the property;</para><para>(b) A map showing the location of the property;</para><para>(c) Clear, current black and white or color photographs showing principal views of the property;</para><para>(d) Designation authority, whether under the National Register of Historic Places or a landmark ordinance or resolution; and</para><para>(e) If it is historically significant and located within a district listed in the National Register of Historic Places or designated under an ordinance or resolution that has been approved by the State Historic Preservation Officer under section 77-1386, the name of the district and a statement describing the contribution of the property to the significance of the district.</para><para>(2) Within thirty days after the receipt of an application, the State Historic Preservation Officer shall determine whether an individual property is eligible to be listed in the National Register of Historic Places and is therefor eligible for historic rehabilitation valuation. The State Historic Preservation Officer may extend the deadline up to an additional forty-five days if he or she determines that a site inspection is necessary.</para><para>(3) Within thirty days after the receipt of an application, the State Historic Preservation Officer shall determine whether a property located within a district on the National Register of Historic Places or designated under an ordinance or resolution that has been approved by the State Historic Preservation Officer under section 77-1386 is of historic significance to the district pursuant to the criteria in 36 C.F.R. 67.5, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2005, and inform the applicant of the decision in writing. The State Historic Preservation Officer may extend the deadline up to an additional forty-five days if he or she determines that a site inspection is necessary.</para><para>(4) Property shall not be eligible for historic rehabilitation valuation if the property has received a final certificate of rehabilitation within the twelve years prior to application.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 66, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>