<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1117"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1117</statuteno><catchline>Recapture of tax credit.</catchline><para>The Tax Commissioner shall recapture, from the taxpayer that claimed the credit on a return, the tax credit allowed under the New Markets Job Growth Investment Act if:</para><para>(1) Any amount of the federal tax credit available with respect to a qualified equity investment that is eligible for a tax credit under this section is recaptured under section 45D of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended. In such case the state's recapture shall be proportionate to the federal recapture with respect to such qualified equity investment;</para><para>(2) The issuer redeems or makes principal repayment with respect to a qualified equity investment prior to the seventh credit allowance date. In such case recapture shall be proportionate to the amount of the redemption or repayment with respect to such qualified equity investment; or</para><para>(3) The issuer fails to invest and satisfy the requirements of subdivision (1)(b) of section 77-1110 and maintain such level of investment in qualified low-income community investments in Nebraska until the last credit allowance date for the qualified equity investment. For purposes of this section, an investment shall be considered held by an issuer even if the investment has been sold or repaid if the issuer reinvests an amount equal to the capital returned to or recovered by the issuer from the original investment, exclusive of any profits realized, in another qualified low-income community investment within twelve months of the receipt of such capital. With respect to the 2021 allocation, amounts received periodically by a qualified community development entity shall be treated as maintained in qualified low-income community investments if the amounts are reinvested in one or more qualified low-income community investments by the end of the following calendar year. An issuer shall not be required to reinvest capital returned from qualified low-income community investments after the sixth credit allowance date, the proceeds of which were used to make the qualified low-income community investment, and the qualified low-income community investment shall be considered held by the issuer through the seventh credit allowance date.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1128, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB682, &#167; 9. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>