<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1719.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1719.02</statuteno><catchline>Collection of taxes, personal; report of sheriff; county treasurer; verify; false return; notice; hearing; finding; penalty.</catchline><para>On or before October 1 of each year, the county treasurer shall verify this report to the county board, and shall make an itemized report covering the amount uncollected. Such itemized report shall include the number of the distress warrant, the name and address of the taxpayer, the amount involved, and the reason for failure to collect same, or the failure of the sheriff to make a legal return on same. If such report of the county treasurer to the county board shows any false return by the sheriff, or failure to make legal return, the county board shall direct the sheriff to appear at a public hearing at a time to be fixed by such board. Notice of the hearing shall be given to the sheriff at least ten days prior thereto. At such hearing, the board shall hear evidence and make its findings as to whether there has been willful neglect of duty on the part of the sheriff. If the board shall find that there has not been willful neglect of duty it shall enter an order finding that the sheriff should be absolved from any liability for failure to collect such distress warrants. If the board shall find there has been willful neglect of duty, it shall cause proceedings to be instituted under sections 23-2001 to 23-2009 to remove such sheriff from office. Failure of the sheriff to comply with the requirements of sections 77-1719 and 77-1719.01 shall be prima facie evidence of willful neglect of duty and willful maladministration in office. The failure or refusal of any member of the county board to carry out the provisions of sections 77-1718 to 77-1719.04 shall be deemed a Class III misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 181, &#167; 2, p. 628; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1719; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 259, &#167; 2(3), p. 847; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 39, &#167; 224; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 34. </para></source></law></legaldoc>