<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id107">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id109" statutenumber="77-1832"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1832</statuteno><catchline id="id112">Real property
taxes; issuance of treasurer's tax deed; service of notice; upon whom made.</catchline><para>(1) Service of the notice provided by section 77-1831 shall be made
by:</para>
<para>(a) Personal or residence service as described in section
25-505.01 upon every person in actual possession or occupancy of the real
property who qualifies as an
owner-occupant under section 77-1824.01; or</para>
<para>(b) Certified mail, return receipt requested, upon the person
in whose name the title to the real property appears of record to the address
where the property tax statement was mailed and upon every encumbrancer of
record in the office of the register of deeds of the county. Whenever the
record of a lien shows the post office address of the lienholder, notice shall
be sent by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the holder of such
lien at the address appearing of record.</para>
<para>(2) Personal or residence
service shall be made by the county sheriff of the county where service is
made or by a person authorized by section 25-507. The sheriff or other person
serving the notice shall be entitled to the statutory fee prescribed in section
33-117. Within twenty days
after the date of request for service of the notice, the person serving the
notice of service shall (a) make proof of service to the person requesting
the service and state the time and place of service including the address
if applicable, the name of the person with whom the notice was left, and the
method of service or (b) return the proof of service with a statement of the
reason for the failure to serve. Failure to make proof of service or delay
in doing so does not affect the validity of the service.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 214, p. 467; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 115, &#167; 1, p. 520; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6542; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 143, &#167; 1, p. 610; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6070; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2022; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1832; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 93, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 158; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 319, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB370, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB341, &#167; 13.</para><operativedate> January 1, 2015</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Actual occupancy or possession means such occupancy or possession as would put an ordinarily prudent man on notice by observation of the premises involved. Thomas v. Flynn, 169 Neb. 458, 100 N.W.2d 37 (1959).</para><para>Service of notice must be made upon the person in whose name the title appears of record, and upon occupant in possession. Kuska v. Kubat, 147 Neb. 139, 22 N.W.2d 484 (1946).</para><para>Personal service is not necessary if owner dead. Sanford v. Scott, 105 Neb. 479, 181 N.W. 148 (1920).</para><para>Notice must be served on person in whose name assessed, and failure to serve notice or show necessity for service by publication renders subsequent proceedings void. Howell v. Jordan, 94 Neb. 264, 143 N.W. 217 (1913).</para><para>Notice to actual occupant is essential. Parsons v. Prudential R. E. Co., 86 Neb. 271, 125 N.W. 521 (1910).</para><para>Service of notice is not essential to foreclosure of lien by purchaser. Carman v. Harris, 61 Neb. 635, 85 N.W. 848 (1901); Merrill v. Ijams, 58 Neb. 706, 79 N.W. 734 (1899).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>