<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id21">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id23" statutenumber="77-1807">
<bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1807</statuteno><catchline id="id26">Real property
taxes; delinquent tax sale; how conducted; sale of part; bid by land bank;
effect.</catchline><para>(1)(a) This
subsection applies until January 1, 2015.</para>
<para>(b) Except as otherwise provided
in subdivision (c) of this subsection, the
person who offers to pay the amount of taxes due on any real property for
the smallest portion of the same shall be the purchaser, and when such person
designates the smallest portion of the real property for which he or she will
pay the amount of taxes assessed against any such property, the portion thus
designated shall be considered an undivided portion.</para>
<para>(c) If a land bank gives an
automatically accepted bid for the real property pursuant to section 19-5217,
the land bank shall be the purchaser, regardless of the bid of any other person.</para>
<para>(d) If no person bids for
a less quantity than the whole and no land bank has given an automatically
accepted bid pursuant to section 19-5217, the treasurer may sell any real
property to any one who will take the whole and pay the taxes and charges
thereon.</para>
<para>(e) If the homestead is listed
separately as a homestead, it shall be sold only for the taxes delinquent
thereon.</para>
<para>(2)(a) This
subsection applies beginning January 1, 2015.</para><para>(b) If a land bank gives
an automatically accepted bid for real property pursuant to section 19-5217,
the land bank shall be the purchaser and no public or private auction shall
be held under sections 77-1801 to 77-1863.</para><para>(c) If no land bank has given an automatically
accepted bid pursuant to section 19-5217, the person who offers to pay the
amount of taxes, delinquent interest, and costs due on any real property shall
be the purchaser.</para><para>(d) The county treasurer shall announce bidding rules at the beginning
of the public auction, and such rules shall apply to all bidders throughout
the public auction.</para><para>(e) The sale, if conducted in a round-robin format, shall be conducted
in the following manner:</para><para>(i) At the commencement of the sale, a count shall be taken of the
number of registered bidders present who want to be eligible to purchase property.
Each registered bidder shall only be counted once. If additional registered
bidders appear at the sale after the commencement of a round, such registered
bidders shall have the opportunity to participate at the end of the next following
round, if any, as provided in subdivision (v) of this subdivision;</para>
<para>(ii) Sequentially
enumerated tickets shall be placed in a receptacle. The number of tickets
in the receptacle for the first round shall equal the count taken in subdivision
(i) of this subdivision, and the number of tickets in the receptacle for each
subsequent round shall equal the number of the count taken in subdivision
(i) of this subdivision plus additional registered bidders as provided in
subdivision (v) of this subdivision;</para><para>(iii) In a manner determined by the county
treasurer, tickets shall be selected from the receptacle by hand for each
registered bidder whereby each ticket has an equal chance of being selected.
Tickets shall be selected until there are no tickets remaining in the receptacle;</para>
<para>(iv) The number
on the ticket selected for a registered bidder shall represent the order in
which a registered bidder may purchase property consisting of one parcel subject
to sale from the list per round; and</para><para>(v) If property listed remains unsold at
the end of a round, a new round shall commence until all property listed is
either sold or, if any property listed remains unsold, each registered bidder
has consecutively passed on the opportunity to make a purchase. Registered
bidders who are not present when it is their turn to purchase property shall
be considered to have passed on the opportunity to make a purchase. At the
beginning of the second and any subsequent rounds, the county treasurer shall
inquire whether there are additional registered bidders. If additional registered
bidders are present, tickets for each such bidder shall be placed in a receptacle
and selected as provided in subdivisions (ii) through (iv) of this subdivision.
The second and any subsequent rounds shall proceed in the same manner and
purchase order as the last preceding round, except that any additional registered
bidders shall be given the opportunity to purchase at the end of the round
in the order designated on their ticket.</para><para>(f) Any property remaining unsold upon completion
of the public auction shall be sold at a private sale pursuant to section
77-1814.</para><para>(g) A bidder shall (i) register with the county treasurer prior
to participating in the sale, (ii) provide proof that it maintains a registered
agent for service of process with the Secretary of State if the bidder is
a foreign corporation, and (iii) pay a twenty-five-dollar registration fee.
The fee is not refundable upon redemption.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 199, p. 461; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6527; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6055; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2007; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 167, &#167; 11, p. 643; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 98, &#167; 11, p. 428; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 157, &#167; 11, p. 614; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-2007; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1807; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 143; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 116; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB341, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB851, &#167; 9.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Effect of sale</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Payment of purchase money</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Payment of subsequent taxes</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Subrogation</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Effect of sale</emphasis></para><para>Sale for less than amount of taxes due is not sale of the land, but it only transfers lien to purchaser. Barker v. Hume, 84 Neb. 235, 120 N.W. 1131 (1909).</para><para>Sale operates to transfer the lien to the purchaser. City Safe Dep. &amp; Agency Co. v. City of Omaha, 79 Neb. 446, 112 N.W. 598 (1907).</para><para>Rule of caveat emptor applies to purchasers of real estate at tax sale. McCague v. City of Omaha, 58 Neb. 37, 78 N.W. 463 (1899); Norris v. Burt County, 56 Neb. 295, 76 N.W. 551 (1898).</para><para><emphasis>2. Payment of purchase money</emphasis></para><para>Tax lien is ordinarily extinguished by payment, except where land is sold for taxes, and subsequent delinquent taxes are paid by holder of certificate. Toy v. McHugh, 62 Neb. 820, 87 N.W. 1059 (1901).</para><para>Statute is notice to purchaser that purchase money must be paid. Richardson County v. Miles, 7 Neb. 118 (1878).</para><para><emphasis>3. Payment of subsequent taxes</emphasis></para><para>Payment of subsequent valid taxes by owner of invalid certificate gives him lien for such valid taxes. John v. Connell, 61 Neb. 267, 85 N.W. 82 (1901).</para><para><emphasis>4. Subrogation</emphasis></para><para>On sale of one tract for taxes levied upon another, purchaser is subrogated to lien of public. Wyman v. Searle, 88 Neb. 26, 128 N.W. 801 (1910).</para><para>Holder of certificate is subrogated to rights of public in any taxes paid to protect his lien. Adams v. Osgood, 60 Neb. 779, 84 N.W. 257 (1900).</para><para>Purchaser is entitled to reimbursement, or subrogation to rights of public. Grant v. Bartholomew, 57 Neb. 673, 78 N.W. 314 (1899); Leavitt v. Bartholomew, 1 Neb. Unof. 756, 93 N.W. 856 (1901).</para><para><emphasis>5. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>In a suit to foreclose, a deficiency judgment is void. Kelley v. Wehn, 63 Neb. 410, 88 N.W. 682 (1902).</para><para>Tax levied on real estate is not a debt against owner, but a charge against the land. Philadelphia M. &amp; T. Co. v. City of Omaha, 63 Neb. 280, 88 N.W. 523 (1901).</para><para>Policy of the law is to encourage competition at the sale. State ex rel. Snow v. Farney, 36 Neb. 537, 54 N.W. 862 (1893).</para><para>Force of tax deed and validity of sale are tested by law in force when sale was made. McCann v. Merriam, 11 Neb. 241, 9 N.W. 96 (1881).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>