<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id47">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id49" statutenumber="77-1822"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1822</statuteno><catchline id="id52">Real property
taxes; certificate of purchase; assignable;
fee.</catchline><para>The certificate of purchase shall
be assignable by endorsement, and an assignment thereof shall vest in the
assignee, or his or her legal representatives, all the right and title of
the original purchaser. The statement in the treasurer's deed of the fact
of the assignment shall be presumptive evidence thereof. An assignment shall
be recorded by the county treasurer who shall collect a reassignment fee of twenty dollars and issue a new certificate to
the assignee. The fee is not
refundable upon redemption.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 210, p. 465; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6538; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6066; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2018; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 167, &#167; 37, p. 663; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 98, &#167; 37, p. 451; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 157, &#167; 37, p. 634; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-2018; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1822; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 994, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB341, &#167; 6.</para></source><annotation><para>A tax sale certificate may be assigned by endorsement; and assignee acquires all the rights of assignor. Security Investment Co. v. Golz, 151 Neb. 172, 36 N.W.2d 862 (1949).</para><para>Possession of certificate, without proof of assignment, will not satisfy burden of proof placed upon plaintiff, where his title as assignee is denied. Wyman v. Searle, 88 Neb. 26, 128 N.W. 801 (1910).</para><para>Proof of endorsement by original purchaser and possession by endorsee are prima facie evidence of ownership. Farmers L. &amp; T. Co. v. Joseph, 86 Neb. 256, 125 N.W. 533 (1910); Leavitt v. Bartholomew, 1 Neb. Unof. 756, 93 N.W. 856 (1901).</para><para>Certificate may be assigned by endorsement, and assignee acquires all rights of assignor. Green v. Hellman, 61 Neb. 875, 86 N.W. 912 (1901).</para><para>A quitclaim deed will convey equitable title to sale certificate on land conveyed. Leavitt v. Bell, 55 Neb. 57, 75 N.W. 524 (1898).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>