<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id63"><sectno id="id64" opdate="April 15, 2008">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id65" statutenumber="77-1230"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id67">77-1230</statuteno><catchline id="id68">Taxable tangible personal property; amended listing; when required; county assessor; duties; refund; additional tax due.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever a person files an amended federal income tax return or whenever a person's return is changed or corrected by the Internal Revenue Service or other competent authority and the amendment, change, or correction affects the Nebraska adjusted basis of the person's taxable tangible personal property, such person shall file an amended list of taxable tangible personal property subject to taxation with the county assessor. The person shall file the amended list within ninety days after the filing of the amended federal return or within ninety days after the date the change or correction becomes final.</para><para>(2) Within the same tax year or the three previous tax years, a person may file an amended list of taxable tangible personal property subject to taxation upon discovery of errors or omissions on his or her filed list.</para><para>(3) If an amended list of taxable tangible personal property subject to taxation is filed, the county assessor shall accept or reject the proposed amendment within fifteen days after filing. The county assessor shall notify the person, on a form prescribed by the Property Tax Administrator, of the action taken, the penalty, if any, and the rate of interest. The notice shall also state the person's appeal rights and appeal procedures, which shall be the same as provided in section 77-1233.06. Such notice shall be given by first-class mail addressed to such person's last-known address.</para><para>(4) Whenever changes are made to a taxable tangible personal property return pursuant to this section, the county assessor shall correct the assessment roll and tax list, if necessary, to reflect such changes.</para><para>(5) If the amendment, change, or correction results in taxable tangible personal property becoming exempt or reduces the net book value of the property for an income tax year, a refund shall be paid pursuant to section 77-1734.01.</para><para>(6) If the amendment, change, or correction results in an increase in the net book value of the taxable tangible personal property or makes other tangible personal property taxable, the county assessor shall compute the additional tax due, along with interest, based on the amended listing. Interest shall be computed from the dates the tax would have been delinquent if the property had been listed on or before May 1 of the appropriate year. If the amended listing is filed within the ninety-day period, no additional penalties shall be added. If the listing is not filed within the ninety-day period, the property shall be subject to a penalty pursuant to subsection (4) of section 77-1233.04.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 8.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 