<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<sectno id="id20">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id21" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-1005"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1005</statuteno><catchline>Approved cost, defined.</catchline><para>Approved cost
means:</para>
<para>(1) Obligations
incurred for labor and to vendors, contractors, subcontractors, builders,
suppliers, delivery persons, and material suppliers in connection with the
acquisition, construction, equipping, and installation of a project;</para>
<para>(2) The cost
of acquiring real property or rights in real property and any cost incidental
thereto;</para><para>(3) The cost of contract bonds and of insurance of all kinds that
may be required or necessary during the course of the acquisition, construction,
equipping, and installation of a project which is not paid by the vendor,
supplier, delivery person, or contractor or otherwise provided;</para>
<para>(4) The cost
of architectural and engineering services, including, but not limited to,
estimates, plans, specifications, preliminary investigations, and supervision
of construction and installation, as well as for the performance of all the
duties required by or consequent to the acquisition, construction, equipping,
and installation of a project;</para><para>(5) The cost required to be paid under the
terms of any contract for the acquisition, construction, equipping, and installation
of a project;</para><para>(6) The cost required for the installation of utilities, including,
but not limited to: Water; sewer; sewer treatment; gas; electricity; and communications,
including offsite construction of facilities paid for by the project owner;
and</para><para>(7) All other costs comparable with those described in this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1018, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>