<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id623"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1120"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1120</statuteno><catchline>Qualified community development entity; report to Tax Commissioner; Tax Commissioner; report to Legislature.</catchline><para>(1) A qualified community development entity that has received an allocation of qualified equity investment authority pursuant to the 2021 allocation shall submit an annual report to the Tax Commissioner on or before the last day of February following the second through seventh credit allowance dates. The annual report shall provide documentation as to the qualified community development entity's qualified low-income community investments and include all of the following:</para><para>(a) A bank statement evidencing each qualified low-income community investment;</para><para>(b) The name, location, and industry of each qualified active low-income community business receiving a qualified low-income community investment; and</para><para>(c) The number of jobs created or retained as a result of each qualified low-income community investment.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner shall electronically submit a report to the Legislature on or before April 1, 2022, and on or before each April 1 thereafter through April 1, 2028, with respect to the 2021 allocation. The report shall include all of the following:</para><para>(a) The name and number of all of the qualified community development entities approved to participate in the 2021 allocation;</para><para>(b) The amount of qualified low-income community investments made by the qualified community development entities;</para><para>(c) The location of each qualified active low-income community business; and</para><para>(d) The number of jobs created or retained as a result of each qualified low-income community investment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB682, &#167; 10. </para><effectivedate>May 26, 2021</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>