<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-1327"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1327</statuteno><catchline>Legislative intent; Property Tax
Administrator; sales file; studies; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1)
It is the intent of the Legislature that accurate and comprehensive information
be developed by the Property Tax Administrator and made accessible to the
taxing officials and property owners in order to ensure the uniformity and
proportionality of the assessments of real property valuations in the state
in accordance with law and to provide the statistical and narrative reports
pursuant to section 77-5027.</para>
<para>(2) All transactions of real property for which the statement required
in section 76-214 is filed shall be available for development of a sales file
by the Property Tax Administrator. All transactions with stated consideration
of more than one hundred dollars or upon which more than two dollars and twenty-five
cents in documentary stamp taxes are paid shall be considered sales. All sales
shall be deemed to be arm's length transactions unless determined to be otherwise
under professionally accepted mass appraisal techniques. The Department of
Revenue shall not overturn a determination made by a county assessor regarding
the qualification of a sale unless the department reviews the sale and determines
through the review that the determination made by the county assessor is incorrect.</para>
<para>(3) The Property Tax Administrator annually shall make and issue comprehensive
assessment ratio studies of the average level of assessment, the degree of
assessment uniformity, and the overall compliance with assessment requirements
for each major class of real property subject to the property tax in each
county. The comprehensive assessment ratio studies shall be developed in compliance
with professionally accepted mass appraisal techniques and shall employ such
statistical analysis as deemed appropriate by the Property Tax Administrator,
including measures of central tendency and dispersion. The comprehensive assessment
ratio studies shall be based upon the sales file as developed in subsection
(2) of this section and shall be used by the Property Tax Administrator for
the analysis of the level of value and quality of assessment for purposes
of section 77-5027 and by the Property Tax Administrator in establishing the
adjusted valuations required by section 79-1016. Such studies may also be
used by assessing officials in establishing assessed valuations.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of determining the level of value of agricultural and
horticultural land subject to special valuation under sections 77-1343 to
77-1347.01, the Property Tax Administrator shall annually make and issue a
comprehensive study developed in compliance with professionally accepted mass
appraisal techniques to establish the level of value if in his or her opinion
the level of value cannot be developed through the use of the comprehensive
assessment ratio studies developed in subsection (3) of this section.</para>
<para>(5) County assessors
and other taxing officials shall electronically report
data on the assessed valuation and other features of the property assessment process for such periods and
in such form and content as the Property Tax Administrator shall deem appropriate.
The Property Tax Administrator shall so construct and maintain the system
used to collect and analyze the data to enable him or her to make intracounty
comparisons of assessed valuation, including school districts and other political subdivisions, as well as
intercounty comparisons of assessed valuation, including school districts and other political subdivisions.
The Property Tax Administrator shall include analysis of real property sales
pursuant to land contracts and similar transfers at the time of execution
of the contract or similar transfer.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 622, &#167; 3, p. 2513; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 207; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 834, &#167; 61; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 166; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1275, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 124; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 36, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 994, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 40, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB166, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB210, &#167; 5.</para></source><annotation><para>The real property transactions eligible for inclusion in the sales file are those transactions for which the statement required by section 76-214 is filed. For those transactions initially eligible for inclusion in the sales file, the price to be included in the sales file is the total consideration paid as listed on the statement described in subsection (1) of section 76-214. Section 77-1371 does not pertain to a compilation of a sales file under subsection (2) of this section. Shaul v. Lang, 263 Neb. 499, 640 N.W.2d 668 (2002).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
