<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1386"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1386</statuteno><catchline>Historically significant real property; landmark ordinance or resolution; approval.</catchline><para>(1) A city, village, or county shall request the State Historic Preservation Officer's approval of any landmark ordinance or resolution which designates individual properties or districts before any such individual properties or historically significant properties within such districts receive historic rehabilitation valuation authorized by section 77-1391. The following documentation shall accompany the request:</para><para>(a) A copy of the ordinance or resolution for which approval is requested;</para><para>(b) A list, including the common addresses and common written boundary descriptions of all individual properties and historic districts designated or proposed to be designated under the ordinance or resolution;</para><para>(c) A description and statement of historical significance for all designated individual properties and historic districts, which includes representative photographic views; and</para><para>(d) A map indicating the location of individual landmarks and historic districts.</para><para>(2) Within forty-five days after receipt of the request and documentation, the State Historic Preservation Officer shall approve the ordinance or resolution if the documentation indicates compliance with the criteria for designation of landmarks and historic districts established by the United States Department of the Interior for the inclusion of properties in the National Register of Historic Places, 36 C.F.R. 60, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2005, and if the ordinance or resolution contains provisions for the following:</para><para>(a) Authorization for historic preservation under section 19-903;</para><para>(b) A statement of purpose;</para><para>(c) Establishment of a historic review commission which:</para><para>(i) Has no fewer than five members;</para><para>(ii) Has demonstrated expertise in the disciplines of history, architectural history, historic architecture, architecture, community planning, real estate, neighborhood conservation, historic preservation, or related fields;</para><para>(iii) Has staggered terms of office for members; and</para><para>(iv) Holds meetings at regular intervals at least four times a year;</para><para>(d) A process and criteria for designation of landmarks and historic districts that are consistent with those established by the United States Department of the Interior for the inclusion of properties in the National Register of Historic Places, 36 C.F.R. 60, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2005;</para><para>(e) A definition of actions that merit review by the historic review commission, which shall include demolitions and major alterations;</para><para>(f) Standards and criteria for review of actions within the jurisdiction of the historic review commission; and</para><para>(g) Procedural due process, such as notification, a hearing, and an appeal procedure.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 66, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>