<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id79" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-1340.04"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1340.04</statuteno><catchline>Property Tax Administrator; relinquish
property tax function; employees; transfer of property; appointment of county
assessor; allocation of costs; contracts.</catchline><para>(1) On July 1,
2013, the Property Tax Administrator shall relinquish the property assessment
function in all counties that transferred the assessment function to the Property
Tax Administrator and have not reassumed the assessment function prior to
such date.</para>
<para>(2) On July 1, 2013, the employees of the Department of Revenue involved
in the performance of the county assessment function shall become county employees
by operation of law.</para>
<para>(3) At the close of business on June 30, 2013, the Property Tax Administrator
shall cease his or her performance of the county assessment function and the
county assessor appointed pursuant to subsection (4) of this section shall
assume the county assessment function. The Property Tax Administrator shall
at that time transfer all books, files, and similar records with regard to
the county assessment function of the county and all furniture, computers,
and other equipment and property used by the state to perform the county assessment
function, other than motor vehicles, to the county assessor.</para>
<para>(4) In such counties, the county board shall appoint an individual with
a valid assessor's certificate to the position of county assessor. The appointment
shall be effective July 1, 2013. On July 1, 2013, the appointed county assessor
shall assume the title and perform the assessment functions and any other
duties mandated of the office of county assessor. The appointed assessor shall
continue to perform the county assessor's duties until an assessor is elected
at the next election.</para>
<para>(5) The Property Tax Administrator shall provide to each county board
of a county that transferred the assessment function to the Property Tax Administrator
on or before October 1, 2009, a line-item allocation of its total cost of
the assessment function for the fiscal year ending June 30, 2009. This allocation
of costs shall also identify the costs attributable to those employees that
perform duties in more than one county.</para>
<para>(6) Contracts of the Department
of Revenue pertaining to the operation of the county assessment function may be assumed by the county.</para>
<para>(7) Counties in which there are employees of the department who provide
services to more than one county shall enter into an agreement pursuant to
section 77-1339 for the continued performance of the services provided by
the employee. No agreement pursuant to section 77-1339 is necessary if one
of the counties in which the employee is providing services agrees to retain
the employee as a permanent full-time employee.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB121, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB55, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>