<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id960"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation"  statutenumber="77-1406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1406</statuteno><catchline>Investment options; state investment officer; fiduciary responsibility.</catchline><para>The State Treasurer and any designated administrator shall provide investment options for the investment of amounts contributed to an account, except that the state investment officer shall have fiduciary responsibility to make all decisions regarding the investment of the money in the expense fund and program fund created in section 77-1407 and any money credited to the Treasury Management Cash Fund for administrative expenses of the program, including the selection of all investment options and the approval of all fees and other costs charged to trust assets except costs for administration, operation, and maintenance of the trust as appropriated by the Legislature, pursuant to the directions, guidelines, and policies established by the Nebraska Investment Council. The State Treasurer shall not adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that in any way interfere with the fiduciary responsibility of the state investment officer to make all decisions regarding the investment of money in the expense fund and program fund or money of the program credited to the Treasury Management Cash Fund. The Nebraska Investment Council may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to provide for the prudent investment of the assets of the program. The council or its designee also has the authority to select and enter into agreements with individuals and entities to provide investment advice and management of the assets held by the program, establish investment guidelines, objectives, and performance standards with respect to the assets held by the program, and approve any fees, commissions, and expenses, which directly or indirectly affect the return on assets.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB591, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>