<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1514"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1514</statuteno><catchline>Abstract of property assessment rolls; prepared by county assessor; file with Property Tax Administrator.</catchline><para>(1) The county assessor shall prepare an abstract of the property assessment rolls of locally assessed real property of his or her county on forms prescribed and furnished by the Tax Commissioner. The county assessor shall file the abstract with the Property Tax Administrator on or before March 19, except beginning January 1, 2014, in any county with a population of at least one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants according to the most recent federal decennial census, the real property abstract shall be filed on or before March 25. The abstract shall show the taxable value of real property in the county as determined by the county assessor and any other information as required by the Property Tax Administrator. The Property Tax Administrator, upon written request from the county assessor, may for good cause shown extend the final filing due date for the abstract and the statutory deadlines provided in section 77-5027. The Property Tax Administrator may extend the statutory deadline in section 77-5028 for a county if the deadline is extended for that county. Beginning January 1, 2014, in any county with a population of at least one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants according to the most recent federal decennial census, the county assessor shall request an extension of the final filing due date by March 22.</para><para>(2) For tax years prior to tax year 2020, the county assessor shall prepare an abstract of the property assessment rolls of locally assessed personal property of his or her county on forms prescribed and furnished by the Tax Commissioner. The county assessor shall electronically file the abstract with the Property Tax Administrator on or before July 20.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 125, p. 431; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6442; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5977; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-1707; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-1514; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 190, &#167; 1, p. 590; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 251, &#167; 39, p. 827; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 371, &#167; 4, p. 1309; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 508, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 129; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 902, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 155; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 91; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 37; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 15, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 261, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB162, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB259, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 128. </para></source><annotation><para>Power of county board of equalization to rectify returns and change assessments is limited to a set number of circumscribed days each year. John Day Co. v. Douglas Cty. Bd. of Equal., 243 Neb. 24, 497 N.W.2d 65 (1993).</para><para>County assessor should forward abstract of assessment rolls by July 1. Fromkin v. State, 158 Neb. 377, 63 N.W.2d 332 (1954); County of Howard v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 339, 63 N.W.2d 441 (1954); County of Douglas v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 325, 63 N.W.2d 449 (1954); County of Grant v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 310, 63 N.W.2d 459 (1954).</para><para>County assessor is required to prepare abstract of assessment and forward to state board. Adair v. Miller, 109 Neb. 295, 190 N.W. 865 (1922).</para><para>Actual levy of taxes cannot occur until after completion of the work of State Board of Equalization and Assessment. United States v. Thurston County, 54 F.Supp. 201 (D. Neb. 1944).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>