<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id749"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-1239"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1239</statuteno><catchline>Reimbursement for tax revenue lost because of exemption; calculation.</catchline><para>(1) Reimbursement to taxing subdivisions for tax revenue that will be lost because of the personal property tax exemptions allowed in subsection (1) of section 77-1238 shall be as provided in this subsection. The county assessor and county treasurer shall, on or before November 30 of each year, certify to the Tax Commissioner, on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, the total tax revenue that will be lost to all taxing subdivisions within his or her county from taxes levied and assessed in that year because of the personal property tax exemptions allowed in subsection (1) of section 77-1238. The county assessor and county treasurer may amend the certification to show any change or correction in the total tax revenue that will be lost until May 30 of the next succeeding year. The Tax Commissioner shall, on or before January 1 next following the certification, notify the Director of Administrative Services of the amount so certified to be reimbursed by the state. Reimbursement of the tax revenue lost shall be made to each county according to the certification and shall be distributed in two approximately equal installments on the last business day of February and the last business day of June. The State Treasurer shall, on the business day preceding the last business day of February and the last business day of June, notify the Director of Administrative Services of the amount of funds available in the General Fund to pay the reimbursement. The Director of Administrative Services shall, on the last business day of February and the last business day of June, draw warrants against funds appropriated. Out of the amount received, the county treasurer shall distribute to each of the taxing subdivisions within his or her county the full tax revenue lost by each subdivision, except that one percent of such amount shall be deposited in the county general fund.</para><para>(2) Reimbursement to taxing subdivisions for tax revenue that will be lost because of the compensating exemption factor in subsection (2) of section 77-1238 shall be as provided in this subsection. The Property Tax Administrator shall establish the average tax rate that will be used for purposes of reimbursing taxing subdivisions pursuant to this subsection. The average tax rate shall be equal to the total property taxes levied in the state divided by the total taxable value of all taxable property in the state as certified pursuant to section 77-1613.01. The Tax Commissioner shall certify, on or before January 30 of each year, to the Director of Administrative Services the total valuation that will be lost to all taxing subdivisions within each county because of the compensating exemption factor in subsection (2) of section 77-1238. Such amount, multiplied by the average tax rate calculated pursuant to this subsection, shall be the tax revenue to be reimbursed to the taxing subdivisions by the state. Reimbursement of the tax revenue lost for public service entities shall be made to each county according to the certification and shall be distributed among the taxing subdivisions within each county in the same proportion as all public service entity taxes levied by the taxing subdivisions. Reimbursement of the tax revenue lost for railroads shall be made to each county according to the certification and shall be distributed among the taxing subdivisions within each county in the same proportion as all railroad taxes levied by taxing subdivisions. Reimbursement of the tax revenue lost for car line companies shall be distributed in the same manner as the taxes collected pursuant to section 77-684. Reimbursement of the tax revenue lost for air carriers shall be distributed in the same manner as the taxes collected pursuant to section 77-1250.</para><para>(3) Each taxing subdivision shall, in preparing its annual or biennial budget, take into account the amounts to be received under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2015, LB259, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>