<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id197"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-1307"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1307</statuteno><catchline>Destroyed real property; legislative findings and declarations; terms, defined.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds and declares that fires, earthquakes, floods, and tornadoes occur with enough frequency in this state that provision should be made to grant property tax relief to owners of real property adversely affected by such events.</para><para>(2) For purposes of sections 77-1307 to 77-1309:</para><para>(a) Calamity means a disastrous event, including, but not limited to, a fire, an earthquake, a flood, a tornado, or other natural event which significantly affects the assessed value of real property;</para><para>(b) Destroyed real property means real property that suffers significant property damage as a result of a calamity occurring on or after January 1, 2019, and before July 1 of the current assessment year. Destroyed real property does not include property suffering significant property damage that is caused by the owner of the property; and</para><para>(c) Significant property damage means:</para><para>(i) Damage to an improvement exceeding twenty percent of the improvement's assessed value in the current tax year as determined by the county assessor;</para><para>(ii) Damage to land exceeding twenty percent of a parcel's assessed land value in the current tax year as determined by the county assessor; or</para><para>(iii) Damage exceeding twenty percent of the property's assessed value in the current tax year as determined by the county assessor if (A) such property is located in an area that has been declared a disaster area by the Governor and (B) a housing inspector or health inspector has determined that the property is uninhabitable or unlivable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 15. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>