<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id424">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id426" statutenumber="77-1375"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-1375</statuteno><catchline id="id429">Improvements
on leased lands; how assessed; apportionment.</catchline><para>(1)
If improvements on leased land are to be assessed separately to the owner
of the improvements, the actual value of the real property shall be determined
without regard to the fact that the owner of the improvements is not the owner
of the land upon which such improvements have been placed.</para>
<para>(2) If the owner of the improvements claims that the value
of his or her interest in the real property is reduced by reason of uncertainty
in the term of his or her tenancy or because of the prospective termination
or expiration of the term, he or she shall serve notice of such claim in writing
by mail
on the owner of the land before January 1 and shall at the same time serve
similar notice on the county assessor, together with his or her affidavit
that he or she has served notice on the owner of the land.</para>
<para>(3) If the county assessor finds, on the basis of the evidence
submitted, that the claim is valid, he or she shall proceed to apportion the
total value of the real property between the owner of the improvements and
the owner of the land as their respective interests appear.</para>
<para>(4) The county assessor shall give notice to the parties
of his or her findings by mail
on or before June 1.</para>
<para>(5) The proportions so established shall continue from year
to year unless changed by the county assessor after notice on or before June
1 or a claim is filed by either the owner of the improvements or the owner
of the land in accordance with the procedure provided in this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 365, &#167; 4, p. 1286; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 199; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 508, &#167; 31; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1990), &#167; 77-1209.02; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 112; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 83; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 32.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>