<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id858"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,239"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,239</statuteno><catchline>Online hosting platform; Tax Commissioner; agreement authorized; powers.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section, online hosting platform means a marketplace connected by computer to one or more other computers or networks, as through a commercial electronic information service or the Internet, through which (a) a seller or hotel operator may rent or furnish any room or rooms, lodgings, or accommodations in a hotel, a motel, an inn, a tourist camp, a tourist cabin, or any other place, (b) such room or rooms, lodgings, or accommodations may be advertised or listed, and (c) a purchaser or occupant may arrange for the occupancy of such room or rooms, lodgings, or accommodations.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner may enter into an agreement with an online hosting platform to permit the online hosting platform to collect and pay the applicable sales taxes imposed under the Local Option Revenue Act, the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the Nebraska Visitors Development Act, and sections 13-318 to 13-326 and 13-2813 to 13-2816 on behalf of the seller or hotel operator otherwise required to collect such taxes for transactions consummated through the online hosting platform. Upon entering into such agreement with the online hosting platform, the Tax Commissioner shall waive the tax collection responsibility of a seller or hotel operator for transactions consummated through the online hosting platform for which the online hosting platform has assumed this responsibility. The online hosting platform shall give written notice to each seller or hotel operator which is covered by the agreement between the online hosting platform and the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(3) Upon entering into an agreement with the Tax Commissioner under this section, the online hosting platform shall report aggregate information on the tax return prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, including an aggregate of gross receipts, exemptions, adjustments, and taxable receipts of all transactions subject to the agreement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB57, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Local Option Revenue Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,148.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Visitors Development Act,</emphasis> see section 81-3701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>