<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id46" statutenumber="77-2704.57"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2704.57</statuteno><catchline id="id49">Personal property used
in C-BED project or community-based energy development project; exemption;
Tax Commissioner; powers and duties; Department of Revenue; recover tax not
paid.</catchline><para>(1) Sales and use tax shall not be imposed on the gross
receipts from the sale, lease, or rental of personal property for use in a
C-BED project or community-based energy development project. This exemption
shall be conditioned upon filing requirements for the exemption as imposed
by the Tax Commissioner. The requirements imposed by the Tax Commissioner
shall be related to ensuring that the property purchased qualifies for the
exemption. The Tax Commissioner may require the filing of the documents showing
compliance with section 70-1907, the organization of the project, the distribution
of the payments, the power purchase agreements, the project pro forma, articles
of incorporation, operating agreements, and any amendments or changes to these
documents during the life of the power purchase agreement.</para>
<para>(2) The Tax Commissioner shall notify an electric utility that has a
power purchase agreement with a C-BED project if there is a change in project
ownership which makes the project no longer eligible as a C-BED project. Purchase
of a C-BED project by an electric utility prior to the end of the power purchase
agreement disqualifies the C-BED project for the exemption, but the Department
of Revenue may not recover the amount of the sales and use tax that was not
paid by the project prior to the purchase.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) C-BED project or community-based energy development project means
a new wind energy project that:</para>
<para>(i) Has an ownership structure as follows:</para>
<para>(A) For a C-BED project that consists of more than two turbines, has
one or more qualified owners with no single individual qualified owner owning
directly or indirectly more than fifteen percent of the project and with at
least thirty-three percent of the gross power purchase agreement payments
flowing to the qualified owner or owners or local community; or</para>
<para>(B) For a C-BED project that consists of one or two turbines, has one
or more qualified owners with at least thirty-three percent of the gross power
purchase agreement payments flowing to a qualified owner or owners or local
community; and</para>
<para>(ii) Has a resolution of support adopted:</para>
<para>(A) By the county board of each county in which the C-BED project is
to be located; or</para>
<para>(B) By the tribal council for a C-BED project located within the boundaries
of an Indian reservation;</para>
<para>(b) Debt financing payments means principal, interest, and other typical
financing costs paid by the C-BED project company to one or more third-party
financial institutions for the financing or refinancing of the construction
of the C-BED project. Debt financing payments does not include the repayment
of principal at the time of a refinancing;</para>
<para>(c) New wind energy project means any tangible personal property incorporated
into the manufacture, installation, construction, repair, or replacement of
a device, such as a wind charger, windmill, or wind turbine, which is used
to convert wind energy to electrical energy or for the transmission of electricity
to the purchaser; and</para>
<para>(d) Qualified owner means:</para>
<para>(i) A Nebraska resident;</para>
<para>(ii) A limited liability company that is organized under the Nebraska
Uniform Limited Liability Company Act and that is entirely made up of members
who are Nebraska residents;</para>
<para>(iii) A Nebraska nonprofit corporation organized under the Nebraska
Nonprofit Corporation Act;</para>
<para>(iv) An electric supplier as defined in section 70-1001.01, except that
ownership in a single C-BED project is limited to no more than:</para>
<para>(A) Fifteen percent either directly or indirectly by a single electric
supplier; and</para>
<para>(B) A combined total of twenty-five percent ownership either directly
or indirectly by multiple electric suppliers; or</para>
<para>(v) A tribal council.</para>
<para>(4) Gross power purchase agreement payments are the total amount of
payments during the life of the agreement. For power purchase agreements entered
into on or before December 31, 2011, if the qualified owners have a combined
total of at least thirty-three percent of the equity ownership in the C-BED
project, gross power purchase agreement payments shall be reduced by the debt
financing payments. For the purpose of determining eligibility of the project,
an estimate of the payments and their recipients shall be used.</para>
<para>(5) Payments to the local community include, but are not limited to,
lease payments to property owners on whose property a turbine is located,
wind agreement payments, and real and personal property tax receipts from
the C-BED project.</para>
<para>(6) The Department of Revenue may examine the actual payments and the
distribution of the payments to determine if the projected distributions were
met. If the payment distributions to qualified owners do not meet the requirements
of this section, the department may recover the amount of the sales or use
tax that was not paid by the project at any time up until the end of three
years after the end of the power purchase agreement.</para>
<para>(7) At any time prior to the end of the power purchase agreements, the
project may voluntarily surrender the exemption granted by the Tax Commissioner
and pay the amount of sales and use tax that would otherwise have been due.</para>
<para>(8) The amount of the tax due under either subsection (6) or (7) of
this section shall be increased by interest at the rate specified in section
45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted, from the date the
tax would have been due if no exemption was granted until the date paid.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB367, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB916, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB561, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB828, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB283, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>