<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,111"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,111</statuteno><catchline>Income tax; taxpayer; depart from state; conceal property; Tax Commissioner; powers.</catchline><para>(1) If the Tax Commissioner finds that a taxpayer is about to (a) depart from the State of Nebraska, (b) remove his property therefrom, (c) conceal himself or his property therein, or (d) do any other act tending to prejudice or render wholly or partially ineffectual any proceedings to collect the income tax for the preceding or current taxable year unless such proceedings be brought without delay, the Tax Commissioner shall declare the taxable period for such taxpayer immediately terminated, and shall cause notice of such findings and declaration to be given the taxpayer, together with a demand for immediate payment of any income tax due for this period, whether or not the time otherwise allowed by law for filing returns and paying the tax has expired. Such tax shall thereupon become immediately due and payable. In any proceedings in court brought to enforce payment of taxes made due and payable by virtue of the provisions of this section, such findings of the Tax Commissioner, whether made after notice to the taxpayer or not, shall be for all purposes prima facie evidence of the taxpayer's design.</para><para>(2) A taxpayer who is not in default in making any income tax return or paying any income taxes assessed under the provisions of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 may furnish to the Tax Commissioner, under regulations to be prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, security that he will duly make the return next thereafter required to be filed and pay the tax next thereafter required to be paid. The Tax Commissioner may approve and accept in like manner security for return and payment of taxes made due and payable by virtue of the provisions of this section.</para><para>(3) If security is approved and accepted pursuant to the provisions of subsection (2) of this section and such further or other security with respect to the tax or taxes covered thereby is given as the Tax Commissioner shall from time to time find necessary and require, payment of such taxes shall not be enforced by any proceedings under the provisions of this section prior to the expiration of the time otherwise allowed for paying such taxes.</para><para>(4) In the case of a bona fide resident of Nebraska about to depart from the state the Tax Commissioner may waive any or all of the requirements placed upon the taxpayer by the provisions of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 111, p. 1625. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 