<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-27,235"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,235</statuteno><catchline>Renewable energy tax credit; Department of Revenue; Environmental Quality Council; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Any producer of electricity generated by a new zero-emission facility shall earn a renewable energy tax credit. For electricity generated on or after July 14, 2006, and before October 1, 2007, the credit shall be .075 cent for each kilowatt-hour of electricity generated by a new zero-emission facility. For electricity generated on or after October 1, 2007, and before January 1, 2010, the credit shall be .1 cent for each kilowatt-hour of electricity generated by a new zero-emission facility. For electricity generated on or after January 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2013, the credit shall be .075 cent per kilowatt-hour for electricity generated by a new zero-emission facility. For electricity generated on or after January 1, 2013, and before January 1, 2018, the credit shall be .05 cent per kilowatt-hour for electricity generated by a new zero-emission facility. The credit may be earned for production of electricity for ten years after the date that the facility is placed in operation on or after July 14, 2006.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Electricity generated by a new zero-emission facility means electricity that is exclusively produced by a new zero-emission facility;</para><para>(b) Eligible renewable resources means wind, moving water, solar, geothermal, fuel cell, methane gas, or photovoltaic technology; and</para><para>(c) New zero-emission facility means an electrical generating facility located in this state that is first placed into service on or after July 14, 2006, which utilizes eligible renewable resources as its fuel source and for which the operation of the facility results in no pollution or emissions that are or may be harmful to the environment as certified by the Department of Environmental Quality.</para><para>(3) The credit allowed under this section may be used to reduce the producer's Nebraska income tax liability or to obtain a refund of state sales and use taxes paid by the producer of electricity generated by a zero-emission facility. A claim to use the credit for refund of the state sales and use taxes paid, either directly or indirectly, by the producer may be filed quarterly for electricity generated during the previous quarter by the twentieth day of the month following the end of the calendar quarter. The credit may be used to obtain a refund of state sales and use taxes paid during the quarter immediately preceding the quarter in which the claim for refund is made, except that the amount refunded under this subsection shall not exceed the amount of the state sales and use taxes paid during the quarter.</para><para>(4) The Department of Revenue may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to permit verification of the validity and timeliness of any renewable energy tax credit claimed.</para><para>(5) The Environmental Quality Council may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to certify that the operation of a new zero-emission facility results in no pollution or emissions that are or may be harmful to the environment.</para><para>(6) The total amount of renewable energy tax credits that may be used by all taxpayers shall be limited to seven hundred fifty thousand dollars without further authorization from the Legislature.</para><para>(7) The credit allowed under this section may not be claimed by a producer who received a sales tax exemption under section 77-2704.57 for the new zero-emission facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 872, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB367, &#167; 24.</para></source></law></legaldoc>