<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2395"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2395</statuteno><catchline>Custodial official; duties.</catchline><para>(1) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a depository provides a deposit guaranty bond or furnishes securities or any combination thereof, pursuant to section 77-2389, the custodial official shall not have on deposit in such depository any public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, unless and until the depository has provided a deposit guaranty bond or furnished securities, or any combination thereof, to the custodial official, and the total value of such deposit guaranty bond and the market value of such securities are in an amount not less than one hundred two percent of the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed.</para><para>(2) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a depository provides a deposit guaranty bond or furnishes securities or any combination thereof, pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-2398, the custodial official shall not have on deposit in such depository any public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, unless and until the depository has provided a deposit guaranty bond or furnished securities, or any combination thereof, pursuant to the Public Funds Deposit Security Act, and the total value of such deposit guaranty bond and the market value of such securities are in an amount not less than one hundred two percent of the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1274, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB622, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>