<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id361" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-2604.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2604.01</statuteno><catchline>Cigarette sales; reports required; contents.</catchline><para>(1) Any person that sells cigarettes from this state into another state shall, within fifteen days following the end of each month, file a report in the manner prescribed by the Tax Commissioner and certify to the state that the report is complete and accurate.</para><para>(2) The report shall contain the following information:</para><para>(a) The total number of cigarettes sold from this state into another state by the person during that month, identifying by name and number of cigarettes (i) the manufacturers of those cigarettes, (ii) the brand families of those cigarettes, and (iii) the name and address of each recipient of those cigarettes;</para><para>(b) The number of stamps of each other state the person affixed to the packages containing those cigarettes during that month, the total number of cigarettes contained in the packages to which it affixed each respective other state's stamp and by name and number of cigarettes, and the manufacturers and brand families of the packages to which it affixed each respective other state's stamp; and</para><para>(c) If the person sold cigarettes during that month from this state into another state in packages not bearing a stamp of the other state, (i) the total number of cigarettes contained in such packages, identifying by name and number of cigarettes, the manufacturers of those cigarettes, the brand families of those cigarettes, and the name and address of each recipient of those cigarettes, and (ii) the person's basis for belief that such state permits the sale of the cigarettes to consumers in a package not bearing a stamp, and the amount of excise, use, or similar tax imposed on the cigarettes paid by the person to such state on the cigarettes. Manufacturers and importers need include the information described in subdivision (2)(c)(i) of this section only as to cigarettes not sold to a person authorized by the law of the other state to affix the stamp required by the other state.</para><para>(3) In the case of a manufacturer or importer, the report shall include cigarettes sold from this state into another state through its sales entity affiliate. A sales entity affiliate shall file a separate report under this section only to the extent that it sold cigarettes from this state into another state not separately reported under this section by its affiliated manufacturer or importer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB261, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB217, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>