<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2365.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2365.01</statuteno><catchline>Funds of state or political subdivisions; deposit with qualifying mutual financial institutions; conditions.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any local ordinance, regulation, or resolution, or any rule or regulation to the contrary, the funds of this state or any political subdivision of the state may be deposited, by the appropriate custodians of such funds, with qualifying mutual financial institutions to the same extent and subject to the same terms, conditions, and limitations, including collateralization required, if any, as may be otherwise provided for the deposit of such funds in banks and capital stock financial institutions. In making such a deposit of public funds, it shall not be necessary for the state or any political subdivision to become an owner of any interest in the qualifying mutual financial institution or to acquire voting rights therein, and a qualifying mutual financial institution is authorized and empowered to receive public funds under these conditions. Qualifying mutual financial institution means a state or federal mutual building and loan association, a state or federal mutual savings and loan association, a state or federal mutual savings bank, or a state or federal mutual organized bank, which has a main chartered office in this state, any branch thereof in this state, or any branch in this state of a qualifying mutual financial institution which maintained a main chartered office in this state prior to becoming a branch of such qualifying mutual financial institution, which, by its charter and bylaws, restricts the rights of the state or a political subdivision as an account holder as follows:</para><para>(i) Interest in the qualifying mutual financial institution is limited to the withdrawal value of the state's or the political subdivision's account;</para><para>(ii) The state or the political subdivision has no voting rights in the qualifying mutual financial institution; and</para><para>(iii) The state or the political subdivision has no entitlement to any distribution of assets upon voluntary or involuntary liquidation, dissolution, or winding up of the affairs of the qualifying mutual financial institution.</para><para>(b) To the extent any deposit in any bank is:</para><para>(i) Required to be subject to check or draft, then such deposit may be subject to order; and</para><para>(ii) Required to be made, maintained, or otherwise dealt with by reference to the capital of any bank, then it may be so made, maintained, or dealt with by reference to the capital or net worth of such qualifying mutual financial institution, and if by reference to the undivided profits, capital notes, debentures, or other capital items of any bank, then to any unimpaired reserves, capital notes, and debentures or comparable capital items of such qualifying mutual financial institution.</para><para>(2) To the extent the state or a political subdivision is or may ever be required by law to deposit funds in a bank, the state or political subdivision shall, to the same extent and subject to the same terms, conditions, and limitations, including collateralization required, be required to make deposits in a qualifying mutual financial institution on the same basis.</para><para>(3) The restriction in subdivision (1)(a)(iii) of this section shall not apply to the interest of the state or political subdivision in any security required by law to be furnished by the qualifying mutual financial institution.</para><para>(4) A qualifying mutual financial institution that amends its charter or bylaws in such a manner that it no longer meets the restrictions set forth in subdivisions (1)(a)(i) through (iii) of this section shall immediately give notice that it is no longer a qualifying mutual financial institution to the custodial official, as that term is defined in section 77-2387, of every state and political subdivision depositor, and that the state or political subdivision must immediately withdraw its deposits.</para><para>(5) This section shall be applied in a manner consistent with the intention of the Legislature which is to provide for the deposit of funds of the state or any political subdivision in qualifying mutual financial institutions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 175, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 48. </para></source></law></legaldoc>