<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2703.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2703.03</statuteno><catchline>Direct mail sourcing.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding section 77-2703.01, a purchaser of direct mail that is not a holder of a direct payment permit shall provide to the seller in conjunction with the purchase either a direct mail form or information to show the jurisdictions to which the direct mail is delivered to recipients.</para><para>(2) Upon receipt of the direct mail form, the seller is relieved of all obligations to collect, pay, or remit the applicable tax and the purchaser is obligated to pay or remit the applicable tax on a direct-pay basis. A direct mail form shall remain in effect for all future sales of direct mail by the seller to the purchaser until it is revoked in writing.</para><para>(3) Upon receipt of information from the purchaser showing the jurisdictions to which the direct mail is delivered to recipients, the seller shall collect the tax according to the delivery information provided by the purchaser. In the absence of bad faith, the seller is relieved of any further obligation to collect tax on any transaction where the seller has collected tax pursuant to the delivery information provided by the purchaser.</para><para>(4) If the purchaser of direct mail does not have a direct payment permit and does not provide the seller with either a direct mail form or delivery information as required by subsection (1) of this section, the seller shall collect the tax according to subsection (6) of section 77-2703.01. Nothing in this subsection shall limit a purchaser's obligation for sales or use tax to any state to which the direct mail is delivered.</para><para>(5) If a purchaser of direct mail provides the seller with documentation of direct-pay authority, the purchaser shall not be required to provide a direct mail form or delivery information to the seller.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 51. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 