<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id00" statutenumber="77-2018.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2018.02</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Inheritance tax; independent proceeding for determination in absence of probate of estate; petition; notice; waiver of notice; notice to Department of Health and Human Services.</catchline><para>(1) In the absence of any proceeding brought under Chapter 30, article 24 or 25, in this state, an independent proceeding for the sole purpose of determining the tax may be instituted in the county court of the county where the property or any part thereof which might be subject to tax is situated.</para><para>(2) Upon the filing of a petition to initiate such an independent proceeding, the county court shall order the petition set for hearing, not less than two nor more than four weeks after the date of filing the petition, and shall cause notice thereof to be given to all persons interested in the estate of the deceased and the property described in the petition, except as provided in subsections (4) and (5) of this section, in the manner provided for in subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3) The notice, provided for by subsection (2) of this section, shall be given by one publication in a legal newspaper of the county or, in the absence of such legal newspaper, then in a legal newspaper of some adjoining county of general circulation in the county. In addition to such publication of notice, personal service of notice of the hearing shall be had upon the county attorney of each county in which the property described in the petition is located, at least one week prior to the hearing.</para><para>(4) If it appears to the county court, upon the filing of the petition, by any person other than the county attorney, that no assessment of inheritance tax could result, it shall forthwith enter thereon an order directing the county attorney to show cause, within one week from the service thereof, why determination should not be made that no inheritance tax is due on account of the property described in the petition and the potential lien thereof on such property extinguished. Upon service of such order to show cause and failure of such showing by the county attorney, notice of such hearing by publication shall be dispensed with, and the petitioner shall be entitled without delay to a determination of no tax due on account of the property described in the petition, and any potential lien shall be extinguished.</para><para>(5) If it appears to the county court that (a) the county attorney of each county in which the property described in the petition is located has executed a waiver of notice upon him or her to show cause, or of the time and place of hearing, and has entered a voluntary appearance in such proceeding in behalf of the county and the State of Nebraska, and (b) either (i) all persons against whom an inheritance tax may be assessed are either a petitioner or have executed a waiver of notice upon them to show cause, or of the time and place of hearing, and have entered a voluntary appearance, or (ii) a party to the proceeding has agreed to pay to the proper counties the full inheritance tax so determined, the court may dispense with the notice provided for in subsections (2) and (3) of this section and proceed without delay to make a determination of inheritance tax, if any, due on account of the property described in the petition.</para><para>(6) If a petition is filed to initiate an independent proceeding under this section and the decedent was fifty-five years of age or older or resided in a medical institution as defined in subsection (1) of section 68-919, notice of the filing of such petition shall be provided to the Department of Health and Human Services with the decedent's social security number and, if the decedent was predeceased by a spouse, the name and social security number of such spouse. A certificate of the providing of the notice to the department shall be filed in the independent proceeding by an attorney for the petitioner or, if there is no attorney, by the petitioner, prior to the entry of an order pursuant to this section. The notice shall be provided to the department in a delivery manner and at an address designated by the department, which manner may include email. The department shall post the acceptable manner of delivering notice on its website. Any notice that fails to conform with such manner is void.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 282, &#167; 8, p. 917; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 375, &#167; 1, p. 1314; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 682, &#167; 1, p. 2609; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 481, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 585, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 456, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB72, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB268, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB315, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB593, &#167; 10. </para></source><annotation><para>Although subsection (5) of this section states that the court may dispense with the notice required under subsections (2) and (3), the court is ultimately responsible for determining the inheritance tax. In re Estate of Chambers, 27 Neb. App. 398, 932 N.W.2d 343 (2019).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>