  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2730"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2730</statuteno><catchline>Individual; resident estate or trust; income derived from another state; credit.</catchline><para>(1) A resident individual and a resident estate or trust shall be allowed a credit against the income tax otherwise due for the amount of any income tax imposed on him or her for each taxable year commencing on or after January 1, 1983, by another state of the United States or a political subdivision thereof or the District of Columbia on income derived from sources therein and which is also subject to income tax under sections 77-2714 to 77-27,123.</para><para>(2) The credit provided under sections 77-2714 to 77-27,135 shall not exceed the proportion of the income tax otherwise due under such sections that the amount of the taxpayer's adjusted gross income or total income derived from sources in the other taxing jurisdiction bears to federal adjusted gross income or total federal income.</para><para>(3) For purposes of subsection (1) of this section, a resident individual, estate, or trust shall be deemed to have paid a portion of the income tax imposed by another state, a political subdivision thereof, or the District of Columbia on the income of any partnership, trust, or estate when such resident individual, estate, or trust is a partner, or beneficiary and (a) the income taxed is included in the federal taxable income of the resident individual, estate, or trust and (b) the taxation of such partnership, trust, or estate by the other state is inconsistent with the taxation of such entity under the Internal Revenue Code. The amount of income tax deemed paid by the resident individual, estate, or trust shall be the same percentage of the total tax paid by the entity as the income included in federal taxable income of the resident is to the total taxable income of the entity as computed for the other state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 30, p. 1584; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 526, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 6, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 773, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 505; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 90. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 