<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,131"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,131</statuteno><catchline>Tax Commissioner; security required; when; sale of security; notice.</catchline><para>(1) Unless otherwise specifically provided, the Tax Commissioner, whenever he or she deems it necessary to insure compliance with the provisions of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, may require any person subject to the act to place with him or her such security as he or she may determine. The amount of the necessary security shall be fixed by the Tax Commissioner but, except as provided in this section, shall not be greater than three times the estimated average amount payable for the reporting period by such persons pursuant to the act. In the case of persons habitually delinquent in their obligations under the act, the amount of the security shall not be greater than five times the estimated average amount payable for the reporting period by such persons pursuant to the act. The amount of the security may be increased or decreased by the Tax Commissioner at any time, subject to the limitations set forth in this subsection.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner may sell the security at public auction or, in the case of security in the form of bearer bonds issued by the United States or this state which have a prevailing market price, at a private sale at a price not lower than the prevailing market price if it becomes necessary to make such sale in order to recover any tax, interest, or penalties due on any amount required to be collected. Notice of the sale shall be given to the person who deposited the security at least ten days before the sale. The notice may be given personally or by mail addressed to the person at the address furnished to the Tax Commissioner and as it appears in the records of the Tax Commissioner. Upon such sale, any surplus above the amounts due shall be returned to the person who placed the security.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 131, p. 1636; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 773, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 15.</para></source></law></legaldoc>