<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id74">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id76" statutenumber="77-2708">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2708</statuteno><catchline id="id79">Sales and use
tax; returns; date due; failure to file; penalty; deduction; amount; claim
for refund; allowance; disallowance; proceedings.</catchline><para>(1)(a)
The sales and use taxes imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 shall
be due and payable to the Tax Commissioner monthly on or before the twentieth
day of the month next succeeding each monthly period unless otherwise provided
pursuant to the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967.</para>
<para>(b)(i) On or before the twentieth day of the month following
each monthly period or such other period as the Tax Commissioner may require,
a return for such period, along with all taxes due, shall be filed with the
Tax Commissioner in such form and content as the Tax Commissioner may prescribe
and containing such information as the Tax Commissioner deems necessary for
the proper administration of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. The Tax Commissioner,
if he or she deems it necessary in order to insure payment to or facilitate
the collection by the state of the amount of sales or use taxes due, may require
returns and payment of the amount of such taxes for periods other than monthly
periods in the case of a particular seller, retailer, or purchaser, as the
case may be. The Tax Commissioner shall by rule and regulation require reports
and tax payments from sellers, retailers, or purchasers depending on their
yearly tax liability. Except as required by the streamlined sales and use
tax agreement, annual returns shall be required if such sellers', retailers',
or purchasers' yearly tax liability is less than nine hundred dollars, quarterly
returns shall be required if their yearly tax liability is nine hundred dollars
or more and less than three thousand dollars, and monthly returns shall be
required if their yearly tax liability is three thousand dollars or more.
The Tax Commissioner shall have the discretion to allow an annual return for
seasonal retailers, even when their yearly tax liability exceeds the amounts
listed in this subdivision.</para>
<para>The Tax Commissioner may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
to allow annual, semiannual, or quarterly returns for any retailer making
monthly remittances or payments of sales and use taxes by electronic funds
transfer or for any retailer remitting tax to the state pursuant to the streamlined
sales and use tax agreement. Such rules and regulations may establish a method
of determining the amount of the payment that will result in substantially
all of the tax liability being paid each quarter. At least once each year,
the difference between the amount paid and the amount due shall be reconciled.
If the difference is more than ten percent of the amount paid, a penalty of
fifty percent of the unpaid amount shall be imposed.</para>
<para>(ii) For purposes of the sales tax, a return shall be filed
by every retailer liable for collection from a purchaser and payment to the
state of the tax, except that a combined sales tax return may be filed for
all licensed locations which are subject to common ownership. For purposes
of this subdivision, common ownership means the same person or persons own
eighty percent or more of each licensed location. For purposes of the use
tax, a return shall be filed by every retailer engaged in business in this
state and by every person who has purchased property, the storage, use, or
other consumption of which is subject to the use tax, but who has not paid
the use tax due to a retailer required to collect the tax.</para>
<para>(iii) The Tax Commissioner may require that returns be signed
by the person required to file the return or by his or her duly authorized
agent but need not be verified by oath.</para>
<para>(iv) A taxpayer who keeps his or her regular books and records
on a cash basis, an accrual basis, or any generally recognized accounting
basis which correctly reflects the operation of the business may file the
sales and use tax returns required by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 on
the same accounting basis that is used for the regular books and records,
except that on credit, conditional, and installment sales, the retailer who
keeps his or her books on an accrual basis may report such sales on the cash
basis and pay the tax upon the collections made during each month. If a taxpayer
transfers, sells, assigns, or otherwise disposes of an account receivable,
he or she shall be deemed to have received the full balance of the consideration
for the original sale and shall be liable for the remittance of the sales
tax on the balance of the total sale price not previously reported, except
that such transfer, sale, assignment, or other disposition of an account receivable
by a retailer to a subsidiary shall not be deemed to require the retailer
to pay the sales tax on the credit sale represented by the account transferred
prior to the time the customer makes payment on such account. If the subsidiary
does not obtain a Nebraska sales tax permit, the taxpayer shall obtain a surety
bond in favor of the State of Nebraska to insure payment of the tax and any
interest and penalty imposed thereon under this section in an amount not less
than two times the amount of tax payable on outstanding accounts receivable
held by the subsidiary as of the end of the prior calendar year. Failure to
obtain either a sales tax permit or a surety bond in accordance with this
section shall result in the payment on the next required filing date of all
sales taxes not previously remitted. When the retailer has adopted one basis
or the other of reporting credit, conditional, or installment sales and paying
the tax thereon, he or she will not be permitted to change from that basis
without first having notified the Tax Commissioner.</para>
<para>(c) Except as provided in the streamlined sales and use tax
agreement, the taxpayer required to file the return shall deliver or mail
any required return together with a remittance of the net amount of the tax
due to the office of the Tax Commissioner on or before the required filing
date. Failure to file the return, filing after the required filing date, failure
to remit the net amount of the tax due, or remitting the net amount of the
tax due after the required filing date shall be cause for a penalty, in addition
to interest, of ten percent of the amount of tax not paid by the required
filing date or twenty-five dollars, whichever is greater, unless the penalty
is being collected under subdivision (1)(i), (1)(j)(i), or (l)(k)(i) of section 77-2703 by a county
treasurer or the Department of Motor Vehicles, in which case the penalty shall
be five dollars.</para>
<para>(d) The taxpayer shall deduct and withhold, from the taxes
otherwise due from him or her on his or her tax return, two and one-half percent
of the first three thousand dollars remitted each month to reimburse himself
or herself for the cost of collecting the tax. Taxpayers filing a combined
return as allowed by subdivision (1)(b)(ii) of this subsection shall compute
such collection fees on the basis of the receipts and liability of each licensed
location.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If the Tax Commissioner determines that any sales or
use tax amount, penalty, or interest has been paid more than once, has been
erroneously or illegally collected or computed, or has been paid and the purchaser
qualifies for a refund under section 77-2708.01, the Tax Commissioner shall
set forth that fact in his or her records and the excess amount collected
or paid may be credited on any sales, use, or income tax amounts then due
and payable from the person under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. Any balance
may be refunded to the person by whom it was paid or his or her successors,
administrators, or executors.</para>
<para>(b) No refund shall be allowed unless a claim therefor is
filed with the Tax Commissioner by the person who made the overpayment or
his or her attorney, executor, or administrator within three years from the
required filing date following the close of the period for which the overpayment
was made, within six months after any determination becomes final under section
77-2709, or within six months from the date of overpayment with respect to
such determinations, whichever of these three periods expires later, unless
the credit relates to a period for which a waiver has been given. Failure
to file a claim within the time prescribed in this subsection shall constitute
a waiver of any demand against the state on account of overpayment.</para>
<para>(c) Every claim shall be in writing on forms prescribed by
the Tax Commissioner and shall state the specific amount and grounds upon
which the claim is founded. No refund shall be made in any amount less than
two dollars.</para>
<para>(d) The Tax Commissioner shall allow or disallow a claim within
one hundred eighty days after it has been filed. A request for a hearing shall
constitute a waiver of the one-hundred-eighty-day period. The claimant and
the Tax Commissioner may also agree to extend the one-hundred-eighty-day period.
If a hearing has not been requested and the Tax Commissioner has neither allowed
nor disallowed a claim within either the one hundred eighty days or the period
agreed to by the claimant and the Tax Commissioner, the claim shall be deemed
to have been allowed.</para>
<para>(e) Within thirty days after disallowing any claim in whole
or in part, the Tax Commissioner shall serve notice of his or her action on
the claimant in the manner prescribed for service of notice of a deficiency
determination.</para>
<para>(f) Within thirty days after the mailing of the notice of
the Tax Commissioner's action upon a claim filed pursuant to the Nebraska
Revenue Act of 1967, the action of the Tax Commissioner shall be final unless
the taxpayer seeks review of the Tax Commissioner's determination as provided
in section 77-27,127.</para>
<para>(g) Upon the allowance of a credit or refund of any sum erroneously
or illegally assessed or collected, of any penalty collected without authority,
or of any sum which was excessive or in any manner wrongfully collected, interest
shall be allowed and paid on the amount of such credit or refund at the rate
specified in section 45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted,
from the date such sum was paid or from the date the return was required to
be filed, whichever date is later, to the date of the allowance of the refund
or, in the case of a credit, to the due date of the amount against which the
credit is allowed, but in the case of a voluntary and unrequested payment
in excess of actual tax liability or a refund under section 77-2708.01, no
interest shall be allowed when such excess is refunded or credited.</para>
<para>(h) No suit or proceeding shall be maintained in any court
for the recovery of any amount alleged to have been erroneously or illegally
determined or collected unless a claim for refund or credit has been duly
filed.</para>
<para>(i) The Tax Commissioner may recover any refund or part thereof
which is erroneously made and any credit or part thereof which is erroneously
allowed by issuing a deficiency determination within one year from the date
of refund or credit or within the period otherwise allowed for issuing a deficiency
determination, whichever expires later.</para>
<para>(j)(i) Credit shall be allowed to the retailer, contractor,
or repairperson for sales or use taxes paid pursuant to the Nebraska Revenue
Act of 1967 on any deduction taken that is attributed to bad debts not including
interest. Bad debt has the same meaning as in 26 U.S.C. 166, as such section
existed on January 1, 2003. However, the amount calculated pursuant to 26
U.S.C. 166 shall be adjusted to exclude: Financing charges or interest; sales
or use taxes charged on the purchase price; uncollectible amounts on property
that remains in the possession of the seller until the full purchase price
is paid; and expenses incurred in attempting to collect any debt and repossessed
property.</para>
<para>(ii) Bad debts may be deducted on the return for the period
during which the bad debt is written off as uncollectible in the claimant's
books and records and is eligible to be deducted for federal income tax purposes.
A claimant who is not required to file federal income tax returns may deduct
a bad debt on a return filed for the period in which the bad debt is written
off as uncollectible in the claimant's books and records and would be eligible
for a bad debt deduction for federal income tax purposes if the claimant was
required to file a federal income tax return.</para>
<para>(iii) If a deduction is taken for a bad debt and the debt
is subsequently collected in whole or in part, the tax on the amount so collected
must be paid and reported on the return filed for the period in which the
collection is made.</para>
<para>(iv) When the amount of bad debt exceeds the amount of taxable
sales for the period during which the bad debt is written off, a refund claim
may be filed within the otherwise applicable statute of limitations for refund
claims. The statute of limitations shall be measured from the due date of
the return on which the bad debt could first be claimed.</para>
<para>(v) If filing responsibilities have been assumed by a certified
service provider, the service provider may claim, on behalf of the retailer,
any bad debt allowance provided by this section. The certified service provider
shall credit or refund the full amount of any bad debt allowance or refund
received to the retailer.</para>
<para>(vi) For purposes of reporting a payment received on a previously
claimed bad debt, any payments made on a debt or account are applied first
proportionally to the taxable price of the property or service and the sales
tax thereon, and secondly to interest, service charges, and any other charges.</para>
<para>(vii) In situations in which the books and records of the
party claiming the bad debt allowance support an allocation of the bad debts
among the member states in the streamlined sales and use tax agreement, the
state shall permit the allocation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 8, p. 1558; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 490, &#167; 5, p. 1665; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 683, &#167; 5, p. 2635; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 996, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 179, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 167, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1982, Spec. Sess., LB 2, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 101, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 571, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 758, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 715, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 775, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1234, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 829, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 183; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 156; </para><para>Laws 1992, Fourth Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 128, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 9, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 118, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1041, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 32, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 71; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB916, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB210, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB801, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB814, &#167; 10.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2014</operativedate></source><annotation><para>A late filing cannot be excused on equitable grounds where the claim was time barred because it was filed beyond the limitations period specified in subsection (2)(b) of this section, as extended by agreement of the parties. Becton, Dickinson &amp; Co. v. Nebraska Dept. of Rev., 276 Neb. 640, 756 N.W.2d 280 (2008).
</para><para>The sales and use tax return contains instructions stating that the entries for each tax remain separate and that the failure to enter "a word, statement, number or figure . . . in the appropriate lines on the return" extends the statute of limitations to 5 years. Where no such entries were made, the department was not given adequate information from which to compute the consumer's use tax owed and the 5-year statute of limitations controls. McDonald's Exec. Off. v. Nebraska Dept. of Revenue, 243 Neb. 82, 497 N.W.2d 377 (1993).</para><para>Use tax is payable only once. Omaha P. P. Dist. v. Nebraska State Tax Commissioner, 210 Neb. 309, 314 N.W.2d 246 (1982).</para><para>This section provides for credit of any sales or use tax erroneously or illegally collected or computed. Anderson v. Tiemann, 182 Neb. 393, 155 N.W.2d 322 (1967).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>