<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,241"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,241</statuteno><catchline>Food bank, food pantry, or food rescue donation; credit; eligibility; application; approval; annual limit; tax credit certification.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Agricultural producer means an individual or entity whose income is primarily attributable to crop or livestock production in the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(b) Department means the Department of Revenue;</para><para>(c) Food bank means an organization in this state that:</para><para>(i) Is exempt from federal income taxation under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended; and</para><para>(ii) Distributes food in ten or more counties in Nebraska and qualifies for the Emergency Food Assistance Program administered by the United States Department of Agriculture;</para><para>(d) Food pantry means an organization in this state that:</para><para>(i) Is exempt from federal income taxation under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended; and</para><para>(ii) Distributes emergency food supplies to low-income individuals in this state who would otherwise not have access to such food supplies;</para><para>(e) Food rescue means an organization in this state that:</para><para>(i) Is exempt from federal income taxation under section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended; and</para><para>(ii) Accepts donations of food and delivers such food to food banks or food pantries so that such food may be distributed to low-income individuals in this state;</para><para>(f) Grocery store retailer means a retailer located in this state that is primarily engaged in business activities classified as code 445110 under the North American Industry Classification System;</para><para>(g) Qualifying agricultural food donation means a donation made by an agricultural producer to a food bank, food pantry, or food rescue of fresh or frozen fruits, vegetables, eggs, dairy products, or meat products grown or produced in the State of Nebraska which meets all applicable quality and labeling standards, along with any other applicable requirements of the food bank, food pantry, or food rescue to which the qualifying agricultural food donation is made; and</para><para>(h) Restaurant means a business located in this state that is primarily engaged in business activities classified as code 722511, 722513, 722514, or 722515 under the North American Industry Classification System.</para><para>(2) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2025, and before January 1, 2026, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, a credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 shall be allowed to:</para><para>(a) Any grocery store retailer or restaurant that donates food to a food bank, food pantry, or food rescue during the taxable year; and</para><para>(b) Any agricultural producer that makes a qualifying agricultural food donation to a food bank, food pantry, or food rescue during the taxable year.</para><para>(3) Subject to subsection (7) of this section, the credit provided in this section shall be a nonrefundable credit in an amount equal to fifty percent of the value of the food donations or qualifying agricultural food donations made during the taxable year, not to exceed two thousand five hundred dollars. Any amount of the credit that the taxpayer is prohibited from claiming in a taxable year may be carried forward to any of the three subsequent taxable years.</para><para>(4) For purposes of this section, food donated by a grocery store retailer or restaurant shall be valued at its wholesale value. A qualifying agricultural food donation shall be valued at the prevailing market value of the product at the time of donation, plus the direct cost incurred by the agricultural producer for processing the product.</para><para>(5) To receive a credit under this section, a taxpayer shall submit an application to the department in a form and manner prescribed by the department. The application shall include the amount of food donated during the taxable year and any other information required by the department.</para><para>(6) If the department determines that an application is complete and that the taxpayer qualifies for credits, the department shall approve the application within the limits set forth in this section and shall certify the amount of credits approved to the taxpayer.</para><para>(7) The department may approve up to five hundred thousand dollars of credits in fiscal year 2025-26. Once credits have reached the annual limit for any fiscal year, no additional credits shall be allowed for such fiscal year. Credits shall be prorated among the credit requests received on the day the annual limit is exceeded.</para><para>(8) A taxpayer shall claim the credit by attaching the tax credit certification received from the department under subsection (6) of this section to the taxpayer's tax return.</para><para>(9) Any amount relating to such food donations or qualifying agricultural food donations that was deducted as a charitable contribution on the taxpayer's federal income tax return must be added back in the determination of Nebraska taxable income before the credit provided in this section may be claimed.</para><para>(10) No credit granted under this section shall be transferred, sold, or assigned. No taxpayer shall be eligible to receive a credit under this section if such taxpayer employs persons who are not authorized to work in the United States under federal law. No taxpayer shall be able to claim more than one credit under this section for a single donation.</para><para>(11) A food bank, food pantry, or food rescue may accept or reject any food donated under this section for any reason. Any food that is rejected shall not qualify for a credit under this section.</para><para>(12) The department may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to carry out this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB727, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB937, &#167; 79; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB208, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB650, &#167; 45. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB208, section 6, with LB650, section 45, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB208 became effective September 3, 2025. Changes made by LB650 became operative May 7, 2025.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>