<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id32">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id34" statutenumber="77-27,139.03"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,139.03</statuteno><catchline id="id37">Aid to municipalities;
calculation of state aid.</catchline><para>(1) State aid provided
to municipalities pursuant to sections 77-27,139.01 to 77-27,139.04 shall
be calculated by determining the average property tax levy for operational
purposes other than for principal and interest payments on the indebtedness
of all incorporated municipalities. The Auditor of Public Accounts shall provide
to the Department of Revenue a list of the bond and nonbond tax request amounts
from the most recent budgets filed by incorporated municipalities. The information
shall be used to calculate the bond and nonbond tax levies for aid purposes
under this section. The auditor shall provide the information to the department
by February 1 each year.</para>
<para>(2) Each municipality shall receive state aid from the Municipal
Equalization Fund equal to (a) the product of the average per capita property
tax of the appropriate population group multiplied by the current population
of the municipality minus (b) the product of the average property tax levy
multiplied by the certified valuation within the incorporated municipality,
except that a municipality shall not receive any aid under this section if
the calculation results in a negative number.</para>
<para>(3) If a municipal tax levy for operational purposes was less
than the average property tax levy in the immediately preceding fiscal year,
the state aid provided to such municipality shall be reduced by twenty percent
for each one-cent increment the levy was below the average property tax levy but the reduction shall not exceed eighty
percent.</para>
<para>(4) If the amount of money in the Municipal Equalization Fund
is less than the total amount of state aid for all municipalities as required
by the allocation formula in subsection (2) of this section, the money in
the fund shall be allocated on a prorated basis to such municipalities. If
the amount of money in the fund is more than the total amount of state aid
for municipalities as required by the allocation formula, the excess money
in the fund shall be credited to the General Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1177, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 989, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 141, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 72; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 622, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB383, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1114, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>