<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id507">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id509" statutenumber="77-27,150"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,150</statuteno><catchline id="id512">Refund; application;
when; contents; hearing; approval.</catchline><para>(1) An application
for a refund of Nebraska sales and use taxes paid for any air or water pollution
control facility may be filed with the Tax Commissioner by the owner of such
facility in such manner and in such form as may be prescribed by the commissioner.
The application for a refund shall contain: (a) Plans and specifications of
such facility including all materials incorporated therein; (b) a descriptive
list of all equipment acquired by the applicant for the purpose of industrial
or agricultural waste pollution control; (c) the proposed operating procedure
for the facility; (d) the acquisition cost of the facility for which a refund
is claimed; and (e) a copy of the final findings of the Department of Environmental
Quality issued pursuant to section 77-27,151.</para>
<para>(2) The Tax Commissioner shall offer an applicant a hearing
upon request of such applicant. The hearing shall not affect the authority
of the Department of Environmental Quality to determine whether or not industrial
or agricultural waste pollution control exists within the meaning of the Air
and Water Pollution Control Tax Refund Act.</para>
<para>(3) A claim for refund received without a copy of the final
findings of the Department of Environmental Quality issued pursuant to section
77-27,151 shall not be considered a valid claim and shall be returned to the
applicant.</para>
<para>(4) Notice of the Tax Commissioner's refusal to issue a refund
shall be mailed to
the applicant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 716, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 820, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 308, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 244, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 45.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>