
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2727"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2727</statuteno><catchline>Income tax; partnership; subject
to act; credit.</catchline><para>(1) A partnership as such shall not be subject
to the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. Persons or
their authorized representatives carrying on business as partners shall be
liable for the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 only
in their separate or individual capacities.</para>
<para>(2) The partners of such partnership who are residents of this state
or corporations shall include in their incomes their proportionate share of
such partnership's income.</para>
<para>(3) If any partner of such partnership is a nonresident individual during
any part of the partnership's reporting year, he or she shall file a Nebraska
income tax return which shall include in Nebraska adjusted gross income that
portion of the partnership's Nebraska income, as determined under the provisions
of sections 77-2728 and 77-2729, allocable to his or her interest in the partnership
and shall execute and forward to the partnership, on or before the original
due date of the Nebraska partnership return, an agreement which states that
he or she will file a Nebraska income tax return and pay income tax on all
income derived from or attributable to sources in this state, and such agreement
shall be attached to the partnership's Nebraska return for such reporting
year.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Except as provided in subdivision (c) of this subsection, in
the absence of the nonresident individual partner's executed agreement being
attached to the Nebraska partnership return, the partnership shall remit a
portion of such partner's income which was derived from or attributable to
Nebraska sources with its Nebraska return for the reporting year. For tax years beginning or deemed to begin before January
1, 2013, the amount of remittance, in such instance, shall be
the highest individual income tax rate determined under section 77-2715.02
multiplied by the nonresident individual partner's share of the partnership
income which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state. For tax years beginning or deemed to
begin on or after January 1, 2013, the amount of remittance, in such instance,
shall be the highest individual income tax rate determined under section 77-2715.03
multiplied by the nonresident individual partner's share of the partnership
income which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state.</para>
<para>(b) Any amount remitted on behalf of any partner shall be allowed as
a credit against the Nebraska income tax liability of the partner.</para>
<para>(c) Subdivision (a) of this subsection does not apply to a publicly
traded partnership as defined by section 7704(b) of the Internal Revenue Code
of 1986, as amended, that is treated as a partnership for the purposes of
the code and that has agreed to file an annual information return with the
Department of Revenue reporting the name, address, taxpayer identification
number, and other information requested by the department of each unit holder
with an income in the state in excess of five hundred dollars.</para>
<para>(5) The Tax Commissioner may allow a nonresident individual partner
to not file a Nebraska income tax return if the nonresident individual partner's
only source of Nebraska income was his or her share of the partnership's income
which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state, the nonresident
did not file an agreement to file a Nebraska income tax return, and the partnership
has remitted the amount required by subsection (4) of this section on behalf
of such nonresident individual partner. The amount remitted shall be retained
in satisfaction of the Nebraska income tax liability of the nonresident individual
partner.</para>
<para>(6) For purposes of this section, any partner that is a grantor trust
of a nonresident shall be disregarded and this section shall apply as though
the nonresident grantor was the partner.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 27, p. 1583; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 531, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 773, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB915, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB970, &#167; 7.</para></source><annotation><para>Only the partners pay income tax and the character of income of the partnership remains the same when accounted for by the partners. Altsuler v. Peters, 190 Neb. 113, 206 N.W.2d 570 (1973).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>