<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2615.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2615.01</statuteno><catchline>Licensees; disciplinary action; procedure; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) In addition to the provisions of sections 77-2615 and 77-2622, for any violation of sections 77-2601 to 77-2622 or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under such sections, the Tax Commissioner may:</para><para>(a) After notice and hearing, suspend or revoke the licenses of any person licensed under sections 28-1420 to 28-1429 or 77-2601 to 77-2622. Notice of hearing shall be given as provided in the Administrative Procedure Act; and</para><para>(b) Impose an administrative penalty not to exceed one thousand dollars for any violation.</para><para>(2) Any person whose license has been so revoked may apply at the expiration of sixty days for a reinstatement of his or her license. The license may be reinstated if it appears to the satisfaction of the Tax Commissioner that the licensee will comply with sections 77-2601 to 77-2622 and the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under such sections.</para><para>(3) No person whose license has been suspended or revoked shall sell cigarettes or permit cigarettes to be sold during the period of suspension or revocation on the premises occupied by him or her. No disciplinary proceeding or action shall be barred or abated by the expiration, transfer, surrender, continuance, renewal, or extension of any license issued under sections 28-1420 to 28-1429 or 77-2601 to 77-2622.</para><para>(4) Any person aggrieved by any decision, order, or finding of the Tax Commissioner may appeal the decision, order, or finding, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 15. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 