<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-23,102"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-23,102</statuteno><catchline>Default; procedure.</catchline> <para>(1) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution experiences an event of default the qualified trustee shall proceed in the following manner: (a) The qualified trustee shall ascertain the aggregate amounts of public money or public funds secured pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-2398 and deposited in the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution which has defaulted, as disclosed by the records of such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution. The qualified trustee shall determine for each custodial official for whom public money or public funds are deposited in the defaulting bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution the accounts and amount of federal deposit insurance or guarantee that is available for each account. It shall then determine for each such custodial official the amount of public money or public funds not insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation and the amount of the deposit guaranty bond or pool of securities pledged, deposited, or in which a security interest has been granted to secure such public money or public funds. Upon completion of this analysis, the qualified trustee shall provide each such custodial official with a statement that reports the amount of public money or public funds deposited by the custodial official in the defaulting bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution, the amount of public money or public funds that may be insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, and the amount of public money or public funds secured by a deposit guaranty bond or secured by a pool of securities pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-2398. Each such custodial official shall verify this information from his or her records within ten business days after receiving the report and information from the qualified trustee; and (b) upon receipt of a verified report from such custodial official and if the defaulting bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution is to be liquidated or if for any other reason the qualified trustee determines that public money or public funds are not likely to be promptly paid upon demand, the qualified trustee shall proceed to enforce the deposit guaranty bond or liquidate the pool of securities held to secure the deposit of public money or public funds and shall repay each custodial official for the public money or public funds not insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation deposited in the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution by the custodial official. In the event that the amount of the deposit guaranty bond or the proceeds of the securities held by the qualified trustee after liquidation is insufficient to cover all public money or public funds not insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation for all custodial officials for whom the qualified trustee serves, the qualified trustee shall pay out to each custodial official available amounts pro rata in accordance with the respective public money or public funds not insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation for each such custodial official.</para> <para>(2) In the event that a federal deposit insurance agency is appointed and acts as a liquidator or receiver of any bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution under state or federal law, those duties under this section that are specified to be performed by the qualified trustee in the event of default may be delegated to and performed by such federal deposit insurance agency.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 34.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>