<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id862"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2706.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2706.02</statuteno><catchline>Construction contractor; buyer-based exemption; appointment of purchasing agent; procedure; failure; client; apply for refund.</catchline><para>(1) This section applies on and after July 1, 2026.</para><para>(2) The appointment of purchasing agents shall be recognized for the purpose of permitting a construction contractor to purchase materials tax free based on the buyer-based exemption of the contractor's client for items that are physically annexed to the structure and which subsequently belong to the client who is eligible for the buyer-based exemption. The appointment of purchasing agents shall be in writing and occur prior to having any buyer-based tax-exempt items annexed to real estate in the construction, improvement, or repair. The contractor who has been appointed as a purchasing agent may purchase the materials tax free or may apply for a refund of or use as a credit against a future use tax liability the tax paid on inventory items annexed to real estate in the construction, improvement, or repair of a project that belongs to the client who is eligible for the buyer-based exemption.</para><para>(3) A client described in subsection (2) of this section which enters into a contract of construction, improvement, or repair with respect to buyer-based tax-exempt items annexed to real estate without first issuing a purchasing agent authorization to a construction contractor prior to such items being annexed to real estate in the project may apply to the Tax Commissioner for a refund of any sales and use tax paid by the contractor on such items physically annexed to real estate in the construction, improvement, or repair.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB727, &#167; 66. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>