<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2701.33"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2701.33</statuteno><catchline>Sale, defined.</catchline><para>Sale means any transfer of title or possession or segregation in contemplation of transfer of title or possession, exchange, barter, lease, or rental, conditional or otherwise, in any manner or by any means, of property for a consideration or the provision of service for a consideration. Sale includes, but is not limited to:</para><para>(1) The producing, fabricating, processing, printing, or imprinting of property for a consideration for consumers who furnish either directly or indirectly the materials used in the producing, fabricating, processing, printing, or imprinting; and</para><para>(2) The renting or furnishing for periods of less than thirty days of any room or rooms, lodgings, or accommodations in any hotel, motel, inn, tourist camp, tourist cabin, or any other place, except a health care facility licensed under the Health Care Facility Licensure Act in which rooms, lodgings, or accommodations are regularly furnished for a consideration or a facility operated by an educational institution established under Chapter 79 or Chapter 85 in which rooms are regularly used to house students for a consideration for periods in excess of thirty days.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 871, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 8, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 150; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1085, &#167; 8; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 77-2702.15; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 37. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 