<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id475" statutenumber="77-2776"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2776</statuteno><catchline id="id478">Income tax; Tax Commissioner; return; examination; failure to file; notice; deficiency; notice.</catchline><para>(1) As soon as practical after an income tax return is filed, the Tax Commissioner shall examine it to determine the correct amount of tax. If the Tax Commissioner finds that the amount of tax shown on the return is less than the correct amount, he or she shall notify the taxpayer of the amount of the deficiency proposed to be assessed. If the Tax Commissioner finds that the tax paid is more than the correct amount, he or she shall credit the overpayment against any taxes due by the taxpayer and refund the difference. The Tax Commissioner shall, upon request, make prompt assessment of taxes due as provided by the laws of the United States for federal income tax purposes.</para><para>(2) If the taxpayer fails to file an income tax return, the Tax Commissioner shall estimate the taxpayer's tax liability from any available information and notify the taxpayer of the amount proposed to be assessed as in the case of a deficiency.</para><para>(3) A notice of deficiency shall set forth the reason for the proposed assessment or for the change in the amount of credit or loss to be carried over to another year. The notice may be mailed to the taxpayer at his or her last-known address. In the case of a joint return, the notice of deficiency may be a single joint notice, except that if the Tax Commissioner is notified by either spouse that separate residences have been established, the Tax Commissioner shall mail joint notices to each spouse. If the taxpayer is deceased or under a legal disability, a notice of deficiency may be mailed to his or her last-known address unless the Tax Commissioner has received notice of the existence of a fiduciary relationship with respect to such taxpayer.</para><para>(4) A notice of deficiency regarding an item of entity income may be mailed to the entity at its last-known address or to the address of the entity's tax matters person for federal income tax purposes. Such notice shall be deemed to have been received by each partner, shareholder, or member of such entity, but only for items of entity income reported by the partner, shareholder, or member. The actions taken thereon on behalf of the partnership, limited liability company, small business corporation, estate, or trust are binding on the partners, members, shareholders, or beneficiaries.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 76, p. 1604; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 24. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>