  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2304</statuteno><catchline>State funds; depositories; form of bond.</catchline><para>Such bond shall be in substance as follows:</para><para>Know all Men by these Presents, That we .......... as principals, and .......... as sureties, are held and firmly bound unto the State of Nebraska, in the just and full sum of .......... Dollars, for the payment of which, well and truly to be made, we bind ourselves, our heirs, executors and our administrators, jointly and severally, by these presents. Dated the .......... day of .................... A.D. .............. .</para><para>Whereas, the said bank, in consideration of the deposit of certain of the money of the State of Nebraska for safekeeping with and in the .......... bank of .......... the amount whereof shall be subject to withdrawal or diminution by the State Treasurer as the requirements of the state shall demand, and which amount may be increased or decreased as the treasurer may determine;</para><para>Now, Therefor, if said ..................... bank of ........................... shall at the end of every month render to the State Treasurer a statement in duplicate showing the daily balance of the state money held by it during the month next preceding, and how the same has been credited, and shall well and truly keep all said sums of money so deposited or to be deposited as aforesaid subject to the check and order of the State Treasurer as aforesaid, and shall pay over the same, and each and every part thereof, upon the written demand of the State Treasurer, and to his successor in office as shall be by him demanded, and shall in all respect save and keep the people of the State of Nebraska, and the State Treasurer harmless and indemnified for and by reason of the making of such deposit or deposits, then this obligation shall be void and of no effect, otherwise to be and remain in full force and virtue.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1891, c. 50, &#167; 3, p. 348; </para><para>Laws 1897, c. 23, &#167; 2, p. 188; </para><para>Laws 1899, c. 74, &#167; 1, p. 321; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 151, &#167; 1, p. 595; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 142, &#167; 1, p. 450; </para><para>Laws 1909, c. 139, &#167; 1, p. 493; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6657; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6188; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 34, &#167; 1, p. 153; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2503; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 135, &#167; 1, p. 376; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 147, &#167; 1, p. 564; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 152, &#167; 2, p. 560; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-2503; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-2304.</para></source></law></legaldoc> 