  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2027"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2027</statuteno><catchline>Inheritance tax; what court has jurisdiction; transfer of proceedings.</catchline><para>The county court in the county in which the real property is situated of a decedent who was not a resident of the state, or in the county of which the deceased was a resident at the time of his death, shall have jurisdiction to hear and determine all questions in relation to all taxes arising under sections 77-2001 to 77-2037. If a court finds that in the interest of justice a proceeding or a file should be located in another county court of this state, the court making the finding may transfer the proceeding or file to the other court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1901, c. 54, &#167; 13, p. 420; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6634; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6165; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2213; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-2027; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 585, &#167; 19. </para></source><annotation><para>County court may determine taxes due upon the clear market value of the beneficial interest taken by the taxpayer. County of Keith v. Triska, 168 Neb. 1, 95 N.W.2d 350 (1959).</para><para>County court has jurisdiction to assess tax on beneficiaries. State ex rel. Nebraska State Bar Assn. v. Richards, 165 Neb. 80, 84 N.W.2d 136 (1957).</para><para>County court has exclusive original jurisdiction over fixing, determining and assessing inheritance taxes. In re Estate of Sautter, 142 Neb. 42, 5 N.W.2d 263 (1942).</para><para>County court, on appeal from order of county judge determining value of estate from appraiser's report, is vested with complete, exclusive jurisdiction in the first instance to determine all questions in relation to inheritance taxes. In re Estate of Piel, 141 Neb. 783, 4 N.W.2d 875 (1942).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 