<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id517">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id519" statutenumber="77-27,152"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,152</statuteno><catchline id="id522">Refund; notice; modify or revoke; when;
effect.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner, after giving
notice by mail
to the applicant and giving an opportunity for a hearing, shall modify or
revoke the refund whenever the following appears: (a) The refund was obtained
by fraud or misrepresentation regarding the payment of tax on materials incorporated
into the facility or facilities; or (b) the Department of Environmental Quality
has modified its findings regarding the facility covered by the refund.</para>
<para>(2) The Department of Environmental Quality may modify its
findings when it determines any of the following: (a) The refund was obtained
by fraud or misrepresentation regarding the facility or planned operation
of the facility; (b) the applicant has failed substantially to operate the
facility for the purpose and degree of control specified in the application
or an amended application; or (c) the facility covered by the refund is no
longer used for the primary purpose of pollution control.</para>
<para>(3) On the mailing to the refund applicant of notice of the action
of the Tax Commissioner modifying or revoking the refund, the refund shall
cease to be in force or shall remain in force only as modified. When a refund
is revoked because a refund was obtained by fraud or misrepresentation, all
taxes which would have been payable if no certificate had been issued shall
be immediately due and payable with the maximum interest and penalties prescribed
by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. No statute of limitations shall operate
in the event of fraud or misrepresentation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 716, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 308, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 3, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 46.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>