<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id45"> <sectno id="id46" opdate="October 1, 2009">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id47" statutenumber="77-2701.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id49">77-2701.03</statuteno><catchline id="id50">Changes; when effective; relief from liability; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) The sales tax rate may only be changed effective at the beginning of a calendar quarter.</para> <para>(2) Any sales tax exemption or repeal of any sales tax exemption shall only be effective at the beginning of a calendar quarter.</para> <para>(3) Any change in sales tax rate or base dealing with a service covering a period of time starting before and ending after the effective date of the change shall be effective as follows: (a) For a rate increase or base expansion, the change shall apply to the first billing period commencing on or after the effective date; and (b) for a rate decrease or base contraction, the change shall apply to bills rendered on or after the effective date.</para> <para>(4) A seller shall be relieved of liability for failing to collect tax at the new effective rate if the state fails to provide a period of at least thirty days between enactment of the statute providing for a rate change and the effective date of such rate change, the seller collected tax at the immediately preceding effective rate, and the seller's failure to collect at the newly effective rate does not extend beyond thirty days after the date of enactment of the new rate.</para><para>(5) Subsection (4) of this section shall not apply if the seller fraudulently failed to collect at the new rate or solicits purchasers based on the immediately preceding effective rate.</para></amendatorysection> </section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB165, &#167; 4.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2009</operativedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>