<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,236" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,236</statuteno><catchline>Biodiesel facility tax credit; conditions; facility; requirements; information not public record.</catchline><para>(1) A taxpayer who makes an investment after January 1, 2008, and prior to January 1, 2015, in a biodiesel facility shall receive a nonrefundable income tax credit as provided in this section.</para><para>(2) The credit provided in subsection (1) of this section shall be equal to thirty percent of the amount invested by the taxpayer in a biodiesel facility. The credit shall be taken over at least four taxable years subject to the following conditions:</para><para>(a) No more than ten percent of the credit provided for in subsection (1) of this section shall be taken in each of the first two taxable years the biodiesel facility produces B100 and no more than fifty percent of the credit provided for in subsection (1) of this section shall be taken in the third taxable year the biodiesel facility produces B100. The credit allowed under subsection (1) of this section shall not exceed fifty percent of the taxpayer's liability in any tax year;</para><para>(b) Any amount of credit not allowed because of the limitations in this section may be carried forward for up to fifteen taxable years after the taxable year in which the investment was made. The aggregate maximum income tax credit a taxpayer may obtain is two hundred fifty thousand dollars;</para><para>(c) The investment shall be at risk in the biodiesel facility. The investment shall be in the form of a purchase of an ownership interest or the right to receive payment of dividends from the biodiesel facility and shall remain in the business for at least three years. The Tax Commissioner may recapture any credits used if the investment does not remain invested for the three-year period. An investment placed in escrow does not qualify under this subdivision;</para><para>(d) The entire amount of the investment shall be expended by the biodiesel facility for plant, equipment, research and development, marketing and sales activity, or working capital;</para><para>(e) A partnership, a subchapter S corporation, a limited liability company that for tax purposes is treated like a partnership, a cooperative, including a cooperative exempt under section 521 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, or any other pass-through entity that invests in a biodiesel facility shall be considered to be the taxpayer for purposes of the credit limitations. Except for the limitation under subdivision (2)(a) of this section, the amount of the credit allowed to a pass-through entity shall be determined at the partnership, corporate, cooperative, or other organizational level. The amount of the credit determined at the partnership, corporate, cooperative, or other organizational level shall be allowed to the partners, members, or other owners in proportion to their respective ownership interests in the pass-through entity;</para><para>(f) The credit shall be taken only if (i) the biodiesel facility produces B100, (ii) the biodiesel facility in which the investment was made produces at a rate of at least seventy percent of its rated capacity continuously for at least one week during the first taxable year the credit is taken and produces at a rate of at least seventy percent of its rated capacity over a six-month period during each of the next two taxable years the credit is taken, (iii) all processing takes place at the biodiesel facility in which the investment was made and which is located in Nebraska, and (iv) at least fifty-one percent of the ownership interest of the biodiesel facility is held by Nebraska resident individuals or Nebraska entities; and</para><para>(g) The biodiesel facility shall provide the Department of Revenue written evidence substantiating that the biodiesel facility has received the requisite authority from the Department of Environment and Energy and from the United States Department of Justice, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives. The biodiesel facility shall annually provide an analysis to the Department of Revenue of samples of the product collected according to procedures specified by the department. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent laboratory meeting standards of the International Organization for Standardization. Prior to collecting the samples, the biodiesel facility shall notify the department which may observe the sampling procedures utilized by the biodiesel facility to obtain the samples to be submitted for independent analysis.</para><para>(3) Any biodiesel facility for which credits are granted shall, whenever possible, employ workers who are residents of the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(4) Trade secrets, academic and scientific research work, and other proprietary or commercial information which may be filed with the Tax Commissioner shall not be considered to be public records as defined in section 84-712.01 if the release of such trade secrets, work, or information would give advantage to business competitors and serve no public purpose. Any person seeking release of the trade secrets, work, or information as a public record shall demonstrate to the satisfaction of the department that the release would not violate this section.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Biodiesel facility means a plant or facility related to the processing, marketing, or distribution of biodiesel; and</para><para>(b) B100 means pure biodiesel containing mono-alkyl esters of long chain fatty acids derived from vegetable oils or animal fats, designated as B100, and meeting the American Society for Testing and Materials standard, ASTM D6751.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB343, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB302, &#167; 102. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>