<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2707"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2707</statuteno><catchline>Sales and use tax; sale of business; liability for tax.</catchline><para>(1) If any person liable for any sales or use tax under the provisions of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 sells out his business or stock of goods or quits the business, his successor or assign shall withhold sufficient of the purchase price to cover such amount until the former owner produces a receipt from the Tax Commissioner showing that it has been paid or a certificate stating that no amount is due.</para><para>(2) If the purchaser of a business or stock of goods fails to withhold a portion of the purchase price as required, he shall become personally liable for the payment of the amount required to be withheld by him to the extent of the purchase price, valued in money. Within sixty days after receiving a written request from the purchaser for a certificate, or within sixty days from the date the former owner's records are made available for audit, whichever period expires the later, the Tax Commissioner shall either issue the certificate or mail notice to the purchaser at his address as it appears on the records of the Tax Commissioner of the amount that must be paid as a condition of issuing the certificate. Failure of the Tax Commissioner to mail the notice shall release the purchaser from any further obligation to withhold a portion of the purchase price as provided in this subsection. The time within which the obligation of the successor may be enforced shall start to run at the time the former owner sells out his business or stock of goods or at the time that the determination against the former owner becomes final, whichever event occurs the later.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 7, p. 1557. </para></source><annotation><para>One found to be a "successor" pursuant to this section would logically be considered the kind of "transferee" denominated "successor" under section 77-27,110. A court's duty is to construe the successor liability statute with a fair, unbiased, and reasonable interpretation, without favor to the taxpayer or the state, to the end that the legislative intent is effectuated and the public interests to be served are thereby furthered. Gottsch Feeding Corp. v. State, 261 Neb. 19, 621 N.W.2d 109 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 