<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id137" statutenumber="77-2717"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2717</statuteno><catchline id="id140">Income tax; estates; trusts; rate; fiduciary return; contents; filing; state income tax; contents; credits.</catchline><para>(1)(a)(i) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin before January 1, 2014, the tax imposed on all resident estates and trusts shall be a percentage of the federal taxable income of such estates and trusts as modified in section 77-2716, plus a percentage of the federal alternative minimum tax and the federal tax on premature or lump-sum distributions from qualified retirement plans. The additional taxes shall be recomputed by (A) substituting Nebraska taxable income for federal taxable income, (B) calculating what the federal alternative minimum tax would be on Nebraska taxable income and adjusting such calculations for any items which are reflected differently in the determination of federal taxable income, and (C) applying Nebraska rates to the result. The federal credit for prior year minimum tax, after the recomputations required by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, and the credits provided in the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act and the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act shall be allowed as a reduction in the income tax due. A refundable income tax credit shall be allowed for all resident estates and trusts under the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act, and the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act. A nonrefundable income tax credit shall be allowed for all resident estates and trusts as provided in the New Markets Job Growth Investment Act.</para><para>(ii) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2014, the tax imposed on all resident estates and trusts shall be a percentage of the federal taxable income of such estates and trusts as modified in section 77-2716, plus a percentage of the federal tax on premature or lump-sum distributions from qualified retirement plans. The additional taxes shall be recomputed by substituting Nebraska taxable income for federal taxable income and applying Nebraska rates to the result. The credits provided in the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act and the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act shall be allowed as a reduction in the income tax due. A refundable income tax credit shall be allowed for all resident estates and trusts under the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act, the Nebraska Higher Blend Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Property Tax Incentive Act, and the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act. A nonrefundable income tax credit shall be allowed for all resident estates and trusts as provided in the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act, the New Markets Job Growth Investment Act, the School Readiness Tax Credit Act, the Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act, and sections 77-27,238 and 77-27,240.</para><para>(b) The tax imposed on all nonresident estates and trusts shall be the portion of the tax imposed on resident estates and trusts which is attributable to the income derived from sources within this state. The tax which is attributable to income derived from sources within this state shall be determined by multiplying the liability to this state for a resident estate or trust with the same total income by a fraction, the numerator of which is the nonresident estate's or trust's Nebraska income as determined by sections 77-2724 and 77-2725 and the denominator of which is its total federal income after first adjusting each by the amounts provided in section 77-2716. The federal credit for prior year minimum tax, after the recomputations required by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, reduced by the percentage of the total income which is attributable to income from sources outside this state, and the credits provided in the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act and the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act shall be allowed as a reduction in the income tax due. A refundable income tax credit shall be allowed for all nonresident estates and trusts under the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act, the Nebraska Higher Blend Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Property Tax Incentive Act, and the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act. A nonrefundable income tax credit shall be allowed for all nonresident estates and trusts as provided in the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act, the New Markets Job Growth Investment Act, the School Readiness Tax Credit Act, the Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act, and sections 77-27,238 and 77-27,240.</para><para>(2) In all instances wherein a fiduciary income tax return is required under the provisions of the Internal Revenue Code, a Nebraska fiduciary return shall be filed, except that a fiduciary return shall not be required to be filed regarding a simple trust if all of the trust's beneficiaries are residents of the State of Nebraska, all of the trust's income is derived from sources in this state, and the trust has no federal tax liability. The fiduciary shall be responsible for making the return for the estate or trust for which he or she acts, whether the income be taxable to the estate or trust or to the beneficiaries thereof. The fiduciary shall include in the return a statement of each beneficiary's distributive share of net income when such income is taxable to such beneficiaries.</para><para>(3) The beneficiaries of such estate or trust who are residents of this state shall include in their income their proportionate share of such estate's or trust's federal income and shall reduce their Nebraska tax liability by their proportionate share of the credits as provided in the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act, the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act, the New Markets Job Growth Investment Act, the School Readiness Tax Credit Act, the Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Higher Blend Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Property Tax Incentive Act, the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act, and sections 77-27,238 and 77-27,240. There shall be allowed to a beneficiary a refundable income tax credit under the Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act for all taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2001, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</para><para>(4) If any beneficiary of such estate or trust is a nonresident during any part of the estate's or trust's taxable year, he or she shall file a Nebraska income tax return which shall include (a) in Nebraska adjusted gross income that portion of the estate's or trust's Nebraska income, as determined under sections 77-2724 and 77-2725, allocable to his or her interest in the estate or trust and (b) a reduction of the Nebraska tax liability by his or her proportionate share of the credits as provided in the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act, the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act, the New Markets Job Growth Investment Act, the School Readiness Tax Credit Act, the Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Higher Blend Tax Credit Act, the Nebraska Property Tax Incentive Act, the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act, and sections 77-27,238 and 77-27,240 and shall execute and forward to the fiduciary, on or before the original due date of the Nebraska fiduciary return, an agreement which states that he or she will file a Nebraska income tax return and pay income tax on all income derived from or connected with sources in this state, and such agreement shall be attached to the Nebraska fiduciary return for such taxable year.</para><para>(5) In the absence of the nonresident beneficiary's executed agreement being attached to the Nebraska fiduciary return, the estate or trust shall remit a portion of such beneficiary's income which was derived from or attributable to Nebraska sources with its Nebraska return for the taxable year. For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin before January 1, 2013, the amount of remittance, in such instance, shall be the highest individual income tax rate determined under section 77-2715.02 multiplied by the nonresident beneficiary's share of the estate or trust income which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state. For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2013, the amount of remittance, in such instance, shall be the highest individual income tax rate determined under section 77-2715.03 multiplied by the nonresident beneficiary's share of the estate or trust income which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state. The amount remitted shall be allowed as a credit against the Nebraska income tax liability of the beneficiary.</para><para>(6) The Tax Commissioner may allow a nonresident beneficiary to not file a Nebraska income tax return if the nonresident beneficiary's only source of Nebraska income was his or her share of the estate's or trust's income which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state, the nonresident did not file an agreement to file a Nebraska income tax return, and the estate or trust has remitted the amount required by subsection (5) of this section on behalf of such nonresident beneficiary. The amount remitted shall be retained in satisfaction of the Nebraska income tax liability of the nonresident beneficiary.</para><para>(7) For purposes of this section, unless the context otherwise requires, simple trust shall mean any trust instrument which (a) requires that all income shall be distributed currently to the beneficiaries, (b) does not allow amounts to be paid, permanently set aside, or used in the tax year for charitable purposes, and (c) does not distribute amounts allocated in the corpus of the trust. Any trust which does not qualify as a simple trust shall be deemed a complex trust.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section, any beneficiary of an estate or trust that is a grantor trust of a nonresident shall be disregarded and this section shall apply as though the nonresident grantor was the beneficiary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 17, p. 1579; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 690, &#167; 1, p. 2683; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 531, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 773, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 977, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1223, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 433, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1003, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB367, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB915, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB389, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB970, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1128, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB308, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB191, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB774, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB884, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB889, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB917, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1261, &#167; 11. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB917, section 4, with LB1261, section 11, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB917 became effective July 21, 2022. Changes made by LB1261 became operative July 21, 2022.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Angel Investment Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6301.</para><para><emphasis>Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5201.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Microenterprise Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Research and Development Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Higher Blend Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-7001.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2901.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Property Tax Incentive Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6701.</para><para><emphasis>New Markets Job Growth Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 77-1101.</para><para><emphasis>Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6601.</para><para><emphasis>School Readiness Tax Credit Act,</emphasis> see section 77-3601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This section and section 77-2715.02, when read together, require the Nebraska Department of Revenue to tax trusts and estates in conformity with the federal tax code. FirsTier Bank v. Department of Revenue, 254 Neb. 918, 580 N.W.2d 537 (1998).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>