<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id00" statutenumber="77-2791"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2791</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Income tax; overpayment; refund; credit; Tax Commissioner; rules and regulations.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner, within the applicable period of limitations, may credit an overpayment of income tax and interest on such overpayment against any liability in respect of any tax imposed by the tax laws of this state on the person who made the overpayment, and the balance shall be refunded by the State Treasurer out of the General Fund.</para><para>(2) If the amount allowable as a credit for income tax withheld from the taxpayer exceeds his or her tax to which the credit relates, the excess shall be considered an overpayment.</para><para>(3) A refundable income tax credit is considered an overpayment even if the taxpayer has no income tax liability prior to applying the refundable credit.</para><para>(4) If there has been an overpayment of tax required to be deducted and withheld under section 77-2753, refund shall be made to the employer or the payor only to the extent that the amount of the overpayment was not deducted and withheld by the employer or the payor.</para><para>(5) The Tax Commissioner may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations providing for the crediting against the estimated income tax for any taxable year of the amount determined to be an overpayment of the income tax for a preceding taxable year.</para><para>(6) If any amount of income tax is assessed or collected after the expiration of the period of limitations properly applicable thereto, such amount shall be considered an overpayment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 91, p. 1613; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 962, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 258, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB776, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2016</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>