<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id109" statutenumber="77-2701.32"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2701.32</statuteno><catchline id="id112">Retailer, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Retailer means any seller.</para><para>(2) To facilitate the proper administration of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the following persons have the duties and responsibilities of sellers for the purposes of sales and use taxes:</para><para>(a) Any person in the business of making sales subject to tax under section 77-2703 at auction of property owned by the person or others;</para><para>(b) Any person collecting the proceeds of the auction, other than the owner of the property, together with his or her principal, if any, when the person collecting the proceeds of the auction is not the auctioneer or an agent or employee of the auctioneer. The seller does not include the auctioneer in such case;</para><para>(c) Every person who has elected to be considered a retailer pursuant to subdivision (1) of section 77-2701.10;</para><para>(d) Every person operating, organizing, or promoting a flea market, craft show, fair, or similar event;</para><para>(e) Every person engaged in the business of providing any service defined in subsection (4) of section 77-2701.16; and</para><para>(f) Every person operating a multivendor marketplace platform that (i) acts as the intermediary by facilitating sales between a seller and the purchaser or that engages directly or indirectly through one or more affiliated persons in transmitting or otherwise communicating the offer or acceptance between the seller and purchaser and (ii) either directly or indirectly through agreements or arrangements with third parties, collects payment from the purchaser and transmits payment to the seller.</para><para>(3) For the proper administration of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the following persons do not have the duties and responsibilities of a seller for purposes of sales and use taxes:</para><para>(a) Any person who leases or rents films when an admission tax is charged under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967;</para><para>(b) Any person who leases or rents railroad rolling stock interchanged pursuant to the provisions of the federal Interstate Commerce Act;</para><para>(c) Any person engaged in the business of furnishing rooms in a facility licensed under the Health Care Facility Licensure Act in which rooms, lodgings, or accommodations are regularly furnished for a consideration or a facility operated by an educational institution established under Chapter 79 or Chapter 85 in which rooms are regularly used to house students for a consideration for periods in excess of thirty days;</para><para>(d) Any person making sales at a flea market, craft show, fair, or similar event when such person does not have a sales tax permit and has arranged to pay sales taxes collected to the person operating, organizing, or promoting such event; or</para><para>(e) Any payment processor appointed by a retailer whose sole activity with regard to a sale or lease transaction is to process the payment made from the customer to the retailer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 871, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 819, &#167; 149; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1085, &#167; 7; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,2002, &#167; 77-2702.14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 759, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB916, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB284, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>April 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Facility Licensure Act,</emphasis> see section 71-401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>