<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2366"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2366</statuteno><catchline>Funds of state or political subdivisions; deposit with capital stock financial institutions; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any local ordinance or regulation, or any rule or regulation to the contrary, the funds of this state or any political subdivision of the state may be deposited, by the appropriate custodians of such funds, with capital stock financial institutions to the same extent and subject to the same terms, conditions, and limitations, including collateralization required, if any, as may be otherwise provided for the deposit of such funds in banks. Capital stock financial institutions shall include state and national banks, capital stock state building and loan associations, capital stock federal savings and loan associations, capital stock federal savings banks, and capital stock state savings banks, which have a main chartered office in this state, any branch thereof in this state, or any branch in this state of a capital stock financial institution which maintained a main chartered office in this state prior to becoming a branch of such capital stock financial institution. To the extent any deposit in any bank is:</para><para>(a) Required to be subject to check or draft, then such deposit may be subject to order; and</para><para>(b) Required to be made, maintained, or otherwise dealt with by reference to the capital of any bank, then it may be so made, maintained, or dealt with by reference to the capital or net worth of such financial institution, and if by reference to the undivided profits, capital notes, debentures, or other capital items of any bank, then to any unimpaired reserves, capital notes, and debentures or comparable capital items of such other financial institution.</para><para>(2) To the extent the state or any political subdivision is or may ever be required by any law to deposit funds in any bank, the state or any such political subdivision shall, to the same extent and subject to the same terms, conditions, and limitations, including collateralization required, be required to make deposits in any capital stock financial institution on the same basis.</para><para>(3) This section shall be applied in a manner consistent with the intention of the Legislature which is to provide for the deposit of funds of the state and any political subdivision in capital stock financial institutions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1988, LB 488, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 757, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 131, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 999, &#167; 49. </para></source></law></legaldoc>