<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-27,143"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,143</statuteno><catchline>Municipalities; sales and use tax
laws; administration; termination; data bases; required.</catchline><para>(1)
The administration of all sales and use taxes adopted under the Local Option
Revenue Act shall be by the Tax Commissioner who may prescribe forms and adopt
and promulgate reasonable rules and regulations in conformity with the act
for the making of returns and for the ascertainment, assessment, and collection
of taxes imposed under such act. The incorporated municipality shall furnish
a certified copy of the adopting or repealing ordinance to the Tax Commissioner
in accordance with such rules and regulations as he or she may adopt and promulgate.
For ordinances passed after October 1, 1969, the effective date shall be the
first day of the next calendar quarter which is at least one hundred twenty
days following receipt by the Tax Commissioner of the certified copy of the
ordinance. The Tax Commissioner shall provide at least sixty days' notice
of the change in tax to retailers. Notice shall be provided to retailers within
the municipality. Notice to retailers may be provided through the web site
of the Department of Revenue or by other electronic means.</para>
<para>(2) For ordinances containing a termination date and passed after October
1, 1986, the termination date shall be the first day of a calendar quarter.
The incorporated municipality shall furnish a certified statement to the Tax
Commissioner no more than one hundred eighty days and at least one hundred
twenty days prior to the termination date that the termination date stated
in the ordinance is still valid. If the certified statement is not furnished
within the prescribed time, the tax shall remain in effect, and the Tax Commissioner
shall continue to collect the tax until the first day of the calendar quarter
which is at least one hundred twenty days after receipt of the certified statement
notwithstanding the termination date stated in the ordinance. The Tax Commissioner
shall provide at least sixty days' notice of the termination of the tax to
retailers. Notice shall be provided to retailers within the municipality.
Notice to retailers may be provided through the web site of the department
or by other electronic means.</para>
<para>(3) For sales and use tax purposes only, local jurisdiction boundary
changes apply only on the first day of a calendar quarter after a minimum
of one hundred twenty days' notice to the Tax Commissioner and sixty days'
notice to sellers.</para>
<para>(4) The state shall provide and maintain a data base that describes
boundary changes for all local taxing jurisdictions. This data base shall
include a description of any change and the effective date of the change for
sales and use tax purposes.</para>
<para>(5) The state shall provide and maintain a data base of all sales and
use tax rates for all of the local jurisdictions levying taxes within the
state. For the identification of counties, cities, and villages, codes corresponding
to the rates shall be provided according to Federal Information Processing
Standards as developed by the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</para>
<para>(6) The state shall provide and maintain a data base that assigns each
five-digit and nine-digit zip code within the state to the proper tax rates
and jurisdictions. For purposes of the streamlined sales and use tax agreement,
the data base shall apply the lowest combined tax rate imposed in the zip
code area if the area includes more than one tax rate in any level of taxing
jurisdictions. If a nine-digit zip code designation is not available for a
street address or if a seller is unable to determine the nine-digit zip code
designation applicable to a purchase after exercising due diligence to determine
the designation, the seller or certified service provider may apply the rate
for the five-digit zip code area. For purposes of this section, there is a
rebuttable presumption that a seller or certified service provider has exercised
due diligence if the seller has attempted to determine the nine-digit zip
code designation by utilizing software approved by the governing board that
makes this designation from the street address and the five-digit zip code
applicable to a purchase.</para>
<para>(7) For purposes of the streamlined sales and use tax agreement, the
state may provide address-based boundary data base records for assigning taxing
jurisdictions and their associated rates which shall be in addition to the
requirements of subsection (6) of this section. The data base records shall
be in the same approved format as the data base records pursuant to subsection
(6) of this section and shall meet the requirements developed pursuant to
the federal Mobile Telecommunications Sourcing Act, 4 U.S.C. 119(a), as such
act existed on January 1, 2003. The governing board may allow a member state
to require sellers that register under the agreement to use an address-based
boundary data base provided by that member state. If any member state develops
an addressed-based boundary data base pursuant to the agreement, a seller
or certified service provider may use those data base records in place of
the five-digit and nine-digit zip code data base records provided for in subsection
(6) of this section. If a seller or certified service provider is unable to
determine the applicable rate and jurisdiction using an address-based boundary
data base after exercising due diligence, the seller or certified service
provider may apply the nine-digit zip code designation applicable to a purchase.
If a nine-digit zip code designation is not available for a street address
or if a seller or certified service provider is unable to determine the nine-digit
zip code designation applicable to a purchase after exercising due diligence
to determine the designation, the seller or certified service provider may
apply the rate for the five-digit zip code area. For the purposes of this
section, there is a rebuttable presumption that a seller or certified service
provider has exercised due diligence if the seller or certified service provider
has attempted to determine the tax rate and jurisdiction by utilizing software
approved by the governing board that makes this assignment from the address
and zip code information applicable to the purchase.</para>
<para>(8) The state may certify vendor-provided address-based boundary data
bases for assigning tax rates and jurisdictions. The data bases shall be in
the same approved format as the data base records pursuant to subsection (7)
of this section and shall meet the requirements developed pursuant to the
federal Mobile Telecommunications Sourcing Act, 4 U.S.C. 119(a) as such act
existed on January 1, 2003. If a state certifies a vendor-provided address-based
boundary data base, a seller or certified service provider may use that data
base in place of the data base provided for in subsection (6) or (7) of this
section. Vendors providing address-based boundary data bases may request certification
of their data bases from the governing board. Certification by the governing
board does not replace the requirement that the data bases be certified by
the states individually.</para>
<para>(9) Pursuant to the streamlined sales and use tax agreement, the state
shall relieve retailers and certified service providers using data bases pursuant
to subsection (6) or (7) of this section from liability to the state and local
jurisdictions for having charged and collected the incorrect amount of sales
or use tax resulting from the retailer or certified service provider relying
on erroneous data provided by a member state on tax rates, boundaries, or
taxing jurisdiction assignments. After providing adequate notice determined
by the governing board, a member state that provides an address-based boundary
data base for assigning taxing jurisdictions pursuant to subsection (7) or
(8) of this section may cease providing liability relief for errors resulting
from the reliance on the data base provided by the member state under the
provisions of subsection (6) of this section. If a seller demonstrates that
requiring the use of the address-based boundary data base would create an
undue hardship, the state and the governing board may extend the relief of
liability to such seller for a designated period of time.</para>
<para>(10) The data bases provided for in this section shall be in a downloadable
format approved by the governing board pursuant to the streamlined sales and
use tax agreement. The data bases may be directly provided by the state or
provided by a vendor as designated by the state. A data base provided by a
vendor as designated by a state shall be applicable to and subject to all
provisions of this section. The data bases shall be provided at no cost to
the user of the data base. The provisions of subsections (6) and (7) of this
section do not apply when the purchased product is received by the purchaser
at the business location of the seller.</para>
<para>(11) A seller that did not
have a requirement to register in this state prior to registering pursuant
to the agreement or a certified service provider shall not be required to
collect sales or use taxes for a state until the first day of the calendar
quarter commencing more than sixty days after the state has provided the data
bases required by this section.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 629, &#167; 2, p. 2530; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 683, &#167; 8, p. 2644; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 890, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 81; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 381, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 277; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 887, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB211, &#167; 7.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2011</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Where the city of Omaha's ordinance of annexation did not contain a certified map clearly defining the annexed area, the municipality failed to sufficiently comply with the Tax Commissioner's regulations to enforce collection of city sales taxes within the newly annexed area. McDonald's Exec. Off. v. Nebraska Dept. of Revenue, 243 Neb. 82, 497 N.W.2d 377 (1993).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>