<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id427">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id429" statutenumber="77-2615.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2615.01</statuteno><catchline id="id432">Licensees;
disciplinary action; procedure; appeal;
joint and several liability; when.</catchline><para>(1)
In addition to sections 77-2615 and 77-2622, for any violation of sections
77-2601 to 77-2622 or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated under
such sections, the Tax Commissioner may:</para>
<para>(a) After notice and hearing, suspend or revoke the licenses
of any person licensed under sections 28-1420 to 28-1429 or 77-2601 to 77-2622.
Notice of hearing shall be given as provided in the Administrative Procedure
Act; and</para>
<para>(b) Impose an administrative penalty not to exceed one thousand
dollars for any violation.</para>
<para>(2) No person whose license has been suspended
or revoked shall sell cigarettes or permit cigarettes to be sold during the
period of suspension or revocation on the premises occupied by him or her.
No disciplinary proceeding or action shall be barred or abated by the expiration,
transfer, surrender, continuance, renewal, or extension of any license issued
under sections 28-1420 to 28-1429 or 77-2601 to 77-2622.</para>
<para>(3) Any person aggrieved by
any decision, order, or finding of the Tax Commissioner may appeal the decision,
order, or finding, and the appeal shall be in accordance with the Administrative
Procedure Act.</para>
<para>(4) If a person's
license has been suspended or revoked and the person's name has been removed
for at least ten days from the list of licensed entities published by the
Tax Commissioner under subsection (4) of section 77-2603, any person that
sells cigarettes to or purchases cigarettes from such person shall be jointly
and severally liable for any taxes applicable to such cigarettes under section
77-2602 and for any escrow due on such cigarettes under section 69-2703.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 36.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
