<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id27">
<sectno id="id28" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 11.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id29" statutenumber="77-2756">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id31">77-2756</statuteno><catchline id="id32">Income tax; employer
or payor; withholding for tax.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided
in subsection (2) of this section, every employer or payor required to deduct
and withhold income tax under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 shall, for
each calendar quarter, on or before the last day of the month following the
close of such calendar quarter, file a withholding return as prescribed by
the Tax Commissioner and pay over to the Tax Commissioner or to a depositary
designated by the Tax Commissioner the taxes so required to be deducted and
withheld in such form and content
as the Tax Commissioner may prescribe and containing such information as the
Tax Commissioner deems necessary for the proper administration of the Nebraska
Revenue Act of 1967. When the aggregate amount required to be
deducted and withheld by any employer or payor for either the first or second
month of a calendar quarter exceeds five hundred dollars, the employer or
payor shall, by the fifteenth day of the succeeding month, pay over such aggregate
amount to the Tax Commissioner or to a depositary designated by the Tax Commissioner.
The amount so paid shall be allowed as a credit against the liability shown
on the employer's or payor's quarterly withholding return required by this
section. The Tax Commissioner may, by rule and regulation, provide for the
filing of returns and the payment of the tax deducted and withheld on other
than a quarterly basis.</para>
<para>(2) When the aggregate amount required to be deducted and
withheld by any employer or payor for the entire calendar year is less than
five hundred dollars or the employer or payor is allowed to file federal withholding
returns annually, the employer or payor shall, for each calendar year, on
or before the last day of the month following the close of such calendar year,
file a withholding return as prescribed by the Tax Commissioner and pay over
to the Tax Commissioner or to a depositary designated by the Tax Commissioner
the taxes so required to be deducted and withheld in such form and content as the Tax Commissioner may prescribe
and containing such information as the Tax Commissioner deems necessary for
the proper administration of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967.
The employer or payor may elect or the Tax Commissioner may require the filing
of returns and the payment of taxes on a quarterly basis.</para>
<para>(3) Whenever any employer or payor fails to collect, truthfully
account for, pay over, or make returns of the income tax as required by this
section, the Tax Commissioner may serve a notice requiring such employer or
payor to collect the taxes which become collectible after service of such
notice, to deposit such taxes in a bank approved by the Tax Commissioner in
a separate account in trust for and payable to the Tax Commissioner, and to
keep the amount of such tax in such account until paid over to the Tax Commissioner.
Such notice shall remain in effect until a notice of cancellation is served
by the Tax Commissioner.</para>
<para>(4) Any employer or payor may appoint an agent in accordance
with section 3504 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, for the
purpose of withholding, reporting, or making payment of amounts withheld on
behalf of the employer or payor. The agent shall be considered an employer
or payor for purposes of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 and, with the actual
employer or payor, shall be jointly and severally liable for any amount required
to be withheld and paid over to the Tax Commissioner and any additions to
tax, penalties, and interest with respect thereto.</para>
<para>(5) The employer or payor shall also file on or before February 1 of the succeeding year a copy of
each statement furnished by such employer or payor to each employee or payee
with respect to taxes withheld on wages or payments subject to withholding.
Any employer, payor, or agent who furnished more than fifty statements for a year shall
file the required copies electronically in a manner approved by the Tax Commissioner
that is compatible with federal electronic filing requirements or methods.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 56, p. 1596; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 962, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1064, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 62, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB879, &#167; 11.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>