<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id262">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id264" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-2704.15"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2704.15</statuteno><catchline id="id267">Purchases
by state, schools, or governmental units; exemption; purchasing agents.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Sales and use taxes shall not be imposed on the gross
receipts from the sale, lease, or rental of and the storage, use, or other
consumption in this state of purchases by the state, including public educational
institutions recognized or established under the provisions of Chapter 85,
or by any county, township, city, village, rural or suburban fire protection
district, city airport authority, county airport authority, joint airport
authority, drainage district organized under sections 31-401 to 31-450, land bank created under the Nebraska Municipal
Land Bank Act, natural resources district, elected county fair
board, housing agency as defined in section 71-1575 except for purchases for
any commercial operation that does not exclusively benefit the residents of
an affordable housing project, cemetery created under section 12-101, or joint
entity or agency formed by any combination of two or more counties, townships,
cities, villages, or other exempt governmental units pursuant to the Interlocal
Cooperation Act, the Integrated Solid Waste Management Act, or the Joint Public
Agency Act, except for purchases for use in the business of furnishing gas,
water, electricity, or heat, or by any irrigation or reclamation district,
the irrigation division of any public power and irrigation district, or public
schools or learning communities established under Chapter 79.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of this subsection, purchases by the state
or by a governmental unit listed in subdivision (a) of this subsection include
purchases by a nonprofit corporation under a lease-purchase agreement, financing
lease, or other instrument which provides for transfer of title to the property
to the state or governmental unit upon payment of all amounts due thereunder.
If a nonprofit corporation will be making purchases under a lease-purchase
agreement, financing lease, or other instrument as part of a project with
a total estimated cost that exceeds the threshold amount, then such purchases
shall qualify for an exemption under this section only if the question of
proceeding with such project has been submitted at a primary, general, or
special election held within the governmental unit that will be a party to
the lease-purchase agreement, financing lease, or other instrument and has
been approved by the voters of such governmental unit. For purposes of this
subdivision, (i) project means the acquisition of real property or the construction
of a public building and (ii) threshold amount means the greater of fifty
thousand dollars or six-tenths of one percent of the total actual value of
real and personal property of the governmental unit that will be a party to
the lease-purchase agreement, financing lease, or other instrument as of the
end of the governmental unit's prior fiscal year.</para>
<para>(2) The appointment of purchasing agents shall be recognized
for the purpose of altering the status of the construction contractor as the
ultimate consumer of building materials which are physically annexed to the
structure and which subsequently belong to the state or the governmental unit.
The appointment of purchasing agents shall be in writing and occur prior to
having any building materials annexed to real estate in the construction,
improvement, or repair. The contractor who has been appointed as a purchasing
agent may apply for a refund of or use as a credit against a future use tax
liability the tax paid on inventory items annexed to real estate in the construction,
improvement, or repair of a project for the state or a governmental unit.</para>
<para>(3) Any governmental unit listed in subsection (1) of this
section, except the state, which enters into a contract of construction, improvement,
or repair upon property annexed to real estate without first issuing a purchasing
agent authorization to a contractor or repairperson prior to the building
materials being annexed to real estate in the project may apply to the Tax
Commissioner for a refund of any sales and use tax paid by the contractor
or repairperson on the building materials physically annexed to real estate
in the construction, improvement, or repair.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 871, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 977, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1207, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 232, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 557, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 123, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1017, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1189, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB392, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB252, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB902, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB97, &#167; 26.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Integrated Solid Waste Management Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2001.</para><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Municipal Land Bank Act,</emphasis> see section 19-5201.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Subsection (2) of this section and section 77-2704.12(3) delimit the circumstances under which the agent of a tax-exempt organization may assume the tax-exempt status of the principal. A &amp; D Tech. Supply Co., Inc. v. Nebraska Dept. of Revenue, 259 Neb. 24, 607 N.W.2d 857 (2000).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>