<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2710"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2710</statuteno><catchline>Sales and use tax; removal of personal property; concealment; Tax Commissioner; action.</catchline><para>(1) If the Tax Commissioner finds that a taxpayer is about to depart from the State of Nebraska, remove his or her personal property therefrom, conceal himself or herself or his or her personal property therein, or do any other act tending to delay, prejudice, or render wholly or partially ineffectual any proceedings to collect the sales or use tax for the preceding or current taxable year unless such proceedings be brought without delay, the Tax Commissioner shall declare the taxable period for such taxpayer immediately terminated, and shall cause notice of such findings and declaration to be given the taxpayer, together with a demand for immediate payment of any such tax due for this period, whether or not the time otherwise allowed by law for filing returns and paying such tax has expired. Such tax shall thereupon become immediately due and payable. In any proceedings in court brought to enforce payment of taxes made due and payable by virtue of the provisions of this section, such findings of the Tax Commissioner, whether made after notice to the taxpayer or not, shall be for all purposes prima facie evidence of the taxpayer's design.</para><para>(2) The person against whom a jeopardy determination is made may petition for the redetermination thereof pursuant to the provisions of section 77-2709. He or she shall file the petition for redetermination with the Tax Commissioner within ten days after the service upon him or her of notice of determination or the determination shall become final at the expiration of the ten-day period and the Tax Commissioner shall not reconsider the determination. The person shall also within the ten-day period deposit with the Tax Commissioner such security as the Tax Commissioner may deem necessary to insure compliance with the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. The security may, if necessary, be sold by the Tax Commissioner in the manner prescribed by the provisions of section 77-27,131.</para><para>(3) A taxpayer who is not in default in making any return or paying any sales or use taxes assessed under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 may furnish to the Tax Commissioner, under regulations to be prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, security that he or she will duly make the return next thereafter required to be filed and pay such tax next thereafter required to be paid. The Tax Commissioner may approve and accept in like manner security for return and payment of sales or use taxes made due and payable by virtue of this section.</para><para>(4) If security is approved and accepted and such further or other security with respect to the tax or taxes covered thereby is given as the Tax Commissioner shall from time to time find necessary, the requirement for payment of such taxes shall not be enforced by any proceedings under this section prior to the expiration of the time otherwise allowed for paying such taxes.</para><para>(5) In the case of a bona fide resident of Nebraska about to depart from the state the Tax Commissioner may waive any or all of the requirements placed upon the taxpayer by this section.</para><para>(6) If a taxpayer violates or attempts to violate any provision of this section there shall, in addition to all other penalties, be added as part of the tax twenty-five percent of the total amount due or fifty dollars, whichever is greater.</para><para>(7) If the taxpayer ignores all demands for payment the Tax Commissioner may employ the services of any qualified collection agency or attorney and pay fees for such services out of any money recovered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 10, p. 1564; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 161, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 977, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 