<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id42" statutenumber="77-27,142.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,142.02</statuteno><catchline id="id45">Incorporated
municipalities; sales and use tax; election; question; effect.</catchline>
<para>Except as otherwise provided by subsection (2) of section 77-27,142, the
power granted by section 77-27,142 shall not be exercised unless and until
the question has been submitted at a primary, general, or special election
held within the incorporated municipality and in which all qualified electors
shall be entitled to vote on such question. The officials of the incorporated
municipality shall order the submission of the question by submitting a certified
copy of the resolution proposing the tax to the election commissioner or county
clerk by March 1 for a primary election, by September 1 for a general election,
or at least fifty days before a special election. Except
as otherwise provided by subsection (2) of section 77-27,142.01, the question
may include any terms and conditions set forth in the resolution proposing
the tax, such as a termination date or the specific project or program for
which the revenue received from such tax will be allocated, and shall include
the following language: Shall the governing body of the incorporated municipality
impose a sales and use tax upon the same transactions within such municipality
on which the State of Nebraska is authorized to impose a tax? If a majority
of the votes cast upon such question shall be in favor of such tax, then the
governing body of such incorporated municipality shall be empowered as provided
by section 77-27,142 and shall forthwith proceed to impose a tax pursuant
to the Local Option Revenue Act. If a majority of those voting on the question
shall be opposed to such tax, then the governing body of the incorporated
municipality shall not impose such a tax.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1978, LB 394, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 116, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 890, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB501, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB357, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>