<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2704.44"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2704.44</statuteno><catchline>Use tax; when imposed.</catchline><para>(1) Except for a transaction that is subject to sales tax under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, use tax shall not be imposed on the keeping, retaining, or exercising of any right or power over property for the purpose of subsequently transporting it outside the state or for the purpose of being processed, fabricated, or manufactured into, attached to, or incorporated into other property to be transported outside the state and thereafter used solely outside the state.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as provided in subdivisions (b) through (e) of this subsection, when a person purchases property in another state, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, any territory or possession of the United States, or any foreign country with the intent of using such property in such other state, commonwealth, territory, possession, or country and such property is actually used in the other state, commonwealth, territory, possession, or country for its intended purpose, the property shall not be subject to tax in this state.</para><para>(b) Subdivision (a) of this subsection only applies to a motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer as defined in the Motor Vehicle Registration Act when it is licensed for operation on the highways of the other state, commonwealth, territory, possession, or country prior to being brought into this state. Licensed for operation on the highways does not include any temporary registration, licensing, or in transit procedure that allows nonresidents to operate the motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer on the highways of the other state, commonwealth, territory, possession, or country for a limited time with the intent to remove the motor vehicle, trailer, or semitrailer from the other state, commonwealth, territory, possession, or country.</para><para>(c) Subdivision (a) of this subsection does not apply to an aircraft which is brought into this state within one year after purchase and (i) is regularly based within this state or (ii) more than one-half of the aircraft's operating hours are within this state. For purposes of this subdivision, operation of the aircraft for the purpose of maintenance, repair, or fabrication with subsequent removal from this state upon completion of such maintenance, repair, or fabrication shall not be considered operating hours.</para><para>(d) Subdivision (a) of this subsection shall only apply to a motorboat as defined in section 37-1204 when it is registered for operation in the other state, commonwealth, territory, possession, or country prior to being brought into this state.</para><para>(e) Subdivision (a) of this subsection does not apply to any property that is manufactured, processed, or fabricated in another state and that is not used for its intended purpose in the other state after its manufacture, processing, or fabrication.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 276. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>