
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id24">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id26" statutenumber="77-2215"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2215</statuteno><catchline id="id29">Lost warrants; replacement issued; conditions; stop-payment
order.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever it shall be made to appear
to the satisfaction of any officer, except the Director of Administrative
Services, authorized by law to issue warrants, that any warrant issued by
him or her has been lost or destroyed, such officer shall have authority to
issue a replacement thereof. No replacement warrant shall be issued until the
party applying for the same shall make an affidavit that such party was the
owner of the original warrant and shall also file with such officer an indemnity
bond with good and sufficient security, conditioned to refund any money received
by the party or his or her assigns on such replacement in case of presentation
and payment of the original by the treasurer upon whom the same is drawn,
whether upon a genuine endorsement thereon or otherwise. The payee of any
lost or destroyed warrant shall not be required to file an indemnity bond
when the affidavit shows that such payee has not received such lost or destroyed
warrant and cannot reasonably expect to receive it.</para>
<para>(2) Whenever it shall have come to the attention of the Director
of Administrative Services that an outstanding warrant has not been presented
for payment, the Director of Administrative Services shall immediately issue
a stop-payment order and notify the State Treasurer of the issuance of such order.
After the expiration of seven working days from the issuance of such order,
if in the meantime such outstanding warrant has not been presented for payment,
the Director of Administrative Services shall have authority to issue a replacement thereof. In an emergency, the Director
of Administrative Services may immediately issue such replacement warrant.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1875, &#167; 1, p. 176; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6654; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6185; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-2413; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-2215; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 208, &#167; 1, p. 769; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 338, &#167; 1, p. 1175; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 137, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 930, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB974, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>