<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-27,189"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,189</statuteno><catchline>Qualified business, defined.</catchline><para>(1) A qualified business means any business engaged in:</para><para>(a) Storage, warehousing, distribution, transportation, or sale of tangible personal property; </para><para>(b) Livestock production; </para><para>(c) Conducting research, development, or testing for scientific, agricultural, animal husbandry, food product, or industrial purposes;</para><para>(d) Performing data processing, telecommunication, insurance, or financial services. For purposes of this subdivision, financial services includes only financial services provided by any financial institution subject to tax under Chapter 77, article 38, or any person or entity licensed by the Department of Banking and Finance or the Securities and Exchange Commission and telecommunication services includes community antenna television service, Internet access, satellite ground station, data center, call center, or telemarketing;</para><para>(e) Assembly, fabrication, manufacture, or processing of tangible personal property;</para><para>(f) Administrative management of any activities, including headquarter facilities relating to such activities; or</para><para>(g) Any combination of the activities listed in this subsection.</para><para>(2) Qualified business does not include:</para><para>(a) Any business activity in which eighty percent or more of the total sales are sales to the ultimate consumer of food prepared for immediate consumption or are sales to the ultimate consumer of tangible personal property which is not (i) assembled, fabricated, manufactured, or processed by the taxpayer or (ii) used by the purchaser in any of the activities listed in subsection (1) of this section; and</para><para>(b) Any casino.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1124, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 270, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 608, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 990, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 19.</para></source></law></legaldoc>