<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id40">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id42" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-2905"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2905</statuteno><catchline>Application for credits; form; contents;
officer; review; allocation of credits; notice of determination; denial; appeal;
limit on credits; holder of allocation; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to commencing work on the historically
significant real property, a person shall file an application for credits
under the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act containing
all required information with the officer on a form prescribed by the officer
and shall include an application fee established by the officer pursuant to
section 77-2907. The officer shall not accept any application for credits
prior to January 1, 2015. The application shall include plans and specifications,
an estimate of the cost of the project prepared by a licensed architect, licensed
engineer, or licensed contractor, and a request for a specific amount of credits
based on such estimate. The officer shall review the application and, within
twenty-one days after receiving the application, shall determine whether the
information contained therein is complete. The officer shall notify the applicant
in writing of the determination within five business days after making the
determination. If the officer fails to provide such notification as required,
the application shall be deemed complete as of the twenty-first day after
the application is received by the officer. If the officer determines the
application is complete or if the application is deemed complete pursuant
to this section, the officer shall reserve for the benefit of the applicant
an allocation of credits in the amount specified in the application and determined
by the officer to be reasonable and shall notify the applicant in writing
of the amount of the allocation. The allocation does not entitle the applicant
to an issuance of credits until the applicant complies with all other requirements
of the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act for the issuance
of credits. The date the officer determines the application is complete or
the date the application is deemed complete pursuant to this section shall
constitute the applicant's priority date for purposes of allocating credits
under this section. For complete applications receiving an allocation under
this section, the officer shall determine whether the application conforms
to the standards, and, if so, the officer shall approve such application or
approve such application with conditions. If the application does not conform
to the standards, the officer shall deny such application. The officer shall
promptly provide the person filing the application and the department with
written notice of the officer's determination. If the officer does not provide
a written notice of his or her determination within thirty days after the
date the application is determined or deemed to be complete pursuant to this
section, the application shall be deemed approved. The officer shall notify
the department of any applications that are deemed approved pursuant to this
section. If the officer denies the application, the credits allocated to the
applicant under this subsection shall be added to the annual amount available
for allocation under subsection (2) of this section. Any denial of an application
by the officer pursuant to this section may be appealed, and the appeal shall
be in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act.</para>
<para>(2) The total
amount of credits that may be allocated by the officer under this section
in any calendar year shall be limited to fifteen million dollars. If the amount
of credits allocated in any calendar year is less than fifteen million dollars,
the unused amount shall be carried forward to subsequent years and shall be
available for allocation in subsequent years until fully utilized, except
as otherwise provided in section 77-2912. The officer shall allocate credits
based on priority date, from earliest to latest. If the officer determines
that the complete applications for credits in any calendar year exceed the
maximum amount of credits available under this section for that year, only
those applications with a priority date on or before the date on which the
officer makes that determination may receive an allocation in that year, and
the officer shall not make additional allocations until sufficient credits
are available. If the officer suspends allocations of credits pursuant to
this section, applications with priority dates on or before the date of such
suspension shall retain their priority dates. Once additional credits are
available for allocation, the officer shall once again allocate credits based
on priority date, from earliest to latest, even if the priority dates are
from a prior calendar year.</para><para>(3) Prior to December 1 of any year, the holder of an allocation
of credits under this section who has not commenced the improvements in his
or her approved application shall notify the officer of his or her intent
to retain or release the allocation. Any released allocation shall be added
to the aggregate amount of credits available for allocation in the following
year. Any holder of an allocation who fails to timely notify the officer of
such intent shall be deemed to have released the allocation.</para>
<para>(4) The holder
of an allocation of credits whose application was approved under this section
shall start substantial work pursuant to the approved application within twenty-four
months after receiving notice of approval of the application or, if no notice
of approval is sent by the officer, within twenty-four months after the application
is deemed approved pursuant to this section. Failure to comply with this subsection
shall result in forfeiture of the allocation of credits received under this
section. Any such forfeited allocation shall be added to the aggregate amount
of credits available for allocation for the year in which the forfeiture occurred.</para>
<para>(5) Notwithstanding
subsection (1) of this section, the person applying for the credit under this
section may, at its own risk, incur eligible expenditures up to six months
prior to the submission of the application required under subsection (1) of
this section if such eligible expenditures are limited to architectural fees,
accounting and legal fees, and any costs related to the protection of the
historically significant real property from deterioration.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB191, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>