<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,142"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,142</statuteno><catchline>Incorporated municipalities; sales and use tax; authorized; election.</catchline><para>(1) Any incorporated municipality by ordinance of its governing body is hereby authorized to impose a sales and use tax of one-half percent, one percent, or one and one-half percent upon the same transactions that are sourced under the provisions of sections 77-2703.01 to 77-2703.04 within such incorporated municipality on which the State of Nebraska is authorized to impose a tax pursuant to the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, as amended from time to time. No sales and use tax shall be imposed pursuant to this section until an election has been held and a majority of the qualified electors have approved such tax pursuant to sections 77-27,142.01 and 77-27,142.02.</para><para>(2) A city of the metropolitan class is hereby authorized to increase any city sales and use tax existing on January 1, 1978, imposed pursuant to this section by an amount not to exceed one-half of one percent if the question of such tax increase is submitted to the voters of such city and the voters by a majority vote approve such increase. The question of such increase shall be submitted to the voters at the primary or general election in 1980 if the city council shall submit a certified copy of a resolution to that effect to the election commissioner not later than forty-one days prior to the primary or general election. Notwithstanding the provisions of section 77-27,143, if the increase is approved by the voters at the primary or general election in 1980, the election commissioner shall file a certified copy of the election results with the Tax Commissioner on or before the last day of the month in which the election is held. If the increase is not approved by the voters at the primary or general election in 1980, no tax increased pursuant to this section shall remain in effect after December 31, 1980.</para><para>(3) A city of the primary class is hereby authorized to increase any city sales and use tax existing on January 1, 1985, imposed pursuant to this section by an amount not to exceed one-half of one percent if the question of such tax increase is submitted to the voters of such city and the voters by a majority vote approve such increase. The question of such increase shall be submitted to the voters at the next primary or general election or at a special election if the city council shall submit a certified copy of a resolution proposing the tax increase to the election commissioner within a reasonable time prior to the primary, general, or special election. If the increase is approved by the voters at the primary, general, or special election, the election commissioner shall file a certified copy of the election results with the Tax Commissioner on or before the last day of the month in which the election is held. If the voters of a city of the primary class have not approved such an increase by December 31, 1987, the question of such an increase shall not be submitted thereafter to the voters and there shall be no increase in the city sales and use tax.</para><para>(4) A city of the first or second class or village is hereby authorized to increase any city sales and use tax existing on January 1, 1986, imposed pursuant to this section by an amount not to exceed one-half of one percent if the question of such tax increase is submitted to the voters of such city or village and the voters by a majority vote approve such increase. The question of such increase shall be submitted to the voters at any primary or general election or at a special election if the city council or village board shall submit a certified copy of a resolution proposing the tax increase to the election commissioner or county clerk within a reasonable time prior to the primary, general, or special election. If the increase is approved by the voters at the primary, general, or special election, the election commissioner shall file a certified copy of the election results with the Tax Commissioner on or before the last day of the month in which the election is held.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 629, &#167; 1, p. 2530; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 394, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 902, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 365, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 40, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 116, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 890, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 80. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>City use tax was properly imposed upon property stored in the city for approximately one year before shipment to its ultimate destination within this state. Omaha P. P. Dist. v. Nebraska State Tax Commissioner, 210 Neb 309, 314 N.W.2d 246 (1982).</para><para>This section does not limit the power to propose or reject ordinances concerning a municipal sales tax to the legislative body of a municipality, and does not except sales tax ordinances from the usual power of initiative and referendum. State ex rel. Boyer v. Grady, 201 Neb. 360, 269 N.W.2d 73 (1978).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 