<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 1, 2010">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-2716"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2716</statuteno><catchline>Income tax; adjustments.</catchline><para>(1) The following adjustments to federal adjusted gross income or, for
corporations and fiduciaries, federal taxable income shall be made for interest
or dividends received:</para>
<para>(a) There shall be subtracted interest or dividends received by the
owner of obligations of the United States and its territories and possessions
or of any authority, commission, or instrumentality of the United States to
the extent includable in gross income for federal income tax purposes but
exempt from state income taxes under the laws of the United States;</para>
<para>(b) There shall be subtracted that portion of the total dividends and
other income received from a regulated investment company which is attributable
to obligations described in subdivision (a) of this subsection as reported
to the recipient by the regulated investment company;</para>
<para>(c) There shall be added interest or dividends received by the owner
of obligations of the District of Columbia, other states of the United States,
or their political subdivisions, authorities, commissions, or instrumentalities
to the extent excluded in the computation of gross income for federal income
tax purposes except that such interest or dividends shall not be added if
received by a corporation which is a regulated investment company;</para>
<para>(d) There shall be added that portion of the total dividends and other
income received from a regulated investment company which is attributable
to obligations described in subdivision (c) of this subsection and excluded
for federal income tax purposes as reported to the recipient by the regulated
investment company; and</para>
<para>(e)(i) Any amount subtracted under this subsection shall be reduced
by any interest on indebtedness incurred to carry the obligations or securities
described in this subsection or the investment in the regulated investment
company and by any expenses incurred in the production of interest or dividend
income described in this subsection to the extent that such expenses, including
amortizable bond premiums, are deductible in determining federal taxable income.</para>
<para>(ii) Any amount added under this subsection shall be reduced by any
expenses incurred in the production of such income to the extent disallowed
in the computation of federal taxable income.</para>
<para>(2) There shall be allowed a net operating loss derived from or connected
with Nebraska sources computed under rules and regulations adopted and promulgated
by the Tax Commissioner consistent, to the extent possible under the Nebraska
Revenue Act of 1967, with the laws of the United States. For a resident individual,
estate, or trust, the net operating loss computed on the federal income tax
return shall be adjusted by the modifications contained in this section. For
a nonresident individual, estate, or trust or for a partial-year resident
individual, the net operating loss computed on the federal return shall be
adjusted by the modifications contained in this section and any carryovers
or carrybacks shall be limited to the portion of the loss derived from or
connected with Nebraska sources.</para>
<para>(3) There shall be subtracted from federal adjusted gross income for
all taxable years beginning on or after January 1, 1987, the amount of any
state income tax refund to the extent such refund was deducted under the Internal
Revenue Code, was not allowed in the computation of the tax due under the
Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, and is included in federal adjusted gross income.</para>
<para>(4) Federal adjusted gross income, or, for a fiduciary, federal taxable
income shall be modified to exclude the portion of the income or loss received
from a small business corporation with an election in effect under subchapter
S of the Internal Revenue Code or from a limited liability company organized
pursuant to the Limited Liability Company Act or the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act that
is not derived from or connected with Nebraska sources as determined in section
77-2734.01.</para>
<para>(5) There shall be subtracted from federal adjusted gross income or,
for corporations and fiduciaries, federal taxable income dividends received
or deemed to be received from corporations which are not subject to the Internal
Revenue Code.</para>
<para>(6) There shall be subtracted from federal taxable income a portion
of the income earned by a corporation subject to the Internal Revenue Code
of 1986 that is actually taxed by a foreign country or one of its political
subdivisions at a rate in excess of the maximum federal tax rate for corporations.
The taxpayer may make the computation for each foreign country or for groups
of foreign countries. The portion of the taxes that may be deducted shall
be computed in the following manner:</para>
<para>(a) The amount of federal taxable income from operations within a foreign
taxing jurisdiction shall be reduced by the amount of taxes actually paid
to the foreign jurisdiction that are not deductible solely because the foreign
tax credit was elected on the federal income tax return;</para>
<para>(b) The amount of after-tax income shall be divided by one minus the
maximum tax rate for corporations in the Internal Revenue Code; and</para>
<para>(c) The result of the calculation in subdivision (b) of this subsection
shall be subtracted from the amount of federal taxable income used in subdivision
(a) of this subsection. The result of such calculation, if greater than zero,
shall be subtracted from federal taxable income.</para>
<para>(7) Federal adjusted gross income shall be modified to exclude any amount
repaid by the taxpayer for which a reduction in federal tax is allowed under
section 1341(a)(5) of the Internal Revenue Code.</para>
<para>(8)(a) Federal adjusted gross income or, for corporations and fiduciaries,
federal taxable income shall be reduced, to the extent included, by income
from interest, earnings, and state contributions received from the Nebraska
educational savings plan trust created in sections 85-1801 to 85-1814.</para>
<para>(b) Federal adjusted gross
income or, for corporations and fiduciaries, federal taxable income shall
be reduced by any contributions as a participant in the Nebraska educational
savings plan trust, to the extent not deducted for federal income tax purposes,
but not to exceed two thousand five hundred dollars per married filing separate
return or five thousand dollars for any other return.</para>
<para>(c) Federal adjusted gross
income or, for corporations and fiduciaries, federal taxable income shall
be increased by the amount resulting from the cancellation of a participation
agreement refunded to the taxpayer as a participant in the Nebraska educational
savings plan trust to the extent previously deducted as a contribution to
the trust.</para>
<para>(9)(a) For income tax returns filed after September 10, 2001, for taxable
years beginning or deemed to begin before January 1, 2006, under the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, federal adjusted gross income or, for corporations
and fiduciaries, federal taxable income shall be increased by eighty-five
percent of any amount of any federal bonus depreciation received under the
federal Job Creation and Worker Assistance Act of 2002 or the federal Jobs
and Growth Tax Act of 2003, under section 168(k) or section 1400L of the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, for assets placed in service after September
10, 2001, and before December 31, 2005.</para>
<para>(b) For a partnership, limited liability company, cooperative, including
any cooperative exempt from income taxes under section 521 of the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, limited cooperative association, subchapter
S corporation, or joint venture, the increase shall be distributed to the
partners, members, shareholders, patrons, or beneficiaries in the same manner
as income is distributed for use against their income tax liabilities.</para>
<para>(c) For a corporation with a unitary business having activity both inside
and outside the state, the increase shall be apportioned to Nebraska in the
same manner as income is apportioned to the state by section 77-2734.05.</para>
<para>(d) The amount of bonus depreciation added to federal adjusted gross
income or, for corporations and fiduciaries, federal taxable income by this
subsection shall be subtracted in a later taxable year. Twenty percent of
the total amount of bonus depreciation added back by this subsection for tax
years beginning or deemed to begin before January 1, 2003, under the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, may be subtracted in the first taxable year
beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2005, under the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, and twenty percent in each of the next four
following taxable years. Twenty percent of the total amount of bonus depreciation
added back by this subsection for tax years beginning or deemed to begin on
or after January 1, 2003, may be subtracted in the first taxable year beginning
or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2006, under the Internal Revenue
Code of 1986, as amended, and twenty percent in each of the next four following
taxable years.</para>
<para>(10) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January
1, 2003, and before January 1, 2006, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986,
as amended, federal adjusted gross income or, for corporations and fiduciaries,
federal taxable income shall be increased by the amount of any capital investment
that is expensed under section 179 of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as
amended, that is in excess of twenty-five thousand dollars that is allowed
under the federal Jobs and Growth Tax Act of 2003. Twenty percent of the total
amount of expensing added back by this subsection for tax years beginning
or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2003, may be subtracted in the first
taxable year beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2006, under
the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, and twenty percent in each
of the next four following tax years.</para>
<para>(11)(a) Federal adjusted gross income shall be reduced by contributions,
up to two thousand dollars per married filing jointly return or one thousand
dollars for any other return, and any investment earnings made as a participant
in the Nebraska long-term care savings plan under the Long-Term Care Savings
Plan Act, to the extent not deducted for federal income tax purposes.</para>
<para>(b) Federal adjusted gross income shall be increased by the withdrawals
made as a participant in the Nebraska long-term care savings plan under the
act by a person who is not a qualified individual or for any reason other
than transfer of funds to a spouse, long-term care expenses, long-term care
insurance premiums, or death of the participant, including withdrawals made
by reason of cancellation of the participation agreement or termination of
the plan, to the extent previously deducted as a contribution or as investment
earnings.</para>
<para>(12) There shall be added to federal adjusted gross income for individuals,
estates, and trusts any amount taken as a credit for franchise tax paid by
a financial institution under sections 77-3801 to 77-3807 as allowed by subsection
(5) of section 77-2715.07.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 16, p. 1579; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 619, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 962, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1124, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 774, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 773, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 458, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 459, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 773, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 504; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 977, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 401, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1028, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1003, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1085, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 596, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 965, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 968, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB338, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB368, &#167; 135; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB456, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB197, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 104.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Long-Term Care Savings Plan Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act,</emphasis> see section 21-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>