<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id71">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id73" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-2909"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2909</statuteno><catchline>Transfer, sale, or assignment of
credit; limitation; use; notice; department; duties; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Persons who receive
the original issuance of credits from the department under section 77-2906
may transfer, sell, or assign up to fifty percent of such credits to any person
or legal entity. If the person who receives the original issuance of credits
from the department is a political subdivision or a tax-exempt entity under
section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, such fifty-percent
limitation shall not apply.</para>
<para>(2) The credits
allowed to be transferred, sold, or assigned pursuant to subsection (1) of
this section may thereafter be transferred, sold, or assigned multiple times,
either in whole or in part, by or to any person or legal entity.</para>
<para>(3) Any person
acquiring credits under this section may use such credits to offset up to
one hundred percent of such person's income tax due under the Nebraska Revenue
Act of 1967 or any tax due under sections 77-907 to 77-918 or 77-3801 to 77-3807
in the year the historically significant real property is placed in service
and in subsequent years until all credits have been utilized, except as otherwise
provided in section 77-2912.</para><para>(4) The person transferring, selling, or
assigning the credits shall notify the officer and the department in writing
within fifteen calendar days following the effective date of the transfer,
sale, or assignment and shall remit to the department the certificate issued
for the credits that were transferred, sold, or assigned. The department shall
then issue new certificates as necessary to effectuate the transfer, sale,
or assignment. The issuance of the new credits by the department shall perfect
the transfer, sale, or assignment of credits.</para><para>(5) The department shall
develop a system to track the transfer, sale, and assignment of credits and
to certify the ownership of the credits.</para><para>(6) The department shall have, with respect
to the Nebraska Job Creation and Mainstreet Revitalization Act, all authority
granted to it in section 77-27,119.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB191, &#167; 9.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>