<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id272">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id274" statutenumber="77-2602"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2602</statuteno><catchline id="id277">Cigarette tax;
rate; disposition of proceeds; priority.</catchline><para>(1) Every stamping agent engaged in distributing or selling
cigarettes at wholesale in this state shall pay to the Tax Commissioner of
this state a special privilege tax. This shall be in addition to all other
taxes. It shall be paid prior to or at the time of the sale, gift, or delivery
to the retail dealer in the several amounts as follows: On each package of
cigarettes containing not more than twenty cigarettes, sixty-four cents per
package; and on packages containing more than twenty cigarettes, the same
tax as provided on packages containing not more than twenty cigarettes for
the first twenty cigarettes in each package and a tax of one-twentieth of
the tax on the first twenty cigarettes on each cigarette in excess of twenty
cigarettes in each package.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning October 1, 2004, the State Treasurer shall
place the equivalent of forty-nine cents of such tax in the General Fund.
The State Treasurer shall reduce the amount placed in the General Fund under
this subsection by the amount prescribed in subdivision (3)(d) of this section.
For purposes of this section, the equivalent of a specified number of cents
of the tax shall mean that portion of the proceeds of the tax equal to the
specified number divided by the tax rate per package of cigarettes containing
not more than twenty cigarettes.</para>
<para>(3) The State Treasurer shall distribute the remaining proceeds
of such tax in the following order:</para>
<para>(a) First, beginning July 1, 1980, the State Treasurer shall
place the equivalent of one cent of such tax in the Nebraska Outdoor Recreation
Development Cash Fund. For fiscal year distributions occurring after FY1998-99,
the distribution under this subdivision shall not be less than the amount
distributed under this subdivision for FY1997-98. Any money needed to increase
the amount distributed under this subdivision to the FY1997-98 amount shall
reduce the distribution to the General Fund;</para>
<para>(b) Second, beginning July 1, 1993, the State Treasurer shall
place the equivalent of three cents of such tax in the Health and Human Services
Cash Fund to carry out sections 81-637 to 81-640. For fiscal year distributions
occurring after FY1998-99, the distribution under this subdivision shall not
be less than the amount distributed under this subdivision for FY1997-98.
Any money needed to increase the amount distributed under this subdivision
to the FY1997-98 amount shall reduce the distribution to the General Fund;</para>
<para>(c) Third, beginning October 1, 2002, and continuing until
all the purposes of the Deferred Building Renewal Act have been fulfilled,
the State Treasurer shall place the equivalent of seven cents of such tax
in the Building Renewal Allocation Fund. The distribution under this subdivision
shall not be less than the amount distributed under this subdivision for FY1997-98.
Any money needed to increase the amount distributed under this subdivision
to the FY1997-98 amount shall reduce the distribution to the General Fund;</para>
<para>(d) Fourth, until July 1, 2009, the State Treasurer shall
place in the Municipal Infrastructure Redevelopment Fund the sum of five hundred
twenty thousand dollars each fiscal year to carry out the Municipal Infrastructure
Redevelopment Fund Act. The Legislature shall appropriate the sum of five
hundred twenty thousand dollars each year for fiscal year 2003-04 through
fiscal year 2008-09;</para>
<para>(e) Fifth, beginning July 1, 2001, and continuing until June
30, 2008, the State Treasurer shall place the equivalent of two cents of such
tax in the Information Technology Infrastructure Fund. The distribution under
this subdivision shall not be less than two million fifty thousand dollars.
Any money needed to increase the amount distributed under this subdivision
to two million fifty thousand dollars shall reduce the distribution to the
General Fund;</para>
<para>(f) Sixth, beginning July 1, 2001, and continuing until June
30, 2016, the State Treasurer shall place one million dollars each fiscal
year in the City of the Primary Class Development Fund. If necessary, the
State Treasurer shall reduce the distribution of tax proceeds to the General
Fund pursuant to subsection (2) of this section by such amount required to
fulfill the one million dollars to be distributed pursuant to this subdivision;</para>
<para>(g) Seventh, beginning July 1, 2001, and continuing until
June 30, 2016, the State Treasurer shall place one million five hundred thousand
dollars each fiscal year in the City of the Metropolitan Class Development
Fund. If necessary, the State Treasurer shall reduce the distribution of tax
proceeds to the General Fund pursuant to subsection (2) of this section by
such amount required to fulfill the one million five hundred thousand dollars
to be distributed pursuant to this subdivision; and</para>
<para>(h) Eighth, beginning July 1, 2008, and continuing until
June 30, 2009, the State Treasurer shall place the equivalent of two million
fifty thousand dollars of such tax in the Nebraska Public Safety Communication
System Cash Fund. Beginning July 1, 2009, and continuing until June 30, 2016,
the State Treasurer shall place the equivalent of two million five hundred
seventy thousand dollars of such tax in the Nebraska Public Safety Communication
System Cash Fund. Beginning July 1, 2016, and every fiscal year thereafter,
the State Treasurer shall place the equivalent of five million seventy thousand
dollars of such tax in the Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash
Fund. If necessary, the State Treasurer shall reduce the distribution of tax
proceeds to the General Fund pursuant to subsection (2) of this section by
such amount required to fulfill the distribution pursuant to this subdivision.</para>
<para>(4) If, after distributing the proceeds of such tax pursuant
to subsections (2) and (3) of this section, any proceeds of such tax remain,
the State Treasurer shall place such remainder in the Nebraska Capital Construction
Fund.</para>
<para>(5) The Legislature hereby finds and determines that the
projects funded from the Municipal Infrastructure Redevelopment Fund and the
Building Renewal Allocation Fund are of critical importance to the State of
Nebraska. It is the intent of the Legislature that the allocations and appropriations
made by the Legislature to such funds or, in the case of allocations for the
Municipal Infrastructure Redevelopment Fund, to the particular municipality's
account not be reduced until all contracts and securities relating to the
construction and financing of the projects or portions of the projects funded
from such funds or accounts of such funds are completed or paid or, in the
case of the Municipal Infrastructure Redevelopment Fund, the earlier of such
date or July 1, 2009, and that until such time any reductions in the cigarette
tax rate made by the Legislature shall be simultaneously accompanied by equivalent
reductions in the amount dedicated to the General Fund from cigarette tax
revenue. Any provision made by the Legislature for distribution of the proceeds
of the cigarette tax for projects or programs other than those to (a) the
General Fund, (b) the Nebraska Outdoor Recreation Development Cash Fund, (c)
the Health and Human Services Cash Fund, (d) the Municipal Infrastructure
Redevelopment Fund, (e) the Building Renewal Allocation Fund, (f) the Information
Technology Infrastructure Fund, (g) the City of the Primary Class Development
Fund, (h) the City of the Metropolitan Class Development Fund, and (i) the
Nebraska Public Safety Communication System Cash Fund shall not be made a
higher priority than or an equal priority to any of the programs or projects
specified in subdivisions (a) through (i) of this subsection.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 267, &#167; 2, p. 861; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 341, &#167; 1, p. 1179; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 457, &#167; 1, p. 1483; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 501, &#167; 2, p. 1595; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 500, &#167; 1, p. 1590; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 645, &#167; 10, p. 2562; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 87, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1433, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 447, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 945, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1975, Spec. Sess., LB 6, &#167; 67; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 1004, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 1006, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 109, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 506, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 753, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 192, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 410, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 469, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 862, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 728, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 653A, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 3, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 258, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 842, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 730, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 218, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 683, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1220, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 703, &#167; 65; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 9, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, Third Spec. Sess., LB 11, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 22, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 595, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 961, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 795; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1190, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1107, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 683, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1349, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 657, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1085, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 440, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 759, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 426, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 703; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB322, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 20.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Deferred Building Renewal Act,</emphasis> see section 81-190.</para><para><emphasis>Municipal Infrastructure Redevelopment Fund Act,</emphasis> see section 18-2601.</para><para><emphasis>Task Force for Building Renewal,</emphasis> see section 81-174.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>This section does not appropriate revenue placed in the Downtown Education Center and Office Rental Fund and revenue placed in that fund may not be expended without a specific legislative appropriation from that fund. Ruge v. State, 201 Neb. 391, 267 N.W.2d 748 (1978).</para><para>This act which includes sections 77-2602, 77-2610, 77-2616, and 85-1,100 is valid under the Constitutions of Nebraska and the United States. Sandberg v. State, 188 Neb. 335, 196 N.W.2d 501 (1972).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
