<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-27,195"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,195</statuteno><catchline>Report; contents; joint hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax
Commissioner shall prepare a report identifying the amount of investment in
this state and the number of equivalent jobs created by each taxpayer claiming
a credit pursuant to the Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act. The report
shall include the amount of credits claimed in the aggregate. The report shall be
issued on or before July 15 of each year for all credits allowed during the previous
calendar year. The Department
of Revenue shall, on or before September 1 of each year, appear at a joint
hearing of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Revenue
Committee of the Legislature and present the report. Any supplemental information
requested by three or more committee members shall be presented within thirty
days after the request.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning with applications filed on or after January 1, 2006, except
for livestock modernization or expansion projects, the report shall provide
information on project-specific total incentives used every two years for
each approved project and shall disclose (a) the identity of the taxpayer,
(b) the location of the project, and (c) the total credits used and refunds
approved during the immediately preceding two years expressed as a single,
aggregated total. The incentive information required to be reported under
this subsection shall not be reported for the first year the taxpayer attains
the required employment and investment thresholds. The information on first-year
incentives used shall be combined with and reported as part of the second
year. Thereafter, the information on incentives used for succeeding years
shall be reported for each project every two years containing information
on two years of credits used and refunds approved. The incentives used shall
include incentives which have been approved by the Department of Revenue,
but not necessarily received, during the previous two calendar years.</para>
<para>(3) For livestock modernization or expansion projects, the report shall
disclose (a) the identity of the taxpayer, (b) the total credits used and
refunds approved during the preceding calendar year, and (c) the location
of the project.</para>
<para>(4) No information shall be provided in the report that is protected
by state or federal confidentiality laws.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1124, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 886, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 608, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 990, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB612, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>April 25, 2013</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>