<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2398"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2398</statuteno><catchline>Deposits in excess of insured or guaranteed amount; requirements.</catchline> <para>(1) As an alternative to the requirements to secure the deposit of public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation pursuant to sections 77-2389 and 77-2394, a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a public depositary may secure the deposits of one or more governmental units by providing a deposit guaranty bond or by depositing, pledging, or granting a security interest in a single pool of securities to secure the repayment of all public money or public funds deposited in the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution by such governmental units and not otherwise secured pursuant to law, if at all times the total value of the deposit guaranty bond is at least equal to the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed or the aggregate market value of the pool of securities so deposited, pledged, or in which a security interest is granted is at least equal to one hundred five percent of the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed. Each such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution shall carry on its accounting records at all times a general ledger or other appropriate account of the total amount of all public money or public funds to be secured by a deposit guaranty bond or by the pool of securities, as determined at the opening of business each day, and the total value of the deposit guaranty bond or the aggregate market value of the pool of securities deposited, pledged, or in which a security interest is granted to secure such public money or public funds.</para> <para>(2) Only the securities listed in subdivision (12) of section 77-2387 may be provided and accepted as security for the deposit of public money or public funds and shall be eligible as collateral. The qualified trustee shall accept no security which is not listed in subdivision (12) of section 77-2387.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 31.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>