<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-27,144"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,144</statuteno><catchline>Municipalities; sales and use tax;
Tax Commissioner; collection; distribution;
refunds; notice; deduction.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall collect the tax
imposed by any incorporated municipality concurrently with collection of a
state tax in the same manner as the state tax is collected. The Tax Commissioner
shall remit monthly the proceeds of the tax to the incorporated municipalities
levying the tax, after deducting the amount of refunds made and three percent
of the remainder to be credited to the Municipal Equalization Fund.</para>
<para>(2) Deductions for a
refund made pursuant to section 77-4105 or 77-5725 shall be delayed for one
year after the refund has been made to the taxpayer. The Department of Revenue
shall notify the municipality liable for the refund of the pending refund,
the amount of the refund, and the month in which the deduction will be made
or begin, except that if the amount of a refund claimed under section 77-4105
or 77-5725 exceeds twenty-five percent of the municipality's total sales and
use tax receipts, net of any refunds or sales tax collection fees, for the
municipality's prior fiscal year, the department shall deduct the refund over
the period of one year in equal monthly amounts beginning after the one-year
notification period required by this subsection. This subsection applies to
refunds owed by cities of the first class, cities of the second class, and
villages. This subsection applies beginning January 1, 2014.</para>
<para>(3) The Tax Commissioner shall
keep full and accurate records of all money received and distributed under
the provisions of the Local Option Revenue Act. When proceeds of a tax levy
are received but the identity of the incorporated municipality which levied
the tax is unknown and is not identified within six months after receipt,
the amount shall be credited to the Municipal Equalization Fund. The municipality
may request the names and addresses of the retailers which have collected
the tax as provided in subsection
(13) of section 77-2711 and
may certify a municipal employee to request and review confidential sales
tax returns and sales tax return information as provided in subsection (14)
of section 77-2711.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 629, &#167; 3, p. 2530; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 53, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 868, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1177, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB94, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB209, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>