<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id173">
<sectno id="id174" opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 12.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id175" statutenumber="77-2789">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id177">77-2789</statuteno><catchline id="id178">Income tax;
failure to file return; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) In case of
failure to file any income tax return required under the provisions of the
Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 on the date prescribed therefor, determined with
regard to any extension of time for filing, unless it is shown that such failure
is the result of reasonable cause and not the result of willful neglect, the
Tax Commissioner may add to the amount required to be shown as tax on such
return, five percent of the amount of such tax if the failure is for not more
than one month, with an additional five percent for each additional month
or fraction thereof during which such failure continues, not exceeding twenty-five
percent in the aggregate. For purposes of this section, the amount of tax
required to be shown on the return shall be reduced by the amount of any part
of the tax which is paid on or before the date prescribed for payment of the
tax and by the amount of any credit against the tax which may be claimed upon
the return.</para>
<para>(2) In case of each failure to file a statement of payment
to another person, including the duplicate statement of tax withheld on wages,
on the date prescribed therefor, determined with regard to any extension of
time for filing, unless it is shown that such failure is the result of reasonable
cause and not willful neglect, the Tax Commissioner may assess a penalty against
the person so failing to file the statement, in the amount of two dollars
for each statement not so filed but the total amount imposed on the delinquent
person for all such failure during any calendar year shall not exceed two
thousand dollars.</para>
<para>(3) In case of failure to file any return for income tax
withheld on the date prescribed therefor, determined with regard to any extension
of time to file, the Tax Commissioner may add to the amount required to be
shown as tax on such return twenty-five dollars or the amount determined under
subsection (1) of this section, whichever is greater.</para>
<para>(4) All determinations
made by the Tax Commissioner under subsection (3) of this section are due
and payable at the time they become final. If they are not paid when final,
a penalty of ten percent of the total amount due, exclusive of interest and
other penalties, shall be added to the total amount due.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 89, p. 1610; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB879, &#167; 12.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>