<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id143">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id145" statutenumber="77-2793">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2793</statuteno><catchline id="id148">Claim for credit
or refund; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) A claim for credit
or refund of an overpayment of any income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue
Act of 1967 shall be filed by the taxpayer within three years from the time
the return was filed or two years from the time the tax was paid, whichever
of such periods expires later. A
claim for credit or refund of a refundable credit shall be filed by the taxpayer
within three years after the due date of the return for the year in which
the refundable credit was allowable. No credit or refund shall
be allowed or made after the expiration of the period of limitation prescribed
in this subsection for the filing of a claim for credit or refund unless a
claim for credit or refund is filed by the taxpayer within such period.</para>
<para>(2) If a claim for credit or refund of an overpayment or for credit or
refund of a refundable credit is filed by the taxpayer during
the applicable three-year
period prescribed in subsection (1) of this section, the amount of the credit
or refund shall not exceed the portion of the tax paid or any refundable credit allowable within the
three years immediately preceding the filing of the claim plus the period
of any extension of time for filing the return if such return was filed prior
to the end of the extension of time. If a claim for credit or refund of an overpayment is not
filed within the three-year period prescribed in subsection (1) of this
section, but is filed within the two-year period prescribed in subsection (1) of this section,
the amount of the credit or refund shall not exceed the portion of the tax
paid during the two years immediately preceding the filing of the claim. If
no claim is filed, the credit or refund shall not exceed the amount which
would be allowable under either of the preceding sentences, as the case may
be, if a claim was filed on the date the credit or refund is allowed.</para>
<para>(3) If an agreement for an extension of the period for assessment
of income taxes is made within the period prescribed in subsection (1) of
this section for the filing of a claim for credit or refund, the period for
filing claim for credit or for making credit or refund if no claim is filed
shall not expire prior to six months after the expiration of the period within
which an assessment may be made pursuant to the agreement or any extension
thereof.</para>
<para>(4) If a taxpayer is required by subsection (1) of section
77-2775 to report a change or correction in federal adjusted gross income,
taxable income, or tax liability reported on his or her federal income tax
return, or to report a change or correction which is treated in the same manner
as if it were an overpayment for federal income tax purposes, or to file an
amended return with the Tax Commissioner, a claim for credit or refund of
any resulting overpayment of tax shall be filed by the taxpayer within two
years from the time the notice of such change or correction or such amended
return was required to be filed with the Tax Commissioner. If the report or
amended return is not filed within the sixty-day period specified in such
subsection, interest on any resulting refund or credit shall cease to accrue
after such sixtieth day. The amount of such credit or refund shall not exceed
the amount of the reduction in tax attributable to such federal change, correction,
or items amended on the taxpayer's amended federal income tax return. This
subsection shall not affect the time within which or the amount for which
a claim for credit or refund may be filed apart from this subsection.</para>
<para>(5)(a) If a taxpayer is required by subsection (2) of section
77-2775 to report a change or correction in the amount of income taxable or
tax credit allowable in one or more states and such changes or corrections
when reflected in the return filed under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967
as most recently amended would result in an overpayment of tax, a claim for
credit or refund shall be filed by the taxpayer within the earlier of (i)
two years from the time the notice of such change or correction or such amended
return was required to be filed with the Tax Commissioner or (ii) ten years
from the due date of the return.</para>
<para>(b) If the report or amended return is not filed within the
sixty-day period specified in such subsection, interest on any resulting refund
or credit shall cease to accrue after such sixtieth day. The amount of such
credit or refund shall not exceed the lesser of (i) the reduction in tax attributable
to the change or correction in the amount of income taxable or the credit
allowable in such other state in the return filed under the Nebraska Revenue
Act of 1967 or (ii) the increase in tax actually paid to such other state
or states.</para>
<para>(c) This subsection shall not affect the time within which
or the amount for which a claim for credit or refund may be filed apart from
this subsection. This subsection shall apply to changes or corrections which
become final on or after May 1, 1993.</para>
<para>(6) If the claim for credit or refund relates to an overpayment
attributable to a net operating loss carryback derived from or connected with
Nebraska sources, the claim may be made under rules and regulations prescribed
by the Tax Commissioner consistent, to the extent possible under the Nebraska
Revenue Act of 1967, with the laws of the United States.</para>
<para>(7) For purposes of this section and section 77-2795, a timely
filed petition for redetermination shall be considered a claim for credit
or refund filed on the date the notice of deficiency determination was mailed.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 93, p. 1614; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 66; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 773, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 70; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB914, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB851, &#167; 13.</para><operativedate>July 18, 2014</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Though this section provides a procedure by which a taxpayer may obtain a refund of overpayment of income taxes, it is exclusive and does not provide for class actions. Boersma v. Karnes, 227 Neb. 329, 417 N.W.2d 341 (1988).</para><para>United States District Court had original jurisdiction of cases to enjoin collection of state tax on income earned by Indians on reservations notwithstanding availability of state remedy. Omaha Tribe of Indians v. Peters, 516 F.2d 133 (8th Cir. 1975).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>