<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2733"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2733</statuteno><catchline>Income tax; nonresident; income in Nebraska; method of determination of tax; exception.</catchline><para>(1) The income of a nonresident individual derived from sources within this state shall be the sum of the following:</para><para>(a) The net amount of items of income, gain, loss, and deduction entering into his or her federal taxable income which are derived from or connected with sources in this state including (i) his or her distributive share of partnership income and deductions determined under section 77-2729, (ii) his or her share of small business corporation or limited liability company income determined under section 77-2734.01, and (iii) his or her share of estate or trust income and deductions determined under section 77-2725; and</para><para>(b) The portion of the modifications described in section 77-2716 which relates to income derived from sources in this state, including any modifications attributable to him or her as a partner.</para><para>(2) Items of income, gain, loss, and deduction derived from or connected with sources within this state are those items attributable to:</para><para>(a) The ownership or disposition of any interest in real or tangible personal property in this state;</para><para>(b) A business, trade, profession, or occupation carried on in this state; and</para><para>(c) Any lottery prize awarded in a lottery game conducted pursuant to the State Lottery Act.</para><para>(3) Income from intangible personal property including annuities, dividends, interest, and gains from the disposition of intangible personal property shall constitute income derived from sources within this state only to the extent that such income is from property employed in a business, trade, profession, or occupation carried on in this state.</para><para>(4) Deductions with respect to capital losses, net long-term capital gains, and net operating losses shall be based solely on income, gains, losses, and deductions derived from or connected with sources in this state, under rules and regulations to be prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, but otherwise shall be determined in the same manner as the corresponding federal deductions.</para><para>(5) If a business, trade, profession, or occupation is carried on partly within and partly without this state, the items of income and deduction derived from or connected with sources within this state shall be determined by apportionment under rules and regulations to be prescribed by the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(6) Compensation paid by the United States for service in the armed forces of the United States performed by a nonresident individual shall not constitute income derived from sources within this state.</para><para>(7) Compensation paid by a resident estate or trust for services by a nonresident fiduciary shall constitute income derived from sources within this state.</para><para>(8) Compensation paid by a business, trade, or profession shall constitute income derived from sources within this state if:</para><para>(a) The individual's service is performed entirely within this state;</para><para>(b) The individual's service is performed both within and without this state, but the service performed without this state is incidental to the individual's service within this state;</para><para>(c) The individual's service is performed without this state, but the service performed without this state is related to the transactions and activity of the business, trade, or profession carried on within this state; or</para><para>(d) Some of the service is performed in this state and (i) the base of operations or, if there is no base of operations, the place from which the service is directed or controlled is in this state or (ii) the base of operations or the place from which the service is directed or controlled is not in any state in which some part of the service is performed, but the individual's residence is in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 33, p. 1585; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 526, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 1124, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 773, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 506; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 134, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State Lottery Act,</emphasis> see section 9-801.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 