<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id43" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-27,188"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,188</statuteno><catchline id="id46">Tax credit; allowed; when; amount; repayment.</catchline><para>(1) A refundable credit against the taxes imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 shall be allowed to any taxpayer who has an approved application pursuant to the Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act, who is engaged in a qualified business as described in section 77-27,189, and who after January 1, 2006:</para><para>(a)(i) Increases employment by two new equivalent employees and makes an increased investment of at least one hundred twenty-five thousand dollars prior to the end of the first taxable year after the year in which the application was submitted in (A) any county in this state with a population of fewer than fifteen thousand inhabitants, according to the most recent federal decennial census, (B) any village in this state, or (C) any area within the corporate limits of a city of the metropolitan class consisting of one or more contiguous census tracts, as determined by the most recent federal decennial census, which contain a percentage of persons below the poverty line of greater than thirty percent, and all census tracts contiguous to such tract or tracts; or</para><para>(ii) Increases employment by five new equivalent employees and makes an increased investment of at least two hundred fifty thousand dollars prior to the end of the first taxable year after the year in which the application was submitted in any county in this state with a population of less than twenty-five thousand inhabitants, according to the most recent federal decennial census, or any city of the second class; and</para><para>(b) Pays a minimum qualifying wage of eight dollars and twenty-five cents per hour to the new equivalent employees for which tax credits are sought under the Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act. The Department of Revenue shall adjust the minimum qualifying wages required for applications filed after January 1, 2004, and each January 1 thereafter, as follows: The current rural Nebraska average weekly wage shall be divided by the rural Nebraska average weekly wage for 2003; and the result shall be multiplied by the eight dollars and twenty-five cents minimum qualifying wage for 2003 and rounded to the nearest one cent. The amount of increase or decrease in the minimum qualifying wages for any year shall be the cumulative change in the rural Nebraska average weekly wage since 2003. For purposes of this subsection, rural Nebraska average weekly wage means the most recent average weekly wage paid by all employers in all counties with a population of less than twenty-five thousand inhabitants as reported by October 1 by the Department of Labor.</para><para>For purposes of this section, a teleworker working in Nebraska from his or her residence for a taxpayer shall be considered an employee of the taxpayer, and property of the taxpayer provided to the teleworker working in Nebraska from his or her residence shall be considered an investment. Teleworker includes an individual working on a per-item basis and an independent contractor working for the taxpayer so long as the taxpayer withholds Nebraska income tax from wages or other payments made to such teleworker. For purposes of calculating the number of new equivalent employees when the teleworkers are paid on a per-item basis or are independent contractors, the total wages or payments made to all such new employees during the year shall be divided by the qualifying wage as determined in subdivision (b) of this subsection, with the result divided by two thousand eighty hours.</para><para>(2) A refundable credit against the taxes imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 shall be allowed to any taxpayer who (a) has an approved application pursuant to the Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act, (b) is engaged in livestock production, and (c) after January 1, 2007, invests at least fifty thousand dollars for livestock modernization or expansion.</para><para>(3) The amount of the credit allowed under subsection (1) of this section shall be three thousand dollars for each new equivalent employee and two thousand seven hundred fifty dollars for each fifty thousand dollars of increased investment. For applications filed before January 1, 2016, the amount of the credit allowed under subsection (2) of this section shall be ten percent of the investment, not to exceed a credit of thirty thousand dollars. For applications filed on or after January 1, 2016, the amount of the credit allowed under subsection (2) of this section shall be ten percent of the investment, not to exceed a credit of one hundred fifty thousand dollars per application. For each application, a taxpayer engaged in livestock production may qualify for a credit under either subsection (1) or (2) of this section, but cannot qualify for more than one credit per application.</para><para>(4) An employee of a qualified employee leasing company shall be considered to be an employee of the client-lessee for purposes of this section if the employee performs services for the client-lessee. A qualified employee leasing company shall provide the Department of Revenue access to the records of employees leased to the client-lessee.</para><para>(5) The credit shall not exceed the amounts set out in the application and approved by the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(6)(a) If a taxpayer who receives tax credits creates fewer jobs or less investment than required in the project agreement, the taxpayer shall repay the tax credits as provided in this subsection.</para><para>(b) If less than seventy-five percent of the required jobs in the project agreement are created, one hundred percent of the job creation tax credits shall be repaid. If seventy-five percent or more of the required jobs in the project agreement are created, no repayment of the job creation tax credits is necessary.</para><para>(c) If less than seventy-five percent of the required investment in the project agreement is created, one hundred percent of the investment tax credits shall be repaid. If seventy-five percent or more of the required investment in the project agreement is created, no repayment of the investment tax credits is necessary.</para><para>(7) For taxpayers who submitted applications for benefits under the Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act before January 1, 2006, subsection (1) of this section, as such subsection existed immediately prior to such date, shall continue to apply to such taxpayers. The changes made by Laws 2005, LB 312, shall not preclude a taxpayer from receiving the tax incentives earned prior to January 1, 2006.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1124, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 270, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 335, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 725, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 134, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 886, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 539, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 169, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 608, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 990, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB895, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB175, &#167; 8. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Ethanol facility eligible for tax credit,</emphasis> requirements, see section 66-1349.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>