<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-2724"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2724</statuteno><catchline>Nonresident estates or trusts; income; how determined.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of taxation of nonresident estates or trusts:</para><para>(a) Items of income, gain, loss, and deduction shall mean those items entering into the definition of federal distributable income;</para><para>(b) Items of income, gain, loss, and deduction entering into the definition of federal distributable net income shall include such items from another estate or trust of which the estate or trust is a beneficiary; and</para><para>(c) The source of items of income, gain, loss, or deduction shall be determined under regulations prescribed by the Tax Commissioner in accordance with the general rules in section 77-2733 as if the estate or trust were a nonresident individual.</para><para>(2) The taxable income of an estate or trust, before the proration required in subdivision (1)(b) of section 77-2717 to determine the tax attributable to income from sources within this state, shall consist of its share of items of income, gain, loss, and deduction which enter into the federal definition of distributable net income (a) increased or reduced by the amount of any items of income, gain, loss, or deduction which are recognized for federal income tax purposes but excluded from the federal definition of distributable net income of the estate or trust, (b) less the amount of the deduction for its federal exemption, and (c) increased or reduced by the modifications contained in section 77-2716 which relate to an item of estate or trust income.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 24, p. 1581; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 773, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 977, &#167; 15. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 