<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id737"><amendatorysection statutenumber="77-2503" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2503</statuteno><catchline>Application; form; qualified project; allocation of credit; assignment; use of credit.</catchline><para>(1) An owner of an affordable housing project seeking a Nebraska affordable housing tax credit shall file an application with the authority on a form prescribed by the authority. A qualified taxpayer shall be allowed a nonrefundable tax credit if the authority determines that the project for which tax credits are sought is a qualified project.</para><para>(2) If the requirements of subsection (1) of this section are met, the authority shall issue an eligibility statement to the owner of such qualified project stating the amount of Nebraska affordable housing tax credits allocated to the qualified project. The amount of such tax credits shall be the amount of federal low-income housing tax credits available to such project, except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section. Tax credits for each qualified project shall be issued for the first six years of the credit period as defined in 26 U.S.C. 42(f)(1). The authority shall only allocate tax credits to qualified projects that are placed in service after January 1, 2018.</para><para>(3) The Nebraska affordable housing tax credit shall be allocated among some or all of the partners, members, or shareholders of the owner of the qualified project in any manner agreed to by such persons. A qualified taxpayer may assign all or part of his or her ownership interest, including his or her interest in the tax credits authorized in this section. For any tax year in which such an interest is assigned pursuant to this subsection, the assignor shall file a written statement with his or her tax return specifying the amount of the credits assigned.</para><para>(4) The maximum amount of Nebraska affordable housing tax credits awarded to all qualified projects in any given allocation year shall be no more than one hundred percent of the total amount of federal low-income housing tax credits awarded by the authority in the same allocation year. Notwithstanding any other provision of the Affordable Housing Tax Credit Act, the authority is prohibited from awarding to a qualified project any combined amount of federal low-income housing tax credits and Nebraska affordable housing tax credits that is more than necessary to make the qualified project financially feasible.</para><para>(5) Any Nebraska affordable housing tax credits granted under this section may be used to offset any income taxes due under section 77-2715 or 77-2734.02, any premium and related retaliatory taxes due under section 44-150 or 77-908, or any franchise taxes due under sections 77-3801 to 77-3807.</para><para>(6) The tax credit shall not be used to reduce the tax liability of the qualified taxpayer to less than zero. Any tax credit claimed but not used in a taxable year may be carried forward.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB884, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>