<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id346">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id348" statutenumber="77-2604">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2604</statuteno><catchline id="id351">Tax Commissioner;
forms; reports; contents; when due;
sharing of information.</catchline><para>(1) Every stamping agent, wholesale dealer, and retail dealer who is subject to sections
77-2601 to 77-2622 shall make and file with the Tax Commissioner, on or before
the fifteenth day of each calendar
month on blanks furnished by the Tax Commissioner, true, correct, and sworn
reports covering, for the last preceding calendar month, the number of cigarettes
purchased, from whom purchased, the specific kinds and brands thereof, the
manufacturer, if known, and such other matters and in such detail as the Tax
Commissioner may require.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Each
manufacturer and importer that sells cigarettes in or into the state shall,
within fifteen days following the end of each month, file a report on a form
and in the manner prescribed by the Tax Commissioner and certify to the state
that the report is complete and accurate.</para><para>(b) The report shall contain the following
information: The total number of cigarettes sold by that manufacturer or importer
in or into the state during that month and identifying by name and number
of cigarettes, (i) the manufacturers of those cigarettes, (ii) the brand families
of those cigarettes, and (iii) the purchasers of those cigarettes. A manufacturer's
or importer's report shall include cigarettes sold in or into the state through
its sales entity affiliate.</para><para>(c) The requirements of this subsection
shall be satisfied and no further report shall be required under this section
with respect to cigarettes if the manufacturer or importer timely submits
to the Tax Commissioner the report or reports required to be submitted by
it with respect to those cigarettes under 15 U.S.C. 376 to the Tax Commissioner
and certifies to the state that the reports are complete and accurate.</para>
<para>(d) Upon request
by the Tax Commissioner, a manufacturer or importer shall provide copies of
all sales reports referenced in subdivisions (2)(a) and (b) of this section
that it filed in other states.</para><para>(e) Each manufacturer and importer that
sells cigarettes in or into the state shall either (i) submit its federal
excise tax returns and all monthly operational reports on Alcohol and Tobacco
Tax and Trade Bureau Form 5210.5 and all adjustments, changes, and amendments
to such reports to the Tax Commissioner no later than sixty days after the
close of the quarter in which the returns were filed or (ii) submit to the
United States Treasury a request or consent under section 6103(c) of the Internal
Revenue Code of 1986 as defined in section 49-801.01 authorizing the federal
Alcohol and Tobacco Tax and Trade Bureau and, in the case of a foreign manufacturer
or importer, the United States Customs Service to disclose the manufacturer's
or importer's federal returns to the Tax Commissioner as of sixty days after
the close of the quarter in which the returns were filed.</para>
<para>(3) The Tax
Commissioner may share the information reported under this section with the
taxing or law enforcement authorities of this state and other states.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 267, &#167; 4, p. 862; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 26.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2013</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
