<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2701.48"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2701.48</statuteno><catchline>Bundled transaction, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Bundled transaction means the retail sale of two or more products, except real property and services to real property, when (a) the products are otherwise distinct and identifiable and (b) the products are sold for one non-itemized price. Bundled transaction does not include the sale of any products in which the sales price varies, or is negotiable, based on the selection by the purchaser of the products included in the transaction.</para><para>(2) Distinct and identifiable products do not include:</para><para>(a) Packaging, such as containers, boxes, sacks, bags, and bottles or other materials such as wrapping, labels, tags, and instruction guides that accompany the retail sale of the products and are incidental or immaterial to the retail sale thereof. Examples of packaging that are incidental or immaterial include grocery sacks, shoeboxes, dry cleaning garment bags, and express delivery envelopes and boxes;</para><para>(b) A product provided free of charge with the required purchase of another product. A product is provided free of charge if the sales price of the product purchased does not vary depending on the inclusion of the product provided free of charge; and</para><para>(c) Items included in the definition of sales price pursuant to section 77-2701.35.</para><para>(3) One non-itemized price does not include a price that is separately identified by product on binding sales or other supporting sales-related documentation made available to the customer in paper or electronic form, including, but not limited to, an invoice, bill of sale, receipt, contract, service agreement, lease agreement, periodic notice of rates and services, rate card, or price list.</para><para>(4) A transaction that otherwise meets the definition of a bundled transaction is not a bundled transaction if it is (a) the retail sale of tangible personal property and a service where the tangible personal property is essential to the use of the service, and is provided exclusively in connection with the service, and the true object of the transaction is the service, (b) the retail sale of services when one service is provided that is essential to the use or receipt of a second service and the first service is provided exclusively in connection with the second service and the true object of the transaction is the second service, or (c) a transaction that includes taxable products and nontaxable products and the purchase price or sales price of the taxable products is de minimus. De minimus means the seller's purchase price or sales price of the taxable products is ten percent or less of the total purchase price or sales price of the bundled products. Sellers shall use either the purchase price or the sales price of the products to determine if the taxable products are de minimus. Sellers may not use a combination of the purchase price and sales price of the products to determine if the taxable products are de minimus. Sellers shall use the full term of a service contract to determine if the taxable products are de minimus.</para><para>(5) Bundled transaction does not include the retail sale of exempt tangible personal property and taxable tangible personal property if (a) the transaction includes food and food ingredients, drugs, durable medical equipment, mobility enhancing equipment, over-the-counter drugs, prosthetic devices, or medical supplies and (b) the seller's purchase price or sales price of the taxable tangible personal property is fifty percent or less of the total purchase price or sales price of the bundled tangible personal property. Sellers may not use a combination of the purchase price and sales price of the tangible personal property when making the fifty-percent determination for a transaction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>