<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2398"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2398</statuteno><catchline>Deposits in excess of insured or guaranteed amount; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) As an alternative to the requirements to secure the deposit of public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation pursuant to sections 77-2389 and 77-2394, a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a public depositary may secure the deposits of one or more governmental units by providing a deposit guaranty bond or by depositing, pledging, or granting a security interest in a single pool of securities or by a combination thereof to secure the repayment of all public money or public funds deposited in the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution by such governmental units and not otherwise secured pursuant to law, if at all times the total value of the deposit guaranty bond and the aggregate market value of the pool of securities so deposited, pledged, or in which a security interest is granted is at least equal to one hundred two percent of the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed. Each such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution shall carry on its accounting records at all times a general ledger or other appropriate account of the total amount of all public money or public funds to be secured by a deposit guaranty bond or by the pool of securities, or any combination thereof, as determined at the opening of business each day, and the total value of the deposit guaranty bond or the aggregate market value of the pool of securities deposited, pledged, or in which a security interest is granted to secure such public money or public funds. For purposes of this section, a pool of securities shall include shares of investment companies registered under the federal Investment Company Act of 1940 when the investment companies' assets are limited to obligations that are eligible for investment by the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution and limited by their prospectuses to owning securities enumerated in section 77-2387.</para><para>(2) A bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution may secure the deposit of public money or public funds using the dedicated method, the single bank pooled method, or both methods as set forth in subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(a) Under the dedicated method, a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution may secure the deposit of public money or public funds by each governmental unit separately by furnishing securities or providing a deposit guaranty bond, or any combination thereof, pursuant to the Public Funds Deposit Security Act.</para><para>(b)(i) Under the single bank pooled method, a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution may secure the deposit of public money or public funds of one or more governmental units by providing a deposit guaranty bond or through a pool of eligible securities established by such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution with a qualified trustee, or any combination thereof, to be held subject to the order of the director or the administrator for the benefit of the governmental units having public money or public funds with such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution as set forth in subsection (1) of this section. A bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution may not retain any deposit of public money or public funds which is required to be secured unless, within ten days thereafter or such shorter period as has been agreed upon by the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution and the director or administrator, it has secured the deposits for the benefit of the governmental units having public money or public funds with such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution pursuant to this section.</para><para>(ii) The director shall designate a bank, savings association, trust company, or other qualified firm, corporation, or association which is authorized to transact business in this state to serve as the administrator with respect to a single bank pooled method. Fees and expenses of such administrator shall be paid by the banks, capital stock financial institutions, or qualifying mutual financial institutions utilizing the single bank pooled method.</para><para>(iii) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution elects to secure the deposit of public money or public funds through the use of the single bank pooled method, such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution shall notify the administrator in writing that it has elected to utilize the single bank pooled method and the proposed effective date thereof.</para><para>(iv) The single bank pooled method shall not be utilized by any bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution unless an administrator has been designated by the director pursuant to subdivision (2)(b)(ii) of this section and is acting as the administrator.</para><para>(3) Only a deposit guaranty bond and the securities listed in subdivision (14) of section 77-2387 may be provided and accepted as security for the deposit of public money or public funds and shall be eligible as collateral. The qualified trustee shall not accept any securities which are not listed in subdivision (14) of section 77-2387.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB78, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB155, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB622, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB909, &#167; 52. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>