 <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id195"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id197" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-2704.09"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id199">77-2704.09</statuteno><catchline id="id200">Insulin; prescription drugs; mobility enhancing equipment; medical equipment; exemptions.</catchline> <para>(1) Sales and use taxes shall not be imposed on the gross receipts from the sale, lease, or rental of and the storage, use, or other consumption in this state of (a) insulin, (b) mobility enhancing equipment and drugs, not including over-the-counter drugs, when sold for a patient's use under a prescription, and (c) the following when sold for a patient's use under a prescription and which are of the type eligible for coverage under the medical assistance program established pursuant to the Medical Assistance Act: Durable medical equipment; home medical supplies; prosthetic devices; oxygen; and oxygen equipment.</para> <para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para> <para>(a) Drug means a compound, substance, preparation, and component of a compound, substance, or preparation, other than food and food ingredients, dietary supplements, or alcoholic beverages:</para> <para>(i) Recognized in the official United States Pharmacopoeia, official Homeopathic Pharmacopoeia of the United States, or official National Formulary, and any supplement to any of them;</para> <para>(ii) Intended for use in the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of disease; or</para> <para>(iii) Intended to affect the structure or any function of the body;</para> <para>(b) Durable medical equipment means equipment which can withstand repeated use, is primarily and customarily used to serve a medical purpose, generally is not useful to a person in the absence of illness or injury, is appropriate for use in the home, and is not worn in or on the body. Durable medical equipment includes repair and replacement parts for such equipment;</para> <para>(c) Home medical supplies means supplies primarily and customarily used to serve a medical purpose which are appropriate for use in the home and are generally not useful to a person in the absence of illness or injury;</para> <para>(d) Mobility enhancing equipment means equipment which is primarily and customarily used to provide or increase the ability to move from one place to another, which is not generally used by persons with normal mobility, and which is appropriate for use either in a home or a motor vehicle. Mobility enhancing equipment includes repair and replacement parts for such equipment. Mobility enhancing equipment does not include any motor vehicle or equipment on a motor vehicle normally provided by a motor vehicle manufacturer;</para> <para>(e) Over-the-counter drug means a drug that contains a label that identifies the product as a drug as required by 21 C.F.R. 201.66, as such regulation existed on January 1, 2003. The over-the-counter drug label includes a drug facts panel or a statement of the active ingredients with a list of those ingredients contained in the compound, substance, or preparation;</para> <para>(f) Oxygen equipment means oxygen cylinders, cylinder transport devices including sheaths and carts, cylinder studs and support devices, regulators, flowmeters, tank wrenches, oxygen concentrators, liquid oxygen base dispensers, liquid oxygen portable dispensers, oxygen tubing, nasal cannulas, face masks, oxygen humidifiers, and oxygen fittings and accessories;</para> <para>(g) Prescription means an order, formula, or recipe issued in any form of oral, written, electronic, or other means of transmission by a duly licensed practitioner authorized under the Uniform Credentialing Act; and</para> <para>(h) Prosthetic devices means a replacement, corrective, or supportive device worn on or in the body to artificially replace a missing portion of the body, prevent or correct physical deformity or malfunction, or support a weak or deformed portion of the body, and includes any supplies used with such device and repair and replacement parts.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 871, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 901, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 280, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 256, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1248, &#167; 85; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB463, &#167; 1308; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB916, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB165, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Medical Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 68-901.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Credentialing Act,</emphasis> see section 38-101.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>