<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="July 1, 2010">Section 1.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id54" statutenumber="77-27,137.02">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id56">77-27,137.02</statuteno><catchline id="id57">Aid to natural
resources districts; distribution; manner.</catchline><para>The appropriation
made pursuant to the authority in section 77-27,136 for aid to natural resources
districts shall be distributed to the various natural resources districts
of the state on the basis of the ratio of the total amount of property taxes
levied by the particular natural resources district to the total amount of
property taxes levied by all natural resources districts within the state
based on amounts stated in the most recent certificate of taxes levied statement
and schedules submitted by each county pursuant to section 77-1613.01. For purposes of calculating the ratio
in this section, in determining the total amount of property taxes levied
by natural resources districts, the total shall exclude those property taxes
levied for the payment of principal or interest on bonds. The
Tax Commissioner shall determine the amount to be distributed to the various
natural resources districts and certify such amounts by voucher to the Director
of Administrative Services. Each amount shall be distributed in seven as nearly
as possible equal monthly payments between the fifth and twentieth day of
each month beginning December 1, 1982, and each December thereafter. The State
Treasurer shall, between the fifth and twentieth day of each month, notify
the Director of Administrative Services of the amount of funds available in
the General Fund for payment purposes. The Director of Administrative Services
shall, upon receipt of such notification and vouchers, draw warrants against
funds appropriated. The proceeds of the payments received by the various natural
resources districts shall be credited to the general fund of the district.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 816, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 268, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 480, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 108, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 109; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB218, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB210, &#167;  1.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>