<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id397">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id399" statutenumber="77-2612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2612</statuteno><catchline id="id402">Tax Commissioner;
personnel; rules and regulations; stamping
agent; license; fee.</catchline>
<para>The Tax Commissioner may employ, with the advice and consent
of the Governor, a sufficient number of inspectors, clerks, assistants, and
agents to enforce sections 77-2601 to 77-2622, including the collection of all
stamp taxes and all revenue from cigarette tax meters. In such enforcement,
the Tax Commissioner may call to his or her aid the Attorney General, any
county attorney, any sheriff, any deputy sheriff, or any other peace officer.
The compensation of all persons employed shall be fixed by the Governor and
shall be paid from the revenue derived under such sections. The expenses
of administering such sections, including necessary assistants,
clerical help, cost of enforcement, cost of stamps, and incidental expenses,
when approved by the Tax Commissioner, shall be paid by warrants, issued against
the General Fund, but such warrants shall not exceed four percent of the funds
collected under such sections, such expenses in each instance
to be approved by the Tax Commissioner.</para>
<para>The Tax Commissioner may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations
which are consistent with sections 77-2601 to 77-2622 and their proper enforcement.</para>
<para>Each stamping
agent shall annually apply to the Tax Commissioner, upon forms
to be furnished by the Tax Commissioner, for
a license to use the tax meter
machines, as set forth in section 77-2603, or to purchase such stamps as provided
in section 77-2608, or both. The license shall expire on December
31 each year. Each wholesale dealer applying
for a stamping agent license shall furnish with such application
evidence satisfactory to the Tax Commissioner showing that the
wholesale dealer has obtained a license as a wholesale dealer
in accordance with section 28-1423. The applicant shall
accompany the application with a fee of five hundred dollars to be placed
in the General Fund if the license is granted and otherwise
to be returned to the applicant. If the applicant is an individual, the application
shall include the applicant's social security number. If the application is
approved and the bond referred to in section 77-2603 is given and approved,
if such bond is required under section 77-2603, the Tax Commissioner shall
issue such license which shall be conspicuously posted in the place of business
of such stamping agent.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 267, &#167; 12, p. 864; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 353, &#167; 8, p. 1246; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 501, &#167; 5, p. 1597; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 500, &#167; 3, p. 1591; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 364, &#167; 19, p. 1193; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 748, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 211; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 989, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB590, &#167; 32.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>