<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id5" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-27,235"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,235</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Renewable energy
tax credit; Department of Revenue; powers.</catchline><para>(1) Any producer
of electricity generated by a new renewable electric generation facility
shall earn a renewable energy tax credit. For electricity generated on or
after July 14, 2006, and before October 1, 2007, the credit shall be .075
cent for each kilowatt-hour of electricity generated by a new renewable
electric generation facility. For electricity generated on or
after October 1, 2007, and before January 1, 2010, the credit shall be .1
cent for each kilowatt-hour of electricity generated by a new renewable
electric generation facility. For electricity generated on or
after January 1, 2010, and before January 1, 2013, the credit shall be .075
cent per kilowatt-hour for electricity generated by a new renewable
electric generation facility. For electricity generated on or
after January 1, 2013, the credit shall be .05 cent per kilowatt-hour
for electricity generated by a new renewable electric generation facility.
The credit may be earned for production of electricity for ten years after
the date that the facility is placed in operation on or after July 14, 2006.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this section:</para>
<para>(a) Electricity generated by a new renewable
electric generation facility means electricity that is exclusively
produced by a new renewable electric generation facility;</para>
<para>(b) Eligible renewable resources means wind, moving water,
solar, geothermal, fuel cell, methane gas, or photovoltaic technology; and</para>
<para>(c) New renewable electric generation facility
means an electrical generating facility located in this state that is first
placed into service on or after July 14, 2006, which utilizes eligible renewable
resources as its fuel source.</para>
<para>(3) The credit allowed under this section may be used to reduce
the producer's Nebraska income tax liability or to obtain a refund of state
sales and use taxes paid by the producer of electricity generated by a new renewable electric generation facility.
A claim to use the credit for refund of the state sales and use taxes paid,
either directly or indirectly, by the producer may be filed quarterly for
electricity generated during the previous quarter by the twentieth day of
the month following the end of the calendar quarter. The credit may be used
to obtain a refund of state sales and use taxes paid during the quarter immediately
preceding the quarter in which the claim for refund is made, except that the
amount refunded under this subsection shall not exceed the amount of the state
sales and use taxes paid during the quarter.</para>
<para>(4) The Department of Revenue may adopt and promulgate rules
and regulations to permit verification of the validity and timeliness of any
renewable energy tax credit claimed.</para>

<para>(5) The total amount of renewable
energy tax credits that may be used by all taxpayers shall be limited to fifty thousand
dollars without further authorization from the Legislature.</para>
<para>(6) The credit allowed under
this section may not be claimed by a producer who received a sales tax exemption
under section 77-2704.57 for the new renewable electric generation facility.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 872, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB367, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB360, &#167; 3.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2011</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>