<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id490">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id492" statutenumber="77-27,130"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-27,130</statuteno><catchline id="id495">Tax Commissioner;
tax; deficiency; disallowed by court; effect; frivolous objections; damages.</catchline>
<para>(1) If the amount of a deficiency determined by the Tax Commissioner
is disallowed in whole or in part by the court of review, the amount so disallowed
shall be credited or refunded to the taxpayer without the making of a claim
therefor or, if payment has not been made, shall be abated.</para>
<para>(2) If the deficiency determined by the Tax Commissioner
is disallowed by the court of review, the taxpayer shall have his or her costs
as they would be allowable under the provisions of section 77-27,129. If the
deficiency is disallowed in part, the court in its discretion may award the
taxpayer a proportionate part of his or her costs.</para>
<para>(3) An assessment of a proposed income deficiency by the
Tax Commissioner shall become final upon the expiration of the period specified
in section 77-2777 for filing a written protest against the proposed assessment
if no such protest has been filed within the time provided or, if the protest
provided in section 77-2778 has been filed, upon the expiration of time provided
for filing a petition for judicial review, upon the final judgment of the
reviewing court, or upon the rendering by the Tax Commissioner of a decision
pursuant to the mandate of the reviewing court. Notwithstanding the foregoing,
for the purpose of making a petition for the review of a determination of
the Tax Commissioner, the determination shall be deemed final on the date
the notice of decision is mailed to the taxpayer as provided in section
77-2779.</para>
<para>(4) If any person institutes proceedings merely for delay
or raises frivolous objections to compliance with the Nebraska Revenue Act
of 1967, the Tax Commissioner may apply to a judge of the district court for
the county where such person resides for damages in an amount not in excess
of five thousand dollars for each tax year to be awarded to the State of Nebraska
for expenses incurred by the Tax Commissioner in securing compliance. Damages
so awarded by the court shall be payable upon notice and demand by the Tax
Commissioner and shall be collected in the same manner as delinquent taxes
under such act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 487, &#167; 130, p. 1635; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 962, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 43.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>