<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id93">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id95" statutenumber="77-2703.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2703.01</statuteno><catchline id="id98">General sourcing
rules.</catchline><para>(1) The determination of whether a sale
or use of property or the provision of services is in this state, in a municipality
that has adopted a tax under the Local Option Revenue Act, or in a county
that has adopted a tax under section 13-319 shall be governed by the sourcing
rules in sections 77-2703.01 to 77-2703.04.</para>
<para>(2) When the property or service is received by the purchaser
at a business location of the retailer, the sale is sourced to that business
location.</para>
<para>(3) When the property or service is not received by the purchaser
at a business location of the retailer, the sale is sourced to the location
where receipt by the purchaser or the purchaser's donee, designated as such
by the purchaser, occurs, including the location indicated by instructions
for delivery to the purchaser or donee, known to the retailer.</para>
<para>(4) When subsection (2) or (3) of this section does not apply,
the sale is sourced to the location indicated by an address or other information
for the purchaser that is available from the business records of the retailer
that are maintained in the ordinary course of the retailer's business when
use of this address does not constitute bad faith.</para>
<para>(5) When subsection (2), (3), or (4) of this section does
not apply, the sale is sourced to the location indicated by an address for
the purchaser obtained during the consummation of the sale, including the
address of a purchaser's payment instrument, if no other address is available,
when use of this address does not constitute bad faith.</para>
<para>(6) When subsection (2), (3), (4), or (5) of this section
does not apply, including the circumstance in which the retailer is without
sufficient information to apply the rules in any such subsection, then the
location will be determined by the address from which property was shipped,
from which the digital good was first available for transmission by the retailer,
or from which the service was provided disregarding for these purposes any
location that merely provided the digital transfer of the product sold.</para>
<para>(7) The lease or rental of tangible personal property, other
than property identified in subsection (8) or (9) of this section, shall be
sourced as follows:</para>
<para>(a) For a lease or rental that requires recurring periodic
payments, the first periodic payment is sourced the same as a retail sale
in accordance with the provisions of subsections (2) through (6) of this section.
Periodic payments made subsequent to the first payment are sourced to the
primary property location for each period covered by the payment. The primary
property location shall be as indicated by an address for the property provided
by the lessee that is available to the lessor from its records maintained
in the ordinary course of business when use of this address does not constitute
bad faith. The property location shall not be altered by intermittent use
at different locations, such as use of business property that accompanies
employees on business trips and service calls; and</para>
<para>(b) For a lease or rental that does not require recurring
periodic payments, the payment is sourced the same as a retail sale in accordance
with the provisions of subsections (2) through (6) of this section.</para>
<para>This subsection does not affect the imposition or computation
of sales or use tax on leases or rentals based on a lump-sum or accelerated
basis or on the acquisition of property for lease.</para>
<para>(8) The lease or rental of motor vehicles, trailers, semitrailers,
or aircraft that do not qualify as transportation equipment under subsection
(9) of this section shall be sourced as follows:</para>
<para>(a) For a lease or rental that requires recurring periodic
payments, each periodic payment is sourced to the primary property location.
The primary property location shall be as indicated by an address for the
property provided by the lessee that is available to the lessor from its records
maintained in the ordinary course of business when use of this address does
not constitute bad faith. This location shall not be altered by intermittent
use at different locations; and</para>
<para>(b) For a lease or rental that does not require recurring
periodic payments, the payment is sourced the same as a retail sale in accordance
with the provisions of subsections (2) through (6) of this section.</para>
<para>This subsection does not affect the imposition or computation
of sales or use tax on leases or rentals based on a lump-sum or accelerated
basis or on the acquisition of property for lease.</para>
<para>(9) The retail sale, including lease or rental, of transportation
equipment shall be sourced the same as a retail sale in accordance with subsections
(2) through (6) of this section. Transportation equipment means any of the
following:</para>
<para>(a) Locomotives and railcars that are utilized for the carriage
of persons or property in interstate commerce;</para>
<para>(b) Trucks and truck-tractors with a gross vehicle weight
rating of ten thousand one pounds or greater, trailers, semitrailers, or passenger
buses that are (i) registered through the International Registration Plan
and (ii) operated under authority of a carrier authorized and certificated
by the United States Department of Transportation or another federal authority
to engage in the carriage of persons or property in interstate commerce;</para>
<para>(c) Aircraft operated by air carriers authorized and certificated
by the United States Department of Transportation or another federal authority
or a foreign authority to engage in the carriage of persons or property in
interstate or foreign commerce; and</para>
<para>(d) Containers designed for use on and component parts attached
or secured on the items set forth in subdivisions (9)(a) through (c) of this
section.</para>
<para>(10) For purposes of this section, receive and receipt mean
taking possession of tangible personal property, making first use of services,
or taking possession or making first use of digital goods, whichever comes
first. The terms receive and receipt do not include possession by a shipping
company on behalf of the purchaser. For purposes of sourcing detective services
subject to tax under subdivision (4)(h) of section 77-2701.16, making first
use of a service shall be deemed to be at the individual's residence, in the
case of a customer who is an individual, or at the principal place of business,
in the case of a business customer.</para>
<para>(11) The sale, not including lease or rental, of a motor
vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer as defined in the Motor Vehicle Registration
Act shall be sourced to the place of registration of the motor vehicle, semitrailer,
or trailer for operation upon the highways of this state or, if no such registration has occurred, the place where
such motor vehicle, semitrailer, or trailer is required to be registered.</para>
<para>(12) The sale or lease for one year or more of motorboats
shall be sourced to the place of registration of the motorboat. The lease
of motorboats for less than one year shall be sourced to the point of delivery.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 282, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 759, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1017, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 275; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB367, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB916, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB851, &#167; 11.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2014</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Local Option Revenue Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,148.</para><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>