<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2395"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2395</statuteno><catchline>Custodial official; duties.</catchline> <para>(1) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a depository furnishes securities pursuant to section 77-2389, the custodial official shall not have on deposit in such depository any public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, unless and until the depository has furnished to the custodial official securities, the market value of which are in an amount not less than one hundred two percent of the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed.</para> <para>(2) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a depository furnishes securities pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-2398, the custodial official shall not have on deposit in such depository any public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, unless and until the depository has furnished to the custodial official securities, the market value of which are in an amount not less than one hundred five percent of the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed.</para> <para>(3) If a bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial institution designated as a depository provides a deposit guaranty bond pursuant to the Public Funds Deposit Security Act, the custodial official shall not have on deposit in such depository any public money or public funds in excess of the amount insured or guaranteed by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, unless and until the depository has provided to the custodial official a deposit guaranty bond in an amount not less than the amount on deposit which is in excess of the amount so insured or guaranteed.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1274, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 932, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 90; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 30.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>