<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section><?Pub Caret1?>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-2734.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-2734.01</statuteno><catchline>Small business corporation shareholders;
limited liability company members; determination of income; credit; Tax Commissioner;
powers; return; when required.</catchline><para>(1) Residents of Nebraska
who are shareholders of a small business corporation having an election in
effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code or who are members
of a limited liability company organized pursuant to the Nebraska
Uniform Limited Liability Company Act shall include in their Nebraska taxable
income, to the extent includable in federal gross income, their proportionate
share of such corporation's or limited liability company's federal income
adjusted pursuant to this section. Income or loss from such corporation or
limited liability company conducting a business, trade, profession, or occupation
shall be included in the Nebraska taxable income of a shareholder or member
who is a resident of this state to the extent of such shareholder's or member's
proportionate share of the net income or loss from the conduct of such business,
trade, profession, or occupation within this state, determined under subsection
(2) of this section. A resident of Nebraska shall include in Nebraska taxable
income fair compensation for services rendered to such corporation or limited
liability company. Compensation actually paid shall be presumed to be fair
unless it is apparent to the Tax Commissioner that such compensation is materially
different from fair value for the services rendered or has been manipulated
for tax avoidance purposes.</para>
<para>(2) The income of any small business corporation having an election
in effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code or limited liability
company organized pursuant to the Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability
Company Act that is derived from or connected with Nebraska sources shall
be determined in the following manner:</para>
<para>(a) If the small business corporation is a member of a unitary group,
the small business corporation shall be deemed to be doing business within
this state if any part of its income is derived from transactions with other
members of the unitary group doing business within this state, and such corporation
shall apportion its income by using the apportionment factor determined for
the entire unitary group, including the small business corporation, under
sections 77-2734.05 to 77-2734.15;</para>
<para>(b) If the small business corporation or limited liability company is
not a member of a unitary group and is subject to tax in another state, it
shall apportion its income under sections 77-2734.05 to 77-2734.15; and</para>
<para>(c) If the small business corporation or limited liability company is
not subject to tax in another state, all of its income is derived from or
connected with Nebraska sources.</para>
<para>(3) Nonresidents of Nebraska who are shareholders of such corporations
or members of such limited liability companies shall file a Nebraska income
tax return and shall include in Nebraska adjusted gross income their proportionate
share of the corporation's or limited liability company's Nebraska income
as determined under subsection (2) of this section.</para>
<para>(4) The nonresident shareholder or member shall execute and forward
to the corporation or limited liability company before the filing of the corporation's
or limited liability company's return an agreement which states he or she
will file a Nebraska income tax return and pay the tax on the income derived
from or connected with sources in this state, and such agreement shall be
attached to the corporation's or limited liability company's Nebraska return
for such taxable year.</para>
<para>(5) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin before January 1,
2013, in the absence of the nonresident shareholder's or member's executed
agreement being attached to the Nebraska return, the corporation or limited
liability company shall remit with the return an amount equal to the highest
individual income tax rate determined under section 77-2715.02 multiplied
by the nonresident shareholder's or member's share of the corporation's or
limited liability company's income which was derived from or attributable
to this state. For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after
January 1, 2013, in the absence of the nonresident shareholder's or member's
executed agreement being attached to the Nebraska return, the corporation
or limited liability company shall remit with the return an amount equal to
the highest individual income tax rate determined under section 77-2715.03
multiplied by the nonresident shareholder's or member's share of the corporation's
or limited liability company's income which was derived from or attributable
to this state. The amount remitted shall be allowed as a credit against the
Nebraska income tax liability of the shareholder or member.</para>
<para>(6) The Tax Commissioner may allow a nonresident individual shareholder
or member to not file a Nebraska income tax return if the nonresident individual
shareholder's or member's only source of Nebraska income was his or her share
of the small business corporation's or limited liability company's income
which was derived from or attributable to sources within this state, the nonresident
did not file an agreement to file a Nebraska income tax return, and the small
business corporation or limited liability company has remitted the amount
required by subsection (5) of this section on behalf of such nonresident individual
shareholder or member. The amount remitted shall be retained in satisfaction
of the Nebraska income tax liability of the nonresident individual shareholder
or member.</para>
<para>(7) A small business corporation or limited liability company return
shall be filed only if one or more of the shareholders of the corporation
or members of the limited liability company are not residents of the State
of Nebraska or if such corporation or limited liability company has income
derived from sources outside this state.</para>
<para>(8) For purposes of this section, any shareholder or member of the corporation
or limited liability company that is a grantor trust of a nonresident shall
be disregarded and this section shall apply as though the nonresident grantor
was the shareholder or member.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1984, LB 1124, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 273, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 773, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 773, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 508; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 216, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB915, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 105; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB970, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB283, &#167; 7.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act,</emphasis> see section 21-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>