<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3209"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3209</statuteno><catchline>Authority; set up accounts; proceeds; how disbursed.</catchline><para>(1) The authority shall set up accounts on its books relating to the operation, management, or other expense of each individual parcel of real estate.</para><para>(2) When any parcel of real estate is sold or otherwise disposed of by the authority, the proceeds therefrom shall be applied and distributed in the following order, except as provided for in section 77-3206:</para><para>(a) To the payment of the expenses of sale, the costs of the care, improvement, operation, demolition, management, and administration of such parcels of real estate as determined by the commissioners and apportioned to such parcel;</para><para>(b) To the payment of any penalties, fees, or costs which were included in the judgment originally entered against such parcel of real estate, plus its proportional part of the costs of the sheriff's foreclosure sale, as shown by the court records; and</para><para>(c) The balance shall be paid to the respective taxing authorities and tax bill owners, if any, in the proportion that the principal amounts of the tax bills of each such party bears to the total principal amount of all the tax bills included in the original judgment relating to such parcel of real estate and in the order of their respective priorities. After deduction of all sums charged to each account for various expenses, distribution shall be made to the respective taxing authorities and to tax bill owners having an interest in such parcel of real estate on January 1 and July 1 of each year and at such other times as the commissioners in their discretion may determine.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 73, &#167; 9. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 