<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3003"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3003</statuteno><catchline>Distributor; license; application; limitations; background check; cause for denial; disciplinary action; fee; cash device winnings; duty to check collection system.</catchline><para>(1) Any distributor shall be required to procure an annual license from the Tax Commissioner permitting him or her to place and either directly or indirectly control or manage a mechanical amusement device within the State of Nebraska. The Tax Commissioner, upon the application of any person, may issue a license, subject to the same limitations as an operator's license under section 77-3002. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number.</para><para>(2)(a) Except for an applicant that holds a liquor license under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act, an applicant for a license as a distributor of a cash device shall be subject to a one-time background check by the department prior to issuance of the license. An applicant shall pay the costs associated with the background check along with any required fees as determined by the department.</para><para>(b) The Tax Commissioner has the authority to deny any application for a license as a distributor of a cash device for cause. Cause for denial of a license application includes instances in which the applicant individually, or in the case of a business entity, any officer, director, employee, or limited liability company member of the applicant or licensee other than an employee whose duties are purely ministerial in nature:</para><para>(i) Violated the provisions, requirements, conditions, limitations, or duties imposed by the Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act;</para><para>(ii) Knowingly caused, aided, abetted, or conspired with another to cause any person to violate any of the provisions of the act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act;</para><para>(iii) Obtained a license or permit under the act by fraud, misrepresentation, or concealment;</para><para>(iv) Has been convicted of, forfeited bond upon a charge of, or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to any offense or crime, whether a felony or a misdemeanor, involving any gambling activity or fraud, theft, willful failure to make required payments or reports, or filing false reports with a governmental agency at any level;</para><para>(v) Denied the department or its authorized representatives, including authorized law enforcement agencies, access to any place where activity required to be licensed under the act is being conducted or failed to produce for inspection or audit any book, record, document, or item required by law, rule, or regulation;</para><para>(vi) Made a misrepresentation of or failed to disclose a material fact to the department;</para><para>(vii) Failed to prove by clear and convincing evidence such applicant's qualifications to be licensed in accordance with the act;</para><para>(viii) Failed to pay any taxes and additions to taxes, including penalties and interest required by the act or any other taxes imposed pursuant to the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967; or</para><para>(ix) Has been cited for a violation of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act and had a liquor license suspended, canceled, or revoked by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission for illegal gambling activities on or about the premises licensed by the commission pursuant to the Nebraska Liquor Control Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to such act.</para><para>(c) No renewal of a license issued pursuant to this section shall be issued when the applicant for renewal would not be eligible for a license upon a first application.</para><para>(3) Beginning January 1, 2025, the annual license for a distributor of a cash device shall be accompanied by a fee of one hundred dollars per cash device up to a maximum of five thousand dollars.</para><para>(4) The Tax Commissioner has the authority to suspend or revoke the license of any distributor that is in violation of the Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act.</para><para>(5) Beginning on the implementation date designated by the Tax Commissioner pursuant to subsection (2) of section 9-1312, prior to the winnings payment of any cash device winnings as defined in section 9-1303, a distributor of a cash device shall check the collection system to determine if the winner has a debt or an outstanding state tax liability as required by the Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act. If such distributor determines that the winner is subject to the collection system, the distributor shall deduct the amount of debt and outstanding state tax liability identified in the collection system from the winnings payment and shall remit the net winnings payment of cash device winnings, if any, to the winner and the amount deducted to the Department of Revenue to be credited against such debt or outstanding state tax liability as provided in section 9-1306.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 635, &#167; 3, p. 2542; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 317, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 214; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB685, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1317, &#167; 87. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act,</emphasis> see section 9-1301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>