<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3444"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3444</statuteno><catchline>Authority to exceed maximum levy; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) A political subdivision may exceed the limits provided in section 77-3442 or a final levy allocation determination as provided in section 77-3443 by an amount not to exceed a maximum levy approved by a majority of registered voters voting on the issue in a primary, general, or special election at which the issue is placed before the registered voters. A vote to exceed the limits provided in section 77-3442 or a final levy allocation as provided in section 77-3443 must be approved prior to October 10 of the fiscal year which is to be the first to exceed the limits or final levy allocation. The governing body of the political subdivision may call for the submission of the issue to the voters (a) by passing a resolution calling for exceeding the limits or final levy allocation by a vote of at least two-thirds of the members of the governing body and delivering a copy of the resolution to the county clerk or election commissioner of every county which contains all or part of the political subdivision or (b) upon receipt of a petition by the county clerk or election commissioner of every county containing all or part of the political subdivision requesting an election signed by at least five percent of the registered voters residing in the political subdivision. The resolution or petition shall include the amount of levy which would be imposed in excess of the limits provided in section 77-3442 or the final levy allocation as provided in section 77-3443 and the duration of the excess levy authority. The excess levy authority shall not have a duration greater than five years. Any resolution or petition calling for a special election shall be filed with the county clerk or election commissioner no later than thirty days prior to the date of the election, and the time of publication and providing a copy of the notice of election required in section 32-802 shall be no later than twenty days prior to the election. The county clerk or election commissioner shall place the issue on the ballot at an election as called for in the resolution or petition which is at least thirty days after receipt of the resolution or petition. The election shall be held pursuant to the Election Act. For petitions filed with the county clerk or election commissioner on or after May 1, 1998, the petition shall be in the form as provided in sections 32-628 to 32-631. Any excess levy authority approved under this section shall terminate pursuant to its terms, on a vote of the governing body of the political subdivision to terminate the authority to levy more than the limits, at the end of the fourth fiscal year following the first year in which the levy exceeded the limit or the final levy allocation, or as provided in subsection (4) of this section, whichever is earliest. A governing body may pass no more than one resolution calling for an election pursuant to this section during any one calendar year. Only one election may be held in any one calendar year pursuant to a petition initiated under this section.</para><para>(2) The ballot question may include any terms and conditions set forth in the resolution or petition and shall include the following: "Shall (name of political subdivision) be allowed to levy a property tax not to exceed ............ cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation in excess of the limits prescribed by law until fiscal year ............ for the purposes of (general operations; building construction, remodeling, or site acquisition; or both general operations and building construction, remodeling, or site acquisition)?". If a majority of the votes cast upon the ballot question are in favor of such tax, the county board shall authorize a tax in excess of the limits in section 77-3442 or the final levy allocation in section 77-3443 but such tax shall not exceed the amount stated in the ballot question. If a majority of those voting on the ballot question are opposed to such tax, the governing body of the political subdivision shall not impose such tax.</para><para>(3) In lieu of the election procedures in subsection (1) of this section, any political subdivision subject to section 77-3443 and villages may approve a levy in excess of the limits in section 77-3442 or the final levy allocation provided in section 77-3443 for a period of one year at a meeting of the residents of the political subdivision or village, called after notice is published in a newspaper of general circulation in the political subdivision or village at least twenty days prior to the meeting. At least ten percent of the registered voters residing in the political subdivision or village shall constitute a quorum for purposes of taking action to exceed the limits or final levy allocation. A record shall be made of the registered voters residing in the political subdivision or village who are present at the meeting. The method of voting at the meeting shall protect the secrecy of the ballot. If a majority of the registered voters present at the meeting vote in favor of exceeding the limits or final levy allocation, a copy of the record of that action shall be forwarded to the county board prior to October 10 and the county board shall authorize a levy as approved by the residents for the year. If a majority of the registered voters present at the meeting vote against exceeding the limits or final allocation, the limit or allocation shall not be exceeded and the political subdivision shall have no power to call for an election under subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(4) A political subdivision may rescind or modify a previously approved excess levy authority prior to its expiration by a majority of registered voters voting on the issue in a primary, general, or special election at which the issue is placed before the registered voters. A vote to rescind or modify must be approved prior to October 10 of the fiscal year for which it is to be effective. The governing body of the political subdivision may call for the submission of the issue to the voters (a) by passing a resolution calling for the rescission or modification by a vote of at least two-thirds of the members of the governing body and delivering a copy of the resolution to the county clerk or election commissioner of every county which contains all or part of the political subdivision or (b) upon receipt of a petition by the county clerk or election commissioner of every county containing all or part of the political subdivision requesting an election signed by at least five percent of the registered voters residing in the political subdivision. The resolution or petition shall include the amount and the duration of the previously approved excess levy authority and a statement that either such excess levy authority will be rescinded or such excess levy authority will be modified. If the excess levy authority will be modified, the amount and duration of such modification shall be stated. The modification shall not have a duration greater than five years. The county clerk or election commissioner shall place the issue on the ballot at an election as called for in the resolution or petition which is at least thirty days after receipt of the resolution or petition, and the time of publication and providing a copy of the notice of election required in section 32-802 shall be no later than twenty days prior to the election. The election shall be held pursuant to the Election Act.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, when the political subdivision is a sanitary and improvement district, registered voter means a person qualified to vote as provided in section 31-735. Any election conducted under this section for a sanitary and improvement district shall be conducted and counted as provided in sections 31-735 to 31-735.06.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section, when the political subdivision is a school district or a multiple-district school system, registered voter includes persons qualified to vote for the members of the school board of the school district which is voting to exceed the maximum levy limits pursuant to this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 343, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 806, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 141, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB289, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB377, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2019</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Election Act,</emphasis> see section 32-101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>