<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id46" statutenumber="77-3517"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3517</statuteno><catchline id="id49">Homestead; application for exemption; county assessor; Tax Commissioner; duties; refunds; liens; interest.</catchline><para>(1) On or before August 1 of each year, the county assessor shall forward the approved applications for homestead exemptions and a copy of the certification of disability status that have been examined pursuant to section 77-3516 to the Tax Commissioner. The Tax Commissioner shall determine if the applicant meets the income requirements and may also review any other application information he or she deems necessary in order to determine whether the application should be approved. The Tax Commissioner shall, on or before November 1, certify his or her determinations to the county assessor. If the application is approved, the county assessor shall make the proper deduction on the assessment rolls. If the application is denied or approved in part, the Tax Commissioner shall notify the applicant of the denial or partial approval by mailing written notice to the applicant at the address shown on the application. The applicant may appeal the Tax Commissioner's denial or partial approval pursuant to section 77-3520. Late applications authorized under section 77-3512 shall be processed in a similar manner after approval by the county assessor. If the Tax Commissioner approves a late application after any of the real estate taxes in question become delinquent, such delinquency and any interest associated with the amount of the approved exemption shall be removed from the tax rolls of the county within thirty days after the county assessor receives notice from the Tax Commissioner of the approved exemption.</para><para>(2)(a) Upon his or her own action or upon a request by an applicant, a spouse, or an owner-occupant, the Tax Commissioner may review any information necessary to determine whether an application is in compliance with sections 77-3501 to 77-3529. Any action taken by the Tax Commissioner pursuant to this subsection shall be taken within three years after December 31 of the year in which the exemption was claimed.</para><para>(b) If after completion of the review the Tax Commissioner determines that an exemption should have been approved or increased, the Tax Commissioner shall notify the applicant, spouse, or owner-occupant and the county treasurer and assessor of his or her determination. The applicant, spouse, or owner-occupant shall receive a refund of the tax, if any, that was paid as a result of the exemption being denied, in whole or in part. The county treasurer shall make the refund and shall amend the county's claim for reimbursement from the state.</para><para>(c) If after completion of the review the Tax Commissioner determines that an exemption should have been denied or reduced, the Tax Commissioner shall notify the applicant, spouse, or owner-occupant of such denial or reduction. The applicant, the spouse, and any owner-occupant may appeal the Tax Commissioner's denial or reduction pursuant to section 77-3520. Upon the expiration of the appeal period in section 77-3520, the Tax Commissioner shall notify the county assessor of the denial or reduction and the county assessor shall remove or reduce the exemption from the tax rolls of the county. Upon notification by the Tax Commissioner to the county assessor, the amount of tax due as a result of the action of the Tax Commissioner shall become a lien on the homestead until paid. Upon attachment of the lien, the county treasurer shall refund to the Tax Commissioner the amount of tax equal to the denied or reduced exemption for deposit into the General Fund. No lien shall be created if a change in ownership of the homestead or death of the applicant, the spouse, and all other owner-occupants has occurred prior to the Tax Commissioner's notice to the county assessor. Beginning thirty days after the county assessor receives approval from the county board to remove or reduce the exemption from the tax rolls of the county, interest at the rate specified in section 45-104.01, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted by the Legislature, shall begin to accrue on the amount of tax due.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 65, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 647, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1258, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 376A, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 84, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 9, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 773, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 133, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 499, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1039, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB877, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1087, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB217, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB313, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB126, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>