<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3604</statuteno><catchline>Child care and education provider; income tax credit; application; contents; approval; distribution.</catchline><para>(1) A child care and education provider whose eligible program provides services to children who participate in the child care subsidy program established pursuant to section 68-1202 may apply to the department to receive a nonrefundable tax credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967.</para><para>(2) The nonrefundable credit provided in this section shall be an amount equal to the average monthly number of children described in subsection (1) of this section who are attending the child care and education provider's eligible program, multiplied by an amount based upon the quality scale rating of such eligible program as follows:</para><para><table frame="none"><tgroup align="left" cols="2"><colspec align="left" colname="col1" colwidth="1.23*" /><colspec align="right" colname="col2" colwidth="1*" /><tbody><row rowsep=""><entry>Quality Scale Rating of Eligible Program</entry><entry>Tax Credit Per Child Attending</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Eligible Program</entry></row><row><entry>Step Five</entry><entry>$1,200</entry></row><row><entry>Step Four</entry><entry>$1,000</entry></row><row><entry>Step Three</entry><entry>$800</entry></row><row><entry>Step Two</entry><entry>$600</entry></row><row><entry>Step One</entry><entry>$400</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para><para>(3) A child care and education provider shall apply for the credit provided in this section by submitting an application to the department with the following information:</para><para>(a) The number of children described in subsection (1) of this section who attended the child care and education provider's eligible program during each month of the most recently completed taxable year;</para><para>(b) Documentation to show the quality scale rating of the child care and education provider's eligible program; and</para><para>(c) Any other documentation required by the department.</para><para>(4) Subject to subsection (5) of this section, if the department determines that the child care and education provider qualifies for tax credits under this section, it shall approve the application and certify the amount of credits approved to the child care and education provider.</para><para>(5) The department shall consider applications in the order in which they are received and may approve tax credits under this section in any taxable year until the aggregate limit allowed under subsection (1) of section 77-3606 has been reached.</para><para>(6) If the child care and education provider is (a) a partnership, (b) a limited liability company, (c) a corporation having an election in effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, or (d) an estate or trust, the tax credit provided in this section may be distributed in the same manner and proportion as the partner, member, shareholder, or beneficiary reports the partnership, limited liability company, subchapter S corporation, estate, or trust income.</para><para>(7) The credit provided in this section shall be available for taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2024, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB889, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB266, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB754, &#167; 17. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>