<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3510"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3510</statuteno><catchline>Homesteads; exemptions; transfers;
claimants; forms; contents; county assessor; furnish; confidentiality.</catchline>
<para>On or before February 1 of each year, the Tax Commissioner shall prescribe
forms to be used by all claimants for homestead exemption or for transfer
of homestead exemption. Such forms shall contain provisions for the showing
of all information which the Tax Commissioner may deem necessary to (1) enable
the county officials and the Tax Commissioner to determine whether each claim
for exemption under sections 77-3506
and 77-3507 to 77-3509 should be allowed and (2) enable the county
assessor to determine whether each claim for transfer of homestead exemption
pursuant to section 77-3509.01 should be allowed. It shall be the duty of
the county assessor of each county in this state to furnish such forms, upon
request, to each person desiring to make application for homestead exemption
or for transfer of homestead exemption. The forms so prescribed shall be used
uniformly throughout the state, and no application for exemption or for transfer
of homestead exemption shall be allowed unless the applicant uses the prescribed
form in making an application. The forms shall require the attachment of an
income statement for any applicant
seeking an exemption under section 77-3507, 77-3508, or 77-3509 as
prescribed by the Tax Commissioner fully accounting for all household income.
The Tax Commissioner shall provide to each county assessor printed claim forms
and address lists of applicants from the prior year. The application and information
contained on any attachments to the application shall be confidential and
available to tax officials only.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 65, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 494, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 396, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 809, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1985, Second Spec. Sess., LB 6, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1258, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 376A, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 84, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 9, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 902, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 135, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 921, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 192, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB145, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1087, &#167; 10.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2015</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>