<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id981"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3124"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3124</statuteno><catchline>Qualifying expenditures; enumerated; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of the Cast and Crew Nebraska Act, qualifying expenditure includes:</para><para>(a) Pre-production, production, and post-production expenditures made in Nebraska that are subject to taxation by the state;</para><para>(b) Scouting and spending related to the production activity in the state prior to application for qualification;</para><para>(c)(i) Above-the-line employee wages for residents of Nebraska or paid through a Nebraska loan out company.</para><para>(ii) Loan out companies will be required to pay applicable Nebraska income taxes.</para><para>(iii) The total above-the-line employee wages and related expenses shall be not more than twenty-five percent of the total instate expenditures of a production activity;</para><para>(d) Below-the-line employee wages;</para><para>(e) Per diems of up to thirty dollars per day per employee; and</para><para>(f) Expenditures not otherwise available for rental or purchase within Nebraska and paid for via a Nebraska supplier.</para><para>(2) Qualifying expenditures do not include:</para><para>(a) Wages paid to independent contractors, or self-employed individuals, except that wages shown to be paid by a Nebraska-based production company for a commercial production activity and wages the taxes of which are shown to be withheld by the employer may be approved by the department on the application for the tax credit;</para><para>(b) Above-the-line employee per diems or living allowance expenses;</para><para>(c) Taxes imposed pursuant to the Federal Insurance Contributions Act and other payroll taxes;</para><para>(d) Contributions under the Federal Unemployment Tax Act and the Employment Security Law; and</para><para>(e) Union dues and benefits.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB937, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>July 19, 2024</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Employment Security Law,</emphasis> see section 48-601.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>