<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection statutenumber="77-3104" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3104</statuteno><catchline>Certification administrator; designation; duties; notice to volunteer member; written report; governing body; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Each volunteer department serving a county, city, village, or rural or suburban fire protection district shall designate one member of the department to serve as the certification administrator. The designation of such individual as the certification administrator shall be confirmed and approved by the governing body of such county, city, village, or rural or suburban fire protection district. The certification administrator shall keep and maintain records on the activities of all volunteer members and award points for such activities based upon the standard criteria for qualified active service.</para><para>(2) The certification administrator shall provide each volunteer member with notice of the total points he or she has accumulated during each six-month period during each year. No later than thirty days following the end of each calendar year of service, the certification administrator shall forward to the governing body of the county, city, village, or rural or suburban fire protection district a written report specifying the name of each volunteer member of the volunteer department, the number of points accumulated by each volunteer during the year of service, and the names of those volunteers who have qualified as active emergency responders, active rescue squad members, or active volunteer firefighters. At the time of the filing of the report, the certification administrator shall notify each volunteer member of the department whose name does not appear on the list of qualified volunteers of such fact in writing by mailing the notification by first-class United States mail, postage prepaid, to the last-known address of such volunteer member.</para><para>(3) The governing body of the county, city, village, or rural or suburban fire protection district shall approve and certify the list of those volunteers who have qualified as active emergency responders, active rescue squad members, or active volunteer firefighters by February 10 of the following calendar year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB886, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB760, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>April 12, 2018</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>