<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3445"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3445</statuteno><catchline>Council on public improvements and services; membership; powers and duties.</catchline><para>A council on public improvements and services may be created within each county or for adjoining counties by resolutions of county boards or by joint resolutions passed by at least three different types of political subdivisions located in the county which are authorized to levy property taxes or which may benefit from property taxes affected by the levy limits imposed by sections 77-3442 to 77-3444. Such councils shall include, but are not limited to, one elected official from each school board, county board, incorporated city or village, natural resources district, community college, educational service unit, hospital district, airport authority, fire protection district, and township taxing property within the county or counties. The elected governing body of each political subdivision which has the legal authority to request property tax funding or a levy set by the county board within a county may by resolution of the governing body appoint one elected official from the governing board to the council on public improvements and services.</para><para>Councils on public improvements and services may meet, beginning in 1996, as often as necessary prior to the adoption of budgets and property tax requests affected by the levy limits described in sections 77-3442 to 77-3444. The council shall jointly examine the budgets and property tax requests of each governmental agency or quasi-governmental agency with statutory authority to request a share of the property tax. The county clerk or designated county official of each county shall attend such meetings and keep a public record of the proceedings. Each council on public improvements and services which is created by resolution as provided in this section shall hold at least one public meeting prior to the adoption of public budgets affected by the levy limits imposed by sections 77-3442 to 77-3444. Such council may continue to meet to discuss issues of public service provision in an effective and coordinated manner, the impacts of levy limits, state and federal law, program, or aid changes, and the joint provision or use of capital facilities and equipment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 39. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 