<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3201</statuteno><catchline>Land Reutilization Authority; created; powers; purpose.</catchline><para>(1) There may be created within each county an authority for the management, sale, transfer, and other disposition of tax-delinquent lands, which authority shall be known as the Land Reutilization Authority of the County of ............... . It shall have authority to accept the grant of any interest in real property made to it or to accept gifts and grant-in-aid assistance. The authority shall have and exercise all the powers conferred by the Land Reutilization Act necessary and incidental to the effective management, sale, transfer, or other disposition of real estate acquired under and by virtue of the foreclosure of the lien for delinquent real estate taxes, and in the exercise of its powers, the authority shall be deemed to be a public corporation acting in a governmental capacity and a political subdivision of this state.</para> <para>(2) The authority shall foster the public purpose of returning land which is in a nonrevenue-generating nontax-producing status to effective utilization in order to provide housing, new industry, and jobs for the citizens of the county and new tax revenue for the county.</para> <para>(3) In counties in which a city of the metropolitan class is located, such a city may create an authority for the management, sale, transfer, and other disposition of tax-delinquent lands which shall be known as the Land Reutilization Authority of the City of ........ . Such authority shall have all of the powers and duties granted to an authority by the act with regard to property located within the corporate boundaries of that city. Such an authority shall be a division of the planning department of such city and shall not be deemed to be a public corporation acting in a governmental capacity or a political subdivision of this state, independent of the city creating the authority. All of the acts of such an authority shall be the acts of such city. If a land reutilization authority for the county in which is situated a city of the metropolitan class exists at the time of creation of an authority by a city of the metropolitan class, the existing authority of the county with regard to property located within the corporate boundaries of the city shall cease to exist within one hundred eighty days after the creation of the land reutilization authority of such city and any real property located within the corporate boundaries of the city held by such land reutilization authority of the county shall be conveyed to the newly created authority of the city of the metropolitan class.</para> <para>(4) Pursuant to the provisions of the Interlocal Cooperation Act, a city of the metropolitan class that creates a land reutilization authority may enter into an agreement with any county to authorize the city's land reutilization authority to exercise on behalf of such county the authority provided by the Land Reutilization Act for its own land reutilization authority upon such terms and conditions as the city and county may agree.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 73, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 862, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 489, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB360, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference>  </law> </legaldoc>