<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id28" statutenumber="77-3506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3506</statuteno><catchline>Certain veterans; exemption; unremarried surviving spouse; application.</catchline><para>(1) All homesteads in this state shall be assessed for taxation the same as other property, except that there shall be exempt from taxation, on any homestead described in subsection (2) of this section, one hundred percent of the exempt amount.</para><para>(2) The exemption described in subsection (1) of this section shall apply to homesteads of:</para><para>(a) A veteran who was discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions), who is drawing compensation from the United States Department of Veterans Affairs because of one hundred percent service-connected disability, and who is not eligible for total exemption under sections 77-3526 to 77-3528, an unremarried surviving spouse of such a veteran, or a surviving spouse of such a veteran who remarries after attaining the age of fifty-seven years;</para><para>(b) An unremarried surviving spouse of any veteran, including a veteran other than a veteran described in section 80-401.01, who was discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable conditions) and who died because of a service-connected disability or a surviving spouse of such a veteran who remarries after attaining the age of fifty-seven years;</para><para>(c) An unremarried surviving spouse of a serviceman or servicewoman, including a veteran other than a veteran described in section 80-401.01, whose death while on active duty was service-connected or a surviving spouse of such a serviceman or servicewoman who remarries after attaining the age of fifty-seven years; and</para><para>(d) An unremarried surviving spouse of a serviceman or servicewoman who died while on active duty during the periods described in section 80-401.01 or a surviving spouse of such a serviceman or servicewoman who remarries after attaining the age of fifty-seven years.</para><para>(3) Application for exemption under this section shall include certification of the status set forth in subsection (2) of this section from the United States Department of Veterans Affairs. Such certification shall not be required in succeeding years if no change in status has occurred, except that the county assessor or the Tax Commissioner may request such certification to verify that no change in status has occurred.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2014, LB1087, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB683, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1089, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 25. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>