<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3207"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3207</statuteno><catchline>Authority; employees; disbursements; fiscal year; audit; warrants.</catchline><para>(1) The commissioners may appoint a director and such other employees as are deemed necessary to carry out the responsibilities and duties imposed by the Land Reutilization Act and may incur such other reasonable and proper costs and expenses related thereto. A land reutilization authority of a city of the metropolitan class shall utilize only city employees for such responsibilities and duties. If such costs and expenses exceed the amount of funds available to the authority under the act, the authority shall obtain approval for such additional or supplemental needs. Such appropriations shall be considered advances to the authority subject to repayment from funds accumulated by the authority under the act.</para> <para>The county treasurer's office, or city treasurer's office in the case of an authority created pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-3201,  shall handle all such appropriated expense funds and disburse the same under the provisions for handling other expenditures.</para> <para>The authority shall deposit all funds received under the act with the county treasurer of the county, or the city treasurer in the case of an authority created pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-3201,  and make disbursements therefrom upon receipt of vouchers duly authorized by the authority under the act and in accordance with standard procedures adopted by and approved by the county treasurer, or the city treasurer in the case of an authority created pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-3201.</para> <para>(2) The fiscal year of the authority shall commence on January 1 of each year. The authority shall audit all claims for the expenditure of money and the chairperson or vice-chairperson thereof shall draw warrants therefor from time to time, or the city treasurer in the case of an authority created pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-3201.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 73, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB710, &#167;  3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB360, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>