<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id6" statutenumber="77-3442"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3442</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Property tax levies; maximum levy; exceptions.</catchline><para>(1) Property tax levies for the support of local governments for fiscal years beginning on or after July 1, 1998, shall be limited to the amounts set forth in this section except as provided in section 77-3444.</para><para>(2)(a) Except as provided in subdivisions (2)(b) and (2)(e) of this section, school districts and multiple-district school systems may levy a maximum levy of one dollar and five cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy.</para><para>(b) For each fiscal year prior to fiscal year 2017-18, learning communities may levy a maximum levy for the general fund budgets of member school districts of ninety-five cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy. The proceeds from the levy pursuant to this subdivision shall be distributed pursuant to section 79-1073.</para><para>(c) Except as provided in subdivision (2)(e) of this section, for each fiscal year prior to fiscal year 2017-18, school districts that are members of learning communities may levy for purposes of such districts' general fund budget and special building funds a maximum combined levy of the difference of one dollar and five cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable property subject to the levy minus the learning community levy pursuant to subdivision (2)(b) of this section for such learning community.</para><para>(d) Excluded from the limitations in subdivisions (2)(a) and (2)(c) of this section are (i) amounts levied to pay for current and future sums agreed to be paid by a school district to certificated employees in exchange for a voluntary termination of employment occurring prior to September 1, 2017, (ii) amounts levied by a school district otherwise at the maximum levy pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section to pay for current and future qualified voluntary termination incentives for certificated teachers pursuant to subsection (3) of section 79-8,142 that are not otherwise included in an exclusion pursuant to subdivision (2)(d) of this section, (iii) amounts levied by a school district otherwise at the maximum levy pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section to pay for seventy-five percent of the current and future sums agreed to be paid to certificated employees in exchange for a voluntary termination of employment occurring between September 1, 2017, and August 31, 2018, as a result of a collective-bargaining agreement in force and effect on September 1, 2017, that are not otherwise included in an exclusion pursuant to subdivision (2)(d) of this section, (iv) amounts levied by a school district otherwise at the maximum levy pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section to pay for fifty percent of the current and future sums agreed to be paid to certificated employees in exchange for a voluntary termination of employment occurring between September 1, 2018, and August 31, 2019, as a result of a collective-bargaining agreement in force and effect on September 1, 2017, that are not otherwise included in an exclusion pursuant to subdivision (2)(d) of this section, (v) amounts levied by a school district otherwise at the maximum levy pursuant to subdivision (2)(a) of this section to pay for twenty-five percent of the current and future sums agreed to be paid to certificated employees in exchange for a voluntary termination of employment occurring between September 1, 2019, and August 31, 2020, as a result of a collective-bargaining agreement in force and effect on September 1, 2017, that are not otherwise included in an exclusion pursuant to subdivision (2)(d) of this section, (vi) amounts levied in compliance with sections 79-10,110 and 79-10,110.02, and (vii) amounts levied to pay for special building funds and sinking funds established for projects commenced prior to April 1, 1996, for construction, expansion, or alteration of school district buildings. For purposes of this subsection, commenced means any action taken by the school board on the record which commits the board to expend district funds in planning, constructing, or carrying out the project.</para><para>(e) Federal aid school districts may exceed the maximum levy prescribed by subdivision (2)(a) or (2)(c) of this section only to the extent necessary to qualify to receive federal aid pursuant to Title VIII of Public Law 103-382, as such title existed on September 1, 2001. For purposes of this subdivision, federal aid school district means any school district which receives ten percent or more of the revenue for its general fund budget from federal government sources pursuant to Title VIII of Public Law 103-382, as such title existed on September 1, 2001.</para><para>(f) For each fiscal year, learning communities may levy a maximum levy of one-half cent on each one hundred dollars of taxable property subject to the levy for elementary learning center facility leases, for remodeling of leased elementary learning center facilities, and for up to fifty percent of the estimated cost for focus school or program capital projects approved by the learning community coordinating council pursuant to section 79-2111.</para><para>(g) For each fiscal year, learning communities may levy a maximum levy of one and one-half cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable property subject to the levy for early childhood education programs for children in poverty, for elementary learning center employees, for contracts with other entities or individuals who are not employees of the learning community for elementary learning center programs and services, and for pilot projects, except that no more than ten percent of such levy may be used for elementary learning center employees.</para><para>(3) For each fiscal year, community college areas may levy the levies provided in subdivisions (2)(a) through (c) of section 85-1517, in accordance with the provisions of such subdivisions. A community college area may exceed the levy provided in subdivision (2)(b) of section 85-1517 by the amount necessary to retire general obligation bonds assumed by the community college area or issued pursuant to section 85-1515 according to the terms of such bonds or for any obligation pursuant to section 85-1535 entered into prior to January 1, 1997.</para><para>(4)(a) Natural resources districts may levy a maximum levy of four and one-half cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy.</para><para>(b) Natural resources districts shall also have the power and authority to levy a tax equal to the dollar amount by which their restricted funds budgeted to administer and implement ground water management activities and integrated management activities under the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act exceed their restricted funds budgeted to administer and implement ground water management activities and integrated management activities for FY2003-04, not to exceed one cent on each one hundred dollars of taxable valuation annually on all of the taxable property within the district.</para><para>(c) In addition, natural resources districts located in a river basin, subbasin, or reach that has been determined to be fully appropriated pursuant to section 46-714 or designated as overappropriated pursuant to section 46-713 by the Department of Natural Resources shall also have the power and authority to levy a tax equal to the dollar amount by which their restricted funds budgeted to administer and implement ground water management activities and integrated management activities under the Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act exceed their restricted funds budgeted to administer and implement ground water management activities and integrated management activities for FY2005-06, not to exceed three cents on each one hundred dollars of taxable valuation on all of the taxable property within the district for fiscal year 2006-07 and each fiscal year thereafter through fiscal year 2017-18.</para><para>(5) Any educational service unit authorized to levy a property tax pursuant to section 79-1225 may levy a maximum levy of one and one-half cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy.</para><para>(6)(a) Incorporated cities and villages which are not within the boundaries of a municipal county may levy a maximum levy of forty-five cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy plus an additional five cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation to provide financing for the municipality's share of revenue required under an agreement or agreements executed pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act. The maximum levy shall include amounts levied to pay for sums to support a library pursuant to section 51-201, museum pursuant to section 51-501, visiting community nurse, home health nurse, or home health agency pursuant to section 71-1637, or statue, memorial, or monument pursuant to section 80-202.</para><para>(b) Incorporated cities and villages which are within the boundaries of a municipal county may levy a maximum levy of ninety cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy. The maximum levy shall include amounts paid to a municipal county for county services, amounts levied to pay for sums to support a library pursuant to section 51-201, a museum pursuant to section 51-501, a visiting community nurse, home health nurse, or home health agency pursuant to section 71-1637, or a statue, memorial, or monument pursuant to section 80-202.</para><para>(7) Sanitary and improvement districts which have been in existence for more than five years may levy a maximum levy of forty cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy, and sanitary and improvement districts which have been in existence for five years or less shall not have a maximum levy. Unconsolidated sanitary and improvement districts which have been in existence for more than five years and are located in a municipal county may levy a maximum of eighty-five cents per hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy.</para><para>(8) Counties may levy or authorize a maximum levy of fifty cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy, except that five cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy may only be levied to provide financing for the county's share of revenue required under an agreement or agreements executed pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act. The maximum levy shall include amounts levied to pay for sums to support a library pursuant to section 51-201 or museum pursuant to section 51-501. The county may allocate up to fifteen cents of its authority to other political subdivisions subject to allocation of property tax authority under subsection (1) of section 77-3443 and not specifically covered in this section to levy taxes as authorized by law which do not collectively exceed fifteen cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation on any parcel or item of taxable property. The county may allocate to one or more other political subdivisions subject to allocation of property tax authority by the county under subsection (1) of section 77-3443 some or all of the county's five cents per one hundred dollars of valuation authorized for support of an agreement or agreements to be levied by the political subdivision for the purpose of supporting that political subdivision's share of revenue required under an agreement or agreements executed pursuant to the Interlocal Cooperation Act or the Joint Public Agency Act. If an allocation by a county would cause another county to exceed its levy authority under this section, the second county may exceed the levy authority in order to levy the amount allocated.</para><para>(9) Municipal counties may levy or authorize a maximum levy of one dollar per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy. The municipal county may allocate levy authority to any political subdivision or entity subject to allocation under section 77-3443.</para><para>(10) Beginning July 1, 2016, rural and suburban fire protection districts may levy a maximum levy of ten and one-half cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy if (a) such district is located in a county that had a levy pursuant to subsection (8) of this section in the previous year of at least forty cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy or (b) such district had a levy request pursuant to section 77-3443 in any of the three previous years and the county board of the county in which the greatest portion of the valuation of such district is located did not authorize any levy authority to such district in such year.</para><para>(11) A regional metropolitan transit authority may levy a maximum levy of ten cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy for each fiscal year that commences on the January 1 that follows the effective date of the conversion of the transit authority established under the Transit Authority Law into the regional metropolitan transit authority.</para><para>(12) Property tax levies (a) for judgments, except judgments or orders from the Commission of Industrial Relations, obtained against a political subdivision which require or obligate a political subdivision to pay such judgment, to the extent such judgment is not paid by liability insurance coverage of a political subdivision, (b) for preexisting lease-purchase contracts approved prior to July 1, 1998, (c) for bonds as defined in section 10-134 approved according to law and secured by a levy on property except as provided in section 44-4317 for bonded indebtedness issued by educational service units and school districts, and (d) for payments by a public airport to retire interest-free loans from the Division of Aeronautics of the Department of Transportation in lieu of bonded indebtedness at a lower cost to the public airport are not included in the levy limits established by this section.</para><para>(13) The limitations on tax levies provided in this section are to include all other general or special levies provided by law. Notwithstanding other provisions of law, the only exceptions to the limits in this section are those provided by or authorized by sections 77-3442 to 77-3444.</para><para>(14) Tax levies in excess of the limitations in this section shall be considered unauthorized levies under section 77-1606 unless approved under section 77-3444.</para><para>(15) For purposes of sections 77-3442 to 77-3444, political subdivision means a political subdivision of this state and a county agricultural society.</para><para>(16) For school districts that file a binding resolution on or before May 9, 2008, with the county assessors, county clerks, and county treasurers for all counties in which the school district has territory pursuant to subsection (7) of section 79-458, if the combined levies, except levies for bonded indebtedness approved by the voters of the school district and levies for the refinancing of such bonded indebtedness, are in excess of the greater of (a) one dollar and twenty cents per one hundred dollars of taxable valuation of property subject to the levy or (b) the maximum levy authorized by a vote pursuant to section 77-3444, all school district levies, except levies for bonded indebtedness approved by the voters of the school district and levies for the refinancing of such bonded indebtedness, shall be considered unauthorized levies under section 77-1606.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 87, &#167; 87; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 141, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 437, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 568, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 898, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1085, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 540, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 962, &#167; 110; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1093, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 38, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 968, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1024, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1226, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB342, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB641, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB701, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB988, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1154, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB121, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1070, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1072, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB59, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB400, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB946, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1104, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB585, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB261, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB325, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB959, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB1067, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 269; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB512, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB63, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB492, &#167; 42. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB63, section 6, with LB492, section 42, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB63 became effective March 8, 2019. Changes made by LB492 became effective September 1, 2019.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para><para><emphasis>Joint Public Agency Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Ground Water Management and Protection Act,</emphasis> see section 46-701.</para>><para><emphasis>Transit Authority Law,</emphasis> see section 14-1826.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Because the levy authorized under subsection (2)(b) of this section benefits all taxpayers in a learning community, which is the relevant taxing district, subsection (2)(b) does not violate the constitutional prohibition in Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 4, against a commutation of taxes. Sarpy Cty. Farm Bureau v. Learning Community, 283 Neb. 212, 808 N.W.2d 598 (2012).</para><para>Because the levy authorized under subsection (2)(b) of this section is uniform throughout the entire learning community, which is the relevant taxing district, subsection (2)(b) does not violate the uniformity clause in Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 1. Sarpy Cty. Farm Bureau v. Learning Community, 283 Neb. 212, 808 N.W.2d 598 (2012).</para><para>Subsection (2)(b) of this section was enacted for substantially local purposes, and therefore it does not violate the prohibition in Neb. Const. art. VIII, sec. 1A, against a property tax for a state purpose. Sarpy Cty. Farm Bureau v. Learning Community, 283 Neb. 212, 808 N.W.2d 598 (2012).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>