<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3002"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3002</statuteno><catchline>Operator; license; application; limitations; background check; cause for denial; disciplinary action; cash device winnings; duty to check collection system.</catchline><para>(1) Any operator shall be required to procure a biennial license from the Tax Commissioner permitting him or her to operate mechanical amusement devices within the State of Nebraska. The Tax Commissioner, upon the application of any person, may issue a license, except that if the applicant (a) is not of good character and reputation in the community in which he or she resides, (b) has been convicted of or has pleaded guilty to a felony under the laws of the State of Nebraska, of any other state, or of the United States, or (c) has been convicted of or has pleaded guilty to being the proprietor of a gambling house, or of any other crime or misdemeanor opposed to decency and morality, no license shall be issued. If the applicant is a corporation whose majority stockholders could not obtain a license, then such corporation shall not be issued a license. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. Procuring a license shall constitute sufficient contact with this state for the exercise of personal jurisdiction over such person in any action arising out of the operation of mechanical amusement devices in this state.</para><para>(2)(a) Except for an applicant that holds a liquor license under the Nebraska Liquor Control Act, an applicant for or person holding a license as an operator of a cash device shall be subject to a background check at any time by the department including fingerprinting and a check of his or her criminal history record information maintained by the Identification Division of the Federal Bureau of Investigation through the Nebraska State Patrol for the purpose of determining whether the Department of Revenue has a basis to deny the license application or to suspend, cancel, revoke, or terminate the person's license. Each applicant for or person holding a license pursuant to this section shall also submit a personal history report to the department on a form provided by the department and may be subject to a background investigation, an inspection of the applicant's or licensee's facilities, or both. An applicant or licensee shall pay the costs associated with the background check along with any required fees as determined by the department.</para><para>(b) The Tax Commissioner has the authority to deny any application for a license as an operator of a cash device for cause. Cause for denial of a license application includes instances in which the applicant individually, or in the case of a business entity, any officer, director, employee, or limited liability company member of the applicant or licensee other than an employee whose duties are purely ministerial in nature:</para><para>(i) Violated the provisions, requirements, conditions, limitations, or duties imposed by the Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act;</para><para>(ii) Knowingly caused, aided, abetted, or conspired with another to cause any person to violate any of the provisions of the act or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to the act;</para><para>(iii) Obtained a license or permit under the act by fraud, misrepresentation, or concealment;</para><para>(iv) Has been convicted of, forfeited bond upon a charge of, or pleaded guilty or nolo contendere to any offense or crime, whether a felony or a misdemeanor, involving any gambling activity or fraud, theft, willful failure to make required payments or reports, or filing false reports with a governmental agency at any level;</para><para>(v) Denied the department or its authorized representatives, including authorized law enforcement agencies, access to any place where activity required to be licensed under the act is being conducted or failed to produce for inspection or audit any book, record, document, or item required by law, rule, or regulation;</para><para>(vi) Made a misrepresentation of or failed to disclose a material fact to the department;</para><para>(vii) Failed to prove by clear and convincing evidence such applicant's qualifications to be licensed in accordance with the act;</para><para>(viii) Failed to pay any taxes and additions to taxes, including penalties and interest required by the act or any other taxes imposed pursuant to the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967; or</para><para>(ix) Has been cited for a violation of the Nebraska Liquor Control Act and had a liquor license suspended, canceled, or revoked by the Nebraska Liquor Control Commission for illegal gambling activities on or about the premises licensed by the commission pursuant to the Nebraska Liquor Control Act or the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant to such act.</para><para>(c) No renewal of a license issued pursuant to this section shall be issued when the applicant for renewal would not be eligible for a license upon a first application.</para><para>(3) The Tax Commissioner has the authority to suspend or revoke the license of any operator that is in violation of the Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act.</para><para>(4) Beginning on the implementation date designated by the Tax Commissioner pursuant to subsection (2) of section 9-1312, prior to the winnings payment of any cash device winnings as defined in section 9-1303, an operator of a cash device shall check the collection system to determine if the winner has a debt or an outstanding state liability as required by the Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act. If such operator determines that the winner is subject to the collection system, the operator shall deduct the amount of debt and outstanding state liability identified in the collection system from the winnings payment and shall remit the net winnings payment of cash device winnings, if any, to the winner and the amount deducted to the Department of Revenue to be credited against such debt or outstanding state liability as provided in section 9-1306.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 635, &#167; 3, p. 2542; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 317, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 213; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB685, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1317, &#167; 86; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB177, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB415, &#167; 16. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB177, section 2, with LB415, section 16, to reflect all amendments.</note></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Gambling Winnings Setoff for Outstanding Debt Act,</emphasis> see section 9-1301.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Liquor Control Act,</emphasis> see section 53-101.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>