  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3002"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3002</statuteno><catchline>Operator; license; application; limitations; renewal; fees; service of process.</catchline><para>(1) Any operator shall be required to procure an annual license from the Tax Commissioner permitting him or her to operate machines or devices within the State of Nebraska. The Tax Commissioner, upon the application of any person, may issue a license, except that if the applicant (a) is not of good character and reputation in the community in which he or she resides, (b) has been convicted of or has pleaded guilty to a felony under the laws of the State of Nebraska, any other state, or of the United States, or (c) has been convicted of or has pleaded guilty to being the proprietor of a gambling house, or of any other crime or misdemeanor opposed to decency and morality, no license shall be issued. If the applicant is a corporation whose majority stockholders could not obtain a license, then such corporation shall not be issued a license. If the applicant is an individual, the application shall include the applicant's social security number. Procuring a license shall constitute sufficient contact with this state for the exercise of personal jurisdiction over such person in any action arising out of the operation of machines or devices in this state.</para><para>(2)(a) For the period beginning July 1, 1998, through December 31, 1999, if the applicant operates ten or more machines, the application shall be accompanied by a fee of two hundred fifty dollars, and such license will remain in effect until December 31, 1999. If the applicant operates fewer than ten machines, no fee is due. Any licensee that places additional machines into operation during this period which results in a total of ten or more machines in operation becomes subject to the two-hundred-fifty-dollar fee.</para><para>(b) Beginning January 1, 2000, the application shall be filed on or before January 1 of each year, and no license fee will be required.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 635, &#167; 3, p. 2542; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 68; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 317, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 213. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 