<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3502</statuteno><catchline>Homestead, defined.</catchline><para>Homestead shall mean either (1) a residence or mobile home, and the land surrounding it, not exceeding one acre, in this state actually occupied as such by a natural person who is the owner of record thereof from January 1 through August 15 in each year, (2) a residence or mobile home located on land leased by the owner of the residence or mobile home, which is located within this state, and is actually occupied by the person who is the owner of record from January 1 through August 15 in each year, or so occupied by the surviving spouse and minor children, if any, of such owner of record during the year of the owner's death, or so much thereof as shall be so occupied, or (3) a residential unit in a dwelling complex, the record title owner of which is a not-for-profit corporation, when the purchase for fair market value of a life tenancy in a taxable unit of the dwelling complex entitles the purchaser to exclusive occupancy of that unit for life, actually occupied by a natural person who has a life tenancy therein from January 1 through August 15 in each year. For purposes of this section, mobile home shall include every transportable or relocatable device of any description without motive power and designed for living quarters, whether or not permanently attached to real estate, but shall not include a cabin trailer registered for operation upon the highways of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 65, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 647, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 168, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 376A, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 