<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3008"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3008</statuteno><catchline>Income tax, occupation tax, net operating revenue tax; distributor, operator, manufacturer; payment required, when; cash device prize; form for player, conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Each distributor of a cash device shall pay taxes owed quarterly to be filed January 1, April 1, June 1, and October 1 of each calendar year. Such taxes required to be paid shall include income tax, occupation tax, and net operating revenue tax.</para><para>(2)(a) Each operator of a cash device shall pay income taxes on income generated by such cash device quarterly to be filed January 1, April 1, June 1, and October 1 of each calendar year.</para><para>(b) Each operator of a cash device shall pay occupation tax and net operating revenue tax for such cash device quarterly to be filed January 1, April 1, June 1, and October 1 of each calendar year if the operator is not subject to a revenue-sharing or other agreement with a distributor who is paying such taxes pursuant to subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(3) Each distributor, operator, or employee or agent of any distributor or operator of a cash device shall provide an Internal Revenue Service Form 1099 to each player that wins a prize in excess of one thousand one hundred ninety-nine dollars from a cash device placed into operation by such distributor or operator. The department shall make this form available on the department's website.</para><para>(4) A distributor or manufacturer located outside the State of Nebraska shall pay income taxes in Nebraska on all income earned in Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 635, &#167; 8, p. 2545; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB538, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB685, &#167; 14. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>