<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id162" statutenumber="77-3519"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3519</statuteno><catchline id="id165">Homestead; exemption; county assessor; rejection; applicant; complaint; contents; hearing; appeal.</catchline><para>In any case when the county assessor rejects an application for homestead exemption, such applicant may obtain a hearing before the county board of equalization by filing a written complaint with the county clerk. If the application for homestead exemption was rejected on the basis of value, the complaint must be filed by June 30. The county board of equalization may, by majority vote, extend such deadline to July 20. If the application for homestead exemption was rejected on any other basis, the complaint must be filed within thirty days from receipt of the notice from the county assessor showing such rejection. Such complaint shall specify his or her grievances and the pertinent facts in relation thereto, in ordinary and concise language and without repetition, and in such manner as to enable a person of common understanding to know what is intended. The board may take evidence pertinent to such complaint, and for that purpose may compel the attendance of witnesses and the production of books, records, and papers by subpoena. The board shall issue its decision on the complaint within thirty days after the filing of the complaint. Notice of the board's decision shall be mailed by the county clerk to the applicant within seven days after the decision. The taxpayer shall have the right to appeal from the board's decision with reference to the application for homestead exemption to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission in accordance with section 77-5013 within thirty days after the decision.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 65, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 376A, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 177; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB512, &#167; 27. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>