<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id15"> <sectno id="id16">Sec. 7.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id17" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-3514.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3514.01</statuteno><catchline>Homestead; exemption; late application or certification because of medical condition; filing; form; county assessor; powers and duties; rejection; notice; hearing.</catchline><para>(1) A late application or certification filed pursuant to section 77-3512, 77-3513, or 77-3514 because of a medical condition which impaired the claimant's ability to apply or certify in a timely manner shall only be for the current tax year. The late application or certification shall be filed with the county assessor on or before the date on which the first half of the real estate taxes levied on the property for the current year become delinquent.</para> <para>(2) The application or certification shall include certification of the medical condition affecting the filing from a physician, physician assistant, or advanced practice registered nurse. The medical certification shall be made on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner.</para><para>(3) The county assessor shall approve or reject the late filing within thirty days of receipt of the late filing. If approved, the county assessor shall mark it approved and sign the application or certification. In case he or she finds that the exemption should not be allowed by reason of not being in conformity to law, the county assessor shall mark the application or certification as rejected and state the reason for rejection and sign the application or certification. In any case when the county assessor rejects an exemption, he or she shall notify the applicant of such action by mailing written notice to the applicant at the address shown in the application or certification. The notice shall be on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. In any case when the county assessor rejects an exemption, such applicant may obtain a hearing before the county board of equalization in the manner described by section 77-3519.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2009, LB94, &#167; 7.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>