<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3205</statuteno><catchline>Authority; seal; adopt; conveyances; requirements.</catchline><para>(1) The authority shall be a continuing body and shall have and adopt an official seal which shall bear on its face the words Land Reutilization Authority of the County of ................... or City of ...................., and shall have the power to issue deeds in its name, which deeds shall be signed by the chairperson or vice-chairperson and attested by the secretary, and shall have the general power to administer its business as any other corporate body. A land reutilization authority of a city of the metropolitan class shall issue deeds in the name of such city and such city, through its employees designated as the commission members, shall have general powers to administer the authority's business.</para> <para>(2) The authority may convey title to any real estate sold or conveyed by it by general or special warranty deed, and may convey an absolute title in fee simple, without in any case procuring any consent, conveyance, or other instrument from the beneficiaries for which it acts. Each such deed shall recite whether the selling price represents a consideration equal to or in excess of two-thirds of the appraised value of such real estate so sold or conveyed. If such selling price represents a consideration of less than two-thirds of the appraised value of such real estate, the approval of such selling price shall be by unanimous action of the authority and evidenced by a copy of such action duly certified to by its secretary and attached to and made a part of such deed. In the event that unanimous action of the authority is not obtained, then the commissioners shall first procure the consent to such selling price of not less than a majority of the appointing authorities, which consent shall be evidenced by a copy of the action of each such appointing authority duly certified to by its clerk or secretary and attached to and made a part of such deed. In the case of a land reutilization authority for a city of the metropolitan class, the commissioners shall procure the planning director's consent.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 73, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 862, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 489, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB360, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>