<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><?Pub Caret1?><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id78" statutenumber="77-3903"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3903</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Notice of lien; filing; requirements; fee; billing.</catchline><para>(1)(a) A notice of lien provided for in the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act upon real property shall be presented in the office of the Secretary of State. Such notice of lien shall be transmitted by the Secretary of State to and filed in the office of the register of deeds by the register of deeds of the county or counties in which the real property subject to the lien is situated as designated in the notice of lien. The register of deeds shall enter the notice in the alphabetical state tax lien index, showing on one line the name and residence of the person liable named in such notice, the last four digits of the social security number or the federal tax identification number of such person, the Tax Commissioner's or Commissioner of Labor's serial number of such notice, the date and hour of filing, and the amount due. Such presentments to the Secretary of State may be made by direct input to the Secretary of State's database or by other electronic means. All such notices of lien shall be retained in numerical order in a file designated state tax lien notices, except that in offices filing by the roll form of microfilm pursuant to section 23-1517.01, the original notices need not be retained. A lien subject to this subsection shall be effective upon real property when filed by the register of deeds as provided in this subsection.</para><para>(b) A notice of lien provided for in the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act upon personal property shall be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. The Secretary of State shall enter the notice in the state's central tax lien index, showing on one line the name and residence of the person liable named in such notice, the last four digits of the social security number or the federal tax identification number of such person, the Tax Commissioner's or Commissioner of Labor's serial number of such notice, the date and hour of filing, and the amount due. Such filings with the Secretary of State may be filed by direct input to the Secretary of State's database or by other electronic means. All such notices of lien shall be retained in numerical order in a file designated state tax lien notices.</para><para>(2) The uniform fee, payable to the Secretary of State, for presenting for filing, releasing, continuing, or subordinating or for filing, releasing, continuing, or subordinating each tax lien pursuant to the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act shall be two times the fee required for recording instruments with the register of deeds as provided in section 33-109. There shall be no fee for the filing of a termination statement. The uniform fee for each county more than one designated pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section shall be the fee required for recording instruments with the register of deeds as provided in section 33-109. The Secretary of State shall remit each fee received pursuant to this subsection to the State Treasurer for credit to the Secretary of State Cash Fund, except that of the fees received pursuant to this subsection, the Secretary of State shall remit the fee required for recording instruments with the register of deeds as provided in section 33-109 to the register of deeds of a county for each designation of such county in a filing pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section.</para><para>(3) The Secretary of State shall bill the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor on a monthly basis for fees for documents presented to or filed with the Secretary of State. No payment of any fee shall be required at the time of presenting or filing any such lien document.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 216; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 179; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1321, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 165, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 46; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 89; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB14, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB152, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB268, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB910, &#167; 32. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2021</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>