<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3004"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3004</statuteno><catchline>Occupation tax; amount; payment.</catchline><para>(1) An occupation tax is hereby imposed and levied, in the amount and in accordance with the terms and conditions hereafter stated, upon the business of operating mechanical amusement devices within the State of Nebraska for profit or gain either directly or indirectly received. Every person who now or hereafter engages in the business of operating such devices in the State of Nebraska shall pay such tax in the amount and manner specified in this section.</para><para>(2) Any operator of a mechanical amusement device within the State of Nebraska shall pay an occupation tax for each machine or device which he or she operates during all of the taxable year. The tax shall be due and payable on January 1 of each year on each machine or device in operation on that date, except that it shall be unlawful to pay any such occupation tax unless the sales or use tax has been paid on such mechanical amusement devices. For every machine or device put into operation on a date subsequent to January 1, and which has not been included in computing the tax imposed and levied by the Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act, the tax shall be due and payable therefor prior to the time the machine or device is placed in operation. All taxes collected pursuant to the act shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the General Fund.</para><para>(3) The amount of the occupation tax shall be fifty dollars for each machine or device for the period from July 1, 1998, through December 31, 1999, except that for machines placed in operation after April 1, 1999, and before January 1, 2000, the occupation tax shall be twenty-five dollars for each machine or device.</para><para>(4) The amount of the occupation tax shall be thirty-five dollars for each machine or device for any period beginning on or after January 1, 2000, except that for machines placed in operation after July 1, and before January 1 of each year, the occupation tax shall be twenty dollars for each machine or device.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 635, &#167; 4, p. 2543; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 353, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 928, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 317, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 