<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id278"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3122"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3122</statuteno><catchline>Legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that:</para><para>(a) Film and television production in Nebraska not only provides jobs for residents of Nebraska and dollars for Nebraska businesses but also enhances the state's image nationwide;</para><para>(b) The high cost of film and television production is driving such production to other states, and the industry is always seeking attractive locations that can help cut the costs of production;</para><para>(c) The retention of Nebraska's youth is one of the top priorities in growing the state's economy. Film studies and creative arts students from the universities and colleges in Nebraska are taking their talents to other states due to the lack of strongly developed media production facilities within the state;</para><para>(d) The State of Nebraska, with a competitive incentive, can build on past success as an attractive site for film and television production;</para><para>(e) Nebraska is presently among several states with minimal incentives to attract the film and television industry; and</para><para>(f) A new and attractive film incentive should be used in conjunction with the Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act, passed by the Ninety-Second Legislature, First Session, 1991, as Legislative Bill 840, for municipalities that have included production of films or television programs as a qualifying business expense.</para><para>(2) It is the intent of the Legislature to provide an incentive that will allow the state to compete with other states and increase film and television production in this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB937, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Local Option Municipal Economic Development Act,</emphasis> see section 18-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>