<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-3203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3203</statuteno><catchline>Land Reutilization Commission; created; members; appointment; serve without compensation.</catchline><para>(1) In each county which creates an authority pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-3201, there is hereby created a Land Reutilization Commission which shall be composed of at least three members, one of whom shall be appointed by the governing body of the most populous city within the county, one of whom shall be appointed by the board of county commissioners, and one of whom shall be appointed by the board of education of the school district serving the most populous city of the county. At the request of the governing body of a city of the first or second class within the county, which is not the most populous city in the county, or the board of education of a school district located predominately within the county, which is not serving the most populous city of the county, the county board shall authorize the appointment of additional members to the Land Reutilization Commission, not to exceed a maximum total of seven members of the commission. The additional members of the commission shall be appointed by the governing body of the respective city or cities of the first or second class or by the board of education of the respective school district or districts. If necessary to establish an odd number of commission members, the county board may appoint a member from a municipality or school district within the county which is not represented on the commission. The members shall serve at the pleasure of the respective appointing authority and may be employees of the appointing authority. No member shall receive compensation for serving on the commission.</para> <para>(2) Any vacancy in the office of commissioner shall be filled by the same appointing authority which made the original appointment.</para> <para>(3) In a city of the metropolitan class which determines to create an authority pursuant to subsection (3) of section 77-3201, the city by ordinance may create a Land Reutilization Commission which shall be composed of a minimum of three members of the planning department of the city of the metropolitan class, appointed by its director. The members shall serve at the pleasure of the director. No member shall receive compensation for serving on the commission.</para></amendatorysection> </section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 73, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 831, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 489, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB360, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>