<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id388"><amendatorysection statutenumber="77-3605" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3605</statuteno><catchline>Eligible staff member; income tax credit; application; contents; approval.</catchline><para>(1) An eligible staff member may apply to the department to receive a refundable tax credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. The amount of the credit shall be based on the eligible staff member’s classification under subsection (4) of section 71-1962 as follows:</para><para><table frame="none"><tgroup align="left" cols="2"><colspec align="left" colname="col1" colwidth="1.23*" /><colspec align="right" colname="col2" colwidth="1*" /><tbody><row><entry>Eligible Staff Member's Classification</entry><entry>Tax Credit</entry></row><row><entry>Level Four</entry><entry>$1,500</entry></row><row><entry>Level Three</entry><entry>$1,250</entry></row><row><entry>Level Two</entry><entry>$750</entry></row><row><entry>Level One</entry><entry>$500</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></para><para>(2) An eligible staff member shall apply for the credit provided in this section by submitting an application to the department with the following information:</para><para>(a) The eligible staff member’s name and place of employment;</para><para>(b) An attestation form provided by the Nebraska Early Childhood Professional Record System verifying the level at which the eligible staff member is classified under subsection (4) of section 71-1962; and</para><para>(c) Any other documentation required by the department.</para><para>(3) Subject to subsection (4) of this section, if the department determines that the eligible staff member qualifies for tax credits under this section, it shall approve the application and certify the amount of credits approved to the eligible staff member. </para><para>(4) The department shall consider applications in the order in which they are received and may approve tax credits under this section in any taxable year until the aggregate limit allowed under subsection (1) of section 77-3606 has been reached.</para><para>(5) The credit provided in this section shall be available for taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2017, and before January 1, 2022, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</para><para>(6) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2018, and before January 1, 2022, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, the Tax Commissioner shall adjust the credit amounts provided for in subsection (1) of this section by the percentage change in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers, as prepared by the United States Department of Labor, Bureau of Labor Statistics, for the twelve-month period ending on August 31 of the year preceding the taxable year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2016, LB889, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2016</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>
