<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id42">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id44" statutenumber="77-3906"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3906</statuteno><catchline id="id47">Distraint and
sale of taxpayer's property; procedures; conditions; powers and duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) In addition to all other remedies or actions provided
by law under any tax program administered by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner
of Labor, it shall be lawful for the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor,
after making demand for payment, to collect any delinquent taxes, together
with any interest, penalties, and additions to such tax by distraint and sale
of the real and personal property of the taxpayer. If the Tax Commissioner
finds that the collection of any tax is in jeopardy pursuant to section 77-2710,
77-27,111, or 77-4311, notice and demand for immediate payment of such tax
may be made by the Tax Commissioner and, upon failure or refusal to pay such
tax, collection by levy shall be lawful.</para>
<para>(2)(a) In case of failure to pay taxes or deficiencies, the
Tax Commissioner, or his or her authorized employee, may levy or, by warrant
issued under his or her own hand, authorize a sheriff or duly authorized employee
of the Tax Commissioner to levy upon, seize, and sell such real and personal
property belonging to the taxpayer, except exempt property, as is necessary
to satisfy the liability for the payment of the amount due. The Tax Commissioner may also issue a levy to a financial
institution pursuant to section 77-3910.</para>
<para>(b) In case of failure to pay taxes or deficiencies, the Commissioner
of Labor, or his or her authorized employee, may levy or, by warrant issued
under his or her own hand, authorize a sheriff or duly authorized employee
of the Department of Labor to levy upon, seize, and sell such real and personal
property belonging to the taxpayer, except exempt property, as is necessary
to satisfy the liability for the payment of the amount due.</para>
<para>(c) As used in this section, exempt property shall mean such
property as is exempt from execution under the laws of this state.</para>
<para>(3) When a warrant is issued or a levy is made by the Tax
Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor, or his or her duly authorized employee,
for the collection of any tax and any interest, penalty, or addition to such
tax imposed by law under any tax program administered by the Tax Commissioner
or Commissioner of Labor or for the enforcement of any tax lien authorized
by the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act, such warrant
or levy shall have the same force and effect of a levy and sale pursuant to
a writ of execution. Such warrant or levy may be issued and sale made pursuant
to it in the same manner and with the same force and effect of a levy and
sale pursuant to a writ of execution. The Tax Commissioner or Commissioner
of Labor shall pay the financial
institution in accordance with section 77-3910 or the levying
sheriff the same fees, commissions, and expenses pursuant to such warrant
as are provided by law for similar services pursuant to a writ of execution,
except that fees for publications in a newspaper shall be subject to approval
by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor. Such fees, commissions,
and expenses shall be an obligation of the taxpayer and may be collected from
the taxpayer by virtue of the warrant. Any such warrant shall show the name
and last-known address of the taxpayer, the identity of the tax program, the
year for which such tax and any interest, penalty, or addition to such tax
is due and the amount thereof, the fact that the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner
of Labor has complied with all provisions of the law for the applicable tax
program which he or she administers in the determination of the amount required
to be paid, and that the tax and any interest, penalty, or addition to such
tax is due and payable according to law.</para>
<para>(4)(a) Any person upon whom a levy is served who fails or
refuses to honor the levy without cause may be held liable for the amount
of the levy up to the value of the assets of the taxpayer under his or her
control at the time the levy was served or thereafter. Such person may be
subject to collection provisions as set forth in the act.</para>
<para>(b) The effect of a levy on salary, wages, or other regular
payments due to or received by a taxpayer shall be continuous from the date
the levy is served until the amount of the levy, with accrued interest, is
satisfied.</para>
<para>(5) Notice of the sale and the time and place of the sale
shall be given, to the delinquent taxpayer and to any other person with an
interest in the property who has filed for record with the appropriate filing
officer on such property, in writing at least twenty days prior to the date
of such sale in the following manner: The notice shall be mailed to the taxpayer
and to any other person with such interest at his or her last-known residence
or place of business in this state. The notice shall also be given by publication
at least once each week for four weeks prior to the date of the sale in the
newspaper of general circulation published in the county in which the property
seized is to be sold. If there is no newspaper of general circulation in the
county, notice shall be posted in three public places in the county twenty
days prior to the date of the sale. The notice shall contain a description
of the property to be sold, a statement of the type of tax due and of the
amount due, including interest, penalties, additions to tax, and costs, the
name of the delinquent taxpayer, and the further statement that unless the
amount due, including interest, penalties, additions to tax, and costs, is
paid on or before the time fixed in the notice for the sale or such security
as may be determined by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor is placed
with the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor, or his or her duly authorized
representative, on or before such time, the property, or so much of it as
may be necessary, will be sold in accordance with law and the notice.</para>
<para>(6) At the sale the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor,
or his or her duly authorized representative, shall sell the property in accordance
with law and the notice and shall deliver to the purchaser a bill of sale
for the property. The bill of sale shall vest the interest or title of the
person liable for the amount in the purchaser. The unsold portion of any property
seized shall remain in the custody and control of the Tax Commissioner or
Commissioner of Labor, or his or her duly authorized representative, until
offered for sale again in accordance with this section or redeemed by the
taxpayer.</para>
<para>(7) Whenever any property which is seized and sold under this
section is not sufficient to satisfy the claim of the state for which distraint
or seizure is made, the sheriff or duly authorized employee of the Tax Commissioner
or Department of Labor may thereafter, and as often as the same may be necessary,
proceed to seize and sell in like manner any other property liable to seizure
of the taxpayer against whom such claim exists until the amount due from such
taxpayer, together with all expenses, is fully paid.</para>
<para>(8) If after the sale the money received exceeds the total
of all amounts due the state, including any interest, penalties, additions
to tax, and costs, and if there is no other interest in or lien upon such
money received, the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor shall return
the excess to the person liable for the amounts and obtain a receipt. If any
person having an interest or lien upon the property files with the Tax Commissioner
or Commissioner of Labor prior to the sale notice of his or her interest or
lien, the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor shall withhold any excess
pending a determination of the rights of the respective parties thereto by
a court of competent jurisdiction. If for any reason the receipt of the person
liable for the amount is not available, the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner
of Labor shall deposit the excess money with the State Treasurer, as trustee
for the owner, subject to the order of the person liable for the amount or
his or her heirs, successors, or assigns. No interest earned, if any, shall
become the property of the person liable for the amount.</para>
<para>(9) All persons and officers of companies or corporations
shall, on demand of a sheriff or duly authorized employee of the Tax Commissioner
or Department of Labor about to distrain or having distrained any property
or right to property, exhibit all books containing evidence or statements
relating to the property or rights of property liable to distraint for the
tax due.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 219; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 260, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 77; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 182; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 36, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 165, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB727, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB33, &#167; 4.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>