<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id199"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3003.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3003.02</statuteno><catchline>Operation of cash device; restrictions; requirements; licensee; disciplinary action.</catchline><para>(1) No cash device shall be operated using a credit card, charge card, or debit card.</para><para>(2) No person under twenty-one years of age shall play or participate in any way in the operation of a cash device. No distributor, operator, or employee or agent of any distributor or operator shall knowingly permit any individual under twenty-one years of age to play or participate in any way in the operation of a cash device. The distributor, operator, or employee or agent shall verify the age of any individual requesting to play a cash device and shall comply with subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(3) Beginning August 1, 2026, an operator of a cash device shall not make such device available for play at a retail establishment unless an attendant is physically present on the premises of such retail establishment and capable of actively supervising play of such cash device. An attendant shall be considered to be actively supervising play of such cash device if the attendant:</para><para>(a) Visually confirms the age of the player; and</para><para>(b) Continuously monitors the area in which a cash device is located and intervenes to prevent play of a cash device by any person under twenty-one years of age.</para><para>(4) No distributor or operator shall charge a fee or require a gratuity in return for the payment of any prize money won by a player of a cash device.</para><para>(5) The Tax Commissioner has the authority to suspend or revoke the license of any distributor or operator of a cash device for a violation of this section.</para><para>(6) The department shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for the implementation and enforcement of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB538, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB685, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB901, &#167; 31. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>