<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3904"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3904</statuteno><catchline>Failure to pay tax or fee; lien; procedures; priority; extension; termination; release or subordination.</catchline><para>(1) If any person liable to pay any tax or fee under any tax program administered by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor neglects or refuses to pay such tax or fee after demand, the amount of such tax or fee, including any interest, penalty, and additions to such tax and such additional costs that may accrue, shall be a lien in favor of the State of Nebraska upon all property and rights to property, whether real or personal, then owned by such person or acquired by him or her thereafter and prior to the expiration of the lien. Unless another date is specifically provided by law, such lien shall arise at the time of the assessment and shall remain in effect (a) for three years from the time of the assessment if the notice of lien is not filed for record in the office of the appropriate filing officer, (b) for ten years from the time of filing for record in the office of the appropriate filing officer, or (c) until such amounts have been paid or a judgment against such person arising out of such liability has been satisfied or has become unenforceable by reason of lapse of time, unless a continuation statement is filed prior to the lapse.</para><para>(2)(a) The Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor may present for filing or file for record in the office of the appropriate filing officer a notice of lien specifying the year the tax was due, the tax program, and the amount of the tax and any interest, penalty, or addition to such tax that are due. Such notice shall be filed for record in the office of the appropriate filing officer within three years after the time of assessment. Such notice shall contain the name and last-known address of the taxpayer, the last four digits of the taxpayer's social security number or federal identification number, the Tax Commissioner's or Commissioner of Labor's serial number, and a statement to the effect that the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor has complied with all provisions of the law for the particular tax program which he or she administers in the determination of the amount of the tax and any interest, penalty, and addition to such tax required to be paid.</para><para>(b) If the assets of the taxpayer are in the control or custody of the court in any proceeding before any court of the United States or of any state or the District of Columbia, before the end of the three-year period in subdivision (2)(a) of this section, the notice shall be filed for record within the three-year period or within six months after the assets are released by the court, whichever is later.</para><para>(3)(a)(i) A lien imposed upon real property pursuant to the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act shall be valid against any subsequent creditor when notice of such lien and the amount due has been presented for filing by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor in the office of the Secretary of State and filed in the office of the register of deeds.</para><para>(ii) A lien imposed upon personal property pursuant to the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act shall be valid against any subsequent creditor when notice of such lien and the amount due has been filed by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor in the office of the Secretary of State.</para><para>(b) In the case of any prior mortgage on real property or secured transaction covering personal property so written as to secure a present debt and future advances, the lien provided in the act, when notice thereof has been filed in the office of the appropriate filing officer, shall be subject to such prior lien unless the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor has notified the lienholder in writing of the recording of such tax lien, in which case the lien of any indebtedness thereafter created under such mortgage or secured transaction shall be junior to the lien provided for in the act.</para><para>(4) The lien may, within ten years from the date of filing for record of the notice of lien in the office of the appropriate filing officer, be extended by filing for record a continuation statement. Upon timely filing of the continuation statement, the effectiveness of the original notice shall be continued for ten years after the last date to which the filing was effective. After such period the notice shall lapse in the manner prescribed in subsection (1) of this section unless another continuation statement is filed prior to such lapse.</para><para>(5) When a termination statement of any tax lien issued by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor is filed in the office where the notice of lien is filed, the appropriate filing officer shall enter such statement with the date of filing in the state tax lien index where notice of the lien so terminated is entered and shall file the termination statement with the notice of the lien.</para><para>(6) The Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor may at any time, upon request of any party involved, release from a lien all or any portion of the property subject to any lien provided for in the Uniform State Tax Lien Registration and Enforcement Act or subordinate a lien to other liens and encumbrances if he or she determines that (a) the tax amount and any interest, penalties, and additions to such tax have been paid or secured sufficiently by a lien on other property, (b) the lien has become legally unenforceable, (c) a surety bond or other satisfactory security has been posted, deposited, or pledged with the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor in an amount sufficient to secure the payment of such taxes and any interest, penalties, and additions to such taxes, or (d) the release, partial release, or subordination of the lien will not jeopardize the collection of such taxes and any interest, penalties, and additions to such tax.</para><para>(7) A certificate by the Tax Commissioner or Commissioner of Labor stating that any property has been released from the lien or the lien has been subordinated to other liens and encumbrances shall be conclusive evidence that the property has in fact been released or the lien has been subordinated pursuant to the certificate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1027, &#167; 217; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 523, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 345, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 180; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 165, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 550, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 90.</para></source></law></legaldoc>