<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-3204"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-3204</statuteno><catchline>Reutilization commission; meeting; officers; bond; oath.</catchline><para>(1) The members of a Land Reutilization Commission shall meet immediately after being appointed and qualified and shall select a chairperson, a vice-chairperson, and a secretary.</para> <para>(2) Each commissioner shall furnish a surety bond in a penal sum of not less than fifteen thousand dollars, the premium of such bond to be paid by the authority from which the commissioner was appointed or which he or she represents. The bond shall be issued by a surety company licensed to do business in the State of Nebraska, shall be conditioned to guarantee the faithful performance of all duties under the Land Reutilization Act, and shall be written to cover all the commissioners.</para> <para>(3) Before entering upon the duties of his or her office, each commissioner shall take and subscribe to the following oath:</para> <para>State of Nebraska)</para> <para>) ss.</para> <para>County of .......)</para> <para>I, .........................., do solemnly swear that I will support the Constitution of the United States, and the Constitution of the State of Nebraska, that I will faithfully and impartially discharge my duties as a member of the Land Reutilization Authority of the County of .............. or City of ................, that I will, according to my best knowledge and judgment, administer tax-delinquent lands held by me in trust according to the laws of this state and for the benefit of the public bodies and the tax bill owners which I represent, so help me God.</para> <para>.............................</para> <para>Subscribed and sworn to this ...... day of ............ 20....</para> <para>My commission expires: ........................ .</para> <para>............................. Notary Public</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 73, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 489, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 813, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB360, &#167;  3.</para><effectivedate>August 30, 2009</effectivedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>