<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-4603"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4603</statuteno><catchline>Special session of Legislature; new certification required; recertification; when.</catchline><para>(1) If an estimate of General Fund net receipts is changed in a regular or extraordinary meeting of the Nebraska Economic Forecasting Advisory Board and such change results in a special session of the Legislature to revise current fiscal year General Fund appropriations, the Tax Commissioner and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall certify the monthly receipt estimates, taking into consideration the most recent estimate of General Fund net receipts made by the Nebraska Economic Forecasting Advisory Board plus legislation enacted which has an impact on receipts that was not included in the forecast. The new monthly certification shall be made by the fifteenth day of the month following the adjournment of the special session of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) If an estimate of General Fund net receipts is reduced in a regular or extraordinary meeting of the Nebraska Economic Forecasting Advisory Board, the Tax Commissioner and the Legislative Fiscal Analyst shall recertify the monthly receipt estimates, taking into consideration the most recent estimate of General Fund net receipts made by the Nebraska Economic Forecasting Advisory Board plus legislation enacted which has an impact on receipts that was not included in the forecast. The new monthly certification shall be made by the fifteenth day of the month following the meeting of the Nebraska Economic Forecasting Advisory Board.</para><para>(3) The new certified annual and monthly receipt estimates shall be used for the public statements required under subsection (2) of section 77-4602.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 38, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1290, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB180, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>