<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id726"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-4423"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4423</statuteno><catchline>Refunding bonds; authorized; proceeds; investment.</catchline><para>(1) Any city which has issued bonds pursuant to the Good Life District Economic Development Act or the Community Development Law, and such bonds remain unpaid and are outstanding, is hereby authorized to issue refunding bonds with which to call and redeem all or any part of such outstanding bonds at or before the maturity or the redemption date of such bonds. Such city may include various series and issues of the outstanding bonds in a single issue of refunding bonds and issue refunding bonds to pay any redemption premium and interest to accrue and become payable on the outstanding bonds being refunded. The refunding bonds may be issued and delivered at any time prior to the date of maturity or the redemption date of the bonds to be refunded that the governing body of such city determines to be in its best interests. The proceeds derived from the sale of the refunding bonds issued pursuant to this section may be invested in obligations of or guaranteed by the United States Government pending the time the proceeds are required for the purposes for which such refunding bonds were issued. To further secure the refunding bonds, any such city may enter into a contract with any bank or trust company within or without the state with respect to the safekeeping and application of the proceeds of the refunding bonds and the safekeeping and application of the earnings on the investment. All bonds issued under the provisions of this section shall be redeemable at such times and under such conditions as the governing body of the city shall determine at the time of issuance.</para><para>(2) Any outstanding bonds issued by any such city for which sufficient funds or obligations of or guaranteed by the United States Government have been pledged and set aside in safekeeping to be applied for the complete payment of such bonds at maturity or upon redemption prior to maturity, interest thereon, and redemption premium, if any, shall not be considered as outstanding and unpaid pursuant to the Good Life District Economic Development Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1317, &#167; 16. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Community Development Law,</emphasis> see section 18-2101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>