<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id634"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-4404"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4404</statuteno><catchline>Good life district; application; contents; confidential; limitations.</catchline><para>(1) Until December 31, 2024, any person may apply to the department to create a good life district. All applications shall be in writing and shall contain:</para><para>(a) A description of the proposed project to be undertaken within the good life district, including a description of any existing development, an estimate of the total new development costs for the project, and an estimate of the number of new jobs to be created as a result of the project;</para><para>(b) A map identifying the good life district to be used for purposes of the project;</para><para>(c) A description of the proposed financing of the project;</para><para>(d) Documentation of local financial commitment to support the project, including all public and private resources pledged or committed to the project and including a copy of any operating agreement or lease with substantial users of the project area; and</para><para>(e) Sufficient documents, plans, and specifications as required by the department to define the project, including the following:</para><para>(i) A statement of how the jobs and taxes obtained from the project will contribute significantly to the economic development of the state and region;</para><para>(ii) Visitation expectations and a plan describing how the number of visitors to the good life district will be tracked and reported on an annual basis;</para><para>(iii) Any unique qualities of the project;</para><para>(iv) An economic impact study, including the anticipated effect of the project on the regional and statewide economies;</para><para>(v) Project accountability, measured according to best industry practices;</para><para>(vi) The expected return on state and local investment the project is anticipated to produce; and</para><para>(vii) A summary of community involvement, participation, and support for the project.</para><para>(2) Upon receiving an application, the department shall review the application and notify the good life district applicant of any additional information needed for a proper evaluation of the application.</para><para>(3) The application and all supporting information shall be confidential except for the location of the project, the total new development costs estimated for the project, and the number of new jobs estimated to be created as a result of the project.</para><para>(4) No more than five good life districts may be created statewide. No more than one good life district may be created in any county with a population of five hundred thousand inhabitants or more, excluding any good life district created within a qualified inland port district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB727, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1344, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB707, &#167; 4. </para><effectivedate>June 5, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>