<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-4107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4107</statuteno><catchline>Recapture or disallowance of incentives.</catchline><para>(1) If the taxpayer fails either to meet the required levels of employment or investment for the applicable project by the end of the sixth year after the end of the year the application was submitted for such project or to utilize such project in a qualified business at employment and investment levels at or above those required in the agreement for the entire entitlement period, all or a portion of the incentives set forth in the Employment and Investment Growth Act shall be recaptured or disallowed.</para><para>(2) The recapture or disallowance shall be as follows:</para><para>(a) In the case of a taxpayer who failed to meet the required levels within the required time period, all reduction in the personal property tax because of the Employment and Investment Growth Act shall be recaptured and any reduction in the corporate income tax arising solely because of an election under subsection (1) of section 77-4105 shall be deemed an underpayment of the income tax for the year in which the election was exercised and shall be immediately due and payable; and</para><para>(b) In the case of a taxpayer who has failed to maintain the project at the required levels of employment and investment for the entire entitlement period, any reduction in the personal property tax, any refunds in tax allowed under subdivision (3)(a) of section 77-4105, and any refunds or reduction in tax allowed because of the use of a credit allowed under subsection (4) of section 77-4105 shall be partially recaptured from either the taxpayer or the owner of the improvement to real estate and any carryovers of credits shall be partially disallowed. One-seventh of the refunds, one-seventh of the reduction in personal property tax, and one-seventh of the credits used shall be recaptured and one-seventh of the remaining carryovers and the last remaining year of personal property tax exemption shall be disallowed for each year the taxpayer did not maintain such project at or above the required levels of employment or investment.</para><para>(3) Any refunds or reduction in tax due, to the extent required to be recaptured, shall be deemed to be an underpayment of the tax and shall be immediately due and payable.</para><para>When tax benefits were received in more than one year, the tax benefits received in the most recent year shall be recovered first and then the benefits received in earlier years up to the extent of the required recapture.</para><para>(4) Any personal property tax that would have been due except for the exemption allowed under the Employment and Investment Growth Act, to the extent it becomes due under this section, shall be considered an underpayment of such tax and shall be immediately due and payable to the county or counties in which the property was located when exempted. All amounts received by a county under this section shall be allocated to each taxing unit levying taxes on tangible personal property in the county in the same proportion that the levy on tangible personal property of such taxing unit bears to the total levy of all of such taxing units.</para><para>(5) Notwithstanding any other limitations contained in the laws of this state, collections of any taxes deemed to be underpayments by this section shall be allowed for a period of ten years after the signing of the agreement or three years after the end of the entitlement period, whichever is later.</para><para>(6) Any amounts due under this section shall be recaptured notwithstanding other allowable credits and shall not be subsequently refunded under any provision of the Employment and Investment Growth Act unless the recapture was in error.</para><para>(7) The recapture required by this section shall not occur if the failure to maintain the required levels of employment or investment was caused by an act of God or national emergency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 775, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1234, &#167; 8. </para></source><annotation><para>By its terms, this section does not provide for the retroactive assessment of interest on recaptured personal property taxes. Ameritas Life Ins. Corp. v. Balka, 257 Neb. 878, 601 N.W.2d 508 (1999).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 