<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id34"> <sectno id="id35" opdate="October 1, 2009">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id36" statutenumber="77-4014"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id38">77-4014</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Licensee; file return; contents; pay tax.</catchline><para>(1) On or before the tenth day of each calendar month, every person licensed under subsection (1) of section 77-4009 shall file a return with the Tax Commissioner showing either the quantity and the price of each tobacco product brought or caused to be brought into this state for sale or the quantity and the price of each tobacco product made, manufactured, or fabricated in this state for sale in this state, whichever is applicable, during the preceding calendar month. For snuff, such return shall also include the net weight as listed by the manufacturer.</para> <para>(2) Every person licensed pursuant to subsection (2) of section 77-4009 shall, in the manner described in subsection (1) of this section, file a return showing in detail the different kinds, quantity, and wholesale sales price of each tobacco product shipped or transported to retailers in this state to be sold by such retailers during the preceding calendar month. For snuff, such return shall also include the net weight as listed by the manufacturer.</para> <para>(3) Returns shall be made upon forms furnished and prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. Each return shall be accompanied by a remittance for the full tax liability shown, less an amount of such liability equal to any amount allowed a payer of the sales and use tax pursuant to subdivision (1)(d) of section 77-2708 as compensation to reimburse the licensee for his or her expenses incurred in complying with the Tobacco Products Tax Act.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 730, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2002, Second Spec. Sess., LB 32, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB89, &#167; 5.</para><operativedate>October 1, 2009</operativedate></source>  </law> </legaldoc>