<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-4110"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4110</statuteno><catchline>Annual report; contents.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall submit electronically an
annual report to the Legislature no later than July 15 of each year.</para>
<para>(2) The report shall list (a) the agreements which have been signed
during the previous calendar year, (b) the agreements which are still in effect,
(c) the identity of each taxpayer, and (d) the location of each project.</para>
<para>(3) The report shall also state by industry group (a) the specific incentive
options applied for under the Employment and Investment Growth Act, (b) the
refunds allowed on the investment, (c) the credits earned, (d) the credits
used to reduce the corporate income tax and the credits used to reduce the
individual income tax, (e) the credits used to obtain sales and use tax refunds,
(f) the number of jobs created, (g) the total number of employees employed
in the state by the taxpayer on the last day of the calendar quarter prior
to the application date and the total number of employees employed in the
state by the taxpayer on subsequent reporting dates, (h) the expansion of
capital investment, (i) the estimated wage levels of jobs created subsequent
to the application date, (j) the total number of qualified applicants, (k)
the projected future state revenue gains and losses, (l) the sales tax refunds
owed to the applicants, (m) the credits outstanding, and (n) the value of
personal property exempted by class in each county.</para>
<para>(4) No information shall be provided in the report that is protected
by state or federal confidentiality laws.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 775, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 431, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 138.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>