<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-4933"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4933</statuteno><catchline>Report; contents; joint hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Revenue shall submit electronically an annual report to the Legislature no later than October 31 of each year. The report shall be on a fiscal year, accrual basis that satisfies the requirements set by the Governmental Accounting Standards Board. The report shall list (a) the agreements which have been signed during the previous fiscal year, (b) the agreements which are still in effect, (c) the identity of each company, and (d) the location of each project. The department shall, on or before December 15 of each even-numbered year, appear at a joint hearing of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Revenue Committee of the Legislature and present the report. Any supplemental information requested by three or more committee members shall be presented within thirty days after the request.</para><para>(2) The report shall also state by industry group (a) the amount of wage benefit credits allowed under the Quality Jobs Act, (b) the number of direct jobs created at the project, (c) the amount of direct capital investment under the act, (d) the estimated wage levels of jobs created by the companies at the projects, (e) the estimated indirect jobs and investment created on account of the projects, and (f) the projected future state and local revenue gains and losses from all revenue sources on account of the direct and indirect jobs and investment created on account of the project.</para><para>(3) No information shall be provided in the report that is protected by state or federal confidentiality laws.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 829, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 139; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB612, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1150, &#167; 6. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>