<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-4106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4106</statuteno><catchline>Credits; use; refund claims; procedures; interest; appointment of purchasing agent.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The credits prescribed in section 77-4105 shall be established by filing the forms required by the Tax Commissioner with the income tax return for the year. The credits may be used after any other nonrefundable credits to reduce the taxpayer's income tax liability imposed by sections 77-2714 to 77-27,135. The credits may be used to obtain a refund of sales and use taxes under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the Local Option Revenue Act, and sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 which are not otherwise refundable that are paid on purchases, including rentals, for use at the project.</para><para>(b) The credits may be used as allowed in subdivision (a) of this subsection and shall be applied in the order in which they were first allowed. Any decision on how part of the credit is applied shall not limit how the remaining credit could be applied under this section.</para><para>(c) The credit may be carried over until fully utilized, except that such credit may not be carried over more than eight years after the end of the entitlement period.</para><para>(2)(a) No refund claims shall be filed until after the required levels of employment and investment have been met.</para><para>(b) Refund claims shall be filed no more than once each quarter for refunds under the Employment and Investment Growth Act, except that any claim for a refund in excess of twenty-five thousand dollars may be filed at any time.</para><para>(c) Any refund claim for sales and use tax on materials incorporated into real estate as a part of the project shall be filed by and the refund paid to the owner of the improvement to real estate. A refund claim for such materials purchased by a purchasing agent shall include a copy of the purchasing agent appointment, the contract price, and a certification by the contractor or repairperson of the percentage of the materials incorporated into the project on which sales and use taxes were paid to Nebraska after appointment as purchasing agent.</para><para>(d) All refund claims shall be filed, processed, and allowed as any other claim under section 77-2708, except that the amounts allowed to be refunded under the Employment and Investment Growth Act shall be deemed to be overpayments and shall be refunded notwithstanding any limitation in subdivision (2)(a) of section 77-2708. The refund may be allowed if the claim is filed within three calendar years from the end of the year the required levels of employment and investment are met or within the period set forth in section 77-2708.</para><para>(e) Interest shall not be allowed on any sales and use taxes refunded under the Employment and Investment Growth Act.</para><para>(3) The appointment of purchasing agents shall be recognized for the purpose of changing the status of a contractor or repairperson as the ultimate consumer of tangible personal property purchased after the date of the appointment which is physically incorporated into the project and becomes the property of the owner of the improvement to real estate. The purchasing agent shall be jointly liable for the payment of the sales and use tax on the purchases with the owner of the improvement to real estate.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 775, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1177, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 60. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Local Option Revenue Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,148.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 