<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id165"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id167" statutenumber="77-4105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id169">77-4105</statuteno><catchline id="id170">Incentives; income tax, personal property tax, sales and use tax; credits.</catchline><para>(1) A taxpayer who has signed an agreement under section 77-4104 may elect to determine taxable income for purposes of the Nebraska income tax using the sales factor only. The election may be made for the year during which the application was filed and for each year thereafter through the eighth year after the end of the entitlement period. The election shall be made for the year of the election by computing taxable income using the sales factor only on the tax return.</para><para>(2) A taxpayer who has signed an agreement under section 77-4104 shall receive the incentive provided in this subsection if the agreement contains one or more projects which together will result in the investment in qualified property of at least ten million dollars and the hiring of at least one hundred new employees. Such ten-million-dollar investment and hiring of at least one hundred new employees shall be considered a required level of investment and employment for this subsection and for the recapture of personal property tax only.</para><para>The following property used in connection with such project or projects and acquired by the taxpayer, whether by lease or purchase, after the date the application was filed shall constitute separate classes of personal property:</para><para>(a) Turbine-powered aircraft, including turboprop, turbojet, and turbofan aircraft, except when any such aircraft is used for fundraising for or for the transportation of an elected official;</para><para>(b) Computer systems, made up of equipment that is interconnected in order to enable the acquisition, storage, manipulation, management, movement, control, display, transmission, or reception of data involving computer software and hardware, used for business information processing which require environmental controls of temperature and power and which are capable of simultaneously supporting more than one transaction and more than one user. A computer system includes peripheral components which require environmental controls of temperature and power connected to such computers. Peripheral components shall be limited to additional memory units, tape drives, disk drives, power supplies, cooling units, data switches, and communication controllers; and</para><para>(c) Personal property which is business equipment located in a single project if (i) the business equipment is involved directly in the manufacture or processing of agricultural products and (ii) the investment in the single project exceeds ten million dollars.</para><para>Such property shall be eligible for exemption from the tax on personal property from the first January 1 following the date of acquisition for property in subdivision (2)(a) of this section, or from the first January 1 following the end of the year during which the required levels were exceeded for property in subdivisions (2)(b) and (2)(c) of this section, through the sixteenth December 31 after the filing of the application. In order to receive the property tax exemptions allowed by subdivisions (2)(a), (2)(b), and (2)(c) of this section, the taxpayer shall annually file a claim for exemption with the Tax Commissioner on or before May 1. The form and supporting schedules shall be prescribed by the Tax Commissioner and shall list all property for which exemption is being sought under this section. A separate claim for exemption must be filed for each project and each county in which property is claimed to be exempt. A copy of this form must also be filed with the county assessor in each county in which the applicant is requesting exemption. The Tax Commissioner shall determine the eligibility of each item listed for exemption and, on or before August 1, certify such to the taxpayer and to the affected county assessor.</para><para>(3) When the taxpayer has met the required levels of employment and investment contained in the agreement, the taxpayer shall also be entitled to the following incentives:</para><para>(a) A refund of all sales and use taxes paid under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the Local Option Revenue Act, and sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 from the date of the application through the meeting of the required levels of employment and investment for all purchases, including rentals, of:</para><para>(i) Qualified property used as a part of the project;</para><para>(ii) Property, excluding motor vehicles, based in this state and used in both this state and another state in connection with the project except when any such property is to be used for fundraising for or for the transportation of an elected official;</para><para>(iii) Tangible personal property by the owner of the improvement to real estate that is incorporated into real estate as a part of a project; and</para><para>(iv) Tangible personal property by a contractor or repairperson after appointment as a purchasing agent of the owner of the improvement to real estate. The refund shall be based on fifty percent of the contract price, excluding any land, as the cost of materials subject to the sales and use tax; and</para><para>(b) A refund of the sales and use taxes paid under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the Local Option Revenue Act, and sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 on the types of purchases, including rentals, listed in subdivision (a) of this subsection for such taxes paid during each year of the entitlement period in which the taxpayer is at or above the required levels of employment and investment.</para><para>(4) Any taxpayer who qualifies for the incentives contained in subsections (1) and (3) of this section and who has added at least thirty new employees at the project shall also be entitled to:</para><para>(a) A credit equal to five percent of the amount by which the total compensation paid during the year to employees who are either Nebraska employees or base-year employees while employed at the project exceeds the average compensation paid at the project multiplied by the number of equivalent base-year employees.</para><para>For the computation of such credit, average compensation shall mean the total compensation paid at the project divided by the total number of equivalent employees at the project; and</para><para>(b) A credit equal to ten percent of the investment made in qualified property at the project.</para><para>The credits prescribed in subdivisions (a) and (b) of this subsection shall be allowable for compensation paid and investments made during each year of the entitlement period that the taxpayer is at or above the required levels of employment and investment.</para><para>The credit prescribed in subdivision (b) of this subsection shall also be allowable during the first year of the entitlement period for investment in qualified property at the project after the date of the application and before the required levels of employment and investment were met.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 775, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 1234, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1177, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 142, &#167; 59; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB223, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB965, &#167; 19.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Local Option Revenue Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,148.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference>  </law></legaldoc> 