<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id868"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id45" statutenumber="77-4017"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4017</statuteno><catchline id="id48">Records; requirements; inspection of business.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Every person licensed or certified under the Tobacco Products Tax Act pursuant to subsection (1) or (2) of section 77-4009 shall keep complete and accurate records for all places of business, including itemized invoices of tobacco products (i) held, purchased, manufactured, or brought in or caused to be brought into this state or (ii) for a person located outside of this state, shipped or transported to retailers in this state. Such records shall be of sufficient detail to identify the manufacturer of each tobacco product held, purchased, manufactured, or brought in or caused to be brought into this state. For snuff, such records shall also include the net weight as listed by the manufacturer.</para><para>(b) Every person licensed under subsection (3) of section 77-4009 shall keep complete and accurate records for all places of business, including all itemized invoices of covered tobacco products sold to consumers in this state. Such persons shall also keep records sufficient to identify the purchase price of the covered tobacco products paid by the licensee on such invoices.</para><para>(2) All books, records, and other papers and documents required to be kept by this section shall be preserved for a period of at least three years after the due date of the tax imposed by the Tobacco Products Tax Act unless the Tax Commissioner, in writing, authorizes their destruction or disposal at an earlier date.</para><para>(3) At any time during usual business hours, duly authorized agents or employees of the Tax Commissioner may enter any place of business of a person licensed or certified under the Tobacco Products Tax Act and inspect the premises, the records required to be kept pursuant to this section, and the tobacco products contained in such place of business for purposes of determining whether or not such person is in full compliance with the act. Refusal to permit such inspection by a duly authorized agent or employee of the Tax Commissioner shall be grounds for revocation, cancellation, or suspension of the license or certification.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 730, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB89, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1204, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB212, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2027</operativedate></source></law></legaldoc>