<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-4212"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-4212</statuteno><catchline>Property tax credit; county treasurer; duties; disbursement to counties; State Treasurer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For tax year 2007, the amount of relief granted under the Property Tax Credit Act shall be one hundred five million dollars. For tax year 2008, the amount of relief granted under the act shall be one hundred fifteen million dollars. It is the intent of the Legislature to fund the Property Tax Credit Act for tax years after tax year 2008 using available revenue. For tax year 2017, the amount of relief granted under the act shall be two hundred twenty-four million dollars. The relief shall be in the form of a property tax credit which appears on the property tax statement.</para><para>(2)(a) For tax years prior to tax year 2017, to determine the amount of the property tax credit, the county treasurer shall multiply the amount disbursed to the county under subdivision (4)(a) of this section by the ratio of the real property valuation of the parcel to the total real property valuation in the county. The amount determined shall be the property tax credit for the property.</para><para>(b) Beginning with tax year 2017, to determine the amount of the property tax credit, the county treasurer shall multiply the amount disbursed to the county under subdivision (4)(b) of this section by the ratio of the credit allocation valuation of the parcel to the total credit allocation valuation in the county. The amount determined shall be the property tax credit for the property.</para><para>(3) If the real property owner qualifies for a homestead exemption under sections 77-3501 to 77-3529, the owner shall also be qualified for the relief provided in the act to the extent of any remaining liability after calculation of the relief provided by the homestead exemption. If the credit results in a property tax liability on the homestead that is less than zero, the amount of the credit which cannot be used by the taxpayer shall be returned to the State Treasurer by July 1 of the year the amount disbursed to the county was disbursed. The State Treasurer shall immediately credit any funds returned under this subsection to the Property Tax Credit Cash Fund. Upon the return of any funds under this subsection, the county treasurer shall electronically file a report with the Property Tax Administrator, on a form prescribed by the Tax Commissioner, indicating the amount of funds distributed to each taxing unit in the county in the year the funds were returned, any collection fee retained by the county in such year, and the amount of unused credits returned.</para><para>(4)(a) For tax years prior to tax year 2017, the amount disbursed to each county shall be equal to the amount available for disbursement determined under subsection (1) of this section multiplied by the ratio of the real property valuation in the county to the real property valuation in the state. By September 15, the Property Tax Administrator shall determine the amount to be disbursed under this subdivision to each county and certify such amounts to the State Treasurer and to each county. The disbursements to the counties shall occur in two equal payments, the first on or before January 31 and the second on or before April 1. After retaining one percent of the receipts for costs, the county treasurer shall allocate the remaining receipts to each taxing unit levying taxes on taxable property in the tax district in which the real property is located in the same proportion that the levy of such taxing unit bears to the total levy on taxable property of all the taxing units in the tax district in which the real property is located.</para><para>(b) Beginning with tax year 2017, the amount disbursed to each county shall be equal to the amount available for disbursement determined under subsection (1) of this section multiplied by the ratio of the credit allocation valuation in the county to the credit allocation valuation in the state. By September 15, the Property Tax Administrator shall determine the amount to be disbursed under this subdivision to each county and certify such amounts to the State Treasurer and to each county. The disbursements to the counties shall occur in two equal payments, the first on or before January 31 and the second on or before April 1. After retaining one percent of the receipts for costs, the county treasurer shall allocate the remaining receipts to each taxing unit based on its share of the credits granted to all taxpayers in the taxing unit.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, credit allocation valuation means the taxable value for all real property except agricultural land and horticultural land, one hundred twenty percent of taxable value for agricultural land and horticultural land that is not subject to special valuation, and one hundred twenty percent of taxable value for agricultural land and horticultural land that is subject to special valuation.</para><para>(6) The State Treasurer shall transfer from the General Fund to the Property Tax Credit Cash Fund one hundred five million dollars by August 1, 2007, and one hundred fifteen million dollars by August 1, 2008.</para><para>(7) The Legislature shall have the power to transfer funds from the Property Tax Credit Cash Fund to the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB367, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1087, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB958, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB217, &#167; 22. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>