<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id6"  statutenumber="77-5723"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5723</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Incentives; application;
contents; fee; approval; when; agreements;
contents; modification.</catchline><para>(1) In order to utilize
the incentives set forth in the Nebraska Advantage Act, the taxpayer shall
file an application, on a form developed by the Tax Commissioner, requesting
an agreement with the Tax Commissioner.</para>
<para>(2) The application shall contain:</para>
<para>(a) A written statement describing the plan of employment
and investment for a qualified business in this state;</para>
<para>(b) Sufficient documents, plans, and specifications as required
by the Tax Commissioner to support the plan and to define a project;</para>
<para>(c) If more than one location within this state is involved,
sufficient documentation to show that the employment and investment at different
locations are interdependent parts of the plan. A headquarters shall be presumed
to be interdependent with each other location directly controlled by such
headquarters. A showing that the parts of the plan would be considered parts
of a unitary business for corporate income tax purposes shall not be sufficient
to show interdependence for the purposes of this subdivision;</para>
<para>(d) A nonrefundable application fee of one thousand dollars
for a tier 1 project, two thousand five hundred dollars for a tier 2, tier
3, or tier 5 project, five thousand dollars for a tier 4 project, and ten
thousand dollars for a tier 6 project. The fee shall be credited to the Nebraska
Incentives Fund; and</para>
<para>(e) A timetable showing the expected sales tax refunds and
what year they are expected to be claimed. The timetable shall include both
direct refunds due to investment and credits taken as sales tax refunds as
accurately as possible.</para>
<para>The application and all supporting information shall be confidential
except for the name of the taxpayer, the location of the project, the amounts
of increased employment and investment, and the information required to be
reported by sections 77-5731 and 77-5734.</para>
<para>(3) An application must be complete to establish the date
of the application. An application shall be considered complete once it contains
the items listed in subsection (2) of this section, regardless of the Tax
Commissioner's additional needs pertaining to information or clarification
in order to approve or not approve the application.</para>
<para>(4) Once satisfied that the plan in the application defines
a project consistent with the purposes stated in the Nebraska Advantage Act
in one or more qualified business activities within this state, that the taxpayer
and the plan will qualify for benefits under the act, and that the required
levels of employment and investment for the project will be met prior to the
end of the fourth year after the year in which the application was submitted
for a tier 1, tier 3, or tier 6 project or the end of the sixth year after
the year in which the application was submitted for a tier 2, tier 4, or tier
5 project, the Tax Commissioner shall approve the application. For a tier
5 project that is sequential to a tier 2 large data center project, the required
level of investment shall be met prior to the end of the fourth year after
the expiration of the tier 2 large data center project entitlement period
relating to direct sales tax refunds.</para>
<para>(5) The Tax
Commissioner shall make his or her determination to approve or not approve
an application within one hundred eighty days after the date of the application.
If the Tax Commissioner requests, by mail or by electronic means, additional
information or clarification from the taxpayer in order to make his or her
determination, such one-hundred-eighty-day period shall be tolled from the
time the Tax Commissioner makes the request to the time he or she receives
the requested information or clarification from the taxpayer. The taxpayer
and the Tax Commissioner may also agree to extend the one-hundred-eighty-day
period. If the Tax Commissioner fails to make his or her determination within
the prescribed one-hundred-eighty-day period, the application shall be deemed
approved.</para><para>(6)
Within one hundred eighty days after approval of the application, the Tax Commissioner shall prepare and mail a written agreement to the taxpayer for the taxpayer's signature.
The taxpayer and the Tax Commissioner shall enter into a written agreement.
The taxpayer shall agree to complete the project, and the Tax Commissioner,
on behalf of the State of Nebraska, shall designate the approved plan of the
taxpayer as a project and, in consideration of the taxpayer's agreement, agree
to allow the taxpayer to use the incentives contained in the Nebraska Advantage
Act. The application, and all supporting documentation, to the extent approved,
shall be considered a part of the agreement. The agreement shall state:</para>
<para>(a) The levels of employment and investment required by the
act for the project;</para>
<para>(b) The time period under the act in which the required levels
must be met;</para>
<para>(c) The documentation the taxpayer will need to supply when
claiming an incentive under the act;</para>
<para>(d) The date the application was filed; and</para>
<para>(e) A requirement that the company update the Department of
Revenue annually on any changes in plans or circumstances which affect the
timetable of sales tax refunds as set out in the application. If the company
fails to comply with this requirement, the Tax Commissioner may defer any
pending sales tax refunds until the company does comply.</para>
<para>(7) The incentives contained
in section 77-5725 shall be in lieu of the tax credits allowed by the Nebraska
Advantage Rural Development Act for any project. In computing credits under
the act, any investment or employment which is eligible for benefits or used
in determining benefits under the Nebraska Advantage Act shall be subtracted
from the increases computed for determining the credits under section 77-27,188.
New investment or employment at a project location that results in the meeting
or maintenance of the employment or investment requirements, the creation
of credits, or refunds of taxes under the Employment and Investment Growth
Act shall not be considered new investment or employment for purposes of the
Nebraska Advantage Act. The use of carryover credits under the Employment
and Investment Growth Act, the Invest Nebraska Act, the Nebraska Advantage
Rural Development Act, or the Quality Jobs Act shall not preclude investment
and employment from being considered new investment or employment under the
Nebraska Advantage Act. The use of property tax exemptions at the project
under the Employment and Investment Growth Act shall not preclude investment
not eligible for the property tax exemption from being considered new investment
under the Nebraska Advantage Act.</para>
<para>(8) A taxpayer and the Tax
Commissioner may enter into agreements for more than one project and may include
more than one project in a single agreement. The projects may be either sequential
or concurrent. A project may involve the same location as another project.
No new employment or new investment shall be included in more than one project
for either the meeting of the employment or investment requirements or the
creation of credits. When projects overlap and the plans do not clearly specify,
then the taxpayer shall specify in which project the employment or investment
belongs.</para>
<para>(9) The taxpayer may request
that an agreement be modified if the modification is consistent with the purposes
of the act and does not require a change in the description of the project.
An agreement may not be modified to a tier that would grant a higher level
of benefits to the taxpayer or to a tier 1 project. Once satisfied that the
modification to the agreement is consistent with the purposes stated in the
act, the Tax Commissioner and taxpayer may amend the agreement. For a tier
6 project, the taxpayer must agree to limit the project to qualified activities
allowable under tier 2 and tier 4.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 45; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1003, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB895, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB914, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB164, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1118, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB34, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Employment and Investment Growth Act,</emphasis> see section 77-4101.</para><para><emphasis>Invest Nebraska Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Rural Development Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,187.</para><para><emphasis>Quality Jobs Act,</emphasis> see section 77-4901.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>