<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id76">
<sectno id="id77">Sec. 8.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id78" statutenumber="77-5013"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno id="id80">77-5013</statuteno><catchline id="id81">Commission; jurisdiction;
time for filing; filing fee.</catchline><para>(1) The commission
obtains exclusive jurisdiction over an appeal or petition when:</para>
<para>(a) The commission has the power or authority to hear the
appeal or petition;</para>
<para>(b) An appeal or petition is timely filed;</para>
<para>(c) The filing fee, if applicable, is timely received and
thereafter paid; and</para>
<para>(d) In the case of an appeal, a copy of the decision, order,
determination, or action appealed from, or other information that documents
the decision, order, determination, or action appealed from, is timely filed.</para>
<para>Only the requirements of this subsection shall be deemed jurisdictional.</para>
<para>(2) A petition, an appeal, or the information required by
subdivision (1)(d) of this section is timely filed and the filing fee, if
applicable, is timely received if placed in the United States mail, postage
prepaid, with a legible postmark for delivery to the commission, or received
by the commission, on or before the date specified by law for filing the appeal
or petition. If no date is otherwise provided by law, then an appeal shall
be filed within thirty days after the decision, order, determination, or action
appealed from is made.</para>
<para>(3) The filing fee for each appeal or petition filed with
the commission is twenty-five dollars, except that no filing fee shall be
required for an appeal by a county assessor,
the Tax Commissioner, or the Property Tax Administrator acting
in his or her official capacity or a county board of equalization acting in
its official capacity.</para>
<para>(4) The form and requirements for execution of an appeal or
petition may be specified by the commission in its rules and regulations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB877, &#167; 8.</para></source>
<annotation><para>A separate filing fee must accompany each appeal to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission and must be timely received by the commission in order for it to have jurisdiction over an appeal. Widtfeldt v. Tax Equal. &amp; Rev. Comm., 15 Neb. App. 410, 728 N.W.2d 295 (2007).</para></annotation>
  </law>
</legaldoc>