<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id219">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id221" statutenumber="77-5007">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5007</statuteno><catchline id="id224">Commission;
powers and duties.</catchline><para>The commission has the power
and duty to hear and determine appeals of:</para>
<para>(1) Decisions of any county board of equalization equalizing
the value of individual tracts, lots, or parcels of real property so that
all real property is assessed uniformly and proportionately;</para>
<para>(2) Decisions of any county board of equalization granting
or denying tax-exempt status for real or personal property or an exemption
from motor vehicle taxes and fees;</para>
<para>(3) Decisions of the Tax Commissioner determining the taxable property of a railroad company,
car company, public service entity, or air carrier within the state;</para>
<para>(4) Decisions of the Tax Commissioner determining adjusted valuation pursuant to section
79-1016;</para>
<para>(5) Decisions of any county board of equalization on the
valuation of personal property or any penalties imposed under sections 77-1233.04
and 77-1233.06;</para>
<para>(6) Decisions of any county board of equalization on claims
that a levy is or is not for an unlawful or unnecessary purpose or in excess
of the requirements of the county;</para>
<para>(7) Decisions of any county board of equalization granting
or rejecting an application for a homestead exemption;</para>
<para>(8) Decisions of the Department of Motor Vehicles determining
the taxable value of motor vehicles pursuant to section 60-3,188;</para>
<para>(9) Decisions of the Tax Commissioner made under section 77-1330;</para>
<para>(10) Any other decision of any county board of equalization;</para>
<para>(11) Any other decision of the Tax Commissioner regarding property valuation,
exemption, or taxation;</para>
<para>(12) Decisions of the Tax Commissioner pursuant to section
77-3520;</para>
<para>(13) Final decisions of a county board of equalization appealed
by the Tax Commissioner or Property Tax Administrator pursuant to section
77-701; and</para>
<para>(14) Any other decision, determination, action, or order
from which an appeal to the commission is authorized.</para>
<para>The commission has the power and duty to hear and grant or
deny relief on petitions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1038, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 270, &#167; 102; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 306, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 140, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 194, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 15, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 261, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 280; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB334, &#167; 96; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB877, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 24.</para></source><annotation><para>A county assessor is not required to file a protest with the county board, as described in section 77-1504, before taking an appeal to the Nebraska Tax Equalization and Review Commission under this section. Phelps Cty. Bd. of Equal. v. Graf, 258 Neb. 810, 606 N.W.2d 736 (2000).</para><para>This section does not create a duty on the part of the Tax Equalization and Review Commission to compel the taxpayer to produce more probative evidence at the hearing. J.C. Penney Co., Inc. v. Lancaster Cty. Bd. of Equal., 6 Neb. App. 838, 578 N.W.2d 465 (1998).</para><para>The commission has the power under this statute to hear and determine appeals of any decision of any county board of equalization. McLaughlin v. Jefferson Cty. Bd. of Equal., 5 Neb. App. 781, 567 N.W.2d 794 (1997).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>