<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id174">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id176" statutenumber="77-5003">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5003</statuteno><catchline id="id179">Tax Equalization
and Review Commission; created; commissioners; term; salary.</catchline><para>(1) The
Tax Equalization and Review Commission is created. The Tax Commissioner has
no supervision, authority, or control over the actions or decisions of the
commission relating to its duties prescribed by law. Prior
to July 1, 2011, the commission shall have four commissioners, one commissioner
from each congressional district and one at-large commissioner. On July 1,
2011, the term of each commissioner shall expire, and thereafter the commission
shall have three commissioners, one from each congressional district, with
terms as provided in subsection (2) of this section. All commissioners
shall be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the
members of the Legislature. The
salaries of the commissioners shall be fixed by the Governor.</para>
<para>(2) The term of the commissioner from district 1 expires
January 1, 2016, the term of the commissioner
from district 2 expires January 1, 2018, and the term of the
commissioner from district 3 expires January 1, 2014. After
the terms of the commissioners are completed as provided in this subsection, each subsequent term shall be for
six years beginning and ending on January 1 of the applicable year. Vacancies
occurring during a term shall be filled by appointment for the unexpired term.
Upon the expiration of his or her term of office, a commissioner shall continue
to serve until his or her successor has been appointed.</para>
<para>(3) The commission
shall designate pursuant to rule and regulation its chairperson and vice-chairperson
on a two-year, rotating basis.</para>
<para>(4) A commissioner may be removed by the Governor for misfeasance,
malfeasance, or willful neglect of duty or other cause after notice and a
public hearing unless notice and hearing are expressly waived in writing by
the commissioner.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 465, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 291, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB167, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 21.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>
