<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id326">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id328"  statutenumber="77-5022"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5022</statuteno><catchline id="id331">Commission;
annual meeting; powers and duties.</catchline><para>The commission
shall annually equalize the assessed value or special value of all real property
as submitted by the county assessors on the abstracts of assessments and equalize
the values of real property that is valued by the state. The commission shall
have the power to recess from time to time until
the equalization process is complete. Meetings held pursuant to this section
may be held by means of videoconference or
telephone conference.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1903, c. 73, &#167; 130, p. 434; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 6447; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 133, art. XI, &#167; 4, p. 591; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5901; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 77-1004; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 129, &#167; 1, p. 505; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 77-1004; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 77-505; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 653, &#167; 1, p. 2569; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 508, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 55; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 77-505; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 40; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 140, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 291, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 63; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 43; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB166, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 33.</para></source><annotation><para>The procedures for a hearing to show cause why an adjustment should not be made to a county's valuation of a class or subclass of real property are not governed by section 77-5016(4). Instead, the show cause hearing is part of equalization procedures under this section and sections 77-5023 and 77-5026. County of Webster v. Nebraska Tax Equal. &amp; Rev. Comm., 296 Neb. 751, 896 N.W.2d 887 (2017).</para><para>Authority to equalize the assessments of property among counties has been reserved exclusively to the State Board of Equalization and Assessment. John Day Co. v. Douglas Cty. Bd. of Equal., 243 Neb. 24, 497 N.W.2d 65 (1993).</para><para>The State Board of Equalization and Assessment values and equalizes the property of centrally assessed taxpayers pursuant to this section. In reviewing the county abstracts pursuant to this section, the State Board of Equalization and Assessment deals only with the values of the taxable property of a county in the aggregate. AT&amp;T Information Sys. v. State Bd. of Equal., 237 Neb. 591, 467 N.W.2d 55 (1991).</para><para>Under former law, state board met on first Monday in July. Fromkin v. State, 158 Neb. 377, 63 N.W.2d 332 (1954); County of Buffalo v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 353, 63 N.W.2d 468 (1954); County of Howard v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 339, 63 N.W.2d 441 (1954); County of Douglas v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 325, 63 N.W.2d 449 (1954); County of Grant v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 158 Neb. 310, 63 N.W.2d 459 (1954).</para><para>Where taxpayer sought a reduction of assessment based on alleged errors in method of computation and elements entering into value, the procedure under this section was not applicable. Mid-Continent Airlines, Inc. v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 154 Neb. 371, 48 N.W.2d 81 (1951).</para><para>Under former law State Board of Equalization and Assessment was required to hold regular meeting on first Monday in July. Antelope County v. State Board of Equalization and Assessment, 146 Neb. 661, 21 N.W.2d 416 (1946).</para><para>Under former law board of equalization was required to forward an abstract of assessment rolls to state board on or before July 10 of each year. Farmers Co-op. Creamery &amp; Supply Company v. McDonald, 100 Neb. 33, 158 N.W. 369 (1916); Farmers Co-op. Creamery &amp; Supply v. McDonald, 97 Neb. 510, 150 N.W. 640 (1915), overruling 97 Neb. 512, 150 N.W. 656 (1915).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
