<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-5410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5410</statuteno><catchline>Incentives; transferable; when; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The incentives allowed under the Rural Economic Opportunities Act shall not be transferable except in the following situations:</para><para>(a) Any credit allowable to a partnership, a limited liability company, a subchapter S corporation, a subchapter T cooperative, or an estate or trust may be distributed to the partners, members, shareholders, or beneficiaries in the same manner as income is distributed for use against their income tax liabilities, and such partners, members, shareholders, or beneficiaries shall be deemed to have made an underpayment of their income taxes for any recapture required by section 77-5409; and</para><para>(b) The incentives previously allowed and the future allowance of incentives may be transferred when a project covered by an agreement is transferred in its entirety by sale or lease to another taxpayer or in an acquisition of assets qualifying under section 381 of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(2) The acquiring taxpayer, as of the date of notification of the Tax Commissioner of the completed transfer, shall be entitled to any unused credits and to any future incentives allowable under the act.</para><para>(3) The acquiring taxpayer shall be liable for any recapture that becomes due after the date of the transfer by the repayment of any benefits received either before or after the transfer.</para><para>(4) If a taxpayer operating a project and allowed a credit under the act dies and there is a credit remaining after the filing of the final return for the taxpayer, the personal representative shall determine the distribution of the credit or any remaining carryover with the initial fiduciary return filed for the estate. The determination of the distribution of the credit may be changed only after obtaining the permission of the Tax Commissioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2000, LB 936, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 