
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id154" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-5727"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5727</statuteno><catchline id="id157">Recapture or
disallowance of incentives.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If the taxpayer fails
either to meet the required levels of employment or investment for the applicable
project by the end of the fourth year after the end of the year the application
was submitted for a tier 1, tier 3, or tier 6 project or by the end of the
sixth year after the end of the year the application was submitted for a tier
2, tier 4, or tier 5 project or to utilize such project in a qualified business
at employment and investment levels at or above those required in the agreement
for the entire entitlement period, all or a portion of the incentives set
forth in the Nebraska Advantage Act shall be recaptured or disallowed.</para>
<para>(b) In the case of a taxpayer who has failed to meet the required levels
of investment or employment within the required time period, all reduction
in the personal property tax because of the act shall be recaptured.</para>
<para>(2) In the case of a taxpayer who has failed to maintain the project
at the required levels of employment or investment for the entire entitlement
period, any reduction in the personal property tax, any refunds in tax allowed
under subsection (2) of section 77-5725, and any refunds or reduction in tax
allowed because of the use of a credit allowed under section 77-5725 shall
be partially recaptured from either the taxpayer or the owner of the improvement
to real estate and any carryovers of credits shall be partially disallowed.
The amount of the recapture shall be a percentage equal to the number of years
the taxpayer did not maintain the project at or above the required levels
of investment and employment divided by the number of years of the project's
entitlement period multiplied by the refunds allowed, reduction in personal
property tax, the credits used, and the remaining carryovers. In addition,
the last remaining year of personal property tax exemption shall be disallowed
for each year the taxpayer did not maintain such project at or above the required
levels of employment or investment.</para>
<para>(3) In the case of a taxpayer qualified under tier 5 who has failed
to maintain the average number of equivalent employees at the project at the
end of the six years following the year the taxpayer attained the required
amount of investment, any refunds in tax allowed under subsection (2) of section
77-5725 or any reduction in the personal property tax under section 77-5725
shall be partially recaptured from the taxpayer. The amount of recapture shall
be the total amount of refunds and reductions in tax allowed for all years
times the reduction in the average number of equivalent employees employed
at the end of the entitlement period from the number of equivalent employees
employed in the base year divided by the number of equivalent employees employed
in the base year. For purposes of this subsection, the average number of equivalent
employees shall be calculated at the end of the entitlement period by adding
the number of equivalent employees in the year the taxpayer attains the required
level of investment and each of the next following six years and dividing
the result by seven.</para>
<para>(4) If the taxpayer receives any refunds or reduction in tax to which
the taxpayer was not entitled or which were in excess of the amount to which
the taxpayer was entitled, the refund or reduction in tax shall be recaptured
separate from any other recapture otherwise required by this section. Any
amount recaptured under this subsection shall be excluded from the amounts
subject to recapture under other subsections of this section.</para>
<para>(5) Any refunds or reduction in tax due, to the extent required to be
recaptured, shall be deemed to be an underpayment of the tax and shall be
immediately due and payable. When tax benefits were received in more than
one year, the tax benefits received in the most recent year shall be recovered
first and then the benefits received in earlier years up to the extent of
the required recapture.</para>
<para>(6)(a) Except as provided in subdivision
(6)(b) of this section, any personal property tax that would have
been due except for the exemption allowed under the Nebraska Advantage Act,
to the extent it becomes due under this section, shall be considered delinquent
and shall be immediately due and payable to the county or counties in which
the property was located when exempted.</para>
<para>(b) For a tier 2 large data center project,
any personal property tax that would have been due except for the exemption
under the Nebraska Advantage Act, together with interest at the rate provided
in section 45-104.01 from the original delinquency date of the tax that would
have been due until the date paid, to the extent it becomes due under this
section, shall be considered delinquent and shall be immediately payable to
the county or counties in which the property was located when exempted.</para>
<para>(c) All amounts received by
a county under this section shall be allocated to each taxing unit levying
taxes on tangible personal property in the county in the same proportion that
the levy on tangible personal property of such taxing unit bears to the total
levy of all of such taxing units.</para>
<para>(7) Notwithstanding any other limitations contained in the laws of this
state, collection of any taxes deemed to be underpayments by this section
shall be allowed for a period of three years after the end of the entitlement
period.</para>
<para>(8) Any amounts due under this section shall be recaptured notwithstanding
other allowable credits and shall not be subsequently refunded under any provision
of the Nebraska Advantage Act unless the recapture was in error.</para>
<para>(9) The recapture required by this section shall not occur if the failure
to maintain the required levels of employment or investment was caused by
an act of God or national emergency.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 49; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1003, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB895, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB164, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1118, &#167; 9.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>