<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-5205"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5205</statuteno><catchline>Board; members; vacancies; removal.</catchline><para>The board shall consist of the following members:</para><para>(1) The Director of Agriculture or his or her designee;</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner or his or her designee;</para><para>(3) One individual representing lenders of agricultural credit;</para><para>(4) One individual of the academic community with extensive knowledge and insight in the analysis of agricultural economic issues; and</para><para>(5) Three individuals, one from each congressional district, who are currently engaged in farming or livestock production and are representative of a variety of farming or livestock production interests based on size of farm, type of farm operation, net worth of farm operation, and geographic location.</para><para>All members of the board shall be resident individuals as defined in section 77-2714.01. Members of the board listed in subdivisions (3) through (5) of this section shall be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the Legislature. All appointments shall be for terms of four years.</para><para>Vacancies in the appointed membership of the board shall be filled for the unexpired term by appointment by the Governor. Members of the board shall serve the full term and until a successor has been appointed by the Governor and approved by the Legislature. Any member is eligible for reappointment. Any member may be removed from the board by the Governor or by an affirmative vote by any four members of the board for incompetence, neglect of duty, or malfeasance.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 630, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 