<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id271">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id273" statutenumber="77-5016"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5016</statuteno><catchline id="id276">Hearing or
proceeding; commission; powers and duties; false statement; penalty; costs.</catchline>
<para>Any hearing or proceeding of the commission shall be conducted
as an informal hearing unless a formal hearing is granted as determined by
the commission according to its rules and regulations. In any hearing or proceeding
heard by the commission:</para>
<para>(1) The commission may admit and give probative effect to
evidence which possesses probative value commonly accepted by reasonably prudent
persons in the conduct of their affairs excluding incompetent, irrelevant,
immaterial, and unduly repetitious evidence and shall give effect to the privilege
rules of evidence in sections 27-501 to 27-513 but shall not otherwise be
bound by the usual common-law or statutory rules of evidence except during
a formal hearing. Any party to an appeal filed under section 77-5007 may request
a formal hearing by delivering a written request to the commission not more
than thirty days after the appeal is filed. The requesting party shall be
liable for the payment of fees and costs of a court reporter pending a final
decision. The commission shall be bound by the rules of evidence applicable
in district court in any formal hearing held by the commission. Fees and costs
of a court reporter shall be paid by the party or parties against whom a final
decision is rendered, and all other costs shall be allocated as the commission
may determine;</para>
<para>(2) The commission may administer oaths, issue subpoenas,
and compel the attendance of witnesses and the production of any papers, books,
accounts, documents, statistical analysis, and testimony. The commission may
adopt and promulgate necessary rules for discovery which are consistent with
the rules adopted by the Supreme Court pursuant to section 25-1273.01;</para>
<para>(3) The commission may consider and utilize the provisions
of the Constitution of the United States, the Constitution of Nebraska, the
laws of the United States, the laws of Nebraska, the Code of Federal Regulations,
the Nebraska Administrative Code, any decision of the several courts of the
United States or the State of Nebraska, and the legislative history of any
law, rule, or regulation, without making the document a part of the record.
The commission may without inclusion in the record consider and utilize published
treatises, periodicals, and reference works pertaining to the valuation or
assessment of real or personal property or the meaning of words and phrases
if the document is identified in the commission's rules and regulations;</para>
<para>(4) All evidence,
other than that described in subdivision (3) of this section,
including records and documents in the possession of the commission of which
it desires to avail itself, shall be offered and made a part of the record
in the case. No other factual information or evidence other than that set
forth in this section shall be considered in the determination of the case.
Documentary evidence may be received in the form of copies or excerpts or
by incorporation by reference;</para>
<para>(5) Every party shall have
the right of cross-examination of witnesses who testify and shall have the
right to submit rebuttal evidence;</para>
<para>(6) The commission may take
notice of judicially cognizable facts and in addition may take notice of general,
technical, or scientific facts within its specialized knowledge or statistical
information regarding general levels of assessment within a county or a class
or subclass of real property within a county and measures of central tendency
within such county or classes or subclasses within such county which have
been made known to the commission. Parties shall be notified either before
or during the hearing or by reference in preliminary reports or otherwise
of the material so noticed. They shall be afforded an opportunity to contest
the facts so noticed. The commission may utilize its experience, technical
competence, and specialized knowledge in the evaluation of the evidence presented
to it;</para>
<para>(7) Any person testifying
under oath at a hearing who knowingly and intentionally makes a false statement
to the commission or its designee is guilty of perjury. For the purpose of
this section, perjury is a Class I misdemeanor;</para>
<para>(8) The commission may determine
any question raised in the proceeding upon which an order, decision, determination,
or action appealed from is based. The commission may consider all questions
necessary to determine taxable value of property as it hears an appeal or
cross appeal;</para>
<para>(9) In all appeals, excepting
those arising under section 77-1606, if the appellant presents no evidence
to show that the order, decision, determination, or action appealed from is
incorrect, the commission shall deny the appeal. If the appellant presents
any evidence to show that the order, decision, determination, or action appealed
from is incorrect, such order, decision, determination, or action shall be
affirmed unless evidence is adduced establishing that the order, decision,
determination, or action was unreasonable or arbitrary;</para>
<para>(10) If the appeal concerns
a decision by the county board of equalization that property is, in whole
or in part, exempt from taxation, the decision to be rendered by the commission
shall only determine the exemption status of the property. The decision shall
not determine the taxable value of the property unless stipulated by the parties
according to subsection (2) of section 77-5017;</para>
<para>(11) If the appeal concerns
a decision by the county board of equalization that property owned by the
state or a political subdivision is or is not exempt and there has been no
final determination of the value of the property, the decision to be rendered
by the commission shall only determine the exemption status of the property.
The decision shall not determine the taxable value of the property unless
stipulated by the parties according to subsection (2) of section 77-5017;</para>
<para>(12) The costs of any appeal,
including the costs of witnesses, may be taxed by the commission as it deems
just, except costs payable by the appellant pursuant to section 77-1510.01,
unless (a) the appellant is the county assessor or county clerk in which case
the costs shall be paid by the county or (b) the appellant is the Tax Commissioner
or Property Tax Administrator in which case the costs shall be paid by the
state;</para>
<para>(13) The commission shall
deny relief to the appellant or petitioner in any hearing or proceeding unless
a majority of the commissioners present determine that the relief should be
granted; and</para>
<para>(14) Subdivisions
(3), (6), (8), (9), (10), (11), and (12) of this section apply to hearings
or proceedings before a single commissioner pursuant to section 77-5015.02.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 140, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 968, &#167; 75; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 170, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 419, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 465, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 994, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 291, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 15, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB167, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB877, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 29.</para></source><annotation><para>Where the only issue raised on appeal to the Nebraska Tax Equalization and Review Commission was whether a natural resources district's parcels were being used for a public purpose as required for property tax exemption, the commission lacked jurisdiction to consider questions beyond whether the parcels were being used for a public purpose, including whether the parcels were leased at fair market value and whether assessment of taxes to surface lessees would violate due process. Upper Republican NRD v. Dundy Cty. Bd. of Equal., 300 Neb. 256, 912 N.W.2d 796 (2018).</para><para>The procedures for a hearing to show cause why an adjustment should not be made to a county's valuation of a class or subclass of real property are not governed by subdivision (4) of this section. Instead, the show cause hearing is part of equalization procedures under sections 77-5022, 77 5023, and 77-5026. County of Webster v. Nebraska Tax Equal. &amp; Rev. Comm., 296 Neb. 751, 896 N.W.2d 887 (2017).</para><para>The Tax Equalization and Review Commission determines de novo all questions raised in proceedings before it. Brenner v. Banner Cty. Bd. of Equal., 276 Neb. 275, 753 N.W.2d 802 (2008).</para><para>The Tax Equalization and Review Commission is not required to accept any and all evidence offered during an informal hearing; it has some discretion in determining the probative value of proffered evidence and may exclude that which it determines to be incompetent, irrelevant, immaterial, and unduly repetitious. Brenner v. Banner Cty. Bd. of Equal., 276 Neb. 275, 753 N.W.2d 802 (2008).</para><para>The Tax Equalization and Review Commission is not required to make specific findings with respect to arguments or issues which it does not deem significant or necessary to its determination. Brenner v. Banner Cty. Bd. of Equal., 276 Neb. 275, 753 N.W.2d 802 (2008).</para><para>The taxpayer's burden is to present clear and convincing evidence to rebut the presumption that the Board of Equalization faithfully performed its valuation duties. Brenner v. Banner Cty. Bd. of Equal., 276 Neb. 275, 753 N.W.2d 802 (2008).</para><para>A presumption exists that a board of equalization has faithfully performed its official duties and has acted upon sufficient competent evidence to justify its actions. This presumption remains until there is competent evidence to the contrary presented. Once the presumption has been rebutted, the burden shifts to the party requesting the exemption to prove its entitlement thereto. City of York v. York Cty. Bd. of Equal., 266 Neb. 297, 664 N.W.2d 445 (2003).</para><para>The only material difference between an appeal from a board of equalization before the passage of LB 490 and after is that subsection (5) of this section allows the Tax Equalization and Review Commission to take judicial notice of general, technical, or scientific facts within its specialized knowledge or statistical information regarding general levels of assessment. J.C. Penney Co., Inc. v. Lancaster Cty. Bd. of Equal., 6 Neb. App. 838, 578 N.W.2d 465 (1998).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>