<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id259">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id261" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-5015.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5015.02</statuteno><catchline>Single commissioner hearing; evidence;
record; rehearing.</catchline><para>(1) A single commissioner may hear an appeal and cross appeal
and appeals and cross appeals consolidated with any such appeal and cross
appeal when:</para>
<para>(a) The taxable
value of each parcel is one million dollars or less as determined by the county
board of equalization; and</para><para>(b) The appeal and cross appeal has been
designated for hearing pursuant to this section by the chairperson of the
commission or in such manner as the commission may provide in its rules and
regulations.</para><para>(2) A proceeding held before a single commissioner shall be informal.
The usual common-law or statutory rules of evidence, including rules of hearsay,
shall not apply, and the commissioner may consider and utilize all matters
presented at the proceeding in making his or her determination.</para>
<para>(3) Any party
to an appeal designated for hearing before a single commissioner pursuant
to this section may, prior to a hearing, elect in writing to have the appeal
heard by the commission. The commissioner conducting a proceeding pursuant
to this section may at any time designate the appeal for hearing by the commission.</para>
<para>(4) Documents
necessary to establish jurisdiction of the commission shall constitute the
record of a proceeding before a single commissioner. No recording shall be
made of a proceeding before a single commissioner.</para><para>(5) A party to a proceeding
before a single commissioner may request a rehearing pursuant to section 77-5005.</para>
<para>(6) An order
entered by a single commissioner pursuant to this section may not be appealed
pursuant to section 77-5019 or any other provision of law.</para>
<para>(7)
Subdivisions (3), (6), (8), (9), (10), (11), and (12) of section 77-5016 apply
to proceedings before a single commissioner.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 28.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>