<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id4"><sectno id="id5">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-5209.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5209.02</statuteno><catchline>Personal property tax exemption; authorized; application; form; county assessor; duties; protest; hearing; appeal; continuation of exemption.</catchline><para>(1) Agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment of a qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer utilized in the beginning farmer's or livestock producer's operation may be exempt from tangible personal property tax to the extent provided in this section.</para><para>(2) A qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer seeking an exemption of taxable agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment from tangible personal property tax under this section shall apply for an exemption to the county assessor on or before December 31 of the year preceding the year for which the exemption is to begin. Application shall be on forms prescribed by the Tax Commissioner. For the initial year of application, an applicant shall provide the original documentation of certification provided by the board pursuant to section 77-5208 with the application. Failure to provide the required documentation shall result in a denial of the exemption for the following year but shall be considered as an application for the year thereafter.</para><para>(3) The county assessor shall approve or deny the application for exemption. On or before February 1, the county assessor shall issue notice of approval or denial to the applicant. If the application is approved, the county assessor shall exempt no more than one hundred thousand dollars of taxable value of agricultural or horticultural machinery and equipment for each year. If the application is denied by the county assessor, a written protest of the denial of the application may be filed within thirty days after the mailing of the denial to the county board of equalization.</para><para>(4) All provisions of section 77-1502 except dates for filing of a protest, the period for hearing protests, and the date for mailing notice of the county board of equalization's decision are applicable to any protest filed pursuant to this section. The county board of equalization shall decide any protest filed pursuant to this section within thirty days after the filing of the protest. The county clerk shall mail a copy of any decision made by the county board of equalization on a protest filed pursuant to this section to the applicant within seven days after the board's decision. Any decision of the county board of equalization may be appealed to the Tax Equalization and Review Commission, in accordance with section 77-5013, within thirty days after the date of the decision. Any applicant may petition the Tax Equalization and Review Commission in accordance with section 77-5013, on or before December 31 of each year, to determine whether the agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment will receive the exemption for that year if a failure to give notice as prescribed by this section prevented timely filing of a protest or appeal provided for in this section.</para><para>(5) A properly granted exemption for taxable agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment under this section shall continue for a period of three years if each year a Nebraska personal property tax return and supporting schedules and depreciation worksheet, showing a list and value of all taxable tangible personal property, are provided and filed by the beginning farmer or livestock producer with the county assessor when due. The value of taxable agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment exempted in any year shall not exceed one hundred thousand dollars. The exemption allowed under this section shall continue irrespective of whether the person claiming the exemption no longer meets the qualification of a beginning farmer or livestock producer pursuant to section 77-5209 during the exemption period unless the beginning farmer or livestock producer discontinues farming or livestock production.</para><para>(6) Any person whose agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment has been exempted from tangible personal property tax pursuant to this section shall be permanently disqualified from any further exemption of agricultural and horticultural machinery and equipment from tangible personal property tax as a qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB1027, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 