<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id31"> <sectno id="id32" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id33" statutenumber="77-5714"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id35">77-5714</statuteno><catchline id="id36">Number of new employees, defined.</catchline><para>(1) Number of new employees, for a tier 1, tier 2, tier 3, or tier 4 project, means the number of equivalent employees that are employed at the project during a year that are in excess of the number of equivalent employees during the base year, not to exceed the number of equivalent employees employed at the project during a year who are not base-year employees and who are paid wages at a rate equal to at least sixty percent of the Nebraska average weekly wage for the year of application. </para> <para>(2) Number of new employees, for a tier 6 project, means the number of equivalent employees that are employed at the project during a year that are in excess of the number of equivalent employees during the base year, not to exceed the number of equivalent employees employed at the project during a year who are not base-year employees and who are paid at a rate equal to or greater than the tier 6 weekly required compensation for the year of application.</para> <para>(3) Teleworkers working for wages or salaries in Nebraska from their residences for a taxpayer on tasks interdependent with the work performed at the project shall be considered to be employed at the project.</para> <para>(4) Employees who work at a military installation in Nebraska for a taxpayer on tasks interdependent with the work performed at the project shall be considered to be employed at the project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 36; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB895, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB164, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>