<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id207">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id209" statutenumber="77-5005">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5005</statuteno><catchline id="id212">Commission;
meetings; quorum; orders.</catchline><para>(1) Within ten days
after appointment, the commissioners shall meet at their office in Lincoln,
Nebraska, and enter upon the duties of their office.</para>
<para>(2) A majority of the commission shall at all times constitute a
quorum to transact business, and one vacancy shall not impair the right of
the remaining commissioners to exercise all the powers of the commission.</para>
<para>(3) Any investigation, inquiry, or hearing held or undertaken
by the commission may be held or undertaken by a single commissioner in those appeals
designated for hearing pursuant to section 77-5015.02.</para>
<para>(4) All investigations, inquiries, hearings, and decisions
of a single commissioner and every
order made by a single commissioner shall
be deemed to be the order of the commission,
except as provided in subsection (6) of section 77-5015.02. The
full commission, on an application
made within thirty days after the date of an order,  may grant
a rehearing and determine de novo any decisions of or orders made by the commission. The commission, on an
application made within thirty days after the date of an order issued after
a hearing by a single commissioner, except for an order dismissing an appeal
or petition for failure of the appellant or petitioner to appear at a hearing
on the merits, shall grant a rehearing on the merits before the commission. The
thirty-day filing period for appeals under subsection (2) of section 77-5019
shall be tolled while a motion for rehearing is pending.</para>
<para>(5) All hearings or proceedings of the commission shall be
open to the public.</para>
<para>(6) The Open Meetings Act applies only to hearings or proceedings
of the commission held pursuant to the rulemaking authority of the commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 465, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 291, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 821, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 15, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 23.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Open Meetings Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1407.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>
