<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section id="id44"> <amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id46"  statutenumber="77-5211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id48">77-5211</statuteno><catchline id="id49">Owner of agricultural assets; tax credit; when.</catchline><para>(1) Except as otherwise disallowed under subsection (5) of this section, an owner of agricultural assets shall be allowed a credit to be applied against the state income tax liability of such owner for agricultural assets rented on a rental agreement basis, including cash rent of agricultural assets or cash equivalent of a share-rent rental, to qualified beginning farmers or livestock producers. Such asset shall be rented at prevailing community rates as determined by the board.</para> <para>(2) The credit allowed shall be for renting agricultural assets used for farming or livestock production. Such credit shall be granted by the Department of Revenue only after approval and certification by the board and a written three-year rental agreement for such assets is entered into between an owner of agricultural assets and a qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer. An owner of agricultural assets or qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer may terminate such agreement for reasonable cause upon approval by the board. If an agreement is terminated without fault on the part of the owner of agricultural assets as determined by the board, the tax credit shall not be retroactively disallowed. If an agreement is terminated with fault on the part of the owner of agricultural assets as determined by the board, any prior tax credits claimed by such owner shall be disallowed and recaptured and shall be immediately due and payable to the State of Nebraska.</para> <para>(3) A credit may be granted to an owner of agricultural assets for renting agricultural assets, including cash rent of agricultural assets or cash equivalent of a share-rent agreement, to any qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer for a period of three years. An owner of agricultural assets shall not be eligible for further credits under the Beginning Farmer Tax Credit Act unless the rental agreement is terminated prior to the end of the three-year period through no fault of the owner of agricultural assets. If the board finds that such a termination was not the fault of the owner of agricultural assets, it may approve the owner for credits arising from a subsequent qualifying rental agreement with a different qualified beginning farmer or livestock producer.</para> <para>(4) Any credit allowable to a partnership, a corporation, a limited liability company, or an estate or trust may be distributed to the partners, members, shareholders, or beneficiaries. Any credit distributed shall be distributed in the same manner as income is distributed.</para> <para>(5) The credit allowed under this section shall not be allowed to an owner of agricultural assets for a rental agreement with a beginning farmer or livestock producer who is a relative, as defined in section 36-702, of the owner of agricultural assets or of a partner, member, shareholder, or trustee of the owner of agricultural assets unless the rental agreement is included in a written succession plan. Such succession plan shall be in the form of a written contract or other instrument legally binding the parties to a process and timetable for the transfer of agricultural assets from the owner of agricultural assets to the beginning farmer or livestock producer. The succession plan shall provide for the transfer of assets to be completed within a period of no longer than thirty years, except that when the asset to be transferred is land owned by an individual, the period of transfer may be for a period up to the date of death of the owner. The owner of agricultural assets shall be allowed the credit provided for qualified rental agreements under this section if the board certifies the plan as providing a reasonable manner and probability of successful transfer.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1999, LB 630, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1223, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 990, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1027, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB165, &#167; 15.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>