
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id102">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id104" statutenumber="77-5731"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5731</statuteno><catchline id="id107">Reports; joint hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Commissioner shall submit electronically an annual
report to the Legislature no later than July 15 of each year. The Department of Revenue shall, on or before September
1 of each year, appear at a joint hearing of the Appropriations Committee
of the Legislature and the Revenue Committee of the Legislature and present
the report. Any supplemental information requested by three or more committee
members shall be presented within thirty days after the request.</para>
<para>(2) The report shall list (a) the agreements which have been
signed during the previous year,
(b) the agreements which are still in effect, (c) the identity of each taxpayer
who is party to an agreement, and (d) the location of each project.</para>
<para>(3) The report shall also state, for taxpayers who are parties
to agreements, by industry group (a) the specific incentive options applied
for under the Nebraska Advantage Act, (b) the refunds allowed on the investment,
(c) the credits earned, (d) the credits used to reduce the corporate income
tax and the credits used to reduce the individual income tax, (e) the credits
used to obtain sales and use tax refunds, (f) the credits used against withholding
liability, (g) the number of jobs created under the act, (h) the
expansion of capital investment, (i) the estimated wage levels
of jobs created under the act subsequent to the application date, (j) the total number of qualified applicants, (k) the projected future state revenue gains
and losses, (l) the sales tax refunds
owed, (m) the credits outstanding
under the act, (n) the value of personal
property exempted by class in each county under the act, (o) the
value of property for which payments equal to property taxes paid were allowed
in each county, and (p) the total amount of the
payments.</para>
<para>(4) In estimating the projected future state revenue gains
and losses, the report shall detail the methodology utilized, state the economic
multipliers and industry multipliers used to determine the amount of economic
growth and positive tax revenue, describe the analysis used to determine the
percentage of new jobs attributable to the Nebraska Advantage Act assumption,
and identify limitations that are inherent in the analysis method.</para>
<para>(5) The report shall provide an explanation of the audit
and review processes of the department in
approving and rejecting applications or the grant of incentives and in enforcing
incentive recapture. The report shall also specify the median period of time
between the date of application and the date the agreement is executed for
all agreements executed by December 31 of the prior year.</para>
<para>(6) The report shall provide information on project-specific
total incentives used every two years for each approved project. The report
shall disclose (a) the identity of the taxpayer, (b) the location of the project,
and (c) the total credits used and refunds approved during the immediately
preceding two years expressed as a single, aggregated total. The incentive
information required to be reported under this subsection shall not be reported
for the first year the taxpayer attains the required employment and investment
thresholds. The information on first-year incentives used shall be combined
with and reported as part of the second year. Thereafter, the information
on incentives used for succeeding years shall be reported for each project
every two years containing information on two years of credits used and refunds
approved. The incentives used shall include incentives which have been approved
by the department, but not necessarily received, during the previous two years.</para>
<para>(7) The report shall include an executive summary which shows
aggregate information for all projects for which the information on incentives
used in subsection (6) of this section is reported as follows: (a) The total
incentives used by all taxpayers for projects detailed in subsection (6) of
this section during the previous two years; (b) the number of projects; (c) the new jobs at the project for which
credits have been granted; (d)
the average compensation paid employees in the state in the year of application
and for the new jobs at the project; and (e) the total investment for which
incentives were granted. The executive summary shall summarize the number
of states which grant investment tax credits, job tax credits, sales and use
tax refunds for qualified investment, and personal property tax exemptions
and the investment and employment requirements under which they may be granted.</para>
<para>(8) No information shall be provided in the report that is
protected by state or federal confidentiality laws.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 53; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB895, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 146; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB34, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB612, &#167; 7.</para></source></law>
</legaldoc>