<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id11" statutenumber="77-5601"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5601</statuteno><catchline id="id14">Tax amnesty program; application; department; powers and duties; Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) From August 1, 2004, through October 31, 2004, there shall be conducted a tax amnesty program with regard to taxes due and owing that have not been reported to the Department of Revenue. Any person applying for tax amnesty shall pay all unreported taxes that were due on or before April 1, 2004. Any person that applies for tax amnesty and is accepted by the Tax Commissioner shall have any penalties and interest waived on unreported and delinquent taxes notwithstanding any other provisions of law to the contrary.</para><para>(2) To be eligible for the tax amnesty provided by this section, the person shall apply for amnesty within the amnesty period, file a return for each taxable period for which the amnesty is requested by December 31, 2004, if no return has been filed, and pay in full all taxes for which amnesty is sought with the return or within thirty days after the application if a return was filed prior to the amnesty period. Tax amnesty shall not be available for any person that is under civil or criminal audit, investigation, or prosecution for unreported or delinquent taxes by this state or the United States Government on or before April 16, 2004.</para><para>(3) The department shall not seek civil or criminal prosecution against any person for any taxable period for which amnesty has been granted. The Tax Commissioner shall develop forms for applying for the tax amnesty program, develop procedures for qualification for tax amnesty, and conduct a public awareness campaign publicizing the program.</para><para>(4) If a person elects to participate in the amnesty program, the election shall constitute an express and irrevocable relinquishment of all administrative and judicial rights to challenge the imposition of the tax or its amount. Nothing in this section shall prohibit the department from adjusting a return as a result of any state or federal audit.</para><para>(5)(a) Except for any local option sales tax collected and returned to the appropriate municipality and any motor vehicle fuel, diesel fuel, and compressed fuel taxes, which shall be deposited in the Highway Trust Fund or Highway Allocation Fund as provided by law, no less than eighty percent of all revenue received pursuant to the tax amnesty program shall be deposited in the General Fund and ten percent, not to exceed five hundred thousand dollars, shall be deposited in the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund. Any amount that would otherwise be deposited in the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund that is in excess of the five-hundred-thousand-dollar limitation shall be deposited in the General Fund.</para><para>(b) For fiscal year 2005-06, all proceeds in the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund shall be appropriated to the department for purposes of employing investigators, agents, and auditors and otherwise increasing personnel for enforcement of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967.</para><para>(c) For fiscal years after fiscal year 2005-06, twenty percent of all proceeds received during the previous calendar year due to the efforts of auditors and investigators hired pursuant to subdivision (5)(b) of this section, not to exceed seven hundred fifty thousand dollars, shall be deposited in the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund for purposes of employing investigators and auditors or continuing such employment for purposes of increasing enforcement of the act.</para><para>(d) Ten percent of all proceeds received during each calendar year due to the contracts entered into pursuant to section 77-367 shall be deposited in the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund for purposes of identifying nonfilers of returns, underreporters, nonpayers of taxes, and improper or fraudulent payments.</para><para>(6)(a) The department shall prepare a report by April 1, 2005, and by February 1 of each year thereafter detailing the results of the tax amnesty program and the subsequent enforcement efforts. For the report due April 1, 2005, the report shall include (i) the amount of revenue obtained as a result of the tax amnesty program broken down by tax program, (ii) the amount obtained from instate taxpayers and from out-of-state taxpayers, and (iii) the amount obtained from individual taxpayers and from business enterprises.</para><para>(b) For reports due in subsequent years, the report shall include (i) the number of personnel hired for purposes of subdivision (5)(b) of this section and their duties, (ii) a description of lists, software, programming, computer equipment, and other technological methods acquired and the purposes of each, and (iii) the amount of new revenue obtained as a result of the new personnel and acquisitions during the prior calendar year, broken down into the same categories as described in subdivision (6)(a) of this section.</para><para>(7) The Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund is created. Transfers may be made from the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. The Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund may receive transfers from the Civic and Community Center Financing Fund at the direction of the Legislature for the purpose of administering the Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act. The Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund shall include any money credited to the fund (a) under section 77-2703, and such money shall be used by the Department of Revenue to defray the costs incurred to implement Laws 2019, LB237, (b) under the Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act, and such money shall be used by the department to defray the costs incurred to implement and enforce Laws 2019, LB538, and any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated to carry out Laws 2019, LB538, and (c) under section 77-2906, and such money shall be used by the Department of Revenue to defray the costs incurred to implement Laws 2020, LB310. Any money in the Department of Revenue Enforcement Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section, taxes mean any taxes collected by the department, including, but not limited to state and local sales and use taxes, individual and corporate income taxes, financial institutions deposit taxes, motor vehicle fuel, diesel fuel, and compressed fuel taxes, cigarette taxes, transfer taxes, and charitable gaming taxes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 1017, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB779, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB297, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB642, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB237, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB538, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB310, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Mechanical Amusement Device Tax Act,</emphasis> see section 77-3011.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para><para><emphasis>Sports Arena Facility Financing Assistance Act,</emphasis> see section 13-3101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>