<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id300" statutenumber="77-5726"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5726</statuteno><catchline id="id303">Credits; use;
refund claims; procedures; interest; appointment of purchasing agent; protest;
appeal.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The credits prescribed in section 77-5725
shall be established by filing the forms required by the Tax Commissioner
with the income tax return for the year. The credits may be used and shall
be applied in the order in which they were first allowed. The credits may
be used after any other nonrefundable credits to reduce the taxpayer's income
tax liability imposed by sections 77-2714 to 77-27,135. Any decision on how
part of the credit is applied shall not limit how the remaining credit could
be applied under this section.</para>
<para>(b) The taxpayer may use the credit provided in subsection (3) of section
77-5725 to reduce the taxpayer's income tax withholding employer or payor
tax liability under section 77-2756 or 77-2757 to the extent such liability
is attributable to the number of new employees at the project, excluding any
compensation in excess of one million dollars paid to any one employee during
the year. The taxpayer may use the credit provided in subsection (4) of section
77-5725 to reduce the taxpayer's income tax withholding employer or payor
tax liability under section 77-2756 or 77-2757 to the extent such liability
is attributable to all employees employed at the project, other than base-year
employees and excluding any compensation in excess of one million dollars
paid to any one employee during the year. To the extent of the credit used,
such withholding shall not constitute public funds or state tax revenue and
shall not constitute a trust fund or be owned by the state. The use by the
taxpayer of the credit shall not change the amount that otherwise would be
reported by the taxpayer to the employee under section 77-2754 as income tax
withheld and shall not reduce the amount that otherwise would be allowed by
the state as a refundable credit on an employee's income tax return as income
tax withheld under section 77-2755.</para>
<para>For a tier 1, tier 2, tier 3, or tier 4 project, the amount of credits
used against income tax withholding shall not exceed the withholding attributable
to new employees employed at the project, excluding any compensation in excess
of one million dollars paid to any one employee during the year.</para>
<para>For a tier 6 project, the amount of credits used against income tax
withholding shall not exceed the withholding attributable to all employees
employed at the project, other than base-year employees and excluding any
compensation in excess of one million dollars paid to any one employee during
the year.</para>
<para>If the amount of credit used by the taxpayer against income tax withholding
exceeds this amount, the excess withholding shall be returned to the Department
of Revenue in the manner provided in section 77-2756, such excess amount returned
shall be considered unused, and the amount of unused credits may be used as
otherwise permitted in this section or shall carry over to the extent authorized
in subdivision (1)(e) of this section.</para>
<para>(c) Credits may be used to obtain a refund of sales and use taxes under
the Local Option Revenue Act, the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, and sections
13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 which are not otherwise refundable that are paid
on purchases, including rentals, for use at the project for a tier 1, tier
2, tier 3, or tier 4 project or for use within this state for a tier 2 large data center project or a tier
6 project.</para>
<para>(d) The credits earned for a tier 6 project may be used to obtain a
payment from the state equal to the real property taxes due after the year
the required levels of employment and investment were met and before the end
of the carryover period, for real property that is included in such project
and acquired by the taxpayer, whether by lease or purchase, after the date
the application was filed. Once
the required levels of employment and investment for a tier 2 large data center
project have been met, the credits earned for a tier 2 large data center project
may be used to obtain a payment from the state equal to the real property
taxes due after the year of application and before the end of the carryover
period, for real property that is included in such project and acquired by
the taxpayer, whether by lease or purchase, after the date the application
was filed. The payment from the state shall be made only after
payment of the real property taxes have been made to the county as required
by law. Payments shall not be allowed for any taxes paid on real property
for which the taxes are divided under section 18-2147 or 58-507.</para>
<para>(e) Credits may be carried over until fully utilized, except that such
credits may not be carried over more than nine years after the year of application
for a tier 1 or tier 3 project, fourteen years after the year of application
for a tier 2 or tier 4 project, or more than one year past the end of the
entitlement period for a tier 6 project.</para>
<para>(2)(a) No refund claims shall be filed until after the required levels
of employment and investment have been met.</para>
<para>(b) Refund claims shall be filed no more than once each quarter for
refunds under the Nebraska Advantage Act, except that any claim for a refund
in excess of twenty-five thousand dollars may be filed at any time.</para>
<para>(c) Refund claims for materials purchased by a purchasing agent shall
include:</para>
<para>(i) A copy of the purchasing agent appointment;</para>
<para>(ii) The contract price; and</para>
<para>(iii)(A) For refunds under subdivision (2)(a)(iii) or (2)(a)(v) of section
77-5725, a certification by the contractor or repairperson of the percentage
of the materials incorporated into or annexed to the project on which sales
and use taxes were paid to Nebraska after appointment as purchasing agent;
or</para>
<para>(B) For refunds under subdivision (2)(a)(iv) of section 77-5725, a certification
by the contractor or repairperson of the percentage of the contract price
that represents the cost of materials annexed to the project and the percentage
of the materials annexed to the project on which sales and use taxes were
paid to Nebraska after appointment as purchasing agent.</para>
<para>(d) All refund claims shall be filed, processed, and allowed as any
other claim under section 77-2708, except that the amounts allowed to be refunded
under the Nebraska Advantage Act shall be deemed to be overpayments and shall
be refunded notwithstanding any limitation in subdivision (2)(a) of section
77-2708. The refund may be allowed if the claim is filed within three calendar
years from the end of the year the required levels of employment and investment
are met or within the period set forth in section 77-2708.</para>
<para>(e) If a claim for a refund of sales and use taxes under the Local Option
Revenue Act or sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 of more than twenty-five
thousand dollars is filed by June 15 of a given year, the refund shall be
made on or after November 15 of the same year. If such a claim is filed on
or after June 16 of a given year, the refund shall not be made until on or
after November 15 of the following year. The Tax Commissioner shall notify
the affected city, village, county, or municipal county of the amount of refund
claims of sales and use taxes under the Local Option Revenue Act or sections
13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 that are in excess of twenty-five thousand dollars
on or before July 1 of the year before the claims will be paid under this
section.</para>
<para>(f) Interest shall not be allowed on any taxes refunded under the Nebraska
Advantage Act.</para>
<para>(3) The appointment of purchasing agents shall be recognized for the
purpose of changing the status of a contractor or repairperson as the ultimate
consumer of tangible personal property purchased after the date of the appointment
which is physically incorporated into or annexed to the project and becomes
the property of the owner of the improvement to real estate or the taxpayer.
The purchasing agent shall be jointly liable for the payment of the sales
and use tax on the purchases with the owner of the property.</para>
<para>(4) A determination that a taxpayer is not engaged in a qualified business
or has failed to meet or maintain the required levels of employment or investment
for incentives, exemptions, or recapture may be protested within sixty days
after the mailing of the written notice of the proposed determination. If
the notice of proposed determination is not protested within the sixty-day
period, the proposed determination is a final determination. If the notice
is protested, the Tax Commissioner shall issue a written order resolving such
protests. The written order of the Tax Commissioner resolving a protest may
be appealed to the district court of Lancaster County within thirty days after
the issuance of the order.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2005, LB 312, &#167; 48; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB895, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB914, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB164, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB879, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB1118, &#167; 8.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Local Option Revenue Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,148.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>