<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id301">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id303" statutenumber="77-5018">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5018</statuteno><catchline id="id306">Appeals; decisions
and orders; requirements; publication on web site; correction of errors.</catchline>
<para>(1) The commission may issue decisions and orders which are
supported by the evidence and appropriate for resolving the matters in dispute.
Every final decision and order adverse to a party to the proceeding, rendered
by the commission in a case appealed to the commission, shall be in writing
or stated in the record and shall be accompanied by findings of fact and conclusions
of law. The findings of fact shall consist of a concise statement of the conclusions
upon each contested issue of fact. Parties to the proceeding shall be notified
of the decision and order in person or by mail. A copy of the decision and
order shall be delivered or mailed to each party or his or her attorney of
record. Within seven days of issuing a decision and order, the commission
shall electronically publish such decision and order on a web site maintained
by the commission that is accessible to the general public. The full text
of final decisions and orders shall
be published on the web site,
except that final decisions and orders that are entered (a) on a dismissal
by the appellant or petitioner, (b) on a default order when the appellant
or petitioner failed to appear, (c)
by agreement of the parties,
or (d) by a single commissioner pursuant to section 77-5015.02 may
be published on the web site in a summary manner identifying the parties,
the case number, and the basis for the final decision and order. Any decision
rendered by the commission shall be certified to the county treasurer and
to the officer charged with the duty of preparing the tax list, and if and
when such decision becomes final, such officers shall correct their records
accordingly and the tax list pursuant to section 77-1613.02.</para>
<para>(2) The commission may, on its own motion, modify or change
its findings or orders, at any time before an appeal and within ten days after
the date of such findings or orders, for the purpose of correcting any ambiguity,
clerical error, or patent or obvious error. The time for appeal shall not
be lengthened because of the correction unless the correction substantially
changes the findings or order.</para>
<para>(3) The Tax Commissioner or the Property Tax Administrator
shall have thirty days after a final decision of the commission to appeal
the commission's decision pursuant
to section 77-5019.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 397, &#167; 39; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 465, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 15, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB166, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB877, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB384, &#167; 31.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>