<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-5016.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5016.05</statuteno><catchline>Witnesses; attendance required; fees.</catchline><para>(1) Witnesses cannot be compelled to attend a hearing out of the state where they are served or at a distance of more than one hundred miles from the place of their residence or from the place where they are served with a subpoena, unless within the same county. Witnesses shall not be obliged to attend a deposition outside the county of their residence or outside the county where the subpoena is served.</para><para>(2) The chairperson of the commission may, upon deposit with the commission of sufficient money to pay the legal fees and mileage and reasonable expenses for hotel and meals of such a witness who attends at points so far removed from his or her residence as to make it reasonably necessary that such expenses be incurred, order a subpoena to issue requiring the hearing attendance, but excluding a deposition appearance, of such witness from a greater distance within the state than that provided in subsection (1) of this section. Mileage shall be computed at the rate provided in section 81-1176. The subpoena shall show that it is issued under this section. After the appearance of such witness in response to any such subpoena, the chairperson of the commission shall enter an order directing the payment to the witness from such deposit of such legal fees, mileage, and the actual expenses for hotel and meals incurred by such witness. If such deposit is not adequate for such purpose, the chairperson of the commission shall direct the party procuring the issuance of such subpoena to pay to such witness the deficiency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 56. </para></source></law></legaldoc>