<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-5003"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-5003</statuteno><catchline>Tax Equalization and Review Commission; created; commissioners; term.</catchline><para>(1) The Tax Equalization and Review Commission is created. The Tax Commissioner has no supervision, authority, or control over the actions or decisions of the commission relating to its duties prescribed by law. The commission shall have three commissioners, one from each congressional district, and beginning on and after January 1, 2002, the commission shall have four commissioners. One at-large commissioner shall be appointed in addition to the commissioners representing the congressional districts. All commissioners shall be appointed by the Governor with the approval of a majority of the members of the Legislature.</para><para>(2) The term of the commissioner from district 1 expires January 1, 2010, the term of the commissioner from district 2 expires January 1, 2012, and the term of the commissioner from district 3 expires January 1, 2008. The term of the at-large commissioner expires on January 1, 2008. After the terms of the commissioners are completed as provided in this section, each subsequent term shall be for six years beginning and ending on January 1 of the applicable year. Vacancies occurring during a term shall be filled by appointment for the unexpired term. Upon the expiration of his or her term of office, a commissioner shall continue to serve until his or her successor has been appointed.</para><para>(3) The Governor shall designate one commissioner, who is an attorney admitted to practice before the Nebraska Supreme Court, to serve as the chairperson of the commission from January 1, 2002, through December 31, 2003. Beginning on January 1, 2004, the commission shall designate pursuant to rule and regulation its chairperson and vice-chairperson on a two-year, rotating basis among the commissioners who are attorneys admitted to practice before the Nebraska Supreme Court.</para><para>(4) A commissioner may be removed by the Governor for misfeasance, malfeasance, or willful neglect of duty or other cause after notice and a public hearing unless notice and hearing are expressly waived in writing by the commissioner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1995, LB 490, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1104, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 465, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 291, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB167, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>