<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6841"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6841</statuteno><catchline>Workforce training and infrastructure development; revolving loan program; legislative findings; Department of Economic Development; duties; ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds that providing job training is critical to the public purpose of attracting and retaining businesses and that the growth of high-paying jobs in Nebraska is limited by an unmet need for workforce training and infrastructure development. The Legislature further finds that many communities in Nebraska lack the infrastructure, including broadband access, necessary to provide high-paying jobs for residents. The Legislature further finds that workforce training and infrastructure development help businesses and improve the quality of life for workers and communities in Nebraska. Because there is a statewide benefit from workforce training and infrastructure development, the Legislature intends to provide a revolving loan program as a rational means to address these needs.</para><para>(2) The Department of Economic Development shall establish and administer a revolving loan program for workforce training and infrastructure development expenses to be incurred by applicants for incentives under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act.</para><para>(3) The ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund is hereby created. The fund shall receive money from appropriations from the Legislature, grants, private contributions, repayment of loans, and all other sources. Transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the direction of the Legislature. Any money in the ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act. It is the intent of the Legislature to transfer five million dollars from the General Fund to the ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund for fiscal years 2022-23 and 2023-24 for purposes of carrying out the workforce training and infrastructure development revolving loan program pursuant to the ImagiNE Nebraska Act. It is the intent of the Legislature to appropriate five million dollars for fiscal years 2022-23 and 2023-24 for purposes of carrying out the workforce training and infrastructure development revolving loan program pursuant to the ImagiNE Nebraska Act.</para><para>(4) The Department of Economic Development, as part of its comprehensive business development strategy, shall administer the ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund and may loan funds to applicants under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act to secure new, high-paying jobs in Nebraska based on the criteria established in sections 77-6842 and 77-6843. Loans made to applicants under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act and interest on such loans may be repaid using credits earned under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act. If that occurs, the Department of Revenue shall certify the credit usage to the State Treasurer, who shall, within thirty days, transfer the amount of the credit used from the General Fund to the ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund.</para><para>(5) If a taxpayer with an agreement under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act obtains a loan under this section and fails to attain the required minimum number of new employees, minimum compensation, and minimum required cumulative investment necessary for that taxpayer to earn a credit, the principal and interest of the loan shall be considered an underpayment of tax and may be recovered by the Department of Revenue.</para><para>(6) Whether repaid using credits or repaid directly by the recipient of the loan, loans made from the ImagiNE Nebraska Revolving Loan Fund shall be repaid with interest at the rate established in section 45-102.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 41; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB264, &#167; 163. </para><operativedate>May 22, 2025</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>