<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id39">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id41" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-6305"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6305</statuteno><catchline id="id44">Individual, trust,
or pass-through entity; certification; application; form; director; duties;
qualification; eligibility for tax credits.</catchline><para>(1)
An individual, trust, or pass-through entity may apply to the director for
certification as a qualified investor for a calendar year. The application
shall be in the form and be made under the procedures specified by the director.
The director shall not certify the following types of individuals, trusts,
or pass-through entities as qualified investors:</para>
<para>(a) An individual who controls fifty percent or more of the
qualified small business receiving the qualified investment;</para>
<para>(b) A venture capital company; or</para>
<para>(c) Any bank, savings and loan association, insurance company,
or similar entity whose normal business activities include venture capital
investments.</para>
<para>(2) Within thirty days after receiving an application for
certification under this section, the director shall certify the individual,
trust, or pass-through entity as satisfying the conditions required of a qualified
investor, request additional information, or deny the application. If the
director requests additional information, the director shall certify the individual,
trust, or pass-through entity or deny the application within thirty days after
receiving the additional information. If the director neither certifies the
individual, trust, or pass-through entity nor denies the application within
thirty days after receiving the original application or within thirty days
after receiving the additional information requested, whichever is later,
then the application is deemed approved if the individual, trust, or pass-through
entity meets the qualifications in subsection (1) of this section. An individual,
trust, or pass-through entity which applies for certification and is denied
may reapply.</para>
<para>(3) In order for a qualified investment in a qualified small
business to be eligible for tax credits, a qualified investor who makes the
qualified investment shall have applied for and received certification for
the calendar year in which the qualified investment was made prior to making
the qualified investment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB389, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1067, &#167; 7.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2014</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>