<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id92"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6607"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6607</statuteno><catchline>Tax credit; amount; use; how claimed.</catchline><para>(1) The tax credit under the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act shall be in an amount equal to the product of seven and one-half cents multiplied by the number of pounds of renewable chemicals produced in this state by the eligible business during each calendar year in excess of the eligible business's pre-eligibility production threshold. The maximum amount of tax credits that may be issued to an eligible business under a single tax credit application shall not exceed one million five hundred thousand dollars per year.</para><para>(2) The tax credit shall be a refundable credit that may be used against any income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. Any credit in excess of the eligible business' tax liability shall be refunded to the taxpayer.</para><para>(3) An eligible business shall not receive a tax credit for renewable chemicals produced before the date the business first qualified as an eligible business.</para><para>(4) The tax credit shall not be available for any renewable chemicals produced before the 2022 calendar year.</para><para>(5) Any tax credit allowable to a partnership, a limited liability company, a subchapter S corporation, or an estate or trust may be distributed to the partners, limited liability company members, shareholders, or beneficiaries in the same manner as income is distributed.</para><para>(6) An eligible business shall claim the tax credit by attaching the tax credit certification received from the department under section 77-6606 to its tax return for the tax year in which the credit was approved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 73. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>