<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id481"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6829"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6829</statuteno><catchline>Qualified locations; base-year employment, compensation, and wage levels; review and certification; effect.</catchline><para>(1) The taxpayer may request the director to review and certify that the location or locations designated in the application are qualified locations under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act. The taxpayer shall describe in detail the activities taking place at the location or locations or the activities that will be taking place at the location or locations. The director shall make the determination based on the information provided by the taxpayer. The director must complete the review within ninety days after the request. If the director requests, by mail or by electronic means, additional information or clarification from the taxpayer in order to make his or her determination, the ninety-day period shall be tolled from the time the director makes the request to the time he or she receives the requested information or clarification from the taxpayer. The taxpayer and the director may also agree to extend the ninety-day period. If the director fails to make his or her determination within the prescribed ninety-day period, the certification is deemed approved for the disclosed activities.</para><para>(2) The taxpayer may request the Tax Commissioner to review and certify that the base-year employment, compensation, and wage levels are as reported by the taxpayer pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-6828. Upon a request for such review, the Tax Commissioner shall be given access to the employment and business records of the proposed location or locations and must complete the review within one hundred eighty days after the request. If the Tax Commissioner requests, by mail or by electronic means, additional information or clarification from the taxpayer in order to make his or her determination, the one-hundred-eighty-day period shall be tolled from the time the Tax Commissioner makes the request to the time he or she receives the requested information or clarification from the taxpayer. The taxpayer and the Tax Commissioner may also agree to extend the one-hundred-eighty-day period. If the Tax Commissioner fails to make his or her determination within the prescribed one-hundred-eighty-day period, the certification is deemed approved.</para><para>(3) Upon review, the director may approve, reject, or amend the qualified locations sought in the application contingent upon the accuracy of the information or plans disclosed by the taxpayer that describe the expected activity at the qualified location or locations. Upon review, the Tax Commissioner may also approve or amend the base-year employment, compensation, or wage levels reported pursuant to subsection (1) of section 77-6828 based upon the payroll information and other financial records provided by the taxpayer. Once the director or Tax Commissioner certifies the qualified location or locations and the employment, compensation, and wage levels at the qualified location or locations, the certification is binding on the Department of Revenue when the taxpayer claims benefits on a return to the extent the activities performed at the location or locations are as described in the application, the information and plans provided by the taxpayer were accurate, and the base-year information is not affected by transfers of employees from another location in Nebraska, the acquisition of a business, or moving businesses or entities to or from the qualified location or locations.</para><para>(4) If the taxpayer does not request review and certification of whether the designated location or locations are qualified, or the base-year employment, compensation, and wage levels, those items are subject to later audit by the Department of Revenue.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 29. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>