<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id726"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6928"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6928</statuteno><catchline>Reports.</catchline><para>(1) On or before July 15, 2024, and on or before July 15 of each year thereafter, the Director of Economic Development shall prepare a report that includes:</para><para>(a) The total amount of investment at qualified locations in the previous calendar year by taxpayers who are receiving incentives pursuant to the Urban Redevelopment Act;</para><para>(b) The total number of equivalent employees added in the previous calendar year by taxpayers who are receiving incentives pursuant to the act; and</para><para>(c) The total amount of credits claimed and refunds approved in the previous calendar year under the act.</para><para>(2) The report shall also provide information on project-specific total incentives used every two years for each approved project, including (a) the identity of the taxpayer, (b) the qualified location of the project, and (c) the total credits used and refunds approved during the immediately preceding two years expressed as a single, aggregated total. The incentive information required to be reported under this subsection shall not be reported for the first year the taxpayer attains the required employment and investment thresholds. The information on first-year incentives used shall be combined with and reported as part of the second year. Thereafter, the information on incentives used for succeeding years shall be reported for each project every two years and shall include information on two years of credits used and refunds approved. The incentives used shall include incentives that have been approved by the Director of Economic Development, but not necessarily received, during the previous two calendar years.</para><para>(3) On or before September 1, 2024, and on or before September 1 of each year thereafter, the Department of Economic Development shall present the report electronically to the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature. Any supplemental information requested by three or more committee members shall be presented within thirty days after the request.</para><para>(4) No information shall be provided in the report that is protected by state or federal confidentiality laws.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB544, &#167; 28. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>