<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" statutenumber="77-6104" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6104</statuteno><catchline>Nebraska long-term care savings plan trust; created; State Treasurer; state investment officer; duties.</catchline><para>If an administrator for the Nebraska long-term care savings plan is selected pursuant to section 77-6103, the Nebraska long-term care savings plan trust shall be created. The State Treasurer shall be the trustee of the trust and as such responsible for the administration, operation, and maintenance of the plan and shall have all powers necessary to carry out and effectuate the purposes, objectives, and provisions of the Long-Term Care Savings Plan Act pertaining to the administration, operation, and maintenance of the trust, except that the state investment officer shall have fiduciary responsibility to make all decisions regarding the investment of the money in the trust, including the selection of all investment options and the approval of all fees and other costs charged to trust assets except costs for administration, operation, and maintenance of the trust, pursuant to the directions, guidelines, and policies established by the Nebraska Investment Council. The State Treasurer may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to provide for the efficient administration, operation, and maintenance of the trust. The State Treasurer shall not adopt and promulgate rules and regulations that in any way interfere with the fiduciary responsibility of the state investment officer to make all decisions regarding the investment of money in the trust. The Nebraska Investment Council may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations to provide for the prudent investment of the assets of the trust. The council or its designee also has the authority to select and enter into agreements with individuals and entities to provide investment advice and management of the assets held by the trust, establish investment guidelines, objectives, and performance standards with respect to the assets held by the trust, and approve any fees, commissions, and expenses which directly or indirectly affect the return on assets. </para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 965, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>