<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id320"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6706"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6706</statuteno><catchline>Tax credit for community college taxes paid.</catchline><para>(1) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2022, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, there shall be allowed to each eligible taxpayer a refundable credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 or against the franchise tax imposed by sections 77-3801 to 77-3807. The credit shall be equal to the credit percentage for the taxable year, as set by the department under subsection (2) of this section, multiplied by the amount of community college taxes paid by the eligible taxpayer during such taxable year.</para><para>(2)(a) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2022, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be fifty million dollars;</para><para>(b) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2023, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be one hundred million dollars;</para><para>(c) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2024, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be one hundred twenty-five million dollars;</para><para>(d) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2025, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be one hundred fifty million dollars;</para><para>(e) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2026, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be one hundred ninety-five million dollars; and</para><para>(f) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2027 and each calendar year thereafter, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be the maximum amount of credits allowed in the prior year increased by the allowable growth percentage.</para><para>(3) If the community college taxes are paid by a corporation having an election in effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code, a partnership, a limited liability company, a trust, or an estate, the refundable credit shall be claimed by such corporation, partnership, limited liability company, trust, or estate.</para><para>(4) For any fiscal year or short year taxpayer, the credit may be claimed in the first taxable year that begins following the calendar year for which the credit percentage was determined. The credit shall be taken for the community college taxes paid by the taxpayer during the immediately preceding calendar year.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2022, LB873, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para> </crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>