<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id873"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6606"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6606</statuteno><catchline>Tax credit; application; contents; requirements; approval; effect.</catchline><para>(1) An eligible business may apply to the Department of Revenue for tax credits under the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act.</para><para>(2) To receive tax credits, the eligible business shall submit a tax credit application to the Department of Revenue on a form prescribed by the department. The tax credit application shall be made during the calendar year following the calendar year in which the eligible business produced the renewable chemicals for which it seeks tax credits. The tax credit application shall include the following information:</para><para>(a) The number of pounds of renewable chemicals produced in the state by the eligible business during the calendar year for which tax credits are sought; and</para><para>(b) Any other information reasonably required by the department in order to establish and verify the amount of credits earned under the act.</para><para>(3) An eligible business shall fulfill all the requirements of the act and its agreement with the director under section 77-6604 before receiving tax credits under the act or entering into a subsequent agreement. If an agreement is not successfully fulfilled, the director may decline to enter into a subsequent agreement and the Department of Revenue may decline to issue a tax credit.</para><para>(4) If the department determines that a tax credit application is complete, that an eligible business qualifies for tax credits, and that the eligible business has fulfilled all requirements of its agreement with the director, the department shall approve the tax credit application within the limits set forth in sections 77-6605 and 77-6607 and shall certify the amount of tax credits approved to the eligible business.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 72. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>