<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id182">
<sectno id="id183">Sec. 15.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" id="id184" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="77-6204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6204</statuteno><catchline>County treasurer; distribute revenue;
calculation.</catchline><para>(1) The county treasurer shall distribute all revenue received
from the Department of Revenue pursuant to section 77-6203 to local taxing
entities which, but for such personal property tax exemption, would have received
distribution of personal property tax revenue from depreciable personal property
used directly in the generation of electricity using wind as the fuel source.</para>
<para>(2) A local
taxing entity's status as eligible for distribution under subsection (1) of
this section shall not be affected when and if the net book value of personal
property used directly in the generation of electricity using wind as the
fuel source becomes zero. A local taxing entity's status as eligible for distribution
under such subsection shall be affected by the disposal of all of the exempt
depreciable personal property used directly in the generation of electricity
using wind as the fuel source.</para><para>(3) The distribution to each eligible local
taxing entity shall be calculated by determining the amount of taxes that
the eligible local taxing entity levied during the taxable year and dividing
this amount by the total tax levied by all of the eligible local taxing entities
during the year. Each eligible entity's resulting fraction shall then be multiplied
by the revenue distributed to the county treasurer by the department to determine
the portion of such revenue due each local taxing entity.</para>
<para>(4) The Department
of Revenue shall not retain any revenue collected pursuant to sections 77-6201
to 77-6204 for distribution, use, transfer, pledge, or allocation to or from
the General Fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 15.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>