<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id237"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6920"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6920</statuteno><catchline>Tax credits; conditions; amounts; teleworker; treatment.</catchline><para>(1) A tax credit shall be allowed to any taxpayer who has an approved application pursuant to the Urban Redevelopment Act if the taxpayer:</para><para>(a) Attains a cumulative investment in qualified property of at least one hundred fifty thousand dollars and hires at least five new employees at the qualified location before the end of the ramp-up period; and</para><para>(b) Pays a minimum qualifying wage of seventy percent of the Nebraska statewide average hourly wage to the new equivalent employees for whom tax incentives are sought under the Urban Redevelopment Act.</para><para>(2) A tax credit shall be allowed to any taxpayer who has an approved application pursuant to the Urban Redevelopment Act if the taxpayer attains a cumulative investment in qualified property of at least fifty thousand dollars at the qualified location before the end of the ramp-up period.</para><para>(3) Subject to subsection (5) of this section, the amount of the credit allowed under subsection (1) of this section shall be:</para><para>(a) Three thousand dollars for each new equivalent employee, except that such amount shall be increased by one thousand dollars for each equivalent employee who lives in an economic redevelopment area; and</para><para>(b) Two thousand seven hundred fifty dollars for each fifty thousand dollars of increased investment.</para><para>(4) Subject to subsection (5) of this section, the amount of the credit allowed under subsection (2) of this section shall be five percent of the investment.</para><para>(5) A taxpayer may qualify for a credit under either subsection (1) or (2) of this section, but cannot qualify for a credit under both such subsections. The credit shall not exceed fifty thousand dollars. The taxpayer shall receive such credit for each year of the performance period that the taxpayer is at or above the required levels of employment and cumulative investment.</para><para>(6) A taxpayer shall not qualify for any credits under the Urban Redevelopment Act if the taxpayer is receiving any benefits under any other tax incentive program offered by the State of Nebraska.</para><para>(7) A teleworker working from his or her residence shall not be considered an equivalent employee of the taxpayer for purposes of the Urban Redevelopment Act unless the teleworker's residence is located in the economic redevelopment area in which the taxpayer's qualified location is located.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB544, &#167; 20. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>