<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id958"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6921"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6921</statuteno><catchline>Existing business acquisition, disposal, reorganization, or relocation; computation; certain transactions excluded.</catchline><para>(1)(a) If the taxpayer acquires an existing business, the increases in investment and employment shall be computed as though the taxpayer had owned the business for the entire taxable year preceding the date of application.</para><para>(b) If the taxpayer disposes of an existing business and the new owner maintains the minimum increases in investment and employment required to create incentives, the taxpayer shall not be required to make any repayment under section 77-6923 solely because of the disposition of the business.</para><para>(2) If the structure of a business is reorganized, the taxpayer shall compute the increases on a consistent basis for all periods.</para><para>(3) If the taxpayer moves a business from one qualified location to another qualified location and the business was operated in a qualified location during the taxable year preceding the date of application, the increases in investment and employment shall be computed as though the taxpayer had operated the business at the new location for the entire taxable year preceding the date of application.</para><para>(4) If the taxpayer enters into any of the following transactions, the transaction shall be presumed to be a transaction entered into for the purpose of generating benefits under the Urban Redevelopment Act and shall not be allowed in the computation of any benefit or the meeting of any required levels under the agreement except as specifically provided in this subsection:</para><para>(a) The purchase or lease of any property that was previously owned by the taxpayer who filed the application or a related taxpayer unless the first purchase by either the taxpayer who filed the application or a related taxpayer was first placed in service at a qualified location after the beginning of the taxable year the application was filed;</para><para>(b) The renegotiation of any lease in existence during the taxable year the application was filed which does not materially change any of the terms of the lease other than the expiration date;</para><para>(c) The purchase or lease of any property from a related taxpayer, except that the taxpayer who filed the application will be allowed any benefits under the act to which the related taxpayer would have been entitled on the purchase or lease of the property if the related taxpayer was considered the taxpayer; and</para><para>(d) Any transaction entered into primarily for the purpose of receiving benefits under the act which is without a business purpose and does not result in increased economic activity in the state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB544, &#167; 21. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>