<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6703"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6703</statuteno><catchline>Tax credit for school district taxes paid.</catchline><para>(1) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2020, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, there shall be allowed to each eligible taxpayer a refundable credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 or against the franchise tax imposed by sections 77-3801 to 77-3807. The credit shall be equal to the credit percentage for the taxable year, as set by the department under subsection (2) of this section, multiplied by the amount of school district taxes paid by the eligible taxpayer during such taxable year.</para><para>(2)(a) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2020, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be one hundred twenty-five million dollars;</para><para>(b) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2021, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be one hundred twenty-five million dollars plus either (i) the amount calculated for such calendar year under subdivision (3)(b)(ii)(B) of section 77-4602 or (ii) the amount calculated for such calendar year under subdivision (3)(c)(ii)(B) of section 77-4602, whichever is applicable;</para><para>(c) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2022, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be five hundred forty-eight million dollars;</para><para>(d) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2023, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be five hundred sixty million seven hundred thousand dollars;</para><para>(e) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2024 through calendar year 2028, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be the maximum amount of credits allowed in the prior year increased by the allowable growth percentage;</para><para>(f) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2029, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be the maximum amount of credits allowed in the prior year increased by the allowable growth percentage plus an additional seventy-five million dollars; and</para><para>(g) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin during calendar year 2030 and each calendar year thereafter, the department shall set the credit percentage so that the total amount of credits for such taxable years shall be the maximum amount of credits allowed in the prior year increased by the allowable growth percentage.</para><para>(3) If the school district taxes are paid by a corporation having an election in effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code, a partnership, a limited liability company, a trust, or an estate, the amount of school district taxes paid during the taxable year may be allocated to the shareholders, partners, members, or beneficiaries in the same proportion that income is distributed for taxable years beginning or deemed to begin before January 1, 2021, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended. The department shall provide forms and schedules necessary for verifying eligibility for the credit provided in this section and for allocating the school district taxes paid. For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2021, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, the refundable credit shall be claimed by the corporation having an election in effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code, the partnership, the limited liability company, the trust, or the estate that paid the school district taxes.</para><para>(4) For any fiscal year or short year taxpayer, the credit may be claimed in the first taxable year that begins following the calendar year for which the credit percentage was determined. The credit shall be taken for the school district taxes paid by the taxpayer during the immediately preceding calendar year.</para><para>(5) For the first taxable year beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2021, and before January 1, 2022, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, for a corporation having an election in effect under subchapter S of the Internal Revenue Code, a partnership, a limited liability company, a trust, or an estate that paid school district taxes in calendar year 2020 but did not claim the credit directly or allocate such school district taxes to the shareholders, partners, members, or beneficiaries as permitted under subsection (3) of this section, there shall be allowed an additional refundable credit. This credit shall be equal to six percent, multiplied by the amount of school district taxes paid during 2020 by the eligible taxpayer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 113; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB181, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB873, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2023, LB243, &#167; 18. </para><operativedate>September 2, 2023</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>