<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id273"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6832"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6832</statuteno><catchline>Income tax credits; use; tax incentive credits; use; refund claims; filing requirements; audit; director; Tax Commissioner; powers and duties; appeal.</catchline><para>(1)(a) The credits prescribed in section 77-6831 for a year shall be established by filing the forms required by the Tax Commissioner with the income tax return for the taxable year which includes the end of the year the credits were earned. The credits may be used and shall be applied in the order in which they were first allowable under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act. To the extent the taxpayer has credits under the Nebraska Advantage Act or the Employment and Investment Growth Act still available for use in a year or years which overlap the performance period or carryover period of the ImagiNE Nebraska Act, the credits may be used and shall be applied in the order in which they were first allowable, and when there are credits of the same age, the older tax incentive program's credits shall be applied first. The credits may be used after any other nonrefundable credits to reduce the taxpayer's income tax liability imposed by sections 77-2714 to 77-27,135. Credits may be used beginning with the taxable year which includes December 31 of the year the required minimum levels were reached. The last year for which credits may be used is the taxable year which includes December 31 of the last year of the carryover period. Any decision on how part of the credit is applied shall not limit how the remaining credit could be applied under this section.</para><para>(b) The taxpayer may use the credit provided in subsection (4) of section 77-6831 to reduce the taxpayer's income tax withholding employer or payor tax liability under section 77-2756 or 77-2757, or to reduce a qualified employee leasing company's income tax withholding employer or payor tax liability under such sections, when the taxpayer is the client-lessee of such company, to the extent such liability is attributable to the number of new employees employed at the qualified location or locations, excluding any wages in excess of one million dollars paid to any one employee during the year. To the extent of the credit used, such withholding shall not constitute public funds or state tax revenue and shall not constitute a trust fund or be owned by the state. The use by the taxpayer or the qualified employee leasing company of the credit shall not change the amount that otherwise would be reported by the taxpayer, or such qualified employee leasing company, to the employee under section 77-2754 as income tax withheld and shall not reduce the amount that otherwise would be allowed by the state as a refundable credit on an employee's income tax return as income tax withheld under section 77-2755. The amount of credits used against income tax withholding shall not exceed the withholding attributable to the number of new employees employed at the qualified location or locations, excluding any wages in excess of one million dollars paid to any one employee during the year. If the amount of credit used by the taxpayer or the qualified employee leasing company against income tax withholding exceeds such amount, the excess withholding shall be returned to the Department of Revenue in the manner provided in section 77-2756, such excess amount returned shall be considered unused, and the amount of unused credits may be used as otherwise permitted in this section or shall carry over to the extent authorized in subdivision (1)(g) of this section.</para><para>(c) Credits may be used to obtain a refund of sales and use taxes under the Local Option Revenue Act, the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, the Qualified Judgment Payment Act, and sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 that are not subject to direct refund under section 77-6831 and that are paid on purchases, including rentals, for use at a qualified location.</para><para>(d) The credits provided in subsections (4) and (5) of section 77-6831 may be used to repay a loan for job training or infrastructure development as provided in section 77-6841.</para><para>(e) Credits may be used to obtain a payment from the state equal to the amount which the taxpayer demonstrates to the director was paid by the taxpayer after the date of the complete application for job training and talent recruitment of employees who qualify in the number of new employees, to the extent that proceeds from a loan described in section 77-6841 were not used to make such payments. For purposes of this subdivision:</para><para>(i) Job training means training for a prospective or new employee that is provided after the date of the complete application by a Nebraska nonprofit college or university, a Nebraska public or private secondary school, a Nebraska educational service unit, or a company that is not a member of the taxpayer's unitary group or a related person to the taxpayer; and</para><para>(ii) Talent recruitment means talent recruitment activities that result in a newly recruited employee who is hired by the taxpayer after the date of the complete application and who is paid compensation during the year of hire at a rate equal to at least one hundred percent of the Nebraska statewide average hourly wage for the year of application, including marketing, relocation expenses, and search-firm fees. Talent recruitment payments that may be reimbursed include, without limitation, payment by the taxpayer, without repayment by the employee, of an employee's student loans, an employee's tuition, and an employee's downpayment on a primary residence in Nebraska. Talent recruitment payments that may be reimbursed shall not include payments for the recruitment of a person who constitutes a related person to the taxpayer when the taxpayer is an individual or recruitment of a person who constitutes a related person to an owner of the taxpayer when the taxpayer is a partnership, a limited liability company, or a subchapter S corporation.</para><para>(f) The credits provided in subsections (4) and (5) of section 77-6831 may be used to obtain a payment from the state equal to the amount which the taxpayer demonstrates to the director was paid for taxpayer-sponsored child care at the qualified location or locations during the performance period and the carryover period.</para><para>(g) Credits may be carried over until fully utilized through the end of the carryover period.</para><para>(2)(a) No refund claims shall be filed until after the required levels of employment and investment have been met.</para><para>(b) Refund claims shall be filed no more than once each quarter for refunds under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act, except that any claim for a refund in excess of twenty-five thousand dollars may be filed at any time.</para><para>(c) Refund claims for materials purchased by a purchasing agent shall include:</para><para>(i) A copy of the purchasing agent appointment;</para><para>(ii) The contract price; and</para><para>(iii)(A) For refunds under subdivision (2)(a)(iii) or (2)(a)(v) of section 77-6831, a certification by the contractor or repairperson of the percentage of the materials incorporated into or annexed to the qualified location on which sales and use taxes were paid to Nebraska after appointment as purchasing agent; or</para><para>(B) For refunds under subdivision (2)(a)(iv) of section 77-6831, a certification by the contractor or repairperson of the percentage of the contract price that represents the cost of materials annexed to the qualified location and the percentage of the materials annexed to the qualified location on which sales and use taxes were paid to Nebraska after appointment as purchasing agent.</para><para>(d) All refund claims shall be filed, processed, and allowed as any other claim under section 77-2708, except that the amounts allowed to be refunded under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act shall be deemed to be overpayments and shall be refunded notwithstanding any limitation in subdivision (2)(a) of section 77-2708. The refund may be allowed if the claim is filed within three years from the end of the year the required levels of employment and investment are met or within the period set forth in section 77-2708. Refunds shall be paid by the Tax Commissioner within one hundred eighty days after receipt of the refund claim. Such payments shall be subject to later recovery by the Tax Commissioner upon audit.</para><para>(e) If a claim for a refund of sales and use taxes under the Local Option Revenue Act, the Qualified Judgment Payment Act, or sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 of more than twenty-five thousand dollars is filed by June 15 of a given year, the refund shall be made on or after November 15 of the same year. If such a claim is filed on or after June 16 of a given year, the refund shall not be made until on or after November 15 of the following year. The Tax Commissioner shall notify the affected city, village, county, or municipal county of the amount of refund claims of sales and use taxes under the Local Option Revenue Act, the Qualified Judgment Payment Act, or sections 13-319, 13-324, and 13-2813 that are in excess of twenty-five thousand dollars on or before July 1 of the year before the claims will be paid under this section.</para><para>(f) For refunds of sales and use taxes under the Local Option Revenue Act, the deductions made by the Tax Commissioner for such refunds shall be delayed in accordance with section 77-27,144.</para><para>(g) Interest shall not be allowed on any taxes refunded under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act.</para><para>(3) The appointment of purchasing agents shall be recognized for the purpose of changing the status of a contractor or repairperson as the ultimate consumer of tangible personal property purchased after the date of the appointment which is physically incorporated into or annexed at a qualified location and becomes the property of the owner of the improvement to real estate or the taxpayer. The purchasing agent shall be jointly liable for the payment of the sales and use tax on the purchases with the owner of the property.</para><para>(4) The determination of whether the application is complete, whether a location is a qualified location, and whether to approve the application and sign the agreement shall be made by the director. All other interpretations of the ImagiNE Nebraska Act shall be made by the Tax Commissioner. The Commissioner of Labor shall provide the director with such information as the Department of Labor regularly receives with respect to the taxpayer which the director requests from the Commissioner of Labor in order to fulfill the director's duties under the act. The director shall use such information to achieve efficiency in the administration of the act.</para><para>(5) Once the director and the taxpayer have signed the agreement under section 77-6828, the taxpayer, and its owners or members where applicable, may report and claim and shall receive all incentives allowed by the ImagiNE Nebraska Act, subject to the base authority limitations provided in section 77-6839, without waiting for a determination by the director or the Tax Commissioner or other taxing authority that the taxpayer has met the required employment and investment levels or otherwise qualifies, has qualified, or continues to qualify for such incentives, provided that the tax return or claim has been signed by an owner, member, manager, or officer of the taxpayer who declares under penalties of perjury that he or she has examined the tax return or claim, including accompanying schedules and statements, and to the best of his or her knowledge and belief (a) the tax return or claim is correct and complete in all material respects, (b) payment of the claim has not been previously made by the state to the taxpayer, and (c) with respect to sales or use tax refund claims, the taxpayer has not claimed or received a refund of such tax from a retailer. The payment or allowance of such a claim shall not prevent the director or the Tax Commissioner or other taxing authority from recovering such payment, exemption, or allowance, within the normal period provided by law, subject to normal appeal rights of a taxpayer, if the director or Tax Commissioner or other taxing authority determines upon review or audit that the taxpayer did not qualify for such incentive or exemption.</para><para>(6) An audit of employment and investment thresholds and incentive amounts shall be made by the Tax Commissioner to the extent and in the manner determined by the Tax Commissioner. Upon request by the director or the Tax Commissioner, the Commissioner of Labor shall report to the director and the Tax Commissioner the employment data regularly reported to the Department of Labor relating to number of employees and wages paid for each taxpayer. The director and Tax Commissioner, to the extent they determine appropriate, shall use such information to achieve efficiency in the administration of the ImagiNE Nebraska Act. The Tax Commissioner may recover any refund or part thereof which is erroneously made and any credit or part thereof which is erroneously allowed by issuing a deficiency determination within three years from the date of refund or credit or within the period otherwise allowed for issuing a deficiency determination, whichever expires later. The director shall not enter into an agreement with any taxpayer unless the taxpayer agrees to electronically verify the work eligibility status of all newly hired employees employed in Nebraska within ninety days after the date of hire. For purposes of calculating any tax incentive under the act, the hours worked and compensation paid to an employee who has not been electronically verified or who is not eligible to work in Nebraska shall be excluded.</para><para>(7) A determination by the director that a location is not a qualified location or a determination by the Tax Commissioner that a taxpayer has failed to meet or maintain the required levels of employment or investment for incentives, exemptions, or recapture, or does not otherwise qualify for incentives or exemptions, may be protested by the taxpayer to the Tax Commissioner within sixty days after the mailing to the taxpayer of the written notice of the proposed determination by the director or the Tax Commissioner, as applicable. If the notice of proposed determination is not protested in writing by the taxpayer within the sixty-day period, the proposed determination is a final determination. If the notice is protested, the Tax Commissioner, after a formal hearing by the Tax Commissioner or by an independent hearing officer appointed by the Tax Commissioner, if requested by the taxpayer in such protest, shall issue a written order resolving such protest. The written order of the Tax Commissioner resolving a protest may be appealed to the district court of Lancaster County in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act within thirty days after the issuance of the order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 32. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para><para><emphasis>Employment and Investment Growth Act,</emphasis> see section 77-4101.</para><para><emphasis>Local Option Revenue Act,</emphasis> see section 77-27,148.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5701.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para><para><emphasis>Qualified Judgment Payment Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>