<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id313"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6604"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6604</statuteno><catchline>Eligible business; program certification application; approval; requirements; agreement.</catchline><para>(1) A business may apply to the director for certification as an eligible business. The program certification application shall be in the form and be made under the procedures specified by the director.</para><para>(2) Within thirty days after receiving a program certification application under this section, the director shall certify the business as satisfying the conditions required of an eligible business, request additional information, or deny the program certification application. If the director requests additional information, the director shall certify the business or deny the program certification application within thirty days after receiving the additional information. If the director neither certifies the business nor denies the program certification application within thirty days after receiving the original program certification application or within thirty days after receiving the additional information requested, whichever is later, then the program certification application is deemed approved if the business meets the requirements in subsection (3) of this section. A business that applies for program certification and is denied may reapply.</para><para>(3) To be certified as an eligible business under the Renewable Chemical Production Tax Credit Act, a business shall meet all of the following requirements:</para><para>(a) The business produced at least one million pounds of renewable chemicals in this state during the calendar year for which tax credits are sought;</para><para>(b) The business is physically located in this state;</para><para>(c) The business organized, expanded, or located in this state on or after January 1, 2021; and</para><para>(d) The business is in compliance with all agreements entered into under the act and pursuant to any other tax credits or programs administered by the Department of Economic Development or the Department of Revenue.</para><para>(4)(a) An eligible business shall enter into an agreement with the director for the successful completion of all requirements of the act. The agreement may certify the business to receive tax credits under the act for up to four years.</para><para>(b) As part of the agreement, the eligible business shall agree to collect and provide any information reasonably required by the director or the Department of Revenue in order to allow the director and department to fulfill their reporting obligations under section 77-6610.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 70. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>