<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id829"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6516"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6516</statuteno><catchline>Wage retention credit; amount; use.</catchline><para>(1) If a key employer has entered into an agreement with the state pursuant to section 77-6517, the key employer shall during each year of the performance period receive the wage retention credit approved by the director in the manner provided in the Key Employer and Jobs Retention Act.</para><para>(2) The wage retention credit shall equal five percent of the total compensation paid by the key employer in the year to all retained employees of the key employer in Nebraska who are paid wages for services rendered at a rate equal to at least one hundred percent of the Nebraska statewide average hourly wage for the year of application. The wage retention credit earned for all qualified key employers shall not exceed four million dollars in any year. If two or more key employers qualify for benefits in any given year, the one with the earlier approval will be fully funded first.</para><para>(3) The wage retention credits shall be allowed for each year in the performance period. Unused credits may carry over only to the end of the performance period.</para><para>(4) The total amount all key employers may receive in credits pursuant to the Key Employer and Jobs Retention Act shall not exceed forty million dollars. If two or more key employers qualify for benefits, the one with the earlier approval will be fully funded first. This benefit is in addition to any benefits the key employer may otherwise qualify for under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act or may have qualified for previously under the Nebraska Advantage Act or the Employment and Investment Growth Act.</para><para>(5) The wage retention credit shall be claimed by filing the forms required by the Tax Commissioner with the income tax return for the taxable year which includes the end of the year the credits were earned. The credits may be used after any other nonrefundable credits to reduce the key employer's income tax liability imposed by sections 77-2714 to 77-27,135. Credits may be used beginning with the taxable year which includes December 31 of the first year in the performance period. The last year for which credits may be used is the taxable year which includes December 31 of the last year of the performance period. Any decision on how part of the credit is applied shall not limit how the remaining credit could be applied under this section.</para><para>(6) The key employer may use the wage retention credit to reduce the key employer's income tax withholding employer or payor tax liability under section 77-2756 or 77-2757. To the extent of the credit used, such withholding shall not constitute public funds or state tax revenue and shall not constitute a trust fund or be owned by the state. The use by the key employer of the credit shall not change the amount that otherwise would be reported by the key employer to the employee under section 77-2754 as income tax withheld and shall not reduce the amount that otherwise would be allowed by the state as a refundable credit on an employee's income tax return as income tax withheld under section 77-2755.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 59. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Employment and Investment Growth Act,</emphasis> see section 77-4101.</para><para><emphasis>ImagiNE Nebraska Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6801.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>