<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id749"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6538"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6538</statuteno><catchline>Wage credit; amount; use.</catchline><para>(1) If a qualified employer has entered into an agreement with the state pursuant to section 77-6539, the qualified employer shall during each year of the performance period receive the wage credit approved by the Tax Commissioner in the manner provided in the Defense Efforts Workforce Act.</para><para>(2) The wage credit shall equal five percent of the total compensation paid by the qualified employer in the year to all qualified employees of the qualified employer in Nebraska. The wage credit earned for all qualified employers shall not exceed four million dollars in any year. If two or more qualified employers qualify for benefits in any given year, the one with the earlier approval will be fully funded first.</para><para>(3) The wage credits shall be allowed for each year in the performance period. Unused credits may carry over and be applied against future state withholdings.</para><para>(4) The total amount all qualified employers may receive in credits pursuant to the Defense Efforts Workforce Act shall not exceed forty million dollars. If two or more qualified employers qualify for benefits, the one with the earlier approval will be fully funded first. This benefit is in addition to any benefits the qualified employer may otherwise qualify for under the ImagiNE Nebraska Act or may have qualified for previously under the Nebraska Advantage Act, the Employment and Investment Growth Act, or the Key Employer and Jobs Retention Act.</para><para>(5) The qualified employer may use the wage credit to reduce the qualified employer's income tax withholding or payor tax liability under section 77-2756 or 77-2757. To the extent of the credit used, such withholding shall not constitute public funds or state tax revenue and shall not constitute a trust fund or be owned by the state. The use by the qualified employer of the credit shall not change the amount that otherwise would be reported by the qualified employer to the employee under section 77-2754 as income tax withheld and shall not reduce the amount that otherwise would be allowed by the state as a refundable credit on an employee's income tax return as income tax withheld under section 77-2755.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB649, &#167; 15. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2027</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Employment and Investment Growth Act,</emphasis> see section 77-4101.</para><para><emphasis>ImagiNE Nebraska Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6801.</para><para><emphasis>Key Employer and Jobs Retention Act,</emphasis> see section 77-6501.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Advantage Act,</emphasis> see section 77-5701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>