<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id829"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-6521"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6521</statuteno><catchline>Reports; joint hearing.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Economic Development and the Department of Revenue shall jointly submit electronically an annual report to the Legislature no later than October 31 of each year. The report shall be on a fiscal year, accrual basis that satisfies the requirements set by the Governmental Accounting Standards Board. The Department of Economic Development and the Department of Revenue shall together, on or before December 15 of each year, appear at a joint hearing of the Appropriations Committee of the Legislature and the Revenue Committee of the Legislature and present the report. Any supplemental information requested by three or more committee members must be provided within thirty days after the request.</para><para>(2) The report shall list (a) the agreements which have been signed during the previous calendar year, (b) the agreements which are still in effect, and (c) the identity of each taxpayer that is a party to an agreement.</para><para>(3) The report shall provide information on agreement-specific total credits used every two years for each agreement. The report shall disclose the identity of the taxpayer and the total credits used during the immediately preceding two years, expressed as a single, aggregated total. The information required to be reported under this subsection shall not be reported for the first year the taxpayer maintains the required employment threshold. The information on first-year credits used shall be combined with and reported as part of the second year. Thereafter, the information on credits used for succeeding years shall be reported for each agreement every two years containing information on two years of credits used.</para><para>(4) No information shall be provided in the report that is protected by state or federal confidentiality laws.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB1107, &#167; 64. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>