<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id532"><amendatorysection statutenumber="77-6403" chaptername="Revenue and Taxation"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6403</statuteno><catchline>Imposition of sales and use tax; procedure; Tax Commissioner; duties.</catchline><para>(1) Any county that has a qualified judgment in excess of twenty-five million dollars rendered against it may, upon adoption of a resolution by the affirmative vote of at least a two-thirds majority of all elected members of the county board, impose a sales and use tax of one-half of one percent on transactions that are subject to the state sales and use tax under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, as amended from time to time, and that are sourced as provided in sections 77-2703.01 to 77-2703.04 within the county. Any sales and use tax imposed pursuant to this section shall be used to pay the qualified judgment.</para><para>(2) The Tax Commissioner shall administer all sales and use taxes imposed pursuant to this section. The Tax Commissioner may prescribe forms and adopt and promulgate rules and regulations in conformity with the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, as amended, for the making of returns and for the ascertainment, assessment, and collection of taxes. The county shall furnish a certified copy of the resolution imposing the tax to the Tax Commissioner. The tax shall begin on the first day of the first calendar quarter which begins at least sixty days after receipt by the Tax Commissioner of the certified copy of the resolution. The Tax Commissioner shall provide at least thirty days' notice of the adoption of the tax to retailers within the county. Such notice may be provided through the website of the Department of Revenue or by other electronic means.</para><para>(3) Any sales and use tax imposed pursuant to this section shall terminate on the first day of the first calendar quarter which begins after the qualified judgment has been paid in full or after seven years, whichever is earlier. The county shall notify the Tax Commissioner of the anticipated termination date at least one hundred twenty days in advance. The Tax Commissioner shall provide at least sixty days' notice of the termination date to retailers within the county. Such notice may be provided through the website of the Department of Revenue or by other electronic means.</para><para>(4) The Tax Commissioner shall collect any sales and use tax imposed pursuant to this section concurrently with collection of a state sales and use tax in the same manner as the state tax is collected. The Tax Commissioner shall remit monthly the proceeds of the tax to the county imposing the tax, after deducting the amount of refunds made and three percent of the remainder as an administrative fee necessary to defray the cost of collecting the tax and the expenses incident thereto. The Tax Commissioner shall keep full and accurate records of all money received and distributed. All receipts from the three-percent administrative fee shall be deposited in the state General Fund.</para><para>(5) Upon any claim of illegal assessment and collection of any sales and use tax imposed pursuant to this section, the taxpayer has the same remedies provided for claims of illegal assessment and collection of the state sales and use tax.</para><para>(6) All relevant provisions of the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, as amended, not inconsistent with this section, shall govern transactions, proceedings, and activities related to any sales and use tax imposed pursuant to this section.</para><para> (7) For purposes of any sales and use tax imposed pursuant to this section, all retail sales, rentals, and leases, as defined and described in the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967, shall be sourced as provided in sections 77-2703.01 to 77-2703.04.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB472, &#167; 3. </para><terminationdate>January 1, 2027</terminationdate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,
    </emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference>
    </law>
</legaldoc>