<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Revenue And Taxation" id="id82" publishedsource="AnnualSupplement" statutenumber="77-6309"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>77-6309</statuteno><catchline id="id85">Department of Economic Development; report; contents; confidentiality of certain information.</catchline><para>(1) By November 15 of each odd-numbered year, the Department of Economic Development shall submit a report to the Legislature and the Governor that includes:</para><para>(a) The number and geographic location of qualified investors;</para><para>(b) The number, geographic location, and amount of qualified investment made into each qualified small business;</para><para>(c) The total amount of all grants, loans, incentives, and investments that are not qualified investments received by each qualified small business since receiving the initial qualified investment;</para><para>(d) A breakdown of the industry sectors in which qualified small businesses are involved;</para><para>(e) The number of actual tax credits issued by project under the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act on an annual basis; and</para><para>(f) The number and annual salary or wage of jobs created at each qualified small business since receiving the initial qualified investment.</para><para>The report submitted to the Legislature shall be submitted electronically.</para><para>(2) Information received, developed, created, or otherwise maintained by the Department of Economic Development and the Department of Revenue in administering and enforcing the Angel Investment Tax Credit Act, other than information required to be included in the report to be submitted by the Department of Economic Development pursuant to this section, may be deemed confidential by the respective departments and not subject to public disclosure.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2011, LB389, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 147; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB1067, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB156, &#167; 3. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>