<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id833"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-7108"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>77-7108</statuteno><catchline>Income tax credits; corporate taxpayer; amounts.</catchline><para>(1) A corporate taxpayer as defined in section 77-2734.04 which makes one or more cash contributions to one or more scholarship-granting organizations during a tax year shall be eligible for a credit against the income tax due under the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967. Except as otherwise provided in the Opportunity Scholarships Act, the amount of the credit shall be equal to whichever of the following amounts is the lowest: (a) The total amount of such contributions made during the tax year; (b) fifty percent of the income tax liability of such taxpayer for the tax year; or (c) one hundred thousand dollars. A taxpayer may only claim a credit pursuant to this section for the portion of the contribution that was not claimed as a charitable contribution under the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>(2) The tax credit allowed under this section shall be a nonrefundable credit. Any amount of the tax credit that is unused may be carried forward and applied against the taxpayer's income tax liability for the next five years immediately following the tax year in which the credit is first allowed. The tax credit cannot be carried back.</para><para>(3) The taxpayer may not designate all or any part of the contribution to a scholarship-granting organization for the benefit of any eligible student specifically identified by the taxpayer.</para><para>(4) The tax credit allowed under this section is subject to section 77-7109.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB753, &#167; 8. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2024</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>