<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id292"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-7204"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>77-7204</statuteno><catchline>Taxpayer; qualifying contribution; tax credit; amount; eligibility; application; approval, conditions.</catchline><para>(1) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2024, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, any taxpayer who makes a qualifying contribution during the taxable year shall be eligible to receive a credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967.</para><para>(2) The credit provided in this section shall be a nonrefundable credit equal to either one hundred percent or seventy-five percent of the taxpayer's qualifying contribution made during the taxable year, except that the credit for a taxpayer shall not exceed one hundred thousand dollars for any single taxable year.</para><para>(3) The credit shall be equal to one hundred percent of the qualifying contribution if:</para><para>(a) The eligible program that receives the contribution has a physical presence in an opportunity zone in this state designated pursuant to the federal Tax Cuts and Jobs Act, Public Law 115-97; or</para><para>(b) The eligible program that receives the contribution has at least one child enrolled in the child care subsidy program established pursuant to sections 68-1202 and 68-1206 and the child care provider is actively caring and billing for the child as verified by the Department of Health and Human Services. Attracting child care providers into the child care subsidy program and retaining providers in the program are directly connected to the administration of the program. Verifying that the child care provider is actively caring and billing for an eligible child is in furtherance of the child care subsidy program. The Department of Revenue shall not use any verification information obtained from the Department of Health and Human Services except for purposes directly connected with the administration of the Child Care Tax Credit Act.</para><para>(4) The credit shall be equal to seventy-five percent of the qualifying contribution if subsection (3) of this section does not apply.</para><para>(5) A taxpayer shall not be eligible for the credit provided in this section if the taxpayer claimed a charitable contribution deduction for the qualifying contribution on the taxpayer's federal income tax return.</para><para>(6) A taxpayer shall apply for the credit provided in this section by submitting an application to the department with the following information:</para><para>(a) Documentation to show that the contribution is a qualifying contribution; and</para><para>(b) Any other documentation required by the department.</para><para>(7) Subject to subsection (8) of this section, if the department determines that the taxpayer qualifies for tax credits under this section, the department shall approve the application and certify the amount of credits approved to the taxpayer.</para><para>(8) The department shall consider applications in the order in which they are received and may approve tax credits under this section each year until the total amount of credits approved for the year equals two million five hundred thousand dollars.</para><para>(9) If a taxpayer's credit under this section exceeds the total tax due, the taxpayer may carry forward the excess credit for up to five taxable years after the taxable year in which the credit was first allowed, but the taxpayer must use the carryover credit in the earliest taxable year possible.</para><para>(10) A contribution shall not qualify for a credit under this section if the contribution is made to a child care provider in which the taxpayer or a person related to the taxpayer has a financial interest, unless the contribution is part of a bona fide arm's length transaction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB754, &#167; 4. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>