<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id293"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-7109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>77-7109</statuteno><catchline>Tax credit; contributions; procedure; annual limit.</catchline><para>(1) Prior to making a contribution to a scholarship-granting organization, any taxpayer desiring to claim a tax credit under the Opportunity Scholarships Act shall notify the scholarship-granting organization of the taxpayer's intent to make a contribution and the amount to be claimed as a tax credit. Upon receiving each such notification, the scholarship-granting organization shall notify the department of the intended tax credit amount. If the department determines that the intended tax credit amount in the notification would exceed the limit specified in subsection (3) of this section, the department shall notify the scholarship-granting organization of its determination within thirty days after receipt of the notification. The scholarship-granting organization shall then promptly notify the taxpayer of the department's determination that the intended tax credit amount in the notification is not available. If an amount less than the amount indicated in the notification is available for a tax credit, the department shall notify the scholarship-granting organization of the available amount and the scholarship-granting organization shall notify the taxpayer of the available amount within three business days.</para><para>(2) In order to be allowed a tax credit as provided by the act, the taxpayer shall make its contribution between thirty-one and sixty days after notifying the scholarship-granting organization of the taxpayer's intent to make a contribution. If the scholarship-granting organization does not receive the contribution within the required time period, it shall notify the department of such fact and the department shall no longer include such amount when calculating whether the limit prescribed in subsection (3) of this section has been exceeded. If the scholarship-granting organization receives the contribution within the required time period, it shall provide the taxpayer with a receipt for the contribution. The receipt shall show the name and address of the scholarship-granting organization, the date the scholarship-granting organization was certified by the department in accordance with section 77-7104, the name, address, and, if available, tax identification number of the taxpayer making the contribution, the amount of the contribution, and the date the contribution was received.</para><para>(3) The department shall consider notifications regarding intended tax credit amounts in the order in which they are received to ascertain whether the intended tax credit amounts are within the annual limit provided in this subsection. The annual limit on the total amount of tax credits for calendar years 2024, 2025, and 2026 shall be twenty-five million dollars. The annual limit on the total amount of tax credits for calendar year 2027 and each calendar year thereafter shall be calculated by taking the annual limit from the prior calendar year and then multiplying such amount by (a) one hundred twenty-five percent if the intended tax credit amounts in the prior calendar year exceeded ninety percent of the annual limit applicable to that calendar year or (b) one hundred percent if the intended tax credit amounts in the prior calendar year did not exceed ninety percent of the annual limit applicable to that calendar year. The annual limit may be increased as provided in this subsection until it reaches one hundred million dollars. Thereafter, no further increases shall be allowed.</para><para>(4) The State Department of Education and the Department of Revenue shall publish on their respective websites information identifying the annual limit when it is increased pursuant to subsection (3) of this section.</para><para>(5) Once credits have reached the designated annual limit for any calendar year, no additional credits shall be allowed for such calendar year. Credits shall be prorated among the notifications received on the day the annual limit is exceeded.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB753, &#167; 9. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>