<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id594"><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-7103"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2023</bookinfo><statuteno>77-7103</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the Opportunity Scholarships Act:</para><para>(1) Department means the Department of Revenue;</para><para>(2) Education scholarship means a financial grant-in-aid to be used to pay all or part of the tuition and fees for attending a qualified school and includes any tuition grants;</para><para>(3) Eligible student means a resident of Nebraska who:</para><para>(a) Is receiving an education scholarship for the first time and is (i) entering kindergarten or ninth grade in a qualified school or (ii) transferring from a public school at which the student was enrolled for at least one semester immediately preceding the first semester for which the student receives an education scholarship to a qualified school and is entering any of grades kindergarten through twelve;</para><para>(b) Has previously received an education scholarship and is continuing education at a qualified school until such student graduates from high school or reaches twenty-one years of age, whichever comes first; or</para><para>(c) Is the sibling of a student who is receiving an education scholarship and resides in the same household as such student;</para><para>(4) Qualified school means any nongovernmental, privately operated elementary or secondary school located in this state that (a) is operated not for profit, (b) complies with the antidiscrimination provisions of 42 U.S.C. 1981 as such section existed on January 1, 2023, (c) complies with all health and life safety laws or codes that apply to privately operated schools, and (d) fulfills the applicable accreditation or approval requirements established by the State Board of Education pursuant to section 79-318;</para><para>(5) Scholarship-granting organization means a charitable organization in this state that is (a) exempt from federal income taxation pursuant to section 501(c)(3) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, and (b) certified pursuant to section 77-7104 to provide tax-credit-supported education scholarships to eligible students to assist them in attending qualified schools; and</para><para>(6) Tuition means any amount charged by a qualified school for enrollment in its instructional program. Tuition shall not exceed the full cost of educating an eligible student at such qualified school.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB753, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2024</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>