<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Revenue and Taxation" statutenumber="77-7203" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>77-7203</statuteno><catchline>Parent or legal guardian; tax credit; eligibility; amount; application; approval, conditions.</catchline><para>(1) For taxable years beginning or deemed to begin on or after January 1, 2024, under the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended, a parent or legal guardian who is a resident of the State of Nebraska shall be eligible to receive a credit against the income tax imposed by the Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967 if:</para><para>(a) The parent's or legal guardian's child is enrolled in a child care program licensed pursuant to the Child Care Licensing Act;</para><para>(b) The parent's or legal guardian's child receives care from an approved license-exempt provider enrolled in the child care subsidy program pursuant to sections 68-1202 and 68-1206; or</para><para>(c) The parent's or legal guardian's total household income is less than or equal to one hundred percent of the federal poverty level.</para><para>(2) The credit provided in this section shall be a refundable tax credit equal to:</para><para>(a) Two thousand dollars per child if the parent's or legal guardian's total household income is no more than seventy-five thousand dollars; or</para><para>(b) One thousand dollars per child if the parent's or legal guardian's total household income is more than seventy-five thousand dollars but no more than one hundred fifty thousand dollars.</para><para>(3) A parent or legal guardian shall not be eligible for a credit under this section if the parent's or legal guardian's total household income is more than one hundred fifty thousand dollars.</para><para>(4) A parent or legal guardian shall apply for the credit provided in this section by submitting an application to the department with the following information:</para><para>(a) The number of children for which the parent or legal guardian is claiming a credit;</para><para>(b) Documentation of the parent's or legal guardian's total household income; and</para><para>(c) Any other documentation required by the department.</para><para>(5) Subject to subsection (6) of this section, if the department determines that the parent or legal guardian qualifies for tax credits under this section, the department shall approve the application and certify the amount of credits approved to the parent or legal guardian.</para><para>(6) The department shall consider applications in the order in which they are received and may approve tax credits under this section each year until the total amount of credits approved for the year equals fifteen million dollars.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2023, LB754, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2025, LB208, &#167; 8. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Child Care Licensing Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1908.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Revenue Act of 1967,</emphasis> see section 77-2701.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>