
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Servicemembers And Veterans" statutenumber="80-401.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>80-401.01</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For
purposes of sections 80-401 to 80-412, unless the context otherwise requires:</para>
<para>(1) Recognized veterans organization means the American Legion, the
American Ex-Prisoners of War, the Disabled American Veterans, the Military
Order of the Purple Heart, the Paralyzed Veterans of America, the Veterans
of Foreign Wars of the United States, the Vietnam Veterans of America, and
any other veterans organization which the Director of Veterans' Affairs determines
(a) is recognized by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs for
claims representation, (b) has a presence in each of this state's congressional
districts, and (c) maintains a state headquarters sanctioned by its national
organization;</para>
<para>(2) Veteran of the Spanish-American War means a person who served on
active duty in the armed forces of the United States between April 21, 1898,
and July 4, 1902, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time
of his or her entry into such service, served with the military forces of
any government allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(3) Veteran of World War I means a person who served on active duty
in the armed forces of the United States between April 6, 1917, and November
11, 1918, or who, being a resident of the United States at the time of his
or her entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(4) Veteran of World War II means a person who served on active duty
in the armed forces of the United States between December 7, 1941, and December
31, 1946, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time of his
or her entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(5) Veteran of the Korean War means a person who served on active duty
in the armed forces of the United States between June 25, 1950, and January
31, 1955, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time of his
or her entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(6) Veteran of the Vietnam War means a person (a) who served on active
duty in the armed forces of the United States (i) between August 5, 1964,
and May 7, 1975, or (ii) in the Republic of Vietnam between February 28, 1961,
and May 7, 1975, and (b) who, being a citizen of the United States at the
time of his or her entry into such service, served with the military forces
of any government allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(7) Veteran of Lebanon means a person who served on active duty in the
armed forces of the United States between August 25, 1982, and February 26,
1984, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time of his or her
entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(8) Veteran of Grenada means a person who served on active duty in the
armed forces of the United States between October 23, 1983, and November 23,
1983, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time of his or her
entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(9) Veteran of Panama means a person who served on active duty in the
armed forces of the United States between December 20, 1989, and January 31,
1990, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time of his or her
entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(10) Veteran of the Persian Gulf War means a person who served on active
duty in the armed forces of the United States beginning on August 2, 1990,
and ending on the date thereafter prescribed by presidential proclamation
or by law, or who, being a citizen of the United States at the time of his
or her entry into such service, served with the military forces of any government
allied with the United States in that war;</para>
<para>(11) Veteran of the Global
War on Terror means a person who served on active duty in the armed forces
of the United States beginning on September 14, 2001, and ending on the date
thereafter prescribed by presidential proclamation or by law, or who, being
a citizen of the United States at the time of his or her entry into such service,
served with the military forces of any government allied with the United States
in that war;</para><para>(12) Active duty means full-time
duty in the armed forces other than active duty for training; and</para>
<para>(13) Active duty for training
means full-time duty in the armed forces performed by reserves for training
purposes.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 306, &#167; 2, p. 927; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 302, &#167; 1, p. 993; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 328, &#167; 1, p. 1024; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 562, &#167; 1, p. 1853; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 561, &#167; 2, p. 1849; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 754, &#167; 1, p. 2835; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 621, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 90, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 571, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 221, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 49, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 626, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 857, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 720, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 835, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 2, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 241, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 368, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 799, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 54, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB422, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>