<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id852"><amendatorysection chaptername="Servicemembers And Veterans" statutenumber="80-336"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>80-336</statuteno><catchline>Property; funds; appropriations; effect of transfer.</catchline><para>On July 1, 2017, all items of property, real and personal, including office furniture and fixtures, books, documents, and records of the Division of Veterans’ Homes of the Department of Health and Human Services pertaining to the duties and functions transferred to the Department of Veterans’ Affairs pursuant to the Nebraska Veterans Services Act shall become the property of the department.</para><para>On July 1, 2017, any federal, cash, canteen, and trust funds remaining in the following program classifications shall be transferred from Agency No. 25, the Department of Health and Human Services, to Agency No. 28, the Department of Veterans' Affairs: Program No. 510, Veterans' Home System Administration; Program No. 519, Grand Island Veterans' Home; Program No. 520, Norfolk Veterans' Home; Program No. 521, Western Nebraska Veterans' Home; and Program No. 522, Eastern Nebraska Veterans' Home.</para><para>Any appropriation and salary limit provided in any legislative bill enacted by the One Hundred Fifth Legislature, First Session, to Agency No. 25, Department of Health and Human Services, in the following program classification, shall be null and void, and any such amounts are hereby appropriated to Agency No. 28, Department of Veterans' Affairs: Program No. 519, Nebraska Veterans' Homes. Any financial obligations of the Department of Health and Human Services for Program No. 519, Nebraska Veterans' Homes, that remain unpaid as of June 30, 2017, and that are subsequently certified as valid encumbrances to the accounting division of the Department of Administrative Services pursuant to sections 81-138.01 to 81-138.04, shall be paid by the Department of Veterans' Affairs from the unexpended balance of appropriations existing in such program classification on June 30, 2017.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB340, &#167; 16. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>