<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id446">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Servicemembers And Veterans" id="id448" statutenumber="80-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>80-401</statuteno><catchline id="id451">Nebraska Veterans'
Aid Fund; Veterans' Aid Income Fund; created; purpose; investment; management.</catchline><para>(1) There
is hereby established a fund to be known as the Nebraska Veterans' Aid Fund.
The Nebraska
Investment Council is directed to purchase bonds or notes issued
by the government of the United States or the State of Nebraska, or any county,
school district, or municipality therein, with a face value of twelve million
dollars, as of August 1, 1984, to carry out sections 80-401 to 80-405 and
to place them in the custody and control of the State Treasurer of the State
of Nebraska under the same conditions as other state money.</para>
<para>(2) Such
fund shall be managed as follows: (a) When necessary to pay
a premium for bonds for such fund, the amount of the premium shall be amortized
over the term of the bonds from the interest received on such bonds; and (b) when bonds for such fund are purchased at
a discount, the amount of the discount shall be used to purchase additional
bonds, it being contemplated that the face amount of the bonds in such fund
may in this manner aggregate in excess of twelve million dollars at some future
time.</para>
<para>(3) The interest on the Nebraska
Veterans' Aid Fund, except so much as may be required for amortization of
premium bond purchases as authorized in this section and so much as may be
required to pay a pro rata share of the budget appropriated for the Nebraska
Investment Council pursuant to section 72-1249.02, shall be paid to the Veterans'
Aid Income Fund, which fund is hereby created. The Veterans' Aid Income Fund,
when appropriated by the Legislature, shall be available to the Director of Veterans' Affairs for aid to needy
veterans as authorized by law.</para>
<para>(4) The Nebraska Investment Council shall
manage the Nebraska Veterans' Aid Fund, with investment and reinvestment to
be made in the same type securities authorized for investment of funds by
the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment
Act.</para>
<para>(5) The director shall advise
the Nebraska Investment Council when
amounts in the Veterans' Aid Income Fund are not immediately required for
aid to needy veterans. The state investment officer shall invest such amounts
available from the Veterans' Aid Income Fund in the same manner as investments
of the Nebraska Veterans' Aid Fund, and the interest thereon shall also become
a part of the Veterans' Aid Income Fund.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 40, &#167; 1, p. 181; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6206; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 126, &#167; 1, p. 311; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 194, &#167; 1, p. 552; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 80-401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 80-401; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 221, &#167; 1, p. 659; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 306, &#167; 1, p. 926; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 301, &#167; 1, p. 990; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 422, &#167; 1, p. 1419; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 486, &#167; 44, p. 1531; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 94, p. 2404; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 234, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 867, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 733, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 157, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 255, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 38, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 786, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 7, &#167; 95; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 29.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Board of Educational Lands and Funds,</emphasis> authorized investments, see sections 8-712, 46-567.04, and 72-202.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>