<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id239">
<amendatorysection chaptername="Soldiers and Sailors" id="id241" statutenumber="80-414"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>80-414</statuteno><catchline>Department of Veterans' Affairs; create
and maintain registry; contents; notation of "veteran" on operator's license
or state identification card; eligibility.</catchline><para>(1) The Department of Veterans' Affairs
shall create and maintain a registry of residents of Nebraska who meet the
requirements of subsection (1) of section 60-4,189. The Department of Veterans'
Affairs may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the establishment
and maintenance of the registry. The registry may be used to assist the department
in carrying out the duties of the department and shall provide for the collection
of sufficient information to identify an individual who qualifies for a notation
of "veteran" on his or her operator's license or state identification card
issued by the Department of Motor Vehicles. The registry may include information
such as identifying information on an individual, an individual's records
on active duty in the armed forces of the United States, or an individual's
status of active duty, retired, discharged, or other.</para>
<para>(2) Any
resident of Nebraska who meets the requirements of subsection (1) of section
60-4,189 shall register with the Department of Veterans' Affairs using the
registry created by this section before being eligible for a notation of "veteran"
on his or her operator's license or state identification card issued by the
Department of Motor Vehicles. No person shall be deemed eligible until his
or her status has been verified on the registry.</para><para>(3) The Department
of Motor Vehicles may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing
use of the registry of the Department of Veterans' Affairs for determination
of eligibility for the notation of "veteran" on operators' licenses and state
identification cards.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB93, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>