<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Servicemembers and Veterans" statutenumber="80-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>80-101</statuteno><catchline>County veterans service committee; members; term; compensation; vacancy, how filled; bond; expenses.</catchline><para>(1) Each county board shall appoint a county veterans service committee of five members, such choice to be made from a list of eligible veterans recommended by the recognized veterans organizations within the county. Such list shall contain not less than three names for each appointment to be made.</para><para>(2) The terms of office of the members of the county veterans service committee initially appointed shall expire on June 30 of the years 1948, 1949, 1950, 1951, and 1952, as designated by the county board in making the respective appointments. As the terms of members expire, the county board shall, during the month of June of each year, appoint or reappoint a member of the committee for a term of five years to succeed the member whose term expires. Each member shall serve until the appointment and qualification of a successor. In case of a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of the term of a member, the appointment shall be made only for the remainder of the term.</para><para>(3) The members of the county veterans service committee shall organize by the appointment of one of their number as chairperson and one as secretary-treasurer. The secretary-treasurer may be the county veterans service officer. The county veterans service officer shall not be a member of the committee. The members of the committee shall qualify by taking the usual oath of office and shall each give bond, if required by the local county board, in an amount determined by the local county board for the faithful performance of the duties of his or her office. The premiums for such bonds shall be paid by the county. Members of the committee shall be entitled to the necessary and actual expenses involved in the performance of their official duties, with mileage reimbursements to be computed at the rate provided in section 81-1176, which shall be paid out of the county general fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1889, c. 72, &#167; 2, p. 528; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 147, &#167; 1, p. 590; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7155; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 128, &#167; 1, p. 289; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6801; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 196, &#167; 1, p. 556; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 80-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 80-101; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 305, &#167; 2, p. 924; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 324, &#167; 2, p. 1071; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 752, &#167; 1, p. 2830; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 164; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 134, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1011, &#167; 33. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County veterans service committee,</emphasis> other provisions, see sections 80-406 to 80-410.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Elected county officials are required to give individual official bonds. Blanket bond is not sufficient. Foote v. County of Adams, 163 Neb. 406, 80 N.W.2d 179 (1956).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>