<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Servicemembers And Veterans" statutenumber="80-403"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>80-403</statuteno><catchline>Veterans relief; persons eligible; disbursements.</catchline><para>(1) All money disbursed through the Director of Veterans' Affairs shall be expended by him or her in furnishing food, shelter, fuel, transportation, wearing apparel, or medical or surgical aid or in assisting with the funeral expenses of discharged veterans who come within one of the classes described in subsection (2) or (3) of this section.</para><para>(2) Such aid shall be provided upon application to veterans as defined in section 80-401.03, their widows, widowers, spouses, and their children age eighteen or younger or until age twenty-three if attending school full time, and at any age if the child was permanently incapable of self-support at age eighteen (a) who are legal residents of this state on the date of such application and (b) who may be in need of such aid.</para><para>(3) In cases in which an eligible veteran or widow or widower dies leaving no next of kin to apply for payment of expenses of last illness and burial, a recognized veterans organization or a county veterans service officer may apply, on behalf of the deceased, for assistance in paying such expenses. All such payments shall be made by the director. There may be expended, for purposes other than those set forth in this section, such sum or sums as may be specifically appropriated by the Legislature for such purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 40, &#167; 2, p. 182; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 6207; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 126, &#167; 2, p. 312; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 194, &#167; 2, p. 554; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 80-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 80-402; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 221, &#167; 2, p. 660; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 306, &#167; 13, p. 932; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 305, &#167; 1, p. 999; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 498, &#167; 1, p. 1589; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 562, &#167; 2, p. 1854; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 561, &#167; 3, p. 1851; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 754, &#167; 7, p. 2840; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 336, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 80, &#167; 113; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 441, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 227, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB904, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB305, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>