<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Soldiers and Sailors" statutenumber="80-601" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>80-601</statuteno><catchline>Veterans; mentally ill or dangerous sex offender; care or treatment by United States Department of Veterans Affairs; commitment; powers.</catchline><para>Whenever in any proceeding under the Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act or the Sex Offender Commitment Act it is determined that a person is mentally ill and dangerous or a dangerous sex offender as defined in section 83-174.01 and it appears that such person is eligible for care or treatment by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs or another agency of the United States Government, the mental health board, upon determination by the department or such other agency that facilities are available and that such person is eligible for care or treatment therein, may commit such person to the department or other agency. Upon commitment, such person shall be subject to the applicable rules and regulations of the department or other agency of the United States operating the institution in which such care or treatment is provided. The chief officer of any facility of the department or institution operated by any other agency of the United States to which a mentally ill and dangerous person or a dangerous sex offender is committed by a proper agency in this state shall have the same powers as chief executive officers of state hospitals for the care of the mentally ill in this state with respect to the custody, transfer, conditional discharge, or discharge of such person.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 307, &#167; 1, p. 936; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 806, &#167; 88; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 2, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1083, &#167; 126; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1199, &#167; 84.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Mental Health Commitment Act,</emphasis> see section 71-901.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc>