<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Servicemembers And Veterans" statutenumber="80-410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>80-410</statuteno><catchline>Director; Veterans' Advisory Commission;
state and county veterans service officers; employees; qualifications.</catchline>
<para>(1) The Director of Veterans' Affairs, all members of the Veterans'
Advisory Commission, all state service officers, all assistant state service
officers, and all personnel, except certain special and clerical help, of
the state veterans service offices shall have served in the armed forces of
the United States during the dates set forth in section 80-401.01, shall have
been discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization of honorable
from such service, and shall have been bona fide residents of the State of
Nebraska continuously for at least five years immediately prior to their assuming
a position in any of the offices mentioned.</para>
<para>(2) All county veterans service officers shall have served on active
duty in the armed forces of the United States, other than active duty for
training, shall have been discharged or otherwise separated with a characterization
of honorable from the service, and shall have been bona fide residents of
the State of Nebraska continuously for at least one year immediately prior
to assuming any such position,
except that if there is no applicant for county veterans service officer in
a county who will have been a bona fide resident of the State of Nebraska
continuously for at least one year prior to assuming such position, the one-year
residency requirement may be waived.</para>
<para>(3) All members of the county veterans service committees and all personnel,
except certain special and clerical help, of the county veterans service offices
shall have all of the qualifications described in subsection (2) of this section,
except that such persons may have been discharged or otherwise separated with
a characterization of general (under honorable conditions).</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 306, &#167; 18, p. 934; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 326, &#167; 4, p. 1080; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 563, &#167; 3, p. 1857; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 754, &#167; 9, p. 2842; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 54, &#167; 33; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB52, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB737, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Director,</emphasis> qualifications of, see section 80-401.02.</para><para><emphasis>Veterans' Advisory Commission,</emphasis> qualifications of members, see section 80-401.06.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>