<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-604.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-604.01</statuteno><catchline>Chartered territory; boundaries.</catchline><para>(1) Except as the same may be further limited or expanded by requirements in Chapter 70, article 6, the chartered territory of any district organized pursuant to and existing by virtue of or subject to the provisions of Chapter 70, article 6, shall include the area in this state within which such district renders electric service of the nature defined in section 70-604.02 and termed its operating area. There may be included, within the chartered area of such district, areas which are outside the operating area as defined in section 70-604.02, but as to which inclusion is nevertheless authorized by other sections of Chapter 70, article 6.</para><para>(2) Subject to the requirements of section 70-662 and the approval of the Nebraska Power Review Board in accordance with sections 70-663 and 70-664, any district organized pursuant to Chapter 70, article 6, and engaged in the operation of electric generation, transmission, or distribution facilities or any combination thereof may, in the discretion of the board of directors of such district and upon a finding by the board of directors of such district that the inclusion or exclusion thereof would be consistent with the best interests of the district and its customers, either include within or exclude from the chartered area all municipalities which have a population of fewer than one thousand five hundred inhabitants as determined by the most recent federal decennial census or the most recent revised certified count by the United States Bureau of the Census and which are within a county where such district provides electric service but are not otherwise in such district's operating area.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 418, &#167; 7, p. 1289; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 949, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB53, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB113, &#167; 52. </para></source><annotation><para>A public power district which does not provide at least 50 percent of the retail or wholesale power requirements of a municipality cannot include that municipality within its charter area. In re Boundaries of McCook P. P. Dist., 217 Neb. 11, 347 N.W.2d 544 (1984).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>