<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-601.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-601.01</statuteno><catchline>Ethanol production and distribution; hydrogen production and distribution; legislative findings.</catchline><para>(1) The Legislature finds and declares that:</para><para>(a) Nebraska has been and will continue to be a state which is dependent on a stable, income-producing farm sector;</para><para>(b) When agriculture fails to produce adequate income for farmers, ranchers, and agricultural business interests within this state, the economic well-being of the state and its citizens will be threatened;</para><para>(c) There currently exists a chronic grain surplus within the state because of underutilization of grain products, and prices for grain remain unreasonably low because of such surplus and underutilization;</para><para>(d) Enlargement of the ethanol industry within the state would result in additional utilization of surplus grain;</para><para>(e) Ethanol will be increasingly in demand in the marketplace because of its efficacy as an octane enhancer and fuel extender;</para><para>(f) The public power industry within the state is experienced in the production and transmission of electrical power; and</para><para>(g) The experience of the public power industry could be used in the development of the production and distribution of ethanol and in the enhancement of the economic well-being of this state.</para><para>(2) The Legislature further finds:</para><para>(a) Hydrogen production and distribution may serve as a viable alternative in the marketplace for use in fuel processes;</para><para>(b) The public power industry within the state is experienced in the production and transmission of electrical power; and</para><para>(c) The experience of the public power industry could be used in the development of the production, storage, and distribution of hydrogen for use in fuel processes and in the enhancement of the economic well-being of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 1230, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 139, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>