<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-627.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-627.02</statuteno><catchline>District; radioactive material and energy; powers; development; contracts; financing; indemnification; when.</catchline><para>In addition to all other rights and powers which may be possessed by a public power district or public power and irrigation district under the petition for its creation and all amendments thereto and other statutes, any such district which has radioactive material available to it in association with facilities constructed in connection with the production of electrical energy shall have the power to: (1) Use, sell, lease, transport, dispose of, furnish, or make available, under contract or otherwise, to any person, firm, corporation, state, county, city, village, governmental subdivision or agency, the government of the United States or any officer, department, bureau or agency thereof, any corporation organized by federal law, or any body politic or corporate, any such radioactive material or the energy therefrom; (2) own, operate, construct, reconstruct, purchase, remove, lease, or otherwise acquire, improve, extend, manage, use, or operate such facilities or property, real or personal; or (3) engage in or transact business or enter into any kind of contract or arrangement with anyone for or incident to the exercise of any one or more of the powers of the district for any and every service involving, employing, or in any manner pertaining to the use of radioactive material or the energy therefrom or for the financing or payment of the cost and expense incident to the acquisition, construction, reconstruction, improvement, or operation of such facilities or property, real or personal, or incident to any obligation or indebtedness entered or incurred by any such district.</para><para>A public power district or public power and irrigation district may indemnify a public or private entity for such entity's own negligence, notwithstanding section 25-21,187, if the district enters into a contract with the public or private entity for the management or operation of a nuclear power plant that provides for compensation on an at-cost basis. This section does not authorize indemnification for any direct damages from the misconduct of such public or private entity engaged in management or operation of a nuclear power plant. The same limitations of liability and other protections available to a public power district or a public power and irrigation district under the Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act shall apply to any public or private entity acting as an agent for a public power district or a public power and irrigation district pursuant to a contract for the management or operation of a nuclear power plant.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 316, &#167; 2, p. 1159; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 165, &#167; 12. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 13-901.</para></crossreference></law></legaldoc> 