<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-627"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-627</statuteno><catchline>Irrigation works; construction; acquisition; contracts authorized.</catchline><para>Subject to the limitations of the petition for its creation and all amendments thereto, a public power district may own, construct, reconstruct, improve, purchase, lease, or otherwise acquire, extend, manage, use or operate any irrigation works, as defined in section 70-601, either within or beyond, or partly within and partly beyond, the boundaries of the district, and any and every kind of property, personal or real, necessary, useful or incident to such acquisition, extension, management, use and operation, whether the same be independent of or in connection or conjunction with an electric light and power business, in whole or in part. In connection with the aforesaid powers, such district shall have the right and power to enter into any contract, lease, agreement or arrangement with any state, county, city, village, governmental or public corporation or association, or with any person, firm or corporation, public or private, or with the government of the United States, the Rural Electrification Administration, the Public Works Administration, or with any officer, department, bureau or agency thereof, or with any corporation organized under federal law, including the Reconstruction Finance Corporation, or any successor thereof, for the purpose of exercising or utilizing any one or more of the above enumerated powers, or for the sale, leasing, or otherwise furnishing or establishing, water rights, water supply, water service or water storage, for irrigation or flood control, or for the financing or payment of the cost and expenses incident to the construction, acquisition or operation of such irrigation works, or incident to any obligation or liability entered into or incurred by such district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 86, &#167; 6, p. 346; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 152, &#167; 5, p. 583; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-706; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 3(3), p. 522; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-627.</para></source><annotation><para>Powers granted by this section are subject to limitations of petition for creation of district. Schroll v. City of Beatrice, 169 Neb. 162, 98 N.W.2d 790 (1959).</para><para>District may acquire fee title to reservoir site. Burnett v. Central Neb. P. P. &amp; I. Dist., 147 Neb. 458, 23 N.W.2d 661 (1946).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 