<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id36">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" id="id38" statutenumber="70-619"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>70-619</statuteno><catchline id="id41">Board of directors;
qualifications.</catchline><para>(1) The
corporate powers of the district shall be vested in and exercised by the board
of directors of the district. No person shall be qualified to hold office
as a member of the board of directors unless (a) he
or she is a registered voter (i) of such chartered territory, (ii) of the subdivision from which a director
is to be elected if such chartered territory is subdivided for election purposes
as provided in subsection (1),
(2), or (3) of section 70-612, or (iii) of
one of the combined subdivisions from which directors are to be elected at
large as provided in section 70-612 or (b) he or she is a retail
customer duly certified in accordance with subsection (3) of section 70-604.03.</para>
<para>(2) No
person who is a full-time or part-time employee of the district shall be eligible
to serve as a member of the board of directors unless such person resigns
or assumes an unpaid leave of absence for the term as a member. The district
shall grant such leave of absence when requested by any employee for the purpose
of the employee serving as a member of the board of directors. No person shall
be qualified to be a member of more than one such district board, except that
a director of a rural public power district may serve as a director of another
public power district formed or organized for the purpose of generating electric
energy or transmitting electric energy exclusively for resale to some other
public power districts, rural electric cooperatives, and membership associations
or municipalities. No member of a governing body of any one of the municipalities
within the areas of the district shall be qualified to serve on the original
board of directors under sections 70-603 to 70-609.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 86, &#167; 5, p. 345; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-705; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 2(1), p. 518; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-619; </para><para>Laws 1944, Spec. Sess., c. 5, &#167; 1(1), p. 106; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 127, &#167; 2, p. 440; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 396, &#167; 1, p. 1258; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 418, &#167; 6, p. 1288; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 364, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 198, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 15, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 2, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 949, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 3, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 585; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB646, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Eligibility,</emphasis> additional requirements, see section 70-610.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>District was not estopped to attack constitutionality of a distinct, separate legislative act. May v. City of Kearney, 145 Neb. 475, 17 N.W.2d 448 (1945).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>