<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-663"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2021</bookinfo><statuteno>70-663</statuteno><catchline>Amendment; approval procedure.</catchline><para>(1) This subsection applies to charter amendments submitted after December 31, 2021. Upon such authorization occurring, the proposed amendment shall thereupon be submitted to the Nebraska Power Review Board, together with a petition setting forth the reasons for the adoption of such amendment, and requesting that the same be approved. The Nebraska Power Review Board shall then cause notice to be given by publication for three consecutive weeks in two legal newspapers of general circulation within such district. Such notice shall set forth in full the proposed amendment and set a date, not sooner than three weeks after the last date of publication of the notice, for protests, complaints, or objections to be filed with the Nebraska Power Review Board in opposition to the adoption of such amendment. The cost of such publication shall be paid by such district. If any person residing in such district, or affected by the proposed amendment, shall, within the time provided, file a protest, complaint, or objection, the Nebraska Power Review Board shall schedule a hearing and give due notice thereof to the district, the district's representative, and the person who filed such protest, complaint, or objection. Any person filing a protest, complaint, or objection may appear at such hearing and contest the approval by the Nebraska Power Review Board of such proposed amendment. After all protests, complaints, or objections have been heard, the Nebraska Power Review Board shall act upon the petition and either approve or disapprove the amendment. If no protests, complaints, or objections are properly filed, the board shall either approve the amendment without a hearing or schedule a hearing to determine whether or not the amendment should be approved. If a hearing is scheduled, due notice shall be provided to the district and the district representative.</para><para>(2) This subsection applies to charter amendments submitted before December 31, 2021. Following the release of the 2020 Census of Population data by the United States Department of Commerce, Bureau of the Census, as required by Public Law 94-171, any public power district seeking an amendment to its charter shall submit the proposed amendment to the Nebraska Power Review Board on or before December 17, 2021. If the proposed amendment is in proper form, the Nebraska Power Review Board shall give conditional approval of the amendment on or before December 30, 2021. The approval process provided in subsection (1) of this section shall occur concurrent with the conditional approval process. If a protest, complaint, or objection is filed and a hearing is set, any decision from the Nebraska Power Review Board rejecting the amendment shall be decided and notification provided to the Secretary of State by March 1, 2022. Immediately upon receiving such notification, the Secretary of State shall notify all election commissioners and county clerks responsible for such elections within the public power district that the conditionally approved boundaries were rejected and that the previous boundaries shall be used for the primary and general elections.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 152, &#167; 9, p. 589; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-717; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-663; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 366, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB285, &#167; 18. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>