<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?> <legaldoc> <law type="statute"> <section> <sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" statutenumber="70-604.05"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-604.05</statuteno><catchline>District; noncompliance; complaint; hearing; notice; order; failure to comply; penalty.</catchline><para>When it appears that one or more districts are in noncompliance with the provisions of Chapter 70, article 6, the corporate amendments required to comply shall be made generally in accordance with the procedures and requirements contained in Chapter 70, article 6. In the absence of voluntary amendment any time subsequent to six months after the publication of the first federal decennial census published after August 30, 2009, any person residing in the geographical area of alleged noncompliance, or any district or any two or more districts, may file a complaint with the Nebraska Power Review Board against one or more other districts alleging the area of noncompliance of such other districts. Upon receipt of such complaint, the Nebraska Power Review Board shall issue an order directed to the alleged noncomplying district, granting a hearing and requiring it to show cause why an amended petition for creation eliminating such noncompliance should not be filed for approval. Thirty-three days' notice of hearing, which includes mailing time, shall be given to such alleged noncomplying district by either registered or certified mail. The alleged noncomplying district may appear by answer or by petition for amended petition for creation of the district. The burden of proof of noncompliance shall be upon the complainant and of proposed amendments upon the petitioner. If the Nebraska Power Review Board finds that an amended petition for creation should be made and the alleged noncomplying district has not proposed an acceptable one, the Nebraska Power Review Board shall frame the amendment to be approved after continuing the hearing to receive such evidence as may be offered by the parties having appeared before the Nebraska Power Review Board regarding the contents of the amendment to be framed by the Nebraska Power Review Board.</para> <para>The members of the board of directors of any noncomplying district, including any district failing to comply with an amended petition as framed by the Nebraska Power Review Board, shall each be liable for a civil penalty of fifty dollars for each day of noncompliance which continues after thirty days following final adjudication of noncompliance. Such penalty shall be recovered in an action brought by the Attorney General in the district court for Lancaster County. Service of summons in such action may be had anywhere in the state. Any penalty collected pursuant to this section shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for distribution in accordance with Article VII, section 5, of the Constitution of Nebraska. No member of any such board shall receive any compensation or reimbursement of expenses during the period for which he or she is liable for such penalty, nor shall he or she be eligible as a candidate for reelection.</para> </amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 418, &#167; 11, p. 1291; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 546, &#167; 1, p. 2200; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 949, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB53, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law> </legaldoc>