<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" statutenumber="70-624"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-624</statuteno><catchline>Officers; compensation; approval; publication; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) In no event shall the compensation, as a salary or otherwise, of any general manager or president, assistant general manager or vice president, or other officer be approved except by the vote of approval of two-thirds or more of the members of the board of directors. The record of such vote of approval, together with the names of the directors so voting, shall be made a part of the permanent records of the board.</para><para>(2) The current salaries of any general manager or president or assistant general manager or vice president and all officers of the district shall be published once each year in three legal newspapers of general circulation in the district in which such general manager or president, assistant general manager or vice president, or officers are employed. The chief executive officer as described in section 70-620.01 shall be responsible for publishing the current salaries as required by this subsection. Any chief executive officer who violates this subsection shall be guilty of a Class V misdemeanor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 86, &#167; 5, p. 345; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-705; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 2(1), p. 520; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-624; </para><para>Laws 1944, Spec. Sess., c. 5, &#167; 1(7), (8), (9), pp. 107, 108; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 199, &#167; 1(1), p. 579; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 243, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 739, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 49, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 915, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 