<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-502</statuteno><catchline>Electric energy; sale or purchase; interconnections; contracts authorized.</catchline><para>For the purpose of selling or purchasing electrical energy for lighting, heating or power purposes, any city, village, or public electric light and power district in this state is hereby authorized to enter into agreements to connect and interconnect its electric light and power plants, distribution system and transmission lines with the electric light and power plant, distribution system or transmission lines of any one or more other cities, villages, or public electric light and power districts in this state, upon such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon between the contracting cities, villages, and public power districts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Initiative Law 1930, No. 324, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 116, &#167; 2, p. 337; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-602; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-502.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not prevent a second-class city from contracting for wholesale power requirement if and when city acquired distribution system. City of O'Neill v. Consumers P. P. Dist., 179 Neb. 773, 140 N.W.2d 644 (1966).</para><para>The provisions of this section were modified by legislative act creating the Nebraska Power Review Board. City of Auburn v. Eastern Nebraska Public Power Dist., 179 Neb. 439, 138 N.W.2d 629 (1965).</para><para>This section did not operate to confer power and authority contrary to petition for creation of district. Schroll v. City of Beatrice, 169 Neb. 162, 98 N.W.2d 790 (1959).</para><para>A municipality owning and operating a public power plant may extend its lines into another municipal corporation's boundaries only upon contract, agreement, or franchise. Central Power Co. v. Nebraska City, 112 F.2d 471 (8th Cir. 1940).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 