<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" statutenumber="70-612"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-612</statuteno><catchline>Board of directors; election; subdivisions; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Subject to the provisions of Chapter 70, article 6, and subject to the approval of the Nebraska Power Review Board, the board of directors of a district may amend the petition for its creation to provide for the division of the territory of such district into two or more subdivisions for the nomination and election of some or all of the directors. Each subdivision shall be composed of one or more voting precincts, or divided voting precincts, and the total population of each such subdivision shall be approximately the same. Two or more subdivisions may be combined for election purposes, and members of the board of directors to be elected from such combined subdivisions may be nominated and elected at large when not less than seventy-five percent of the population of the combined subdivisions is within the corporate limits of any city. In the event a district formed includes all or part of two or more counties and is (a) engaged in furnishing electric light and power and more than fifty percent of its customers are rural customers or (b) engaged in furnishing electric light and power and in the business of owning and operating irrigation works, then and in that event such subdivisions may be formed by following precinct or county boundary lines without regard to population if in the judgment of the Nebraska Power Review Board the interests of the rural users of electricity or of users of irrigation water service in such district will not be prejudiced thereby.</para><para>(2) Any public power district or public power and irrigation district owning and operating irrigation works may, with approval of the Nebraska Power Review Board, add representation on its board of directors from any county which is outside its chartered territory but in which is located some or all of such irrigation works.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 152, &#167; 4, p. 581; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 137, &#167; 1, p. 542; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-704; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 145, &#167; 1(3), p. 511; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 1, p. 516; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-612; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 418, &#167; 3, p. 1287; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 198, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 949, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 424, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 573, &#167; 9. </para></source><annotation><para>Amendments to the petition for creation of the district are authorized. Schroll v. City of Beatrice, 169 Neb. 162, 98 N.W.2d 790 (1959).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 