<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-624.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>70-624.02</statuteno><catchline>Board of directors; expenses; compensation; prohibitions; exceptions.</catchline><para>The members of the board of directors shall be paid their actual expenses, while engaged in the business of the district under the authority of the board of directors, and, for their services, such compensation as shall be fixed by the board of directors.</para><para>The boards of directors of those districts with gross revenue of less than five hundred million dollars may fix compensation at not to exceed thirteen thousand four hundred forty dollars per year as to all members except the president and not exceeding fifteen thousand one hundred twenty dollars a year as to the president.</para><para>The boards of directors of those districts with gross revenue of five hundred million dollars or more may fix compensation at not to exceed twenty-six thousand eight hundred eighty dollars per year as to all members except the president or chairperson of the board and not exceeding thirty thousand two hundred forty dollars per year as to the president or chairperson of the board. All salaries and compensation shall be obligations against and be paid solely from the revenue of the district.</para><para>No director shall receive any other compensation from the district, except as provided in this section, during the term for which he or she was elected or appointed or in the year following the expiration of his or her term, and resignation from such board of directors shall not be construed as the termination of the term of office for which he or she was elected or appointed.</para><para>A member of the board of directors of a public power district organized under the laws of this state shall not be limited to service on the board of directors in the district in which he or she has been elected so as to preclude service in similar positions of trust on a state, regional, or national level which are the result of his or her membership as a director on such board. For time expended in his or her duties in such position of trust, the director shall not be limited to any existing provisions of law of this state relating to payment of per diem for services as a member of such board of directors, but shall be entitled to receive such additional compensation as may be provided for such service, regardless of the fact that such compensation may be paid from funds to which his or her district has made contributions in the form of dues or otherwise.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1933, c. 86, &#167; 5, p. 345; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 70-705; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 2(1), p. 520; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-624; </para><para>Laws 1944, Spec. Sess., c. 5, &#167; 1(7), (8), (9), pp. 107, 108; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 199, &#167; 1(3), p. 580; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 405, &#167; 1, p. 1304; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 406, &#167; 1, p. 1306; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 548, &#167; 1, p. 2204; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 308, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 226, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 837, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 49, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 730, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 6, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 901, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1300, &#167; 44. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>