<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-626.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-626.01</statuteno><catchline>Generating power agency; duty to sell electrical energy; when.</catchline><para>A district, individual municipality, or group of municipalities registered with the Nebraska Power Review Board which is engaged in the generation and transmission of electrical energy, all of which are referred to in Chapter 70, article 6, by the term generating power agency, shall be required to sell electrical energy at wholesale under the terms and conditions of a fair and reasonable contract directly to any municipality, registered group of municipalities, district, political subdivision in the state, or any nonprofit electric cooperative corporation organized under Chapter 70, article 7, all of which are referred to in Chapter 70, article 6, by the term distribution power agency, when such distribution power agency makes application for the purchase of electrical energy, if such sale is not in violation of an agreement of the generating power agency approved by the Nebraska Power Review Board and such generating power agency has the requested amount of electrical energy available for sale, and the distribution power agency agrees to make or pay for the necessary physical connection with the electrical facilities of such generating power agency.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 146, &#167; 3(2), p. 522; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 70-626.01; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 421, &#167; 2, p. 1295; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 349, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 18. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Wholesale service to municipalities,</emphasis> when required, see section 19-708.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Formerly this section required public power districts to sell electrical energy at wholesale to municipalities. As amended in 1971, the proviso if such sale is not in violation of an agreement of the generating power agency approved by the Nebraska Power Review Board was added. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska P. P. Dist., 191 Neb. 556, 216 N.W.2d 722 (1974).</para><para>Powers granted by this section are subject to limitations of petition for creation of district. Schroll v. City of Beatrice, 169 Neb. 162, 98 N.W.2d 790 (1959).</para><para>Sale direct to municipalities, and not to association of municipalities, was contemplated. State ex rel. League of Municipalities v. Loup River Public Power Dist., 158 Neb. 160, 62 N.W.2d 682 (1954).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 