<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-1326"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1326</statuteno><catchline>Arbitration board; decision; reversal, modification, or vacation; procedure.</catchline><para>The procedure to obtain reversal, modification, or vacation of a decision rendered by the arbitration board shall be (1) by filing notice of appeal with the Nebraska Power Review Board within thirty days after the date of the filing of the decision with the Nebraska Power Review Board as provided in section 70-1321 or (2) by filing with the arbitration board and with the Nebraska Power Review Board a motion for rehearing within ten days after the filing of the decision with the Nebraska Power Review Board as provided in section 70-1321. If the arbitration board denies the motion for rehearing, a notice of appeal must be filed with the arbitration board and with the Nebraska Power Review Board within thirty days after the date of the filing by the arbitration board with the Nebraska Power Review Board of the decision denying the motion to the party appealing, except that when the arbitration board fails to file a decision on the motion for rehearing within thirty days after such motion is filed, the appeal to the Court of Appeals may be perfected by filing a notice of appeal before the arbitration board files a decision on the motion for rehearing and the review shall be the same as if the board had denied the motion for rehearing. Oral arguments on a motion for rehearing shall be granted when requested. An appeal shall be deemed perfected and the appellate court shall have jurisdiction of the cause when a notice of an appeal has been filed with the Nebraska Power Review Board and appeal has been taken in the manner provided by law for appeals from the district court in civil cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 207, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 125; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 360, &#167; 31. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 