  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-1002"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1002</statuteno><catchline>Suppliers of electricity; agreements; specify service areas; submission to board; purpose of section.</catchline><para>(1) All suppliers of electricity, including public power districts, public power and irrigation districts, individual municipalities, registered groups of municipalities, electric membership associations, and cooperatives, serving customers at retail in adjoining service areas shall have the authority to enter into written agreements with each other specifying either the service area or customers each shall serve with electric energy. Before such agreements shall be effective, except agreements referred to in subsection (2) of this section, they shall be submitted to and approved by the Nebraska Power Review Board created by section 70-1003. In the event that such suppliers fail to consummate such agreements, except agreements referred to in subsection (2) of this section, the matter shall be referred to the Nebraska Power Review Board created by section 70-1003.</para><para>(2) When two or more suppliers serve the same municipality at retail, such agreements shall specify the service areas within such municipality which each supplier is to serve.</para><para>(3) It is declared to be the purpose of this section to promote and encourage the making of such agreements. Such agreements may be amended by the parties thereto at any time, and, except agreements referred to in subsection (2) of this section, shall require the approval of the Nebraska Power Review Board, and they shall be submitted to the board for amendment before the transfer of ownership or control of the facilities serving a service area.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 397, &#167; 2, p. 1259; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 43. </para></source><annotation><para>Realignment agreement cannot confer greater rights on one than was possessed by other. Cornhusker P. P. Dist. v. Loup River P. P. Dist., 184 Neb. 789, 172 N.W.2d 235 (1969).</para><para>Suppliers of electricity were required to enter into agreement specifying their service areas. City of Schuyler v. Cornhusker P. P. Dist., 181 Neb. 704, 150 N.W.2d 588 (1967).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 