<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-1417"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1417</statuteno><catchline>Directors; establish rates and fees; limitation; pledge; lien.</catchline><para>A two-thirds majority vote of the directors of the joint authority present, with each member casting the number of votes to which he or she is entitled, is authorized to fix, charge, and collect rents, rates, fees, and charges for electric power and energy, hydrogen, ethanol, and other services, related to the generation, transmission, and sale of electric energy, to the production, storage, or distribution of hydrogen, or to the production or distribution of ethanol. For so long as any bonds of a joint authority are outstanding and unpaid, the rents, rates, fees, and charges shall be so fixed as to provide revenue at least sufficient, together with other available funds, to pay all costs of and charges and expenses in connection with the proper operation and maintenance of its projects and all necessary repairs, replacements, or renewals of such projects, to pay when due the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on all bonds payable from such revenue, to create and maintain reserves and comply with such covenants as may be required by any resolution or trust agreement authorizing and securing bonds, and to pay any and all amounts which the joint authority may be obligated to pay from such revenue by law or contract.</para><para>Any pledge made by a joint authority pursuant to the Joint Public Power Authority Act shall be valid and binding from the date the pledge is made. The revenue, securities, and other money so pledged and then held or thereafter received by the joint authority or any fiduciary shall immediately be subject to the lien of the pledge without any physical delivery of such pledge or further act, and the lien of the pledge shall be valid and binding as against all parties having claims of any kind in tort, contract, or otherwise against the member district or joint authority without regard to whether such parties have notice of such lien.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 852, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1230, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 139, &#167; 25. </para></source></law></legaldoc>