<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-1813" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1813</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Issuance of mandated project bonds; authorized; proceeds; use.</catchline><para>(1) A public entity has the authority to issue mandated project bonds, including refunding bonds, in one or more series. A public entity also may create a mandated project bond issuer pursuant to section 70-1818 to issue mandated project bonds. Mandated project charges to which the public entity may at any time be entitled shall be pledged, without any necessity for specific authorization of the pledge by the public entity, to the mandated project bonds. Each such series of mandated project bonds shall be secured by and payable from a first lien on mandated project charges pledged for such purpose. Any separate consensual lien or security interest shall be created in accordance with and governed by the Nebraska Governmental Unit Security Interest Act. The proceeds of such bonds shall be applied exclusively to payment of mandated project costs and financing costs and, in the case of proceeds of refunding bonds, the retirement or defeasance of mandated project bonds.</para><para>(2) The public entity and any successor or assignee of the public entity shall be obligated to impose and collect the mandated project charges in amounts sufficient to pay debt service on the mandated project bonds as due. The pledge of mandated project charges shall be irrevocable, and the state, the public entity, or any successor or assignee of the public entity may not reduce, impair, or otherwise adjust mandated project charges, except that the public entity and any successor or assignee thereof shall implement the periodic adjustment method established by the authorizing resolution pursuant to subdivision (1)(d) of section 70-1812. Revenue from mandated project charges shall be deemed special revenue and shall not constitute revenue of the public entity for purposes of any pledge of revenue, receipts, or other income that such public entity has made or will make for the security of debt other than the mandated project bonds to which the revenue from the mandated project charges is expressly pledged.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 548, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB141, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Governmental Unit Security Interest Act,</emphasis> see section 10-1101.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>