<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id475"><amendatorysection statutenumber="70-1507" chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1507</statuteno><catchline>Agricultural self-generation facility; electric service; regulation.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Agricultural or horticultural purposes has the same meaning as in section 77-1359;</para><para>(b) Agricultural self-generation facility means a facility for the production of electricity that:</para><para>(i) Uses methane, wind, solar, biomass, hydropower, or geothermal resources as its energy source;</para><para>(ii) Is controlled by the owner-generator and located entirely on the same premises as the owner-generator's electric account with the local distribution utility;</para><para>(iii) Is owned, leased, or otherwise controlled by the owner-generator and used for agricultural or horticultural purposes;</para><para>(iv) Has a rated capacity of one hundred kilowatts or less;</para><para>(v) Utilizes a device which prevents any backfeed of electricity to the local distribution system; and</para><para>(vi) Is not used for purposes of net metering;</para><para>(c) Local distribution system means the equipment and facilities used by a local distribution utility to distribute electricity to end-use customers;</para><para>(d) Local distribution utility means the owner or operator of a local distribution system. Local distribution utility includes a public power district, a public power and irrigation district, an electric cooperative, or a municipal electric system;</para><para>(e) Net metering has the same meaning as in section 70-2002; and</para><para>(f) Owner-generator means the person controlling an agricultural self-generation facility.</para><para>(2) No local distribution utility shall deny or refuse electric service to a customer that owns an agricultural self-generation facility. An owner-generator is subject to the interconnection requirements, safety standards, electric rates and charges, and service agreement requirements of the local distribution utility in whose service area the agricultural self-generation facility is located. Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to prohibit a local distribution utility from establishing the rates or fees necessary to fully cover its costs to serve a customer that is an owner-generator.</para><para>(3) An owner-generator shall notify the local distribution utility of such owner-generator's intent to install an agricultural self-generation facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB20, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>September 3, 2025</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>