<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id3">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" id="id5" statutenumber="70-1014"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1014</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Electric generation
facilities and transmission lines; approval or denial of application; findings
required; regional line or
facilities; additional consideration.</catchline><para>After
hearing, the board shall have authority to approve or deny the application.
Except as provided in section 70-1014.01 for special generation applications
and except as provided in section 70-1014.02, before approval of an application,
the board shall find that the application will serve the public convenience
and necessity, and that the applicant can most economically and feasibly supply
the electric service resulting from the proposed construction or acquisition,
without unnecessary duplication of facilities or operations.</para>
<para>If the application
involves a transmission line or related facilities planned and approved by
a regional transmission organization and the regional transmission organization
has issued a notice to construct or similar notice or order to a utility to
construct the line or related facilities, the board shall also consider information
from the regional transmission organization's planning process and may consider
the benefits to the region, which shall include Nebraska, provided by the
proposed line or related facilities as part of the board's process in determining
whether to approve or deny the application.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 397, &#167; 14, p. 1265; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 51; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 65, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB742, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>In determining whether a proposed application should be approved, the Nebraska Power Review Board does not have the power to determine that the proposed transmission line should be built along a particular route. Lincoln Electric System v. Terpsma, 207 Neb. 289, 298 N.W.2d 366 (1980).</para><para>Nebraska Power Review Board is authorized, after hearing, to decide which of two competing facilities shall furnish service. City of Auburn v. Eastern Nebraska Public Power Dist., 179 Neb. 439, 138 N.W.2d 629 (1965).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>