<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id435">
<sectno id="id436">Sec. 43.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" id="id437" statutenumber="70-1020"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno id="id439">70-1020</statuteno><catchline id="id440">Board; expenses;
assessments levied against suppliers; apportionment; collection; interest;
Nebraska Power Review Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>In
order to defray the expenses of the Nebraska Power Review Board, there shall
be imposed upon each public power district, public power and irrigation district,
electric membership association, electric cooperative company, and municipality
having an electric distribution system or generation and distribution system,
and also upon all registered groups of municipalities, an assessment each
fiscal year in such sum as shall be determined by the board and approved by
the Governor. The total of such assessments shall not exceed the expenses
of the board which may reasonably be anticipated for the fiscal year for which
assessment is made and shall be apportioned among the various agencies in
proportion to their gross income in the preceding calendar year. The board
shall determine and certify such assessment to each supplier after approval
of the board's budget by the Legislature and Governor. The supplier shall
remit the amount of its assessment to the board within forty-five days after
the mailing of the assessment. Any assessment not paid when due shall draw
interest at a rate equal to the rate of interest allowed per annum under section
45-104.02, as such rate may from time to time be adjusted. The proceeds of
such assessment shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit to the
Nebraska Power Review Fund, which fund is hereby created and which, when appropriated
by the Legislature, shall be used to administer the powers granted to the
Nebraska Power Review Board,
except that transfers may be made from the fund to the General Fund at the
direction of the Legislature. Any money in the Nebraska
Power Review Fund available for investment shall be invested by
the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act
and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 397, &#167; 20, p. 1266; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 407, &#167; 1, p. 1307; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 584, &#167; 65, p. 2385; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 55; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 730, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1992, Fourth Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1066, &#167; 64; </para><para>Laws 2009, First Spec. Sess., LB3, &#167; 43.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>