<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id25">
<sectno id="id26">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" id="id27" statutenumber="70-1001"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id29">70-1001</statuteno><catchline id="id30">Declaration of
policy.</catchline><para>In order to provide the citizens of the
state with adequate electric service at as low overall cost as possible, consistent
with sound business practices, it is the policy of this state to avoid and
eliminate conflict and competition between public power districts, public
power and irrigation districts, individual municipalities, registered groups
of municipalities, electric membership associations, and cooperatives in furnishing
electric energy to retail and wholesale customers, to avoid and eliminate
the duplication of facilities and resources which result therefrom, and to
facilitate the settlement of rate disputes between suppliers of electricity.</para>
<para>It is also the policy of the state to prepare for an evolving
retail electricity market if certain conditions are met which indicate that
retail competition is in the best interests of the citizens of the state.
The determination on the timing and form of competitive markets is a matter
properly left to the states as each state must evaluate the costs and benefits
of a competitive retail market based on its own unique conditions. Consequently,
there is a need for the state to
monitor whether the conditions necessary for its citizens to benefit from
retail competition exist.</para>
<para>It is also
the policy of the state to encourage and allow opportunities for private developers
to develop, own, and operate renewable energy facilities intended primarily
for export from the state under a statutory framework which protects the ratepayers
of consumer-owned utility systems operating in the state from subsidizing
the costs of such export facilities through their rates.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 397, &#167; 1, p. 1259; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 349, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 901, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>Public policy underlying encouragement of publicly owned electric utilities is to provide power to consumers at reasonable rates at as low overall cost as possible and to avoid duplication of facilities. Nebraska P. P. Dist. v. City of York, 212 Neb. 747, 326 N.W.2d 22 (1982).</para><para>Before any electric generation facilities may be constructed, an application must be filed with the board, a hearing held at which any interested party may appear, and approval by the board obtained. Omaha P. P. Dist. v. Nebraska P. P. Project, 196 Neb. 477, 243 N.W.2d 770 (1976).</para><para>The 1971 amendment extended the policy of the act to wholesale as well as retail sales of electrical energy. City of Lincoln v. Nebraska P. P. Dist., 191 Neb. 556, 216 N.W.2d 722 (1974).</para><para>Public policy of state with regard to electrical service stated. Cornhusker P. P. Dist. v. Loup River P. P. Dist., 184 Neb. 789, 172 N.W.2d 235 (1969).</para><para>Legislature authorized board on notice and hearing to establish service areas in the event of nonagreement. City of Gering v. Gering Valley Rural P. P. Dist., 180 Neb. 241, 142 N.W.2d 155 (1966).</para><para>The article, of which this section is a part, is constitutional. City of Auburn v. Eastern Nebraska Public Power Dist., 179 Neb. 439, 138 N.W.2d 629 (1965).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>