<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id36">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" id="id38" statutenumber="70-1904"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1904</statuteno><catchline id="id41">C-BED project
developer; electric utility; negotiation; power purchase agreement; development
of project; restriction on transfer; eligibility for net energy billing; approval
or certification; notice of change in ownership.</catchline><para>(1)
A C-BED project developer and an electric utility are authorized to negotiate
in good faith mutually agreeable power purchase agreement terms.</para>
<para>(2) A qualified owner or any combination of qualified owners
may develop a C-BED project with an equity partner that is not a qualified
owner.</para>
<para>(3) Except for an inherited interest, the transfer of the interest of a qualified owner in a
C-BED project to any person other than another qualified owner or other qualified owners is
prohibited during the initial ten years of the power purchase agreement.</para>
<para>(4) A C-BED project that is operating under a power purchase
agreement is not eligible for any applicable net energy billing.</para>
<para>(5) A C-BED project shall be subject to approval by the Nebraska
Power Review Board in accordance with Chapter 70, article 10, or shall receive
certification as a qualifying facility in accordance with the federal Public
Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978, 16 U.S.C. 2601 et seq., with written
notice of such certification provided to the Nebraska Power Review Board.</para>
<para>(6) A C-BED project developer shall notify any electric
utility that has a power purchase agreement with the C-BED
project if there is a change in project ownership which makes the project
no longer eligible as a C-BED project.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2007, LB629, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB916, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB561, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB402, &#167; 2.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2014</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>