<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" id="id36" statutenumber="70-1001.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1001.01</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Terms, defined.</catchline>
<para>For purposes of sections 70-1001 to 70-1027, unless the context otherwise
requires:</para>
<para>(1) Board means the Nebraska Power Review Board;</para>
<para>(2) Certified renewable export facility means a facility approved under
section 70-1014.02 that (a) will generate electricity using solar, wind, biomass,
or landfill gas, (b) will be constructed and owned by an entity other than
a municipality, a registered group of municipalities, a public power district,
a public power and irrigation district, an electric cooperative, an electric
membership association, or any other governmental entity, and (c) has a power
purchase or similar agreement or agreements with an initial term of ten years
or more for the sale of at least ninety percent of the output of the facility
with a customer or customers located outside the State of Nebraska and maintains
such an agreement or agreements for the life of the facility. Output sold
pursuant to subdivision (2)(a)(iv) of section 70-1014.02 shall not be included
when calculating such ninety percent. Certified renewable export facility
includes all generating equipment, easements, and interconnection equipment
within the facility and connecting the facility to the transmission grid;</para>
<para>(3) Except as expressly provided in section
70-1014.02, electric suppliers or suppliers of electricity means
any legal entity supplying, producing, or distributing electricity within
the state for sale at wholesale or retail;</para>
<para>(4) Regional transmission organization means an entity independent from
those entities generating or marketing electricity at wholesale or retail,
which has operational control over the electric transmission lines in a designated
geographic area in order to reduce constraints in the flow of electricity
and ensure that all power suppliers have open access to transmission lines
for the transmission of electricity;</para>
<para>(5) Representative organization means an organization designated by
the board and organized for the purpose of providing joint planning and encouraging
maximum cooperation and coordination among electric suppliers. Such organization
shall represent electric suppliers owning a combined electric generation plant
capacity of at least ninety percent of the total electric generation plant
capacity constructed and in operation within the state;</para>
<para>(6) State means the State of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(7) Stranded asset means a generation or transmission facility owned
by an electric supplier as defined in subsection (1) of section 70-1014.02
which cannot earn a favorable economic return due to regulatory or legislative
actions or changes in the market and, at the time an application is filed
with the board under such section, either exists or has been approved by the
board or the governing body of an electric supplier as defined in such subsection;
and</para>
<para>(8) Unbundled retail rates means the separation of utility bills into
the individual price components for which an electric supplier charges its
retail customers, including, but not limited to, the separate charges for
the generation, transmission, and distribution of electricity.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 302, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1996), &#167; 70-1023; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 901, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 65, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB208, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>