<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-1002.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1002.02</statuteno><catchline>Suppliers of electricity; sale in violation of approved agreement; prohibited; commercial electric vehicle charging station operator; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) No supplier shall offer, provide, or sell electric energy at wholesale in areas, or to customers, in violation of any agreement entered into and approved by the Nebraska Power Review Board pursuant to section 70-1002.01.</para><para>(2) A commercial electric vehicle charging station operator may receive electric energy solely from an electric supplier with the right to serve the location of the commercial electric vehicle charging station and shall not offer, provide, sell, or resell electric energy at wholesale or retail for any purpose or use other than the charging of electric vehicles at the location of the commercial electric vehicle charging station. A commercial electric vehicle charging station operator may charge electric vehicle charging customers on the basis of kilowatt-hours consumed. A commercial electric vehicle charging station is subject to the interconnection requirements, electric rates, and service regulations of the electric supplier in whose certified service area the commercial electric vehicle charging station is located. Nothing in sections 70-1001 to 70-1028 shall prohibit an electric supplier from owning and operating an electric vehicle charging station or recovering its costs to provide electric service to a commercial electric vehicle charging station.</para><para>(3) A commercial electric vehicle charging station funded in whole or part by state or federal funds shall only be installed by an installer who has obtained certification from the Electric Vehicle Infrastructure Training Program.</para><para>(4) Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit the use of batteries with a commercial electric vehicle charging station if such battery is charged with electric energy received solely from an electric supplier.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 349, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB1317, &#167; 66. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>