<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id439"><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" statutenumber="70-1506"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1506</statuteno><catchline>Cryptocurrency mining operation; regulation.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Cryptocurrency mining means validating transactions for addition to a blockchain distributed ledger;</para><para>(b) Cryptocurrency mining operation means any facility of one megawatt in size or greater that conducts cryptocurrency mining; and</para><para>(c) Public power supplier means a public power district, municipal electric utility, or any other government entity providing electric service.</para><para>(2) A public power supplier may impose requirements on any cryptocurrency mining operation for the cost of infrastructure upgrades necessitated by such operations, including, but not limited to:</para><para>(a) Requiring direct payment or a letter of credit from such operation for such cost; or</para><para>(b) Imposing terms and conditions on such operation.</para><para>(3) Requirements imposed pursuant to this section shall be fair, reasonable, and not unduly discriminatory.</para><para>(4) Before any requirement is imposed pursuant to this section, the public power supplier shall conduct a load study to determine the costs, impacts, and infrastructure upgrades necessitated by the cryptocurrency mining operation.</para><para>(5) Any person intending to install a cryptocurrency mining operation is responsible for notifying the local public power supplier of such intent, and such operation is subject to the interconnection requirements of such supplier.</para><para>(6) Each public power supplier shall make available to the public on the supplier's website the number of cryptocurrency mining operations under the jurisdiction of the supplier and the annual energy usage of each operation.</para><para>(7) A cryptocurrency mining operation shall allow a public power supplier to interrupt such operation's electric service according to such supplier's established rate schedules and policies.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB526, &#167; 1. </para><operativedate>October 1, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>