<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id63">
<sectno id="id64">Sec. 6.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" id="id65" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="70-1014.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1014.02</statuteno><catchline>Certified renewable export facilities;
approval of application; board; powers and duties; conditional approval; final
approval; failure to commence construction; effect; application fee; eminent
domain; revocation of certification; procedure; recertification.</catchline><para>(1)
For purposes of this section, electric supplier means a public power district,
a public power and irrigation district, an individual municipality, a registered
group of municipalities, an electric membership association, or a cooperative.</para>
<para>(2)(a) The
board shall conditionally approve an application for a certified renewable
export facility if it finds that only the criteria described in subdivisions
(a)(i) through (iv) of this subsection are met: (i) The facility will provide
reasonably identifiable and quantifiable public benefits, including economic
development, to the residents of Nebraska or the local area where the facility
will be located; (ii) the facility meets the requirements of subdivisions
(2)(a) and (b) of section 70-1001.01; (iii) the facility has a memorandum
of understanding or other written evidence of mutual intent to negotiate a
power purchase agreement or agreements with a purchaser or purchasers outside
the State of Nebraska for at least ninety percent of the output of the facility
for ten years or more; and (iv) the applicant offers electric suppliers serving
loads greater than fifty megawatts at the time the initial application is
filed an option to purchase in the aggregate an amount of power up to ten
percent of the output of any facility with greater than eighty megawatts of
nameplate capacity contingent upon the applicant and electric suppliers negotiating
in good faith a power purchase agreement and any other necessary agreements.
Such electric suppliers shall be entitled to a minimum of their pro rata share
based on the load ratio share of Nebraska electric load served among those
electric suppliers eligible under this subdivision (iv). If an electric supplier
declines to contract for some or all of its pro rata share, the remaining
eligible electric suppliers may share the balance on a pro rata basis. The
ten percent may be above the total generation amount proposed in the application
for a certified renewable export facility and shall require no separate approval
by the board. Any transmission studies, additions, or upgrades due to participation
by electric suppliers serving loads greater than fifty megawatts shall be
the responsibility of the participating electric supplier. Upon receiving
the initial application under this section, the board shall notify electric
suppliers identified in this subdivision (iv) of a pending application with
a nameplate capacity greater than eighty megawatts. Such suppliers shall have
forty-five days following the date of the board's notice to notify the applicant
of an interest in exercising the option to purchase power, except that such
suppliers may withdraw their option to purchase power once the costs of the
transmission additions and upgrades are determined. Electric suppliers withdrawing
their option to purchase power are responsible for their pro rata share of
any costs resulting from their participation in and withdrawal from the generation
interconnection and transmission delivery studies.</para><para>(b) Following the board's
conditional approval of an application under subdivision (a) of this subsection,
the applicant shall notify the board within eighteen months that it is prepared
to proceed to consideration of the criteria in subdivision (c) of this subsection.
The board may extend such eighteen-month deadline not more than twelve additional
months for good cause shown. If the applicant fails to notify the board within
such time that it is so prepared, the conditional approval granted under this
subdivision is void.</para><para>(c) Upon finding that the criteria described in subdivisions (c)(i)
through (viii) of this subsection have also been met by the applicant and
after the board has fulfilled the requirements of subsection (3) of section
37-807, the board shall grant final approval of an application for a certified
renewable export facility:</para><para>(i) The facility will not have a materially
detrimental effect on the retail electric rates paid by any Nebraska ratepayers,
except that, notwithstanding subdivisions (c)(v) and (vi) of this subsection,
the determination of a materially detrimental effect on rates shall not include
regional transmission improvements dictated by a regional transmission operator
or transmission improvements required due to participation by an eligible
entity pursuant to subdivision (2)(a)(iv) of this section;</para>
<para>(ii) The applicant
has obtained the necessary generation interconnection and transmission service
approvals from and has executed agreements for such generation interconnection
and transmission service with the appropriate regional transmission organization,
transmission owner, or transmission provider;</para><para>(iii) There has been no demonstration
that the proposed facility will result in a substantial risk of creating stranded
assets;</para><para>(iv) The applicant has certified that it has applied for and is
actively pursuing the required approvals from any other federal, state, or
local entities with jurisdiction or permitting authority over the certified
renewable export facility;</para><para>(v) The applicant and the electric supplier
owning the transmission facilities to which the certified renewable export
facility will be interconnected, along with any electric supplier which owns
transmission facilities of one hundred fifteen thousand volts or more and
is required to receive notice pursuant to section 70-1013, have entered into
a joint transmission development agreement on reasonable terms and conditions
consistent with and subject to the notice to construct or other directives
of any regional transmission organization with jurisdiction over the addition
or upgrade to transmission facilities or, for any electric supplier that is
not a member of a regional transmission organization with which the facility
will interconnect, covers the addition or upgrade to transmission facilities
required as a result of the certified renewable export facility. Such joint
transmission development agreement shall include provisions addressing construction,
ownership, operation, and maintenance of such additions or upgrades to transmission
facilities. The electric supplier or suppliers shall have the right to purchase
and own transmission facilities as set forth in the joint transmission development
agreement;</para><para>(vi) The applicant agrees to reimburse any costs that are not covered
by a regional transmission organization tariff or that are allocated through
the tariff to the electric suppliers as a result of the certified renewable
export facility or not covered by the tariff of a transmission owner or transmission
provider that is not a member of a regional transmission organization, costs
incurred by any electric supplier as a result of adding the certified renewable
export facility, including, but not limited to, renewable integration costs,
and costs which allow the interconnected electric supplier to operate and
maintain the transmission facilities under reasonable terms and conditions
agreed to by the parties within the joint transmission development agreement;</para>
<para>(vii)
The applicant shall submit a decommissioning plan. The applicant or owner
of the facility shall establish decommissioning security by posting an instrument,
a copy of which is given to the board, no later than the tenth year following
final approval of the facility to ensure sufficient funding is available for
removal of the facility and reclamation at the end of the useful life of such
facility pursuant to the decommissioning plan. The owner of the certified
renewable export facility shall be solely responsible for decommissioning.
If the applicant or any subsequent owner of the facility intends to transfer
ownership of the facility, the proposed new owner shall provide the board
with adequate evidence demonstrating that substitute decommissioning security
has been posted or given prior to transfer of ownership. The requirements
of this subdivision (vii) shall be waived if a local governmental entity with
authority to create requirements for decommissioning has enacted decommissioning
requirements for the applicable jurisdiction; and</para><para>(viii) The facility meets
the requirements of subdivisions (2)(a) through (c) of section 70-1001.01.</para>
<para>(3)
If the applicant does not commence construction of the certified renewable
export facility within eighteen months after receiving final approval from
the board under subsection (2) of this section, the approval is void. Upon
written request filed by the applicant, the board may, for good cause shown,
extend the time period during which an approval will remain valid. Good cause
includes, but is not limited to, national or regional economic conditions,
lack of transmission infrastructure, or an applicant's inability to obtain
authorization from other required governmental regulatory authorities despite
the applicant's exercise of a good-faith effort to obtain such approvals.</para>
<para>(4)
The applicant shall remit an application fee of five thousand dollars with
the application. The fee shall be remitted to the State Treasurer for credit
to the Nebraska Power Review Fund. The board shall use the application fee
to defray the board's reasonable expenses associated with reviewing and acting
upon the application, including the costs of the hearing. If the board incurs
expenses of more than five thousand dollars associated with the application,
the board shall provide written notification to the applicant of the additional
sum needed or already expended, after which the applicant shall promptly submit
an additional sum sufficient to cover the board's anticipated or incurred
expenses or shall file an objection with the board. If, after completion of
the application process and any subsequent legal action, including appeal
of the board's decision, the board's expenses associated with processing and
acting upon the application do not equal the amount submitted by the applicant,
the board shall return the unused funds to the applicant if the amount is
fifty dollars or more. The applicant shall reimburse the board for any reasonable
expenses the board incurs as a result of an appeal of the board's decision
or shall file an objection with the board. The board shall rule on any objection
brought pursuant to this subsection within thirty days. The applicant may
request a hearing on its objection, in which case the board shall hold such
hearing within thirty days after the request and shall rule within forty-five
days after the hearing.</para><para>(5) No facility or part of a facility which
is a certified renewable export facility is subject to eminent domain by an
electric supplier or by any other entity if the purpose of the eminent domain
proceeding is to acquire the facility for electric generation or transmission.</para>
<para>(6)
Except as provided in subsection (5) of this section, only an electric supplier
may exercise its eminent domain authority to acquire the land rights necessary
for the construction of transmission lines and related facilities to provide
transmission services for a certified renewable export facility. The exercise
of eminent domain to provide needed transmission lines and related facilities
for a certified renewable export facility is a public use. Nothing in this
section shall be construed to grant the power of eminent domain to a private
entity.</para><para>(7) If any transmission facilities serving a certified renewable
export facility are proposed to cross the service area of any electric supplier
which owns transmission facilities of one hundred fifteen thousand volts or
more and is required to receive notice pursuant to section 70-1013, then such
electric supplier may elect to be a party to a joint transmission development
agreement for such transmission facilities.</para><para>(8) If a certified renewable export facility
no longer meets the requirements of subdivisions (2)(a) through (c) of section
70-1001.01, the owner of the facility shall notify the board. An electric
supplier or a governmental entity with regulatory jurisdiction over the certified
renewable export facility may apply to the board or the board may file its
own motion to have the certification of a certified renewable export facility
revoked upon a showing by the applicant for decertification that the facility
no longer meets the requirements of such subdivisions. Upon the filing of
such application and making of a prima facie showing by the applicant for
decertification that the facility no longer meets the requirements of such
subdivisions, the board shall set the matter for hearing. The hearing shall
be held within forty-five days unless an extension is necessary for good cause
shown. The applicant for decertification shall have the burden of proof. Within
forty-five days after the conclusion of the hearing, the board shall enter
an order to either reaffirm the facility's status as a certified renewable
export facility or to revoke the certification. During the pendency of the
application for decertification and before the board's final order on decertification,
the facility may continue to operate if the electricity generated at the facility
is sold to customers outside the State of Nebraska, or to an electric supplier
pursuant to a power purchase agreement or similar agreement. The board shall
retain jurisdiction over the decertification action for at least thirty days
after entry of such an order. Within thirty days after a final order revoking
certification, the owner of the facility may apply for recertification, with
the time period for recertification being no longer than one year unless the
board extends the time period for good cause shown. Such application for recertification
shall extend the board's jurisdiction over the decertification action until
the board completes its review of the application for recertification and
enters an order granting or denying the application. If the applicant for
recertification demonstrates to the board that it is working diligently and
in good faith to restore its compliance with subdivisions (2)(a) through (c)
of section 70-1001.01, the board shall not terminate the application for recertification.
During the pendency of the application for recertification and before the
board's final order on recertification, the facility may continue to operate
if the electricity generated at the facility is sold to customers outside
the state, or to an electric supplier pursuant to a power purchase agreement
or similar agreement. If the board retains jurisdiction over the decertification
action, the prohibition on eminent domain set forth in subsection (5) of this
section shall remain in full force and effect. If the board enters an order
decertifying a certified renewable export facility and such order becomes
final due to a failure to timely seek recertification or judicial review,
the prohibition on eminent domain set forth in subsection (5) of this section
shall no longer apply. Nothing in this section shall prohibit a decertified
facility from being recertified in the same manner as a new facility.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB1048, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>