<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Power Districts And Corporations" statutenumber="70-1015"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>70-1015</statuteno><catchline>Suppliers; electric generation facilities and transmission lines; unauthorized construction, acquisition, or service; injunction; violation; actions authorized; private electric supplier; commencement of construction prior to providing notice; violation; fine; executive director; powers and duties; dispute; hearing; procedure; decision; costs.</catchline><para>(1) If any supplier violates Chapter 70, article 10, by either (a) commencing the construction or finalizing or attempting to finalize the acquisition of any generation facilities, any transmission lines, or any related facilities without first providing notice or obtaining board approval, whichever is required, or (b) serving or attempting to serve at retail any customers located in Nebraska or any wholesale customers in violation of section 70-1002.02, such construction, acquisition, or service of such customers shall be enjoined in an action brought in the name of the State of Nebraska until such supplier has complied with Chapter 70, article 10.</para><para>(2) If the executive director of the board determines that a private electric supplier commenced construction of a privately developed renewable energy generation facility less than thirty days prior to providing the notice required in subdivision (1)(a) of section 70-1014.02, the executive director shall send notice via certified mail to the private electric supplier, informing it of the determination that the private electric supplier is in violation of such subdivision and is subject to a fine in the amount of five hundred dollars. The private electric supplier shall have twenty days from the date on which the notice is received in which to submit the notice described in such subdivision and to pay the fine. Within ten days after the private electric supplier submits a notice compliant with the provisions of subsection (1) of section 70-1014.02 and payment of the fine, the executive director of the board shall issue the written acknowledgment described in subsection (2) of section 70-1014.02. If the private electric supplier fails to submit a notice compliant with the provisions of subsection (1) of section 70-1014.02 and pay the fine within twenty days after the date on which the private electric supplier receives the notice from the executive director of the board, the private electric supplier shall immediately cease construction or operation of the privately developed renewable energy generation facility.</para><para>(3) If the private electric supplier disputes that construction was commenced less than thirty days prior to submitting the written notice required by subdivision (1)(a) of section 70-1014.02, the private electric supplier may request a hearing before the board. Such request shall be submitted within twenty days after the private electric supplier receives the notice sent by the executive director pursuant to subsection (2) of this section. If the private electric supplier does not accept the certified mail sent pursuant to such subsection, the executive director shall send a second notice to the private electric supplier by first-class United States mail. The private electric supplier may submit a request for hearing within twenty days after the date on which the second notice was mailed.</para><para>(4) Upon receipt of a request for hearing, the board shall set a hearing date. Such hearing shall be held within sixty days after such receipt. The board shall provide to the private electric supplier written notice of the hearing at least twenty days prior to the date of the hearing. The board or its hearing officer may grant continuances upon good cause shown or upon the request of the private electric supplier. Timely filing of a request for hearing by a private electric supplier shall stay any further enforcement under this section until the board issues an order pursuant to subsection (5) of this section or the request for hearing is withdrawn.</para><para>(5) The board shall issue a written decision within sixty days after conclusion of the hearing. All costs of the hearing shall be paid by the private electric supplier if (a) the board determines that the private electric supplier commenced construction of the privately developed renewable energy generation facility less than thirty days prior to submitting the written notice required pursuant to subsection (1) of section 70-1014.02 or (b) the private electric supplier withdraws its request for hearing prior to the board issuing its decision.</para><para>(6) A private electric supplier which the board finds to be in violation of the requirements of subsection (1) of section 70-1014.02 shall either (a) pay the fine described in this section and submit a notice compliant with the provisions of subsection (1) of section 70-1014.02 or (b) immediately cease construction or operation of the privately developed renewable energy generation facility.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 397, &#167; 15, p. 1265; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 426, &#167; 1, p. 1302; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 181, &#167; 52; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB208, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB824, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB1008, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>