<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id921"><amendatorysection chaptername="Power Districts and Corporations" statutenumber="70-2203"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>70-2203</statuteno><catchline>Public power suppliers; establish standards for interconnecting large load customers; additional requirements.</catchline><para>(1) Public power suppliers shall establish standards for interconnecting large load customers in a manner designed to support business development in this state while mitigating the potential for stranded infrastructure costs and maintaining system reliability. The standards shall include, but are not limited to:</para><para>(a) A requirement for each large load customer to disclose to the interconnecting public power supplier whether the customer is pursuing a substantially similar request for electric service the approval of which would result in the customer materially changing, delaying, or withdrawing the interconnection request. The disclosure may redact competitively sensitive details. The public power supplier shall not sell, share, or disclose the information submitted to it under this subdivision;</para><para>(b) A requirement for each interconnected large load customer to disclose to the interconnecting public power supplier information about the customer's onsite backup generating facilities. The public power supplier shall use such information for purposes of the procedure described in section 70-2204;</para><para>(c) A study fee of fifty thousand dollars or one thousand dollars per megawatt, whichever is greater, to be paid to the interconnecting public power supplier for initial studies for loads that exceed the load threshold described in subdivision (1) of section 70-2202. A large load customer that requests additional capacity following the study shall pay an additional study fee based on the new request. The public power supplier shall complete the study within one year after receiving the study fee;</para><para>(d) A method for a large load customer to demonstrate site control for the proposed load location; and</para><para>(e) Financial commitment requirements for the development of transmission and generation infrastructure needed to serve a large load customer.</para><para>(2) A public power supplier is authorized to establish or negotiate rates, charges, and operating standards for each large load customer that fairly allocate electricity system costs to the large load customer and also mitigate (a) operational and resource adequacy risks and (b) financial risks to other customers, without regard to the requirements of section 70-655.</para><para>(3) A public power supplier may impose electric service requirements for large load customers on its system in addition to the standards established under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2026, LB1010, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 18, 2026</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>