<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Homesteads" statutenumber="40-105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>40-105</statuteno><catchline>Homestead; selection; procedure.</catchline><para>When an execution
for the enforcement of a judgment obtained in a case not within the classes
enumerated in section 40-103 is levied upon the lands or tenements of a claimant, the claimant may at any time prior
to confirmation of sale apply to the district court in the county in which
the homestead is situated for an order to determine whether or not such lands
or tenements, or any part thereof, are exempt as a homestead and, if so, the
value thereof.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 5, p. 58; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 3080; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 2820; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 40-105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 40-105; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 153, &#167; 1, p. 420; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB907, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB964, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>Application for determination of homestead exemption was properly made. Sanne v. Sanne, 167 Neb. 683, 94 N.W.2d 367 (1959); Schroeder v. Ely, 161 Neb. 262, 73 N.W.2d 172 (1955).</para><para>Homestead exemption is not a proper subject for consideration upon confirmation of judicial sale. Enquist v. Enquist, 146 Neb. 708, 21 N.W.2d 404 (1946).</para><para>Where husband and wife reside upon homestead and wife dies, homestead character of the land continues, and, although husband may have no children or dependents, he may still claim the benefit of the homestead laws. Bartels v. Seefus, 132 Neb. 841, 273 N.W. 485 (1937).</para><para>Objection to confirmation of execution sale of homestead is no bar to action to remove cloud of sheriff's deed, or other appropriate remedy. Kaley v. Eselin, 108 Neb. 544, 188 N.W. 254 (1922).</para><para>Administrator's sale of homestead is not void, after confirmation, for failure to segregate homestead interest and to order it preserved. Pohlenz v. Panko, 106 Neb. 156, 182 N.W. 972 (1921).</para><para>There is no provision for setting off of the homestead except when it is sought to be taken on execution. Sanford v. Anderson, 69 Neb. 249, 95 N.W. 632 (1903).</para><para>The homestead character of real estate upon which an attachment has been levied is not a proper question to be heard and determined upon motion to discharge attachment. Quigley v. McEvony, 41 Neb. 73, 59 N.W. 767 (1894).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>