<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-201"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-201</statuteno><catchline>Township organization; adoption.</catchline><para>At any general election that may be held in the several counties of the state, the qualified voters in any county may vote for or against township organization in such county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 28, &#167; 1, p. 131; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 987; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 887; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-201; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-201.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Officers</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Vacancies</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Construction</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Officers</emphasis></para><para>Township organization is provided for and affords supervisors, who divide the county into townships. Franek v. Butler County, 126 Neb. 797, 254 N.W. 489 (1934).</para><para>Under former law, cities entitled to two supervisors voted as one district and for both supervisors. State ex rel. Brown v. Welsh, 62 Neb. 721, 87 N.W. 529 (1901).</para><para>Member of board is township officer and should address his resignation to town clerk. State ex rel. Godard v. Taylor, 26 Neb. 580, 42 N.W. 729 (1889).</para><para>Commissioners act until supervisors are organized. State ex rel. Lichty v. Musselman, 20 Neb. 174, 29 N.W. 307 (1886).</para><para>Adoption of township organization does not shorten term of county officers. State ex rel. Crossley v. Hedlund, 16 Neb. 566, 20 N.W. 876 (1884).</para><para><emphasis>2. Vacancies</emphasis></para><para>Vacancies in cities are filled by mayor and council. State ex rel. Truesdell v. Plambeck, 36 Neb. 401, 54 N.W. 667 (1893).</para><para>Vacancies on temporary organization of town should be filled by county clerk. State ex rel. Davis v. Forney, 21 Neb. 223, 31 N.W. 802 (1887).</para><para><emphasis>3. Construction</emphasis></para><para>York County stated to have adopted township form of government. Thompson v. James, 125 Neb. 350, 250 N.W. 237 (1933).</para><para>Act of 1895 relating to township organization sustained as constitutional. Van Horn v. State ex rel. Abbott, 46 Neb. 62, 64 N.W. 365 (1895).</para><para>The several statutes on township organization should be construed together. Albert v. Twohig, 35 Neb. 563, 53 N.W. 582 (1892).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>