<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-104.01" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>23-104.01</statuteno><catchline>Agreements; conditions; limitations; powers.</catchline><para>Any agreement between counties for the joint exercise of powers shall:</para><para>(1)(a) Be in writing and signed by a majority of the board of supervisors or county commissioners of each county that is a party to the agreement; and</para><para>(b) After being signed pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section, be filed and recorded in the office of the county clerk of each county that is a party to the agreement;</para><para>(2) Specify the powers and obligations of each party under the agreement. Such powers shall:</para><para>(a) Be limited to powers imposed by law upon a county that is a party to the agreement or its board of supervisors or county commissioners; and</para><para>(b) Not include powers specifically conferred upon and required to be carried out by other elected officers of a county that is a party to the agreement;</para><para>(3) Specify the allocation and payment of expenses to be paid by each county under the agreement;</para><para>(4) Provide for the following to be reserved to and remain a function of the board of supervisors or county commissioners of each county that is a party to the agreement:</para><para>(a) Final action upon the allowance and payment of any claims and obligations against each county; and</para><para>(b) The levy and collection of taxes to pay claims and obligations under the agreement; and</para><para>(5) Be subject to the Interlocal Cooperation Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 48, &#167; 3, p. 174; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB940, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Consolidation of common functions and services,</emphasis> see section 22-401 et seq.</para><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>