<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-126"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-126</statuteno><catchline>Special tax; submission to voters; notice.</catchline><para>The mode of submitting questions to the people for any purpose authorized by law shall be as follows: The whole question, including the sum desired to be raised, or the amount of tax desired to be levied, or the rate per annum, and the whole regulation, including the time of its taking effect, if it be of a nature to be set forth, and the penalty of its violation, if there be one, is to be published for four weeks in some newspaper published in the county. If there be no such newspaper, the publication is to be made by being posted in at least one of the most public places in each election precinct in the county, and in all cases the notice shall name the time when such question will be voted upon, and the form in which the question shall be taken, and a copy of the question submitted shall be posted at each place of voting during the day of election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 27, p. 363; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 956; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 856; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-110; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-126.</para></source><annotation><para>In absence of controlling special provision, section controls borrowing of money by people of county. Lang v. Sanitary District of Norfolk, 160 Neb. 754, 71 N.W.2d 608 (1955).</para><para>Mode of submitting improvement of mail route roads is covered by this section. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. County of Gosper, 153 Neb. 805, 46 N.W.2d 147 (1951).</para><para>Requirement that notice be published four weeks and that it contain statement of amount desired to be levied is mandatory. Richardson v. Kildow, 116 Neb. 648, 218 N.W. 429 (1928).</para><para>General provision contained in above section as regards procedure for submitting question of issuing bonds does not apply to erection of courthouse. Majority vote is sufficient. State ex rel. Polk County v. Marsh, 106 Neb. 760, 184 N.W. 901 (1921).</para><para>Notice of election and time required to be published stated. State ex rel. Harris v. Hanson, 80 Neb. 738, 117 N.W. 412 (1908).</para><para>Publication of notice "during four weeks" means during full period. State v. Cherry County, 58 Neb. 734, 79 N.W. 825 (1899).</para><para>Question of issuing bonds under special act must be submitted to vote. In re House Roll No. 284, 31 Neb. 505, 48 N.W. 275 (1891).</para><para>Water and paving bonds of cities may be issued only after vote. State ex rel. City of Fremont v. Babcock, 25 Neb. 500, 41 N.W. 450 (1889).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>