<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-302"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-302</statuteno><catchline>County resurvey; election; canvass of votes.</catchline><para>The vote on the proposition shall be canvassed in the same manner as the vote on county officers. If a majority of the votes upon said proposition shall be in favor of the same, the county board shall within thirty days notify the Board of Educational Lands and Funds who shall require such resurvey to be made under its instructions by such competent deputy state surveyor as it shall appoint, assisted by the county surveyor of the county wherein the work is to be done, and according to the laws governing surveys by the State Surveyor and deputy state surveyors. Such surveys shall be made in accordance with the laws of the United States and the rules and regulations of the United States Department of Interior, Bureau of Land Management, governing the restoration of lost and obliterated corners and the specifications and instructions of the Board of Educational Lands and Funds. The field notes and plats of said resurvey shall be made in the manner and form prescribed by the Bureau of Land Management for the return of field notes and maps of United States surveys, and shall be filed in the office of the county clerk of the county where the work is done and duplicate copies filed in the office of the Board of Educational Lands and Funds at Lincoln, Nebraska, before being paid for; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> when any integral part of said resurvey is completed upon filing proof of its completion together with plats and field notes for the same approved as provided by law, the county board may allow payment for the part so completed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 36, &#167; 2, p. 220; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1109; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 84, &#167; 1, p. 301; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1043; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-737; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-302; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 127, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>