<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id54"><sectno id="id55">Sec. 10.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id56" statutenumber="23-297"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id58">23-297</statuteno><catchline id="id59">Commissioner system creation; districts; elected members; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) If the voters vote for creation of a seven-member county board of commissioners, the commissioner districts shall be the same districts as the former supervisor districts unless changed at a later date as provided by section 23-149 and the supervisors whose terms have not expired on the effective date of the reorganization prescribed in section 23-293 shall continue in office as commissioners for the remainder of their unexpired terms.</para><para>(2)(a) If the voters vote for creation of a five-member county board of commissioners, the county clerk, county treasurer, and county attorney shall meet on the first Saturday after the first Tuesday of January following such election and redistrict the county into five commissioner districts with substantially equal population. Such redistricting shall be completed within thirty days after such initial meeting and shall specify where necessary the newly established districts which the members will serve for the balance of the unexpired terms as designated in subdivision (b) of this subsection. The newly established districts will not be effective until the effective date of the reorganization prescribed in section 23-293 except for purposes of being nominated and elected for office from such districts.</para><para>(b)(i) If three members of the county board of supervisors were elected for four-year terms at the election to create a five-member county board of commissioners, each such supervisor shall serve two of such years as a supervisor and two of such years as a commissioner representing the newly established districts as designated under subdivision (a) of this subsection and two commissioners shall be elected for four-year terms from the newly established districts at the next general election.</para><para>(ii) If four members of the county board of supervisors were elected for four-year terms at the election to create a five-member county board of commissioners, the three of such supervisors receiving the most votes at such election shall serve two of such years as a supervisor and two of such years as a commissioner representing the newly established districts as designated under subdivision (a) of this subsection, the fourth of such supervisors shall serve a term of two years as a supervisor, and two commissioners shall be elected for four-year terms from the newly established districts at the next general election.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 43, &#167; 6, p. 237; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1061; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 963; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-277; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-297; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 42, &#167; 3, p. 203; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 331, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB269, &#167;  10.</para></source><annotation><para>Appointments will not be enjoined on account of irregularities in election, as quo warranto is the proper remedy. Fort v. Thompson, 49 Neb. 772, 69 N.W. 110 (1896).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>
