<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id6" statutenumber="23-149"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>23-149</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Commissioners; number; petition to change; resolution by county board; election; ballot; form.</catchline><para>(1)(a) In counties not under township organization, a registered voter may file a petition or petitions for the submission of the question regarding the number of commissioners on the county board. The petition or petitions shall be signed by registered voters equal in number to five percent of the voters registered in the county at the preceding statewide general election.</para><para>(b) In counties not under township organization, the county board may, by majority vote of all members, adopt a resolution for the submission of the question regarding the number of commissioners on the county board.</para><para>(2) When the petition or petitions or the resolution is filed with the election commissioner or county clerk not less than seventy days before the date of any general election, the election commissioner or county clerk shall cause the question to be submitted to the voters of the county at such election and give notice thereof in the general notice of such election. The forms of ballots shall be respectively: For three commissioners and For five commissioners; and the same shall be printed upon the regular ballots cast for officers voted for at such election and shall be counted and canvassed in the same manner.</para><para>(3) If a majority of votes cast at the election favor the proposition For five commissioners, thereafter the county shall have five commissioners, and if a majority of the ballots cast at the election favor the proposition For three commissioners, thereafter the county shall have three commissioners.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1891, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 226; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 30, &#167; 1, p. 277; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 978; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 18, &#167; 1, p. 78; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 69, &#167; 1, p. 183; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 878; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-132; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-149; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 259, &#167; 1, p. 958; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 789, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB269, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 24. </para></source><annotation><para>Results of election required change in number of commissioner districts. Ludwig v. Board of County Commissioners of Sarpy County, 170 Neb. 600, 103 N.W.2d 838 (1960).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>