<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-320.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-320.01</statuteno><catchline>Flood control; powers of county board; contracts with federal government; appropriation of funds.</catchline><para>In any county of the State of Nebraska in which the Corps of Engineers of the United States Army, the Bureau of Reclamation, Natural Resources Conservation Service, or other department or agency of the federal government shall be authorized by Congress to construct works for flood control, watershed protection and flood prevention, irrigation, soil and water conservation, drainage, or similar projects, or in cooperation with the programs of natural resources districts, irrigation districts, reclamation districts, or similar agencies, the county board thereof shall, if in its opinion the construction is necessary for the public welfare, have the power to: (1) Enter into an undertaking, in the name of the county, to hold the United States of America free from any damage to persons or property resulting during the construction or after the completion thereof, (2) contract with the federal government, in the name of the county, that when the work is completed the county will maintain, keep in repair, and operate such flood control works or other similar projects, (3) furnish all necessary lands, rights-of-way, and easements, as provided in section 23-320.02, (4) appropriate such funds as may be necessary to fully develop, plan, and carry out a coordinated program of flood control or soil and water resource development for such county, and (5) appropriate such funds as may be necessary to pay the construction costs and expenses in excess of funds to be provided by the federal government.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 77, &#167; 1, p. 241; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 67, &#167; 1, p. 218; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 89, &#167; 1, p. 310; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 154, &#167; 1, p. 722; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 403, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc>