<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-919"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-919</statuteno><catchline>Violations; penalty; liability to county.</catchline><para>Any official, employee or member of the county board violating the provisions of sections 23-901 to 23-918, shall be guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor. As part of the judgment of conviction, the court shall forfeit the term and tenure of the office or the employment of the person so convicted and shall order his removal from his said office or employment. Any vacancy arising by reason of said forfeiture and removal shall be filled as provided by law in the case of a vacancy in said office for any other cause. Any member of the county board or any other official whose duty it is to allow claims and issue warrants therefor, or to make purchases, incur indebtedness, enter into contracts for or on behalf of the county, who issues warrants or evidences of indebtedness, or makes any purchase, incurs any indebtedness or enters into any contract for or on behalf of the county contrary to the provisions of said sections, shall be liable to the county for such violations in the full amount of such expenditures, and for the full amount which the county may be required to pay by reason of any purchase made, indebtedness incurred or contract made contrary to the provisions of said sections, whether the liability of the county to pay for such supplies, materials, merchandise, equipment or services is based upon said contract or upon quasi-contract, or upon an obligation arising by operation of law, and recovery may be had against the bondsman of such official for said amounts. Any county treasurer or other official whose duty it is to pay warrants and evidences of indebtedness, who shall pay such warrants and evidences of indebtedness contrary to the provisions of said sections, shall likewise be liable to the county for such violations in the full amount of such expenditures, and recovery may be had against his bondsman for said amount. Suit may be brought either by the county or by any taxpayer thereof for the benefit of the county for any amount for which any official, employee or member of the county board may be liable, as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1937, c. 56, &#167; 12, p. 229; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-2112; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-919; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 40, &#167; 94. </para></source><annotation><para>County is protected against deficits resulting from claims for which county was not liable. Becker v. County of Platte, 155 Neb. 180, 50 N.W.2d 814 (1952).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>