<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-320.07"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-320.07</statuteno><catchline>Flood control; cities; powers; eminent domain; bonds; tax levy; funds, how used.</catchline><para>Except as herein otherwise expressly provided, all of the rights, powers, authority, and jurisdiction conferred on counties and county boards by sections 23-320.01 to 23-320.06 are hereby also conferred upon and vested in any city of the first or second class or village located in any county such as described in section 23-320.01 and the governing body thereof. The governing body of any such city or village, in the name of the city or village, shall have the power to enter into undertakings and contracts and make agreements in like manner and for like purposes as provided in sections 23-320.01 to 23-320.06 for county boards. Such governing body may provide funds for construction costs and expenses in excess of amounts contributed by the federal government, may acquire lands, rights-of-way, and easements either within or without the limits of the city or village in like manner and for like purposes as provided in section 23-320.02 for county boards, and without further authorization may issue general obligation bonds of the city or village to pay the costs thereof and expenses connected therewith in the manner now provided by law, but the aggregate of any such bonds so issued shall not be in excess of one and eight-tenths percent of the taxable value of the taxable property of the city or village. Such bonds shall not be subject to nor included in any restrictions or limitations upon the amount of bonded indebtedness of the city or village contained in any other law. Funds received from the sale of bonds by any such city or village may be used to pay any loss, damage, or expense for which the city or village or the governing body thereof may be liable in like manner as counties are authorized to pay such loss, damage, or expense under section 23-320.04. For the purposes of maintaining and operating flood control works constructed by the United States Army Corps of Engineers or other agencies of the United States Government, when the flood control works have been completed and turned over to the city or village, the governing body of such city or village shall be empowered to make an annual tax levy of not to exceed five and two-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of the taxable property within such city or village. It shall be the duty of the governing body of the city or village to keep all such flood control works in serviceable condition and to make such repairs as may from time to time be necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1947, c. 77, &#167; 7, p. 244; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 287, &#167; 43, p. 956; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 108, &#167; 1, p. 435; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 99, &#167; 2, p. 421; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 154, &#167; 4, p. 724; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 100; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 43. </para></source><annotation><para>City is required to keep flood control works in serviceable condition and to make necessary repairs. Gruntorad v. Hughes Bros., 161 Neb. 358, 73 N.W.2d 700 (1955).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>