<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-136"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-136</statuteno><catchline>Claims; allowance; appeal by taxpayer; procedure.</catchline><para>Any taxpayer may likewise appeal from the allowance of any claim against the county by serving a like notice within ten days and giving a bond similar to that provided for in section 23-135.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 38, p. 366; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 37, &#167; 1, p. 212; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 966; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 866; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-120; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-136.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Right to appeal</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Effect on warrants</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Right to appeal</emphasis></para><para>This ten-day time is applicable to an appeal from the action of the county board of equalization in setting the nonresident high school tuition levy. In re 1981-82 County Tax Levy of Saunders County Bd. of Equal., 214 Neb. 624, 335 N.W.2d 299 (1983).</para><para>Taxpayers may appeal from order allowing claim against county, though board's action may be result of compromise of disputed claim. Campbell Co. v. Boyd County, 117 Neb. 186, 220 N.W. 240 (1928).</para><para>Taxpayer may appeal from allowance to agricultural society. Sheldon v. Gage County Soc. of Agri., 71 Neb. 411, 98 N.W. 1045 (1904).</para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para>Taxpayer may appeal from allowance of claim by serving notice and giving bond. Reiber v. Harris, 179 Neb. 582, 139 N.W.2d 353 (1966).</para><para>Notice of appeal is jurisdictional and taxpayer must serve notice within ten days after board's decision. Sommerville v. Board of County Commissioners of Douglas County, 116 Neb. 282, 216 N.W. 815 (1927).</para><para>Judgment is an entirety; appeal puts all in issue. Dakota County v. Borowsky, 67 Neb. 317, 93 N.W. 686 (1903).</para><para>Right to appeal does not arise until claim has been allowed. Shepard v. Easterling, 61 Neb. 882, 86 N.W. 941 (1901).</para><para>Appeal may be dismissed if made in bad faith. Gage County v. King Bridge Co., 58 Neb. 827, 80 N.W. 56 (1899).</para><para>Remedy of appeal is exclusive. Taylor v. Davey, 55 Neb. 153, 75 N.W. 553 (1898).</para><para>Bona fide attempt to appeal will not be dismissed on account of informalities or omissions in bond. Rube v. Cedar County, 35 Neb. 896, 53 N.W. 1009 (1892); State ex rel. Hagberg v. County Comrs. of Furnas County, 10 Neb. 361, 6 N.W. 434 (1880).</para><para><emphasis>3. Effect on warrants</emphasis></para><para>Delivery of the warrant in suit prior to lapse of time for taking taxpayer's appeal, in violation of statute, does not affect taxpayer's right of appeal. Beadle v. Harmon, 130 Neb. 389, 265 N.W. 18 (1936).</para><para>Warrants should not be delivered or registered until time for appeal has expired. Means v. Webster, 23 Neb. 432, 36 N.W. 809 (1888).</para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Cited but not discussed. Clark v. Sweet, 183 Neb. 723, 163 N.W.2d 881 (1969).</para><para>Taxpayer, in absence of statutory authority, cannot collect attorney fees from county. Minshull v. Sherman County, 95 Neb. 835, 146 N.W. 1009 (1914).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>