<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id112">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id114" statutenumber="23-186"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>23-186</statuteno><catchline id="id117">Consolidation
of services; county board; designation of official; county treasurer; duties.</catchline>
<para>(1) Until the implementation date designated by the Director
of Motor Vehicles under subsection (2) of this section, a county board may
consolidate, under the office of a designated county official, the services
provided to the public by the county assessor, the county clerk, and the county
treasurer relating to the issuance of certificates of title, registration
certificates, certificates of number, license plates, and renewal decals,
the notation and cancellation of liens, and the collection of taxes and fees
for motor vehicles, all-terrain vehicles, utility-type vehicles, minibikes,
snowmobiles, trailers, and motorboats as provided in the Motor Vehicle Certificate
of Title Act, the Motor Vehicle Registration Act, the State Boat Act, and
sections 18-1738, 18-1738.01, and 60-1803. In a county in which a city of
the metropolitan class is located, the county board may designate the county
treasurer to provide the services. In any other county, the county board may
designate the county assessor, the county clerk, or the county treasurer to
provide the services.</para>
<para>(2) Beginning on an implementation date designated by the
Director of Motor Vehicles, but no later than January 1, 2011, the county
treasurer of each county shall be the county official who provides services
to the public relating to the issuance of certificates of title, registration
certificates, certificates of number, license plates, and renewal decals,
the notation and cancellation of liens, and the collection of taxes and fees
for motor vehicles, all-terrain vehicles, utility-type vehicles, minibikes,
snowmobiles, trailers, and motorboats as provided in the Motor Vehicle Certificate
of Title Act, the Motor Vehicle Registration Act, the State Boat Act, section 60-1803, and, until the implementation date designated
by the director under section 60-3,113.01, sections 18-1738 and 18-1738.01.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1993, LB 112, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 37, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 464, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 271, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 333, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 274, &#167; 227; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 276, &#167; 99; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB49, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB650, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB163, &#167; 13.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act,</emphasis> see section 60-101.</para><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Registration Act,</emphasis> see section 60-301.</para><para><emphasis>State Boat Act,</emphasis> see section 37-1201.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>