
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id66" statutenumber="23-299"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-299</statuteno><catchline id="id69">Township organization; cessation; town records; indebtedness and unexpended balances; how discharged; township library; disposition.</catchline><para>(1) If township organization is discontinued in any county, the town clerk in each town in such county, as soon as the county board is qualified pursuant to section 23-297, shall deposit with the county clerk of the county all town records, papers, and documents pertaining to the affairs of such town and certify to the county clerk the amount of indebtedness of such town outstanding at the time of such discontinuance. The county board shall have full and complete power to settle all the unfinished business of the town as fully as might have been done by the town itself and to dispose of any and all property belonging to such town, the proceeds of which, after paying all indebtedness, shall be disposed of by the county board for the benefit of the taxable inhabitants thereof by such board crediting all unexpended balances of the town to the district road fund and in no other manner. The county board, at such time as provided by law, shall levy a tax upon the taxable property of such town to pay any unliquidated indebtedness it may have outstanding.</para><para>(2) If township organization is discontinued in any county with a township library, the county board shall hold a public hearing to determine if the township library shall (a) be disposed of, (b) merge with a city, village, or county library, or (c) continue operation. Such public hearing shall occur within one year after voters have approved the discontinuance of township organization. Notice of such hearing shall be published for two consecutive weeks in a newspaper of general circulation in the county. At the same time notice is first published, the county board shall provide notice of such hearing to the Nebraska Library Commission and the regional library system for the region in which the township library is located. No later than sixty days following such hearing, the county board shall adopt a resolution stating the disposition of the library and the effective date of such disposition prior to the discontinuance of township operation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 43, &#167; 8, p. 237; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1063; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 965; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-279; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-299; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 42, &#167; 5, p. 204; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB269, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB75, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>