
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-114.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-114.01</statuteno><catchline>County planning commission; appointment;
qualifications; terms; vacancies; compensation; expenses; powers; duties;
appeal.</catchline><para>(1) In order to avail itself of the powers conferred
by section 23-114, the county board shall appoint a planning commission to
be known as the county planning commission. The members of the commission
shall be residents of the county to be planned and shall be appointed with
due consideration to geographical and population factors. Since the primary
focus of concern and control in county planning and land-use regulatory programs
is the unincorporated area, a majority of the members of the commission shall
be residents of unincorporated areas, except that this requirement shall not
apply to joint planning commissions. Members of the commission shall hold
no county or municipal office, except that a member may also be a member of
a city, village, or other type of planning commission. The term of each member
shall be three years, except that approximately one-third of the members of
the first commission shall serve for terms of one year, one-third for terms
of two years, and one-third for terms of three years. All members shall hold
office until their successors are appointed. Members of the commission may
be removed by a majority vote of the county board for inefficiency, neglect
of duty, or malfeasance in office or other good and sufficient cause upon
written charges being filed with the county board and after a public hearing
has been held regarding such charges. Vacancies occurring otherwise than through
the expiration of terms shall be filled for the unexpired terms by individuals
appointed by the county board. Members of the commission shall be compensated
for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in connection with their
duties in an amount to be fixed by the county board. Reimbursement for mileage
shall be made at the rate provided in section 81-1176. Each county board may
provide a per diem payment for members of the commission of not to exceed
fifteen dollars for each day that each such member attends meetings of the
commission or is engaged in matters concerning the commission, but no member
shall receive more than one thousand dollars in any one year. Such per diem
payments shall be in addition to and separate from compensation for expenses.</para>
<para>(2) The commission: (a) Shall prepare and adopt as its policy statement
a comprehensive development plan and such implemental means as a capital improvement
program, subdivision regulations, building codes, and a zoning resolution;
(b) shall consult with and advise public officials and agencies, public utilities,
civic organizations, educational institutions, and citizens relating to the
promulgation of implemental programs; (c) may delegate authority to any of
the groups named in subdivision (b) of this subsection to conduct studies
and make surveys for the commission; and (d) shall make preliminary reports
on its findings and hold public hearings before submitting its final reports.
The county board shall not hold its public meetings or take action on matters
relating to the comprehensive development plan, capital improvements, building
codes, subdivision development, or zoning until it has received the recommendations
of the commission.</para>
<para>(3) The commission may, with the consent of the governing body, in its
own name: Make and enter into contracts with public or private bodies; receive
contributions, bequests, gifts, or grants of funds from public or private
sources; expend the funds appropriated to it by the county board; employ agents
and employees; and acquire, hold, and dispose of property. The commission
may, on its own authority: Make arrangements consistent with its program;
conduct or sponsor special studies or planning work for any public body or
appropriate agency; receive grants, remuneration, or reimbursement for such
studies or work; and at its public hearings, summon witnesses, administer
oaths, and compel the giving of testimony.</para>
<para>(4) In all counties in the state, the county planning commission may
grant conditional uses or special exceptions to property owners for the use
of their property if the county board of commissioners or supervisors has
officially and generally authorized the commission to exercise such powers
and has approved the standards and procedures the commission adopted for equitably
and judiciously granting such conditional uses or special exceptions. The
granting of a conditional use permit or special exception shall only allow
property owners to put their property to a special use if it is among those
uses specifically identified in the county zoning regulations as classifications
of uses which may require special conditions or requirements to be met by
the owners before a use permit or building permit is authorized. The applicant
for a conditional use permit or special exception for a livestock operation
specifically identified in the county zoning regulations as a classification
of use which may require special conditions or requirements to be met within
an area of a county zoned for agricultural use may request a determination
of the special conditions or requirements to be imposed by the county planning
commission or by the county board of commissioners or supervisors if the board
has not authorized the commission to exercise such authority. Upon request
the commission or board shall issue such determination of the special conditions
or requirements to be imposed in a timely manner. Such special conditions
or requirements to be imposed may include, but are not limited to, the submission
of information that may be separately provided to state or federal agencies
in applying to obtain the applicable state and federal permits. The commission
or the board may request and review, prior to making a determination of the
special conditions or requirements to be imposed, reasonable information relevant
to the conditional use or special exception. If a determination of the special
conditions or requirements to be imposed has been made, final permit approval
may be withheld subject only to a final review by the commission or county
board to determine whether there is a substantial change in the applicant's
proposed use of the property upon which the determination was based and that
the applicant has met, or will meet, the special conditions or requirements
imposed in the determination. For purposes of this section, substantial change
shall include any significant alteration in the original application including
a significant change in the design or location of buildings or facilities,
in waste disposal methods or facilities, or in capacity.</para>
<para>(5) The power to grant conditional uses or special exceptions as set
forth in subsection (4) of this section shall be the exclusive authority of
the commission, except that the county board of commissioners or supervisors
may choose to retain for itself the power to grant conditional uses or special
exceptions for those classifications of uses specified in the county zoning
regulations. The county board of commissioners or supervisors may exercise
such power if it has formally adopted standards and procedures for granting
such conditional uses or special exceptions in a manner that is equitable
and which will promote the public interest. In any county other than a county in which
is located a city of the primary class, an appeal of a decision
by the county planning commission or county board of commissioners or supervisors
regarding a conditional use or special exception shall be made to the district
court. In any county in which
is located a city of the primary class, an appeal of a decision by the county
planning commission regarding a conditional use or special exception shall
be made to the county board of commissioners or supervisors, and an appeal
of a decision by the county board of commissioners or supervisors regarding
a conditional use or special exception shall be made to the district court.</para>
<para>(6) Whenever a county planning commission or county board is authorized
to grant conditional uses or special exceptions pursuant to subsection (4)
or (5) of this section, the planning commission or county board shall, with
its decision to grant or deny a conditional use permit or special exception,
issue a statement of factual findings arising from the record of proceedings
that support the granting or denial of the conditional use permit or special
exception. If a county planning commission's role is advisory to the county
board, the county planning commission shall submit such statement with its
recommendation to the county board as to whether to approve or deny a conditional
use permit or special exception.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 117, &#167; 2, p. 366; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 186, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 601, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 259, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1011, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 754, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 973, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB970, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Subsection (5) of this section provides for a right of appeal to the district court from a decision by the county planning commission or county board of commissioners or supervisors, without setting forth any procedure for prosecuting the appeal. Therefore, the appeal procedure in section 25-1937 is also implicated. In re Application of Olmer, 275 Neb. 852, 752 N.W.2d 124 (2008).</para><para>If there is a conflict between a comprehensive plan and a zoning ordinance, the latter is controlling when questions of a citizen's property rights are at issue. Stones v. Plattsmouth Airport Authority, 193 Neb. 552, 228 N.W.2d 129 (1975).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>