<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-129"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-129</statuteno><catchline>Special tax; approval by voters; number required; effect.</catchline><para>If it appears that a majority of the total number of votes cast upon the proposition at the election in which the proposition is submitted are in favor of the proposition, except the proposal for bonds as provided in section 23-3501, which require a majority of votes cast upon the proposition at the election at which the proposition is submitted, and it also appears that the requirements of the law have been fully complied with, the same shall be entered at large by the county board upon the book containing the record of its proceedings, and it shall then have power to levy and collect the special tax in the same manner as other county taxes are collected. Propositions thus acted upon cannot be rescinded by the county board.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 30, p. 364; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 959; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 859; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-113; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-129; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 37, &#167; 1, p. 129; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 177; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 85, &#167; 1, p. 296; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 534, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 38. </para></source><annotation><para>Favorable vote of two-thirds of electors is required to issue bonds of sanitary drainage district. Lang v. Sanitary District of Norfolk, 160 Neb. 754, 71 N.W.2d 608 (1955).</para><para>Where levy in excess of constitutional limit is required, two-thirds vote in favor of bond issue is required. State ex rel. Shelley v. Board of County Commissioners of Frontier County, 156 Neb. 583, 57 N.W.2d 129 (1953).</para><para>Approval of levy for improvement of mail route road did not of itself authorize levy above constitutional limit. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. County of Gosper, 153 Neb. 805, 46 N.W.2d 147 (1951).</para><para>Provisions are not applicable to erection of courthouse. Majority vote is sufficient. State ex rel. Polk County v. Marsh, 106 Neb. 760, 184 N.W. 901 (1921).</para><para>Provisions are not applicable to special acts. State ex rel. Douglas County v. Cornell, 54 Neb. 72, 74 N.W. 432 (1898).</para><para>Section is applicable to submission of proposition to sell lands of county. Stenberg v. State ex rel. Keller, 50 Neb. 127, 69 N.W. 849 (1897); Stenberg v. State ex rel. Keller, 48 Neb. 299, 67 N.W. 190 (1896).</para><para>This section applies to courthouse bonds. Fenton v. Yule, 27 Neb. 758, 43 N.W. 1140 (1889).</para><para>Section means two-thirds of total vote cast. State ex rel. Mann v. Anderson, 26 Neb. 517, 42 N.W. 421 (1889).</para><para>Purchaser need look no further than record to determine compliance with requirements of the law. Valley County v. McLean, 79 F. 728 (8th Cir. 1897).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>