<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-134"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-134</statuteno><catchline>Warrants; issuance in excess of limitations; liability of county board.</catchline><para>Any warrant drawn after eighty-five percent of the amount levied for the year is exhausted, and where there are no funds in the treasury for the payment of the same, shall not be chargeable as against the county, but may be collected by civil action from the county board making the same, or any member thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 36, p. 365; </para><para>Laws 1881, c. 43, &#167; 2, p. 223; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 964; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 864; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-118; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-134.</para></source><annotation><para>In action against county commissioners to recover money alleged to have been unlawfully expended after the annual tax levy, it must be shown that warrants in excess of the levy for the current year were issued, and that there was no money in the proper fund for their payment. Thiles v. County Board of Sarpy County, 189 Neb. 1, 200 N.W.2d 13 (1972).</para><para>No recovery quantum meruit can be had where there is a constitutional or statutory disqualification to make the contract or create the liability. Warren v. County of Stanton, 147 Neb. 32, 22 N.W.2d 287 (1946).</para><para>Where warrants on their face disclosed that amount issued exceeded levy authorized, recovery could not be had quantum meruit for the excess. Warren v. County of Stanton, 147 Neb. 32, 22 N.W.2d 287 (1946).</para><para>No action can be maintained against county upon warrants issued in violation of this section. Warren v. Stanton County, 145 Neb. 220, 15 N.W.2d 757 (1944).</para><para>Where warrants on their face show that amount of levy has been exceeded, county cannot be estopped to deny liability thereon. Warren v. Stanton County, 145 Neb. 220, 15 N.W.2d 757 (1944).</para><para>In action against county commissioners to recover money alleged to have been unlawfully expended, it must be shown not only that warrants in excess of eighty-five percent of the amount levied by tax for the current year were issued, but also that there was no money in the proper fund for their payment. Beadle v. Harmon, 130 Neb. 389, 265 N.W. 18 (1936).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>