<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-105</statuteno><catchline>County property; control; duty of county board; annual inventory.</catchline><para>The county boards of the several counties shall have the power to take and have the care and custody of all the real and personal estate owned by the county; and, in connection with the foregoing, to file and to require each county officer of the county to file the annual inventory statements with respect to county personal property, as required by sections 23-346 to 23-350.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 23, p. 360; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 350; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 44, &#167; 1, p. 287; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 952; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 73; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 852; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 93, &#167; 1, p. 273; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 60, &#167; 2, p. 231; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 40, &#167; 1, p. 134; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 236; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 5, p. 144; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 48, &#167; 2, p. 235; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 1(1), p. 224; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-105.</para></source><annotation><para>Under former law county had power of examination of its own records and could contract with auditor for that purpose. Campbell v. Douglas County, 142 Neb. 773, 7 N.W.2d 764 (1943).</para><para>Purchase by commissioners of electric refrigerator for county jail is proper exercise of power. Beadle v. Harmon, 130 Neb. 389, 265 N.W. 18 (1936).</para><para>Where one of county commissioners has moved out of his district into that of another commissioner, and where he continues to act as member of county board, the fact of such removal does not render order of board void. Horton v. Howard, 97 Neb. 575, 150 N.W. 633 (1915).</para><para>County as corporate body has power to cancel twenty-five year lease with consent of lessee, and to execute a new lease for a longer period. Lancaster County v. Lincoln Aud. Assn., 87 Neb. 87, 127 N.W. 226 (1910).</para><para>Court of equity will not interfere unless board exceeds powers. Roberts v. Thompson, 82 Neb. 458, 118 N.W. 106 (1908).</para><para>Board cannot transact business except at regular or special meetings. Morris v. Merrell, 44 Neb. 423, 62 N.W. 865 (1895).</para><para>Regular or special meetings must be held at county seat. Merrick County v. Batty, 10 Neb. 176, 4 N.W. 959 (1880).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>