<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-389"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-389</statuteno><catchline>County; provide for horseracing facilities; paid for by revenue bonds; bond anticipation notes; procedure.</catchline><para>Any county of the State of Nebraska may acquire a site or sites and construct, purchase, or otherwise acquire, remodel, repair, furnish, and equip grandstands, pavilions, exhibition halls, barns, racetracks, and other horseracing facilities by issuing revenue bonds payable solely from the revenue therefrom. The bonds shall not constitute a debt of the county or the State of Nebraska but shall be payable solely out of the revenue. Such bonds shall mature in not to exceed thirty years and bear interest at such rates and have such other terms and conditions as the county board shall determine. A county undertaking construction and acquisition of such facilities shall have the power from time to time to issue bond anticipation notes to mature not less than thirty months from the date thereof in an amount not exceeding the aggregate at any time outstanding of the amount of bonds then or theretofore authorized. Payment of such notes shall be made from any money or revenue which the county may have available for such purposes or from the proceeds of the sale of the revenue bonds authorized in this section. The county may pledge any revenue derived from the operation, management, or sale of the property constructed or acquired with the proceeds of the bonds for the payment of such notes and revenue bonds. Such bonds shall be registered with the county clerk.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 519, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 420, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>