<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-114.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-114.04</statuteno><catchline>Zoning regulations; enforcement; county zoning administrator; appoint; compensation; permits; fees.</catchline><para>(1) The county board shall provide for enforcement of the zoning regulations within its county by requiring the issuance of permits prior to the erection, construction, reconstruction, alteration, repair, or conversion of any nonfarm building or structure within a zoned area, and the county board may provide for the withholding of any permit if the purpose for which it is sought would conflict with zoning regulations adopted for the particular district in which the building or structure is situated or in which it is proposed to be erected. All plats for subdivisions in the area outside the corporate limits of cities and villages and outside of an unincorporated area wherein a city or village has been granted subdivision jurisdiction and is exercising such jurisdiction must be approved by the county planning commission.</para><para>(2) The county board may establish and appoint a county zoning administrator, who may also serve as a building inspector, and may fix his compensation or may authorize any administrative official of the county to assume the functions of such position in addition to his regular duties. The county board may also fix a reasonable schedule of fees for the issuance of permits under the provisions of subsection (1) of this section. The permits shall not be issued unless the plans of and for the proposed erection, construction, reconstruction, alteration, use or change of use, including sanitation, plumbing and sewage disposal, are filed in writing in the building inspector's office and such plans fully conform to all zoning regulations then in effect.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 117, &#167; 5, p. 370; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 23. </para></source></law></legaldoc>