<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-140"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-140</statuteno><catchline>Debts due county; settlement.</catchline><para>All persons chargeable with money belonging to any county shall render their accounts to and settle with the county board at the time required by law, and pay into the county treasury any balance which may be due the county, take duplicate receipts therefor, and deposit one of the same with the clerk of the county within five days thereafter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 43, p. 367; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 970; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 870; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-124; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-140.</para></source><annotation><para>A county clerk, chargeable with money belonging to the county by collection of fees, is required to render accounts and settle with county board as provided in this section. Hoctor v. State, 141 Neb. 329, 3 N.W.2d 558 (1942).</para><para>If the board allows greater compensation than that fixed by law, action is void. Maurer v. Gage County, 72 Neb. 441, 100 N.W. 1026 (1904).</para><para>Board acts ministerially in adjusting accounts of county officers. Smith v. Clay County, 71 Neb. 614, 99 N.W. 501 (1904); Mitchell v. Clay County, 69 Neb. 779, 96 N.W. 673 (1903), reversed on rehearing 69 Neb. 795, 98 N.W. 662 (1904).</para><para>Action of board allowing officer to retain fees illegally does not make members liable unless they acted corruptly, and such action does not protect officer. Otoe County v. Dorman, 71 Neb. 408, 98 N.W. 1064 (1904).</para><para>Mandamus is not proper action to litigate right to retain fees. Maurer v. State ex rel. Gage County, 71 Neb. 24, 98 N.W. 426 (1904).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>