<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-106</statuteno><catchline>County funds; management; establish petty cash fund; purpose; power of county board.</catchline><para>(1) The county board shall manage the county funds and county business except as otherwise specifically provided.</para><para>(2) The county board shall have the authority to establish a petty cash fund for such county for the purpose of making payments for subsidiary general operational expenditures and purchases. Such county board shall set, by resolution of the board, the amount of money to be carried in such petty cash fund and the dollar limit of an expenditure from such fund and such amount shall be stated in the fiscal policy of the county board budget message.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 23, p. 360; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 350; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 44, &#167; 1, p. 287; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 952; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 73; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 852; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 93, &#167; 1, p. 273; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 60, &#167; 2, p. 231; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 40, &#167; 1, p. 134; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 236; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 5, p. 144; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 48, &#167; 2, p. 235; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 1(2), p. 224; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-106; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 686, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 643, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>A county board in managing county business may employ necessary agents or servants to carry out duties not imposed by law upon others. Thiles v. County Board of Sarpy County, 189 Neb. 1, 200 N.W.2d 13 (1972).</para><para>County board has duty to deduct personal taxes from claims allowed. State ex rel. Bates v. Morgan, 154 Neb. 234, 47 N.W.2d 512 (1951).</para><para>County board may make all contracts within scope of powers of county acting as a body corporate. Speer v. Kratzenstein, 143 Neb. 310, 12 N.W.2d 360 (1943).</para><para>Board has power to employ and pay for clerical assistance to county attorney. Emberson v. Adams County, 93 Neb. 823, 142 N.W. 294 (1913).</para><para>Implied powers of county board stated. Wherry v. Pawnee County, 88 Neb. 503, 129 N.W. 1013 (1911); Berryman v. Schalander, 85 Neb. 281, 122 N.W. 990 (1909).</para><para>Powers of board are construed strictly. Morton v. Carlin, 51 Neb. 202, 70 N.W. 966 (1897).</para><para>Appointments are not a judicial act of board. Prather v. Hart, 17 Neb. 598, 24 N.W. 282 (1885).</para><para>Board has no power to alter amount of fees. Kemerer v. State ex rel. Garber, 7 Neb. 130 (1878).</para><para>Contracts should be let to lowest bidder. People ex rel. Putnam v. Commissioners of Buffalo County, 4 Neb. 150 (1875).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>