<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-224"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-224</statuteno><catchline>Annual town meeting; powers of electors present.</catchline><para>The electors present at the annual town meeting shall have power:</para><para>(1) To make all orders for sale, conveyance, regulation, or use of the corporate property of the town that may be deemed to be conducive to the interests of the inhabitants;</para><para>(2) To take all necessary measures and give directions for the exercise of their corporate powers;</para><para>(3) To provide for the institution, defense, or disposition of suits at law or in equity in which the town is interested;</para><para>(4) To take such action as shall induce the planting and cultivation of trees along the highways in such towns and to protect and preserve trees standing along or on highways;</para><para>(5) To construct and keep in repair public wells and to regulate the use thereof;</para><para>(6) To prevent the exposure or deposit of offensive or injurious substances within the limits of the town;</para><para>(7) To make such bylaws, rules, and regulations as may be deemed necessary to carry into effect the powers herein granted and to impose such fines and penalties, not exceeding twenty dollars for one offense, as shall be deemed proper, except when a fine or penalty is already allowed by law, which fine or penalty shall be imposed by the county court;</para><para>(8) To direct the raising of money by taxation, subject to approval by the county board, (a) for constructing and repairing roads and bridges within the town to the extent allowed by law; (b) for the prosecution or defense of suits by or against the town or in which it is interested; (c) for any other purpose required by law; (d) for the purpose of building or repairing bridges over streams dividing the town from any other town; (e) for the compensation of town officers at the rate allowed by law and, when no rate is fixed for such amount, as the electors may direct; and (f) for the care and maintenance of abandoned or neglected cemeteries within the town, except that the town board shall not expend more than one hundred dollars in any one year for such purposes. When any county discontinues township organization, the county shall care for and maintain such abandoned or neglected cemeteries;</para><para>(9) To guard against the destruction of property in the town by prairie fire;</para><para>(10) To restrain, regulate, or prohibit the running at large of cattle, horses, mules, asses, swine, sheep, and goats and determine when such animals may go at large, if at all. All votes thereon shall be by ballot;</para><para>(11) To authorize the distraining, impounding, and sale of cattle, horses, mules, asses, sheep, goats, and swine for penalties incurred and costs of proceedings. The owner of such animals shall have the right to redeem the same from the purchaser thereof at any time within one month from the day of sale by paying the amount of the purchaser's bid, with reasonable costs for their keeping and interest at the rate of seven percent per annum;</para><para>(12) To purchase, hold, plat, improve, and maintain grounds for cemetery purposes; to sell and convey lots in such cemeteries for the burial of the dead and to contract with the purchaser to perpetually care for and keep in order the lots so sold; and to elect trustees who shall have power to manage such cemetery under such bylaws as the electors of the township at the annual town meeting shall from time to time adopt. When any county discontinues township organization, the county shall care for and maintain such abandoned or neglected cemeteries; and</para><para>(13) To hold an election or town meeting to exceed the levy limits established by section 77-3443.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 28, &#167; 22, p. 137; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 285; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1008; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 60, &#167; 1, p. 166; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 910; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 218; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-224; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-224; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 120, &#167; 1, p. 382; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 111; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 39. </para></source><annotation><para>County may appropriate money for portion of state road through township. State v. Bone Creek Township, 109 Neb. 202, 190 N.W. 586 (1922).</para><para>In counties under township organization where no poorhouse has been established, the duty of supporting the poor devolves upon the townships. Custer Township v. Board of Supervisors of Antelope County, 103 Neb. 128, 170 N.W. 600 (1919).</para><para>Township, expending money for board and hospital fees, cannot recover same from county. Newark Township v. Kearney County, 99 Neb. 142, 155 N.W. 797 (1915).</para><para>County having no poorhouse is liable to another county for care of its poor. Rock County v. Holt County, 78 Neb. 616, 111 N.W. 366 (1907).</para><para>In counties under township organization, duty to keep ordinary township highways and culverts in repair is imposed on township. Goes v. Gage County, 67 Neb. 616, 93 N.W. 923 (1903).</para><para>Township is not liable for support of poor unless county has not established a poorhouse. Town of Clearwater v. Town of Garfield, 65 Neb. 697, 91 N.W. 496 (1902).</para><para>Townships are liable for support of pauper only when made so by statute. Gilligan v. Town of Grattan, 63 Neb. 242, 88 N.W. 477 (1901).</para><para>Town is liable on supervisor's contract to support poor whether levy is made or not. Waltham v. Town of Mullally, 27 Neb. 483, 43 N.W. 252 (1889).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>