<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-114"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-114</statuteno><catchline>Zoning regulations; when authorized;
powers; manufactured homes; limitation of jurisdiction.</catchline><para>(1)
The county board shall have power: (a) To create
a planning commission with the powers and duties set forth in sections 23-114
to 23-114.05, 23-168.01 to 23-168.04, 23-172 to 23-174, 23-174.02, 23-373,
and 23-376; (b) to make, adopt, amend,
extend, and implement a county comprehensive development plan; (c) to adopt a zoning resolution, which shall
have the force and effect of law; and (d) to cede and transfer jurisdiction
pursuant to section 13-327 over land otherwise subject to the authority of
the county board pursuant to this section.</para>
<para>(2) The zoning resolution may regulate and restrict: (a) The location,
height, bulk, number of stories, and size of buildings and other structures,
including tents, cabins, house trailers, and automobile trailers; (b) the
percentage of lot areas which may be occupied; (c) building setback lines;
(d) sizes of yards, courts, and other open spaces; (e) the density of population;
(f) the uses of buildings; and (g) the uses of land for agriculture, forestry,
recreation, residence, industry, and trade, after considering factors relating
to soil conservation, water supply conservation, surface water drainage and
removal, or other uses in the unincorporated area of the county. If a zoning
resolution or regulation affects the Niobrara scenic river corridor as defined
in section 72-2006, the Niobrara Council shall act on the measure as provided
in section 72-2010.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The county board shall not adopt or enforce any zoning resolution
or regulation which prohibits the use of land for a proposed residential structure
for the sole reason that the proposed structure is a manufactured home if
such manufactured home bears an appropriate seal which indicates that it was
constructed in accordance with the standards of the Uniform Standard Code
for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles, the Nebraska Uniform Standards
for Modular Housing Units Act, or the United States Department of Housing
and Urban Development. The county board may require that a manufactured home
be located and installed according to the same standards for foundation system,
permanent utility connections, setback, and minimum square footage which would
apply to a site-built, single-family dwelling on the same lot. The county
board may also require that manufactured homes meet the following standards:</para>
<para>(i) The home shall have no less than nine hundred square feet of floor
area;</para>
<para>(ii) The home shall have no less than an eighteen-foot exterior width;</para>
<para>(iii) The roof shall be pitched with a minimum vertical rise of two
and one-half inches for each twelve inches of horizontal run;</para>
<para>(iv) The exterior material shall be of a color, material, and scale
comparable with those existing in residential site-built, single-family construction;</para>
<para>(v) The home shall have a nonreflective roof material which is or simulates
asphalt or wood shingles, tile, or rock; and</para>
<para>(vi) The home shall have wheels, axles, transporting lights, and removable
towing apparatus removed.</para>
<para>(b) The county board may not require additional standards unless such
standards are uniformly applied to all single-family dwellings in the zoning
district.</para>
<para>(c) Nothing in this subsection shall be deemed to supersede any valid
restrictive covenants of record.</para>
<para>(4) For purposes of this section, manufactured home shall mean (a) a
factory-built structure which is to be used as a place for human habitation,
which is not constructed or equipped with a permanent hitch or other device
allowing it to be moved other than to a permanent site, which does not have
permanently attached to its body or frame any wheels or axles, and which bears
a label certifying that it was built in compliance with National Manufactured
Home Construction and Safety Standards, 24 C.F.R. 3280 et seq., promulgated
by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development, or (b) a
modular housing unit as defined in section 71-1557 bearing a seal in accordance
with the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act.</para>
<para>(5) Special districts or zones may be established in those areas subject
to seasonal or periodic flooding, and such regulations may be applied as will
minimize danger to life and property.</para>
<para>(6) The powers conferred by this section shall not be exercised within
the limits of any incorporated city or village nor within the area over which
a city or village has been granted or ceded zoning jurisdiction and is exercising
such jurisdiction. At such time as a city or village exercises control over
an unincorporated area by the adoption or amendment of a zoning ordinance,
the ordinance or amendment shall supersede any resolution or regulation of
the county.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 48, &#167; 2, p. 237; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 1(10), p. 226; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-114; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 381, &#167; 1, p. 1325; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 117, &#167; 1, p. 366; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 511, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 57; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 822, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1234, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 729, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB709, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1555.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles,</emphasis> see section 71-4601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>If the mode or manner by which a certain action is to be taken is prescribed in a statute or charter, that method must generally be followed. State ex rel. Musil v. Woodman, 271 Neb. 692, 716 N.W.2d 32 (2006).</para><para>If there is a conflict between a comprehensive plan and a zoning ordinance, the latter is controlling when questions of a citizen's property rights are at issue. Stones v. Plattsmouth Airport Authority, 193 Neb. 552, 228 N.W.2d 129 (1975).</para><para>City zoning plan covering property within two miles of city limits supersedes county zoning regulations respecting that area. Deans v. West, 189 Neb. 518, 203 N.W.2d 504 (1973).</para><para>Owner's right to use property is subject to reasonable regulation; the burden is on one who attacks the validity of a zoning ordinance to prove facts which establish its invalidity. Stahla v. Board of Zoning Adjustment of Hall County, 186 Neb. 219, 182 N.W.2d 209 (1970).</para><para>County board has authority to adopt zoning resolution. City of Grand Island v. Ehlers, 180 Neb. 331, 142 N.W.2d 770 (1966).</para><para>Counties are empowered to adopt a comprehensive zoning plan by resolution. Crane v. Board of County Commissioners of Sarpy County, 175 Neb. 568, 122 N.W.2d 520 (1963).</para><para>Zoning resolution adopted by county board must be published. Board of Commissioners of Sarpy County v. McNally, 168 Neb. 23, 95 N.W.2d 153 (1959).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>