<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-269"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-269</statuteno><catchline>County supervisor districts; boundaries; change.</catchline><para>The supervisor districts may be changed after each state and federal census if it appears from an examination that the population has become unequal among the several districts. In the event of any change or amendment of sections 23-201 to 23-299 which may necessitate a change in the boundaries of such supervisor districts or any one of them, the county board shall make such change in boundary at its next regular meeting after such change or amendment takes effect. Those counties under township organization may change their procedures for electing members to their governing board from district to at large or from at large to district following the provisions of section 32-554.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1895, c. 28, &#167; 72, p. 153; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1053; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 17, &#167; 3, p. 82; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 955; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-269; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-269; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 552, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 789, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 540. </para></source><annotation><para>Where census indicated supervisory districts unequal as to population, mandatory duty was imposed upon board of supervisors to redistrict county. State ex rel. Rowe v. Emanuel, 142 Neb. 583, 7 N.W.2d 156 (1942).</para><para>After election adopting township organization, the county judge, county clerk, and county treasurer must divide the county into supervisor districts under rules in this section, but redistricting when required must be done under same rules by the county board. Obermiller v. Siegel, 340 F.Supp. 208 (D. Neb. 1972).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>