<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="23-114.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-114.03</statuteno><catchline>Zoning regulations; purpose; districts.</catchline>
<para>Zoning regulations shall be adopted or amended by the county board only
after the adoption of the county comprehensive development plan by the county
board and the receipt of the planning commission's specific recommendations. Such zoning regulations shall be consistent
with an adopted comprehensive development plan and designed for the purpose
of promoting the health, safety, morals, convenience, order, prosperity, and
welfare of the present and future inhabitants of Nebraska, including, among
others, such specific purposes as:</para>
<para>(1) Developing both urban and nonurban areas;</para>
<para>(2) Lessening congestion in the streets or roads;</para>
<para>(3) Reducing the waste of excessive amounts of roads;</para>
<para>(4) Securing safety from fire and other dangers;</para>
<para>(5) Lessening or avoiding the hazards to persons and damage to property
resulting from the accumulation or runoff of storm or flood waters;</para>
<para>(6) Providing adequate light and air;</para>
<para>(7) Preventing excessive concentration of population and excessive and
wasteful scattering of population or settlement;</para>
<para>(8) Promoting such distribution of population, such classification of
land uses, and such distribution of land development as will assure adequate
provisions for transportation, water flowage, water supply, drainage, sanitation,
recreation, soil fertility, food supply, and other public requirements;</para>
<para>(9) Protecting the tax base;</para>
<para>(10) Protecting property against blight and depreciation;</para>
<para>(11) Securing economy in governmental expenditures;</para>
<para>(12) Fostering the state's agriculture, recreation, and other industries;</para>
<para>(13) Encouraging the most appropriate use of land in the county; and</para>
<para>(14) Preserving, protecting, and enhancing historic buildings, places,
and districts.</para>
<para>Within the area of jurisdiction and powers established by section 23-114,
the county board may divide the county into districts of such number, shape,
and area as may be best suited to carry out the purposes of this section and
regulate, restrict, or prohibit the erection, construction, reconstruction,
alteration, or use of nonfarm buildings or structures and the use, conditions
of use, or occupancy of land. All such regulations shall be uniform for each
class or kind of land or buildings throughout each district, but the regulations
in one district may differ from those in other districts. An official map
or maps indicating the districts and regulations shall be adopted, and within
fifteen days after adoption of such regulations or maps, they shall be published
in book or pamphlet form or once in a legal newspaper published in and of
general circulation in the county or, if none is published in the county,
in a legal newspaper of general circulation in the county. Such regulations
shall also be spread in the minutes of the proceedings of the county board
and such map or maps filed with the county clerk. The county board may decide
whether buildings located on farmsteads used as residences shall be subject
to such county's zoning regulations and permit requirements.</para>
<para>For purposes of this section and section 23-114.04, nonfarm buildings
are all buildings except those buildings utilized for agricultural purposes
on a farmstead of twenty acres or more which produces one thousand dollars
or more of farm products each year.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 117, &#167; 4, p. 368; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 960, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 822, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 366, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB709, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The farm building exemption contained in this section prohibits counties from requiring building permits on buildings utilized for agricultural purposes on a farmstead of 20 acres or more which produces $1,000 or more of farm products per year. Premium Farms v. County of Holt, 263 Neb. 415, 640 N.W.2d 633 (2002).</para><para>An official zoning map or a zoning plan adopted as part of county zoning regulations which incorporate the map by reference must be published in book or pamphlet form or in legal newspaper. Deans v. West, 189 Neb. 518, 203 N.W.2d 504 (1973).</para><para>Under the 1967 act, a county engaged in zoning ought to adopt a comprehensive development plan within a reasonable time. Bagley v. County of Sarpy, 189 Neb. 393, 202 N.W.2d 841 (1972).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>