<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-131"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-131</statuteno><catchline>Warrants; how issued; claims of jurors.</catchline>
<para>(1) Upon the allowance of any claim or account against the county, the
county board shall direct the county clerk to draw a warrant upon the county
treasurer in payment thereof. The warrant shall be signed by the chairperson
of the county board, except as hereinafter provided, and countersigned by
the county clerk. Warrants may also be issued as provided in section 23-1303.
All warrants payable to officers or employees of the county and claims or
accounts allowed in full shall be delivered by the county clerk upon completion
of entries so required in the warrant and distribution records of the officer
in charge of such records. If a claim or account is not allowed in full, the
warrant shall not be delivered to the party until the time for taking an appeal
has expired and, if such appeal be taken, then not until the appeal has been
determined.</para>
<para>(2) Jurors in the district courts shall, immediately upon the completion
of their services, be entitled to a statement under seal from the clerk of
the court wherein their services were rendered, certifying the amount due
them for service as jurors in such court. Upon presentation by a juror of the certified statement to the
county clerk, the county clerk shall immediately issue a warrant upon the
county general fund for the amount due as shown by the certified statement, unless the juror has voluntarily waived
such amount due for service as a juror. Before delivery of the
warrant, the county clerk shall deduct therefrom the amount of any delinquent
personal taxes then due from the juror, except that in a county having a county
comptroller, the county board shall direct the comptroller to draw the warrant,
and the warrant shall be executed as provided in this section, except that
it shall be countersigned and issued by the comptroller. If the county clerk
or the county comptroller is unable to issue the warrant to the jurors because
of insufficient funds, a record of the date of presentation of the certified
statements, together with the names and addresses of the jurors, shall be
made by the county clerk or the county comptroller and the amount due thereon
shall draw interest until there are sufficient funds upon which to draw and
pay the warrants, whereupon each juror shall be immediately notified by registered
letter, return receipt requested, that upon presentation of a certified statement
for juror's fee, a warrant will be drawn therefor with interest, less whatever
delinquent personal taxes are then due from him or her.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 33, p. 365; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 165; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 197; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 961; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 861; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-115; </para><para>Laws 1937, c. 58, &#167; 1, p. 234; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-115; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-131; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 86, &#167; 1, p. 297; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 81, p. 325; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 135, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 38, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 889, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 86, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB865, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Where landowner appealed order opening road, warrant for payment of damages could not properly be issued. Barrett v. Hand, 158 Neb. 273, 63 N.W.2d 185 (1954).</para><para>Delivery of warrant prior to lapse of time for taking taxpayer's appeal, in violation of statute, does not affect taxpayer's right to appeal. Beadle v. Harmon, 130 Neb. 389, 265 N.W. 18 (1936).</para><para>County treasurer cannot pay out public funds in unauthorized manner, take assignment of claim, be reimbursed by county, and thus indirectly liquidate claim against county. Woods v. Brown County, 125 Neb. 256, 249 N.W. 601 (1933).</para><para>Amendment of act in 1907 relating to county comptroller sustained as constitutional. Allan v. Kennard, 81 Neb. 289, 116 N.W. 63 (1908).</para><para>The allowance by the county board of a claim against the county, even though there is no money in the treasury at the time and no tax levy against which a warrant can be drawn, is irregular, but is not in excess of the power given to examine and settle all claims against the county. State ex rel. McDonald v. Farrington, 80 Neb. 628, 114 N.W. 1100 (1908).</para><para>Seal is not always essential if claim is otherwise properly authenticated. Dakota County v. Bartlett, 67 Neb. 62, 93 N.W. 192 (1903).</para><para>Account must be allowed before warrant is drawn. Wilson v. State ex rel. Plasters, 53 Neb. 113, 73 N.W. 456 (1897).</para><para>Treasurer should not register until after ten days. Means v. Webster, 23 Neb. 432, 36 N.W. 809 (1888).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>