<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-135"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-135</statuteno><catchline>Claims; time of filing; approval of certain purchases; procedure; payment in advance of services; authorized; disallowance of claim; notice; appeal.</catchline><para>(1) All claims against a county shall be filed with the county clerk within ninety days from the time when any materials or labor, which form the basis of the claims, have been furnished or performed, except that (a) the fees of jurors serving in the district courts shall be paid as provided for in section 23-131, (b) payment may be approved as provided in subsection (2) of this section, and (c) payments may be made as provided in subsection (3) of this section. The county board may authorize procedures whereby claims may be filed electronically. The electronic filing shall include the following: Information with respect to the person filing the claim, the basis of the claim, the amount of the claim, the date of the claim, and any other information the county board may require. The county clerk shall keep records of each electronic claim. The records shall be accessible for public viewing in either electronic or printed format.</para><para>(2) A county board may by resolution, which resolution constitutes a claim pursuant to subsection (1) of section 23-1303, approve the payment for a particular piece of personal property prior to the receipt of such property by the county. A county board may by resolution approve the payment for a particular piece of real or personal property at the auction at which such property is sold if the resolution states the maximum amount which the county may bid for the particular piece of real or personal property.</para><para>(3) The county board may pay in advance of services being rendered if it is pursuant to a contract entered into with the state. Such contract shall meet the requirements of the Interlocal Cooperation Act.</para><para>(4) When the claim of any person against the county is disallowed in whole or in part by the county board, such person may appeal from the decision of the board to the district court of such county by causing a written notice to be served on the county clerk within twenty days after making such decision and executing a bond to such county, with sufficient security, to be approved by the county clerk, conditioned for the faithful prosecution of such appeal and the payment of all costs that shall be adjudged against the appellant. Upon the disallowance of any claim, the county clerk shall notify the claimant, his or her agent, or his or her attorney in writing of the fact within five days after such disallowance. Notice mailed within such time shall be deemed sufficient. In a county with a county comptroller, all claims shall be filed with the comptroller and not with the county clerk. The comptroller shall keep records of each electronic claim. The records shall be accessible for public viewing in either electronic or printed format. When an appeal is taken, it shall be the duty of the county clerk to immediately notify the county comptroller of such appeal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 37, p. 366; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 37, &#167; 1, p. 211; </para><para>Laws 1907, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 165; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 198; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 965; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 865; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-119; </para><para>Laws 1935, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 176; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-119; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-135; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 59, &#167; 1, p. 276; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 828, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 86, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 331, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For tort claims against county,</emphasis> see the Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act, section 13-901.</para><para><emphasis>Interlocal Cooperation Act,</emphasis> see section 13-801.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. What are claims</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Filing</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Auditing</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Allowance</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Appeal</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>6. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. What are claims</emphasis></para><para>Under the provisions of this section, the Legislature has expressly waived the counties' sovereign immunity with respect to contractual disputes. This section does not apply where the county is not required to make a determination of facts based upon the evidence. Hoiengs v. County of Adams, 245 Neb. 877, 516 N.W.2d 223 (1994).</para><para>Any action at law against a county for payment for services or labor which arises out of a contractual relationship is subject to the county claims statute, and any petition stating such a claim but failing to allege compliance with the statutory requirements of this section is demurrable. Jackson v. County of Douglas, 223 Neb. 65, 388 N.W.2d 64 (1986).</para><para>This section applies to all claims arising from or out of a contract, and a petition which is subject to its provisions is demurrable unless it shows on its face that the claim was filed with the county clerk within the statutory time. Zeller Sand &amp; Gravel v. Butler Co., 222 Neb. 847, 388 N.W.2d 62 (1986).</para><para>Reimbursement of taxes paid for void tax sale certificate is a claim. Farm Investment Co. v. Scotts Bluff County, 125 Neb. 582, 251 N.W. 115 (1933).</para><para>Section refers only to claim originating in contract. Douglas County v. Taylor, 50 Neb. 535, 70 N.W. 27 (1897).</para><para>Section does not apply to demands arising upon torts. Hollingsworth v. Saunders County, 36 Neb. 141, 54 N.W. 79 (1893).</para><para>Costs of redeeming land, wrongfully sold for taxes, is proper claim. Fuller v. Colfax County, 33 Neb. 716, 50 N.W. 1044 (1892).</para><para>Taxes paid under protest may form basis of claim. Richardson County v. Hull, 28 Neb. 810, 45 N.W. 53 (1890).</para><para>Expense of redeeming land from wrongful sale for taxes is a claim against the county. Richardson County v. Hull, 24 Neb. 536, 39 N.W. 608 (1888).</para><para><emphasis>2. Filing</emphasis></para><para>The purpose of the filing requirement of this section is to provide the county with full information of the rights asserted against it and enable it to make proper investigation concerning the merits of claims against it and to settle those of merit without the expense of litigation. Olson v. County of Lancaster, 230 Neb. 904, 434 N.W.2d 307 (1989).</para><para>Requirement that claims shall be filed within ninety days applies only to claims ex contractu. McCollough v. County of Douglas, 150 Neb. 389, 34 N.W.2d 654 (1948).</para><para>Requirement for filing within ninety days includes all claims arising ex contractu whether express or implied. Coverdale &amp; Colpitts v. Dakota County, 144 Neb. 166, 12 N.W.2d 764 (1944).</para><para>Provisions as to filing claim and time within which filing must be made are both mandatory. Verges v. County of Morrill, 143 Neb. 173, 9 N.W.2d 221 (1943).</para><para>Amendment of 1935 requiring claims for materials or labor to be filed within ninety days is constitutional. Consolidated Chemical Laboratories v. County of Cass, 141 Neb. 486, 3 N.W.2d 920 (1942).</para><para>Claims must be filed with county clerk, who is also clerk of board of supervisors. Formal pleadings are not necessary in presenting claims. Gibson v. Sherman County, 97 Neb. 79, 149 N.W. 107 (1914).</para><para>Action upon a claim for a tort or unliquidated damages may be commenced by filing a claim with the county board. Wherry v. Pawnee County, 88 Neb. 503, 129 N.W. 1013 (1911).</para><para>Claim is filed when delivered to clerk. State ex rel. Thomas Clock Co. v. Board of County Comrs. of Cass County, 60 Neb. 566, 83 N.W. 733 (1900).</para><para>Claim agreed upon by two counties need not be presented to board before suit. Perkins County v. Keith County, 58 Neb. 323, 78 N.W. 630 (1899).</para><para>Claim for an account against a county cannot be sued upon but must be filed. State ex rel. Clark v. Board of County Comrs. of Buffalo County, 6 Neb. 454 (1877).</para><para>All claims arising ex contractu against a county must be filed with the county clerk within 90 days. Shaul v. Brenner, 10 Neb. App. 732, 637 N.W.2d 362 (2001).</para><para><emphasis>3. Auditing</emphasis></para><para>This section regulates the exercise of the power granted to examine and settle all accounts against the county. State ex rel. McDonald v. Farrington, 80 Neb. 628, 114 N.W. 1100 (1908).</para><para>County board cannot audit claim previous to rendition of service. Wilson v. State ex rel. Plasters, 53 Neb. 113, 73 N.W. 456 (1897).</para><para>Board alone has power to audit claims. Gage County v. Hill, 52 Neb. 444, 72 N.W. 581 (1897); Cuming County v. Thiele, 48 Neb. 888, 67 N.W. 883 (1896); State ex rel. Franklin County v. Vincent, 46 Neb. 408, 65 N.W. 50 (1895); Heald v. Polk County, 46 Neb. 28, 64 N.W. 376 (1895); Sioux County v. Jameson, 43 Neb. 265, 61 N.W. 596 (1895).</para><para>Board cannot audit claim until warrant can be legally drawn therefor. Lancaster County v. State ex rel. Miller, 13 Neb. 523, 14 N.W. 517 (1882).</para><para>Board cannot be compelled by mandamus to audit an account, but may be compelled to act upon it in proper case. State ex rel. Hagberg v. Furnas County, 10 Neb. 361, 6 N.W. 434 (1880).</para><para><emphasis>4. Allowance</emphasis></para><para>County board has exclusive original jurisdiction of claim for attorney's fees for collection of taxes. Strawn v. County of Sarpy, 154 Neb. 844, 49 N.W.2d 677 (1951).</para><para>County board has exclusive original jurisdiction to examine and allow a claim against the county arising out of contract. County of Sarpy v. Gasper, 149 Neb. 51, 30 N.W.2d 67 (1947).</para><para>Failure to verify claim does not deprive county commissioners of jurisdiction to act on claims against county. Beadle v. Harmon, 130 Neb. 389, 265 N.W. 18 (1936).</para><para>Equitable relief may be granted where no notice is given claimants that claim for damages, arising out of location of road, is disallowed. Horner v. Eells, 114 Neb. 210, 206 N.W. 733 (1925).</para><para>County commissioners may pass on claim though same is not in statutory form. Bartlett v. Dahlsten, 104 Neb. 738, 178 N.W. 636 (1920).</para><para>Board acts ministerially where amount is fixed by law. Otoe County v. Stroble, 71 Neb. 415, 98 N.W. 1065 (1904); Crouch v. Pyle, 70 Neb. 60, 96 N.W. 1049 (1903); Mitchell v. Clay County, 69 Neb. 779, 96 N.W. 673 (1903).</para><para>Settlement with county officers is conclusive, except for fraud, mistake, or imposition. Wilcox v. Perkins County, 70 Neb. 139, 97 N.W. 236 (1903).</para><para>Board acts ministerially when adjusting accounts of county officer, but judicially when allowing claims. Chase County v. Kelly, 69 Neb. 426, 95 N.W. 865 (1903); Trites v. Hitchcock County, 53 Neb. 79, 73 N.W. 215 (1897).</para><para>Allowance of claim against "advertising fund" constitutes allowance against general fund. Dakota County v. Bartlett, 67 Neb. 62, 93 N.W. 192 (1903).</para><para>Board acts ministerially upon claim of officer for salary. Gallaher v. City of Lincoln, 63 Neb. 339, 88 N.W. 505 (1901).</para><para>Board acts judicially only on claims they have right to pass upon. Hayes County v. Christner, 61 Neb. 272, 85 N.W. 73 (1901).</para><para>Board has exclusive original jurisdiction. In absence of fraud, payment cannot be enjoined. Board of Comrs. of Dixon County v. Barnes, 13 Neb. 294, 13 N.W. 623 (1882); Brown v. Otoe County, 6 Neb. 111 (1877).</para><para>No formal judgment need be entered in passing on claims. Black v. Saunders County, 8 Neb. 440, 1 N.W. 144 (1879).</para><para><emphasis>5. Appeal</emphasis></para><para>An appeal from a final order of the county civil service commission is a petition in error, not an original breach of contract action against the county; an employee appealing the order is not required to file a claim with the county under this section. Pierce v. Douglas Cty. Civil Serv. Comm., 275 Neb. 722, 748 N.W.2d 660 (2008).</para><para>In order to perfect an appeal to the district court from a county board of equalization, all activities necessary, including the filing of notice of appeal, must be carried out within forty-five days of the adjournment of the board. Knoefler Honey Farms v. County of Sherman, 193 Neb. 95, 225 N.W.2d 855 (1975).</para><para>Method of giving notice of appeal in this particular case from freeholders' board, in a county where by law county clerk is ex officio clerk of the district court, held sufficient. Elson v. Harbert, 190 Neb. 437, 208 N.W.2d 703 (1973).</para><para>Manner of taking appeal under this section was made applicable to appeals from action of freeholders' board involving school districts. Reiber v. Harris, 179 Neb. 582, 139 N.W.2d 353 (1966).</para><para>This section governs manner of appeal from action of county superintendents in reorganization of school districts. Roy v. Bladen School Dist. No. R-31, 165 Neb. 170, 84 N.W.2d 119 (1957).</para><para>Before an appeal can be taken, claim must be disallowed, in whole or in part, by the county board. Verges v. County of Morrill, 143 Neb. 173, 9 N.W.2d 221 (1943).</para><para>Failure to verify petition on appeal is not a jurisdictional defect. Myers v. Hall County, 130 Neb. 13, 263 N.W. 486 (1935).</para><para>Form of notice of appeal is not prescribed by statute, and written notice which causes clerk to make up full transcript is sufficient. State v. Odd Fellows Hall Assn., 123 Neb. 440, 243 N.W. 616 (1932).</para><para>Claimant, party having direct interest, must serve notice within twenty days after the board's decision. Sommerville v. Board of Commissioners of Douglas County, 117 Neb. 507, 221 N.W. 433 (1928).</para><para>Appeal from board of county supervisors' order, allowing claim against county, brings action to district court for trial de novo. Campbell Co. v. Boyd County, 117 Neb. 186, 220 N.W. 240 (1928); Box Butte County v. Noleman, 54 Neb. 239, 74 N.W. 582 (1898).</para><para>Words "recovery by suit" include suits instituted by appeal from action of board on claim. Cass County v. Sarpy County, 83 Neb. 435, 119 N.W. 685 (1909).</para><para>Where funds can be distributed only upon warrants authorized by board, a claim therefor may be filed and an appeal taken. School Dist. No. 30 of Cuming County v. Cuming County, 81 Neb. 606, 116 N.W. 522 (1908).</para><para>Claimant is allowed twenty days from the order of disallowance in which to appeal. Lincoln Township v. Kearney County, 79 Neb. 299, 112 N.W. 608 (1907).</para><para>District court should not try appeal until issues are joined by pleadings. Loup County v. Wirsig, 73 Neb. 505, 103 N.W. 56 (1905); Haskell v. Valley County, 41 Neb. 234, 59 N.W. 680 (1894).</para><para>Appeal bonds. Requisites and validity. Hitchcock County v. Brown, 73 Neb. 254, 102 N.W. 456 (1905); Holmes v. State, 17 Neb. 73, 22 N.W. 232 (1885); Gage County v. Fulton, 16 Neb. 5, 19 N.W. 781 (1884); Stewart v. Carter, 4 Neb. 564 (1876).</para><para>Appeal vacates the decision of board and applies to whole claim. Dakota County v. Borowsky, 67 Neb. 317, 93 N.W. 686 (1903).</para><para>Service of notice of appeal is made when delivered to clerk. Jarvis v. Chase County, 64 Neb. 74, 89 N.W. 624 (1902).</para><para>Jurisdiction of district court is not original. Shepard v. Easterling, 61 Neb. 882, 86 N.W. 941 (1901).</para><para>On appeal to district court, the issues need not be the same as before the board. Sheibley v. Dixon County, 61 Neb. 409, 85 N.W. 399 (1901).</para><para>Appeal brings action to district court for trial de novo. Box Butte County v. Noleman, 54 Neb. 239, 74 N.W. 582 (1898).</para><para>Appeal to Supreme Court; issues to be decided. State ex rel. Thomas Clock Co. v. Board of County Comrs. of Cass County, 53 Neb. 767, 74 N.W. 254 (1898).</para><para>Appeal lies on claim for taxes paid under protest. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. Nemaha County, 50 Neb. 393, 69 N.W. 958 (1897).</para><para>Dismissal of appeal is final adjudication. State ex rel. Marquett, Deweese &amp; Hall v. Baushausen, 49 Neb. 558, 68 N.W. 950 (1896).</para><para>Taxpayer may appeal. Board of Comrs. of Dixon County v. Barnes, 13 Neb. 294, 13 N.W. 623 (1882).</para><para>Appeal is dismissed unless bond is properly approved. Cedar County v. McKinney L. &amp; Inv. Co., 1 Neb. Unof. 411, 95 N.W. 605 (1901).</para><para><emphasis>6. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Where the salary or compensation of a public officer is fixed by statute, no judicial action in that respect is required, and therefore this section is inapplicable. Heinzman v. County of Hall, 213 Neb. 268, 328 N.W.2d 764 (1983).</para><para>Where state and local purposes are commingled, the crucial issue turns upon a determination of whether the controlling purposes are state or local. Counties may be required to pay attorney's fees for one appointed to defend an indigent defendant. Kovarik v. County of Banner, 192 Neb. 816, 224 N.W.2d 761 (1975).</para><para>Claim by defendant county that this statute of limitation applied in this case was not decided because not raised by cross-appeal as required by rules of the Supreme Court. Hays v. County of Douglas, 192 Neb. 580, 223 N.W.2d 143 (1974).</para><para>Cited but not discussed. Clark v. Sweet, 183 Neb. 723, 163 N.W.2d 881 (1969).</para><para>Claim for attorney's fees in tax foreclosure was barred. Strawn v. County of Sarpy, 156 Neb. 797, 58 N.W.2d 168 (1953).</para><para>County treasurer is without authority to liquidate claims against county. Woods v. Brown County, 125 Neb. 256, 249 N.W. 601 (1933).</para><para>Under former law, this section governed the verification of claims against the county. Uttley v. Sievers, 100 Neb. 59, 158 N.W. 373 (1916).</para><para>Claim is not barred until four years from act authorizing county to pay same. Gibson v. Sherman County, 97 Neb. 79, 149 N.W. 107 (1914).</para><para>County attorney has authority to bind county for expenses of suit. Christner v. Hayes County, 79 Neb. 157, 112 N.W. 347 (1907).</para><para>Members of board are liable for warrant drawn without legal authority. Otoe County v. Stroble, 71 Neb. 415, 98 N.W. 1065 (1904).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>