
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id27" statutenumber="23-293"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-293</statuteno><catchline id="id30">Township organization; discontinuance; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) In counties under township organization, a registered voter may file a petition or petitions for submission of the question of the discontinuance of township organization to the registered voters of the county. The petition or petitions shall be signed by registered voters equal in number to five percent of the voters registered in the county at the preceding statewide general election. The petition or petitions shall be filed in the office of the election commissioner or county clerk by September 1 of the year of the general election at which the petitioners wish to have the question submitted for a vote. If such petition or petitions are filed in conformance with this subsection, the question shall be submitted to the registered voters at the next general election held after the filing of the petition or petitions.</para><para>(2) In counties under township organization, the county board may, by a resolution supported by a majority of the county board, submit the question of discontinuance of township organization to the registered voters of the county. If such resolution is filed in the office of the election commissioner or county clerk by September 1 of the year of the general election at which the board wishes to have the question submitted for a vote, the question shall be submitted to the registered voters at the next general election held after the filing of the resolution.</para><para>(3) A petition or county board resolution for discontinuance of township organization shall specify whether the county board of commissioners to be formed pursuant to section 23-151 will have five or seven members and that reorganization as a county board of commissioners will be effective at the expiration of the supervisors' terms of office in January of the third calendar year following the election to discontinue township organization.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 43, &#167; 2, p. 236; </para><para>Laws 1895, c. 29, &#167; 1, p. 154; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1057; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 959; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-273; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-293; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 75, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 422, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB269, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB411, &#167; 26. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>