<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id950"><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-118"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>23-118</statuteno><catchline>Electric generation facility; site selection; contract approval; county board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Immediate family member means a child residing in an official's household, the spouse of an official, or an individual claimed by an official or the official's spouse as a dependent for federal income tax purposes; and</para><para>(b) Official means a member of a county board or a member of a county planning commission.</para><para>(2) When the construction of any new electric generation facility is being considered within a county, prior to project site selection for the facility or approval of any contract by the county related to the facility, the county board shall:</para><para>(a) Conduct a public meeting announcing the proposed project; and</para><para>(b) If any official involved in the selection of such project site or approval of such contract or an immediate family member of such official holds, directly or indirectly, a financial interest in such facility, or in the ownership or lease of the property within the county where such facility will be constructed:</para><para>(i) Publish notice of the official's financial interest and whether such official has indicated his or her intent to vote to select such project site or approve such contract; and</para><para>(ii) Within ninety days after the publication of such notice, hold a public meeting regarding the official's intention to vote to select such project site or approve such contract.</para><para>(3)(a) This section shall not affect the validity of any contract or apply to the ownership or lease of any property existing on March 12, 2024.</para><para>(b) This section shall not affect any conflict-of-interest provisions of the Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB569, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>March 12, 2024</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Political Accountability and Disclosure Act,</emphasis> see section 49-1401.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>