<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id20" statutenumber="23-172"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>23-172</statuteno><catchline id="id23">Standard codes; adoption;
copy on file; area where applicable.</catchline><para>The county board may
adopt by resolution, which shall have the force and effect of law, the conditions,
provisions, limitations, and terms of a building code, a plumbing code, an
electrical code, a fire prevention code, or any other code relating to building
or relating to the erection, construction, reconstruction, alteration, repair,
conversion, maintenance, placing, or using of any building, structure, automobile
trailer, house trailer, or cabin trailer. For this purpose, the county board
may adopt any standard code which contains rules or regulations printed as
a code in book or pamphlet form by reference to such code or portions thereof
without setting forth in the resolution the conditions, provisions, limitations,
or terms of such code. When such code or any such standard code or portion
thereof is incorporated by reference into any resolution, it shall have the
same force and effect as though it has been spread at large in such resolution
without further or additional publication. One copy of such code or such standard
code or portion thereof shall be filed for use and examination by the public
in the office of the clerk of such county prior to its adoption.</para>
<para>If there
is no county resolution adopting a plumbing code in effect for such county,
the 2009 Uniform Plumbing Code accredited by the American National Standards
Institute shall apply to all buildings.</para>
<para>Any code
adopted and approved by the county board, as provided in this section, or
if there is no county resolution adopting a plumbing code in effect for such
county, the 2009 Uniform Plumbing Code accredited by the American National
Standards Institute, and the building permit requirements or occupancy permit
requirements imposed by such code or by sections 23-114.04 and 23-114.05,
shall apply to all of the county except within the limits of any incorporated
city or village and except within an unincorporated area where a city or village
has been granted zoning jurisdiction and is exercising such jurisdiction.</para>
<para>Nothing in
this section shall be interpreted as creating an obligation for the county
to inspect plumbing work done within its jurisdiction to determine compliance
with the plumbing code.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 131, &#167; 19, p. 515; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-159; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-172; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 87, &#167; 6, p. 302; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 57, &#167; 5, p. 241; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 117, &#167; 12, p. 375; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 35, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1304, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB42, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB802, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>