<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-101"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-101</statuteno><catchline>Counties; corporate name.</catchline><para>Each county, established in this state according to the laws thereof, shall be a body politic and corporate, by the name and style of The county of ..............., and by that name may sue and be sued, plead and shall be impleaded, defend and be defended against, in any court having jurisdiction of the subject matter, either in law or equity, or other place where justice shall be administered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 20, p. 359; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 948; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 848; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-101; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-101.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Status of county</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Suit by county</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Suit against county</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Pleadings</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Liability of county</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Status of county</emphasis></para><para>A county is a governmental subdivision of the state, corporate in character, and created and organized for public purposes. Speer v. Kratzenstein, 143 Neb. 310, 12 N.W.2d 360 (1943).</para><para>A county is not a "municipal corporation", as the term is used in section 7, Article VIII, of the Constitution, and imposition of gasoline tax on counties is not prohibited. State v. Cheyenne County, 127 Neb. 619, 256 N.W. 67 (1934).</para><para>A county is a body politic and corporate. Cheney v. County Board of Commissioners of Buffalo County, 123 Neb. 624, 243 N.W. 881 (1932).</para><para>A county, even though a body politic and corporate, is a creature of statute and has only such powers as are conferred by Legislature. Lindburg v. Bennett, 117 Neb. 66, 219 N.W. 851 (1928).</para><para><emphasis>2. Suit by county</emphasis></para><para>County is proper party defendant in suit to enjoin collection of alleged void tax. Offutt Housing Co. v. County of Sarpy, 160 Neb. 320, 70 N.W.2d 382 (1955).</para><para>County's interest in Supreme Court Reports is not sufficient to maintain replevin. Clifford v. Hall County, 60 Neb. 506, 83 N.W. 661 (1900).</para><para><emphasis>3. Suit against county</emphasis></para><para>A county must be sued in the name designated by statute. Jameson v. Plischke, 184 Neb. 97, 165 N.W.2d 373 (1969).</para><para>Suit was brought where no warrant was issued. Strong v. Thurston County, 84 Neb. 86, 120 N.W. 922 (1909).</para><para>Action to recover a money judgment upon county warrant may be maintained when the money for payment of such warrant has been collected and wrongfully applied by the county authorities. Thurston County v. McIntyre, 75 Neb. 335, 106 N.W. 217 (1905).</para><para>Suit authorized where board has not exclusive jurisdiction. Ayres v. Thurston County, 63 Neb. 96, 88 N.W. 178 (1901).</para><para><emphasis>4. Pleadings</emphasis></para><para>Demurrer is not proper pleading to raise question of authority when suing. Otoe County v. Dorman, 71 Neb. 408, 98 N.W. 1064 (1904).</para><para><emphasis>5. Liability of county</emphasis></para><para>County is not liable for negligent acts of officers unless made so by statute. Hopper v. Douglas County, 75 Neb. 329, 106 N.W. 330 (1905).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>