<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id6" statutenumber="23-148"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>23-148</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Commissioners; number; election; when authorized.</catchline><para>The county board of commissioners in all counties having not more than three hundred thousand inhabitants shall consist of three persons except as follows:</para><para>(1) The registered voters in any county containing not more than three hundred thousand inhabitants may vote at any general election as to whether their county board shall consist of three or five commissioners. Upon the completion of the canvass by the county canvassing board, the proposition shall be decided and, if the number of commissioners is increased from three to five commissioners, vacancies shall be deemed to exist and the procedures set forth in sections 32-567 and 32-574 shall be instituted; and</para><para>(2) The registered voters of any county under township organization voting to discontinue township organization may also vote as to the number of county commissioners as provided in sections 23-292 to 23-299.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 53, p. 369; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 29, &#167; 1, p. 359; </para><para>Laws 1891, c. 21, &#167; 1, p. 225; </para><para>Laws 1903, c. 30, &#167; 1, p. 277; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 978; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 16, &#167; 1, p. 77; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 69, &#167; 1, p. 182; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 878; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-132; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-148; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 42, &#167; 1, p. 202; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 62, &#167; 2, p. 197; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 48, &#167; 1, p. 165; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 60, &#167; 1, p. 278; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 331, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 53, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 789, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 534; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB269, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB575, &#167; 3. </para><operativedate>August 30, 2015</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For discontinuance of township organization,</emphasis> see sections 23-292 to 23-299.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Increase in number of commissioner districts requires redistricting. Ludwig v. Board of County Commissioners of Sarpy County, 170 Neb. 600, 103 N.W.2d 838 (1960).</para><para>Removal of county commissioner out of district, where he continues to act, does not render void any order of county board in which he participates. Horton v. Howard, 97 Neb. 575, 150 N.W. 633 (1915).</para><para>Member of board must reside in district from which elected and office becomes vacant when he removes. State ex rel. Malloy v. Skirving, 19 Neb. 497, 27 N.W. 723 (1886).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>