<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-164"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-164</statuteno><catchline>Adjacent territory; regulation; hearings; notice by publication; written notice to chairperson of planning commission.</catchline><para>The county board shall provide for the manner in which such regulations and restrictions and the boundaries of such districts shall be determined, established, enforced, and, from time to time, amended, supplemented, or changed. No such regulation, restriction, or boundary shall become effective until after public hearings are held by both the county planning commission and county board in relation thereto, when its parties in interest and citizens shall have an opportunity to be heard. Notice of the time and place of such hearing shall be given by the publication thereof in a legal newspaper of general circulation in such county one time at least ten days prior to such hearing. Notice of the time and place of such hearing shall also be given in writing to the chairperson of any municipal, county, or joint planning commission in the State of Nebraska which has jurisdiction over land within three miles of the property affected by such action. In the absence of a planning commission, such notice shall be given to the clerks of units of local government in the State of Nebraska having jurisdiction over land within three miles of the property affected by such action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 131, &#167; 12, p. 511; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-152; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-164; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 410, &#167; 25; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 299, &#167; 17. </para></source><annotation><para>Timely objection by a litigant with standing may nullify a rezoning resolution by a county board that has not adopted a comprehensive development plan conformable to statute. Bagley v. County of Sarpy, 189 Neb. 393, 202 N.W.2d 841 (1972).</para><para>Board's only statutory power being to grant zoning variances resolution purporting to grant exemption construed to grant variance and action presumed correct until changed by court, and requirement of immediate compliance proper. Adler v. Lynch, 415 F.Supp. 705 (D. Neb. 1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>