<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-303</statuteno><catchline>County resurvey; cost; tax; bonds; submission to voters.</catchline><para>In case the question of said resurvey has been submitted to the voters of the entire county, the cost of said resurvey may be paid out of the county general fund in case there is money there available for that purpose. If not, the cost may be provided for by an issue of bonds or special tax levy, in which case the proposition for bonds or special tax levy shall be submitted to the voters as a part of the resurvey proposition; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> when a proposition for resurvey has already been submitted to the voters of a county, and a majority have voted in favor of such proposition, it shall be legal for the county board to proceed to make contract for such resurvey in accordance with the provisions of sections 23-301 to 23-303 providing for such contract; <emphasis type="italic">provided further,</emphasis> in case the question has been submitted to the voters of any one or more governmental townships of any county under the provisions of section 23-301, and a majority have voted in favor of such proposition, the cost of said resurvey may be paid out of the general fund and said fund may be reimbursed the amount of such expenditure by the assessment of a special tax by the county board of such county equally apportioning the cost of such resurvey upon the area of all real estate in such governmental township or townships according to the acreage in each tract as shown by the original United States survey thereof, and including in addition thereto any accreted lands to such original United States survey as may be shown by the resurvey herein provided.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1909, c. 36, &#167; 3, p. 221; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 153, &#167; 1, p. 392; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1110; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1044; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-738; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-303.</para></source></law></legaldoc>