<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-109"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-109</statuteno><catchline>Claims; audit; settlement; imprest system of accounting.</catchline><para>(1) The county board shall have power to examine and settle all accounts against the county and all accounts concerning the receipts and expenditures of the county.</para><para>(2) The county board may adopt by resolution an imprest system of accounting for the county and authorize the county clerk to establish an imprest vendor, payroll, or other account for the payment of county warrants in accordance with any guidelines issued by the Auditor of Public Accounts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 23, p. 360; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 26, &#167; 1, p. 351; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 44, &#167; 1, p. 288; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 952; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 74; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 852; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 93, &#167; 1, p. 274; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 60, &#167; 2, p. 232; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 40, &#167; 1, p. 135; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 36, &#167; 1, p. 237; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 5, p. 145; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 48, &#167; 2, p. 236; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-105; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 1(5), p. 225; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-109; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 34, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Even though county board acts ministerially in allowing claim, it has authority to deduct unpaid personal taxes. State ex rel. Bates v. Morgan, 154 Neb. 234, 47 N.W.2d 512 (1951).</para><para>Board may audit and settle claims when work is completed though no warrant may issue until after levy has been made. Central Bridge &amp; Construction Co. v. Saunders County, 106 Neb. 484, 184 N.W. 220 (1921).</para><para>Claims for tort or for unliquidated damages may be filed with county board. Wherry v. Pawnee County, 88 Neb. 503, 129 N.W. 1013 (1911).</para><para>County boards are given power to examine and settle all accounts against the county. Cass County v. Sarpy County, 83 Neb. 435, 119 N.W. 685 (1909).</para><para>Allowance of claims when no money is in treasury or tax levy made does not exceed powers. State ex rel. McDonald v. Farrington, 80 Neb. 628, 114 N.W. 1100 (1908).</para><para>Power to act upon claims is derived from this section. State ex rel. Thomas Clock Co. v. Board of County Comrs. of Cass County, 60 Neb. 566, 83 N.W. 733 (1900).</para><para>Order disallowing claims, reconsidered, is not an adjudication. Dean v. Saunders County, 55 Neb. 759, 76 N.W. 450 (1898).</para><para>Board acts judicially in allowance of claims. Heald v. Polk County, 46 Neb. 28, 64 N.W. 376 (1895).</para><para>Board may disallow claims. Boone County v. Armstrong, 23 Neb. 764, 37 N.W. 626 (1888).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>