<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-107.01" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>23-107.01</statuteno><catchline>Real estate owned by county; sale or lease; terms and procedures.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section and section 80-329, any county board has power to sell or lease real estate owned by the county and not required for county purposes at a fair market value regardless of the value of the property. The county board of such county shall hold an open and public hearing prior to any such sale or lease at which any interested party may appear and speak for or against the sale or lease and raise any issue regarding the fair market value of the property as determined by the county board. Public notice of any such public hearing shall be run once each week for two consecutive weeks prior to the hearing date in any newspaper or legal publication distributed generally throughout the county.</para><para>(b) The county board shall set a date of sale which shall be within two months of the date of public hearing pursuant to subdivision (1)(a) of this section and shall offer such real estate for sale or lease to the highest bidder.</para><para>(c) The county board shall cause to be printed and published once at least ten days prior to the sale or lease in a legal newspaper in the county an advertisement for bids on the property to be sold or leased. The advertisement shall state the legal description and address of the real estate and that the real estate shall be sold or leased to the highest bidder.</para><para>(d) If the county board receives no bids or if the bids received are substantially lower than the fair market value, the county board may negotiate a contract for sale or lease of the real estate if such negotiated contract is in the best interests of the county.</para><para>(2) A county board may, by majority vote, sell real estate owned by the county in fee simple to another political subdivision in fee simple in such manner and upon such terms and conditions as may be deemed in the best interest of the county. A county board shall cause to be printed and published at least thirty days prior to the sale in a legal newspaper in the county a notice of the intent to sell county real estate to another political subdivision. The notice shall state the legal description and address of the real estate to be sold.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1975, LB 125, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 805, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 93; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 184, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 396, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB525, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>