<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-104</statuteno><catchline>Powers.</catchline><para>Each county shall have power: (1) To purchase and hold the real and personal estate necessary for the use of the county; (2) to purchase, lease, lease with option to buy, acquire by gift or devise, and hold for the benefit of the county real estate sold by virtue of judicial proceedings in which the county is plaintiff or is interested; (3) to hold all real estate conveyed by general warranty deed to trustees in which the county is the beneficiary, whether the real estate is situated in the county so interested or in some other county or counties of the state; (4) to sell, convey, exchange, or lease any real or personal estate owned by the county in such manner and upon such terms and conditions as may be deemed in the best interest of the county; (5) to enter into compacts with other counties to exercise and carry out powers possessed by or conferred by law upon each county separately; and (6) to make all contracts and to do all other acts in relation to the property and concerns of the county necessary to the exercise of its corporate powers, except that no lease agreement for the rental of equipment shall be entered into if the consideration for all lease agreements for the fiscal year exceeds one-tenth of one percent of the total taxable value of the taxable property of the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 22, p. 359; </para><para>Laws 1889, c. 61, &#167; 1, p. 491; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 951; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 851; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-104; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-104; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 48, &#167; 2, p. 174; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 109, &#167; 1, p. 437; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 116, &#167; 1, p. 364; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 92; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 13. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Powers authorized</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Powers not authorized</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Powers authorized</emphasis></para><para>A county, through its county board, has authority to contract with the state Auditor of Public Accounts to achieve a county audit required by section 23-1608. County of York v. Johnson, 230 Neb. 403, 432 N.W.2d 215 (1988).</para><para>Unless otherwise provided for by law, county boards have implied power to employ agents or servants required for county purposes. Thiles v. County Board of Sarpy County, 189 Neb. 1, 200 N.W.2d 13 (1972).</para><para>Purchase by commissioners of electric refrigerator for county jail is proper exercise of power. Beadle v. Harmon, 130 Neb. 389, 265 N.W. 18 (1936).</para><para>County board's lease for ninety-nine years of county's real estate, not used or needed for actual purposes, is valid. Lindburg v. Bennett, 117 Neb. 66, 219 N.W. 851 (1928).</para><para>County board is clothed not only with powers expressly conferred upon them by statute, but also with such powers as are requisite to enable them to discharge official duties devolved upon them by law. Wherry v. Pawnee County, 88 Neb. 503, 129 N.W. 1013 (1911).</para><para>County board has the power to pay traveling expenses of county attorney incurred in prosecuting criminal offenses. Berryman v. Schalander, 85 Neb. 281, 122 N.W. 990 (1909).</para><para>Unless prohibited by statute, county may sue to enforce all contracts. Johnson County v. Chamberlain Banking House, 74 Neb. 549, 104 N.W. 1061 (1905).</para><para><emphasis>2. Powers not authorized</emphasis></para><para>Selling of crushed rock produced by county to general public was not authorized. State ex rel. Johnson v. County of Gage, 154 Neb. 822, 49 N.W.2d 672 (1951).</para><para>Counties are not permitted to indulge in real estate business on competitive basis. City of Grand Island v. Willis, 142 Neb. 686, 7 N.W.2d 457 (1943).</para><para>Counties are without power to contract with townships to construct and maintain township roads for an agreed consideration. Lynn v. Kearney County, 121 Neb. 122, 236 N.W. 192 (1931).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The board of county commissioners could not create a contractual obligation of the county through ratification when a majority of the commissioners did not know of the representations being made. Christiansen v. County of Douglas, 288 Neb. 564, 849 N.W.2d 493 (2014).</para><para>Contract "concerns" county which relates or belongs to county, its business or affairs. Speer v. Kratzenstein, 143 Neb. 310, 12 N.W.2d 360 (1943).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>