<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-325"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-325</statuteno><catchline>Real estate; appropriation; power of county board; procedure.</catchline><para>The county board shall have power to acquire, take, hold, appropriate, and condemn such real estate as may be necessary for convenience from time to time for the public use of the county; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> no appropriation of private property for the use of the county as aforesaid shall be made until full and just compensation therefor shall have been first made to the owner thereof. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1927, c. 56, &#167; 1, p. 211; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-709; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-325; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 69, p. 478. </para></source><annotation><para>In condemnation proceedings Department of Roads and Irrigation follows procedural requirements set out herein. Hoesly v. Department of Roads &amp; Irrigation, 142 Neb. 383, 6 N.W.2d 365 (1942).</para><para>Word "owner" in statute includes mortgagee and mortgagee is necessary party in action to condemn realty for public use under right of eminent domain. Northwestern Mutual Life Ins. Co. v. Nordhues, 129 Neb. 379, 261 N.W. 687 (1935).</para><para>Former act declared unconstitutional for failure to provide notice to landowners of steps on appraisement of damages. Sheridan County v. Hand, 114 Neb. 813, 210 N.W. 273 (1926).</para><para>Trial in condemnation proceedings may be had in name of person as plaintiff who owned land condemned at time proceedings were commenced. In such case, court should order payment of judgment to party entitled to damages. Sternberger v. Sanitary District No. 1 of Lancaster County, 100 Neb. 449, 160 N.W. 740 (1916).</para><para>Right of eminent domain is exercised only for public benefit. State v. Boone County, 78 Neb. 271, 110 N.W. 629 (1907).</para><para>County authorities will be discharged from liability upon making compensation to person, apparently sole owner. Cedar County v. Lammers, 73 Neb. 744, 103 N.W. 433 (1905).</para><para>County cannot be enjoined from acts necessary to improve road. Churchill v. Bethe, 48 Neb. 87, 66 N.W. 992 (1896).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>