<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-362"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-362</statuteno><catchline>Indians; support; state aid to counties;
purpose; conditions; audit; certificate of county assessor; alcohol-related
programs; participation by county board.</catchline><para>In order to equitably
distribute the added burden of law enforcement imposed upon certain counties
of this state by reason of the passage of Public Law 280 of the Eighty-third
Congress dealing with state jurisdiction and the resulting withdrawal of federal
law enforcement in such counties, there shall each fiscal year be paid out
of the state treasury, on the warrant of the Director of Administrative Services
as directed by the chairperson of the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement
and Criminal Justice, not to exceed one hundred one thousand dollars for the
benefit of Indians in any county which has land held in trust by the United
States Government for the benefit of Indians to be used for purposes of law
enforcement and jail operations. Such funds shall be divided as equally as
possible between the areas of law enforcement and jail operations. The Auditor
of Public Accounts or his or her designee shall conduct, at such time as he
or she determines necessary, an audit of the funds distributed pursuant to
this section. A detailed report shall be submitted on December 31 of each
year, including discussion of the operation and expenditures of the office
of the county sheriff and, when completed, a copy of the audit, to the Executive
Board of the Legislative Council and the Governor. The report submitted to the executive board shall be submitted
electronically. Such payment shall be made to any county of this
state meeting the following conditions:</para>
<para>(1) Such county shall have on file in the office of the Nebraska Commission
on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice a certificate of the county assessor
that there are within such county over twenty-five hundred acres of land held
in trust by the United States or subject to restriction against alienation
imposed by the United States; and</para>
<para>(2) The county board of each such county may participate in alcohol-related
programs with nonprofit corporations.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 69, &#167; 1, p. 293; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 91, &#167; 1, p. 315; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 123, &#167; 1, p. 397; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 161, &#167; 1, p. 735; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 131, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 871, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 584, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 607, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 263, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1001, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB337, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB782, &#167; 22.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>