<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-165"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-165</statuteno><catchline>Adjacent territory; regulation; amendments; objections; hearings.</catchline><para>Such regulations, restrictions, and boundaries may from time to time be amended, supplemented, changed, modified, or repealed. In case, however, of a protest against such change, signed by the owners of twenty percent or more either of the area of the lots included in such proposed change, or of those immediately adjacent in the rear thereof extending one hundred feet therefrom, or to those directly opposite thereto extending one hundred feet from the street frontage of such opposite lots, and such change is not in accordance with the comprehensive development plan, such amendments shall not become effective except by the favorable vote of two-thirds majority of the county board. The provisions of section 23-164 relative to public hearings and official notice shall apply equally to all changes or amendments.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1941, c. 131, &#167; 13, p. 511; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-153; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-165; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 161, &#167; 11. </para></source><annotation><para>Timely objection by a litigant with standing may nullify a rezoning resolution by a county board that has not adopted a comprehensive development plan conformable to statute. Bagley v. County of Sarpy, 189 Neb. 393, 202 N.W.2d 841 (1972).</para><para>Board's only statutory power being to grant zoning variances resolution purporting to grant exemption construed to grant variance and action presumed correct until changed by court, and requirement of immediate compliance proper. Adler v. Lynch, 415 F.Supp. 705 (D. Neb. 1976).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>