<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1203"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1203</statuteno><catchline>Opinions; civil cases; additional counsel; compensation.</catchline><para>The county attorney shall without fee or reward give opinions and advice to the board of county commissioners and other civil officers of their respective counties, when requested so to do by such board or officers, upon all matters in which the state or county is interested, or relating to the duty of the board or officers in which the state or county may have an interest; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> in all counties of this state the county board may employ such additional counsel in civil matters as it may deem necessary. Such attorney or attorneys shall counsel the board or county officers on such civil matters as the board may lay before him or them, and shall prosecute or defend, on behalf of the county or any of its officers, such civil actions or proceedings as the interests of the county may in their judgment require, and shall receive such reasonable compensation in each case as the board and such counsel may agree upon.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 40, &#167; 4, p. 217; </para><para>Laws 1895, c. 7, &#167; 1, p. 73; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5598; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4915; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-903; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1203; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 88, &#167; 1, p. 397. </para></source><annotation><para>Special attorneys to conduct tax foreclosure cases were employed pursuant to this section. Strawn v. County of Sarpy, 146 Neb. 783, 21 N.W.2d 597 (1946).</para><para>County board may hire attorney to collect judgment on contingent fee basis. Miles v. Cheyenne County, 96 Neb. 703, 148 N.W. 959 (1914).</para><para>County is not liable for services rendered on request of county attorney unless authorized or ratified by board. Card v. Dawes County, 71 Neb. 788, 99 N.W. 662 (1904).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>