<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-1201.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1201.01</statuteno><catchline>County attorney; residency; appointment of nonresident attorney, when; contract.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, a qualified person need not be a resident of the county when he or she files for election as county attorney, but if elected as county attorney, such person shall reside in a county for which he or she holds office, except that a county attorney serving in a county which does not have a city of the metropolitan, primary, or first class may reside in an adjoining Nebraska county.</para><para>(2) If there is no county attorney elected pursuant to section 32-522 or if a vacancy occurs for any other reason, the county board of such county may appoint a qualified attorney from any Nebraska county to the office of county attorney. In making such appointment, the county board shall negotiate a contract with the attorney, such contract to specify the terms and conditions of the appointment, including the compensation of the attorney, which compensation shall not be subject to sections 23-1114.02 to 23-1114.06.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 60, &#167; 1, p. 234; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1201.01; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 109, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 812, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 468, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 541; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 669, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 84, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>Failure by a county attorney to reside in the county he or she holds office is not official misconduct. Residing in the county where one holds office as county attorney is not an official duty. Hynes v. Hogan, 251 Neb. 404, 558 N.W.2d 35 (1997).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>