<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id17">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id19" statutenumber="23-1213"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id21">23-1213</statuteno><catchline id="id22">Nebraska County Attorney Standards Advisory Council;
created; members; qualifications; appointment; terms; vacancy.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) There
is hereby created the Nebraska County Attorney Standards Advisory Council
which, except as provided in
subdivision (b) of this subsection, shall consist of seven members,
four of whom shall be either a county attorney or deputy county attorney,
one member being a professor of law or
professor of forensic science, and two members being county commissioners
or supervisors. The members of such council shall be appointed by the Governor.
Of the county attorneys or deputy county attorneys appointed to such council,
one shall be from Douglas County, one shall be from Lancaster County, and
the remaining two shall be appointed from the remainder of the state. Members
of the council shall serve a term of four years, except that of the members
first appointed one member shall serve a term of one year, two members shall
serve a term of two years, two members shall serve a term of three years,
and two members shall each serve a term of four years.</para>
<para>(b) On and after August 30, 2009, the
council shall consist of eleven members with the addition of the following
four new members: (i) Two members who shall be either county attorneys or
deputy county attorneys from counties other than Douglas County or Lancaster
County; (ii) one member who is a county sheriff or a chief of police; and
(iii) one member who is a certified forensic pathologist. The new members
shall serve terms of four years, except that of the new members first appointed
two members shall serve terms of two years and two members shall serve terms
of three years.</para>
<para>(2) A member may be reappointed
at the expiration of his or her term. Any vacancy occurring other than by
expiration of a term shall be filled for the remainder of the unexpired term
in the same manner as the original appointment. The council shall select one
of its members as chairperson. The Governor shall make the appointments under
this section within ninety days of July 19, 1980.</para>
<para>(3) Members
of the council shall have such membership terminated if they cease to hold
the office of county attorney, deputy county attorney, county commissioner or supervisor, or county sheriff or chief of police.
A member of the council may be removed from the council for good cause upon
written notice and upon an opportunity to be heard before the Governor. After
the hearing, the Governor shall file in the office of the Secretary of State
a complete statement of the charges and the findings and disposition together
with a complete record of the proceedings.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 790, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB671, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>