<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-1719"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1719</statuteno><catchline>Sheriff; deputy; uniform; specifications.</catchline><para>(1) The uniform required by section 23-1717 shall be readily distinguishable from the uniform of other law enforcement agencies in the State of Nebraska and shall consist of:</para><para>(a) Brown felt hat, center crease in sheriff or western style;</para><para>(b) Brown straw hat, center crease in sheriff or western style;</para><para>(c) Chocolate brown color shirt with either long or short sleeves depending on season;</para><para>(d) Pink tan color trousers in appropriate seasonal weights;</para><para>(e) Pink tan color skirts in appropriate seasonal weights;</para><para>(f) Pink tan color necktie;</para><para>(g) Shoes or boots in the same color as the leather worn;</para><para>(h) Chocolate brown color service jacket, zipper front with badge holder;</para><para>(i) Hip-length year-round outer jacket, dark brown in color;</para><para>(j) Badge bearing state or state seal, rank, and county:</para><para>(i) Gold in color for sheriff and deputies of the rank of sergeant or above;</para><para>(ii) Silver in color for deputies under the rank of sergeant; and</para><para>(iii) Consisting of seven-point star;</para><para>(k) Collar ornaments:</para><para>(i) Gold for sheriff and deputies of the rank of sergeant or above; and</para><para>(ii) Silver for deputies under the rank of sergeant;</para><para>(l) Shoulder emblem to be worn on upper sleeve and include sheriff's department and county name - design optional;</para><para>(m) Leather to be either brown or black at the individual department's choice; and</para><para>(n) Brown winter cap with flap.</para><para>(2) Uniforms shall be purchased directly from the supplier or suppliers with whom the Department of Administrative Services has contracted.</para><para>(3) A committee from the Nebraska Sheriffs' and Peace Officers' Association shall assist the Department of Administrative Services in developing specifications and selecting material for the uniforms.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1967, c. 113, &#167; 3, p. 361; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 186, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>