<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-1210"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1210</statuteno><catchline>Coroner; duties; county attorney shall perform; expenses; delegation of duties.</catchline><para>(1) The county attorney shall perform all of the duties enjoined by law upon the county coroner and the county attorney shall be the ex officio county coroner. The county attorney shall receive no additional fees for the performance of duties prescribed by statutes for county coroner but shall be reimbursed for all actual necessary expenses incurred by him or her in the performance of such duties with reimbursement for mileage to be made at the rate provided in section 81-1176.</para><para>(2) The county attorney may delegate to the county sheriff, deputy county sheriff, or any other peace officer that part of the coroner's duties as now prescribed by statute which relates to viewing dead bodies and serving papers, except that in cases when there may be occasion to serve papers upon the sheriff, the county attorney may delegate such duty to the county clerk.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 224, &#167; 1, p. 493; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4922; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-910; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 96, &#167; 3, p. 384; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-910; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1210; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 70, &#167; 2, p. 295; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 204, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 313, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1011, &#167; 10. </para></source><annotation><para>Section is constitutional. Effect is to incorporate in new law the existing laws defining the duties of coroner. State ex rel. Crosby v. Moorhead, 100 Neb. 298, 159 N.W. 412 (1916).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>