<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1602" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1602</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Warrants; nonpayment for want of funds; endorsement; interest.</catchline><para id="id00">All warrants issued by the county board shall, upon being presented for payment, if there are not sufficient funds in the treasury to pay the same, be endorsed by the county treasurer not paid for want of funds, and the county treasurer shall also endorse thereon the date of such presentation and sign his or her name thereto. Warrants so endorsed shall draw interest from the date of such endorsement, at the rate to be fixed by the county board at the time of issuance and inserted in the warrant. No account or claim whatsoever against a county, which has been allowed by the county board, shall draw interest until a warrant has been drawn in payment thereof and endorsed as provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 92, p. 379; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5638; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4965; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-1302; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1602; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 171, &#167; 1, p. 518; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 87, p. 329; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB786, &#167; 5. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2018</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>County is not liable for interest prior to judgment on claim to recover invalid special assessment. McClary v. County of Dodge, 176 Neb. 627, 126 N.W.2d 849 (1964).</para><para>County treasurer undertaking to pay unallowed salary claims against county from sinking fund without warrant cannot take assignments of claims and thereafter recover thereon as valid obligation of county unless sinking funds are reimbursed prior thereto. Woods v. Brown County, 125 Neb. 256, 249 N.W. 601 (1933).</para><para>Interest cannot be allowed against county unless so provided by statute or by a contract therefor lawfully made. Central Bridge &amp; Construction Co. v. Saunders County, 106 Neb. 484, 184 N.W. 220 (1921).</para><para>Interest may be allowed against county in favor of state for money wrongfully withheld by county. State v. Stanton County, 100 Neb. 747, 161 N.W. 264 (1917).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>