<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1732"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1732</statuteno><catchline>Deputy sheriffs in active employment; examinations; when required.</catchline><para>(1) All deputy sheriffs in active employment on January 1, 1970, in counties of three hundred thousand inhabitants or more and on January 1, 1973, in counties having a population of more than one hundred fifty thousand but less than three hundred thousand inhabitants, and who have been such for more than two years immediately prior thereto, shall hold their positions without examinations until discharged, reduced, promoted, or transferred in accordance with sections 23-1721 to 23-1736.</para><para>(2) All deputy sheriffs in active employment on January 1, 1975, in counties having a population of more than sixty thousand but not more than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants, and who have been deputy sheriffs for more than two years immediately prior thereto, or who have been certified by the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center and who have received a certificate of completion shall hold their positions without examinations until discharged, reduced, promoted, or transferred in accordance with sections 23-1721 to 23-1736.</para><para>(3) All deputy sheriffs in active employment on January 1, 1977, in counties having a population of more than forty thousand but not more than sixty thousand inhabitants, and who have been deputy sheriffs for more than two years immediately prior thereto, or who have been certified by the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center and who have received a certificate of completion shall hold their positions without examinations until discharged, reduced, promoted, or transferred in accordance with sections 23-1721 to 23-1736.</para><para>(4) All deputy sheriffs in active employment on January 1, 1982, in counties having a population of twenty-five thousand or more but not more than forty thousand inhabitants, and who have been deputy sheriffs for more than two years immediately prior thereto, or who have been certified by the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center, and who have received a certificate of completion shall hold their positions without examinations until discharged, reduced, promoted, or transferred in accordance with sections 23-1721 to 23-1736.</para><para>(5) All deputy sheriffs who have been so employed for more than six months and less than two years on such date shall be required to take qualifying examinations, and all such deputy sheriffs who have been so employed for less than six months on such date shall be required to take competitive examinations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 140, &#167; 12, p. 646; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1093, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 315, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 122, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 782, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 222, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>