<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id00" statutenumber="23-1901"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1901</statuteno><catchline id="id00">County surveyor; county engineer; qualifications; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) It shall be the duty of the county surveyor to make or cause to be made all surveys within his or her county that the county surveyor may be called upon to make and record the same.</para><para>(2) In all counties having a population of at least one hundred thousand inhabitants but less than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants, the county surveyor shall be ex officio county engineer and shall be either a professional engineer as provided in the Engineers and Architects Regulation Act or a registered land surveyor as provided in the Land Surveyors Regulation Act or both. In such counties, the office of surveyor shall be full time.</para><para>In counties having a population of one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants or more, a county engineer shall be a professional engineer as provided in the act and shall be elected as provided in section 32-526.</para><para>(3) The county engineer or ex officio county engineer shall:</para><para>(a) Prepare all plans, specifications, and detail drawings for the use of the county in advertising and letting all contracts for the building and repair of bridges, culverts, and all public improvements upon the roads;</para><para>(b) Make estimates of the cost of all such contemplated public improvements, make estimates of all material required for such public improvements, inspect the material and have the same measured and ascertained, and report to the county board whether the same is in accordance with its requirements;</para><para>(c) Superintend the construction of all such public improvements and inspect and require that the same shall be done according to contract;</para><para>(d) Make estimates of the cost of all labor and material which shall be necessary for the construction of all bridges and improvements upon public highways, inspect all of the work and materials placed in any such public improvements, and make a report in writing to the county board with a statement in regard to whether the same comply with the plans, specifications, and detail drawings of the county board prepared for such work or improvements and under which the contract was let; and</para><para>(e) Have charge and general supervision of work or improvements authorized by the county board, inspect all materials, direct the work, and make a report of each piece of work to the county board.</para><para>The county engineer or surveyor shall also have such other and further powers as are necessarily incident to the general powers granted.</para><para>(4) The county surveyor shall prepare and file the required annual inventory statement of county personal property in his or her custody or possession as provided in sections 23-346 to 23-350.</para><para>(5) In counties having a population of one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants or more, the county engineer shall appoint a full-time county surveyor. The county surveyor shall perform all the duties prescribed in sections 23-1901 to 23-1913 and any other duties assigned to him or her by the county engineer. The county surveyor shall be a registered land surveyor as provided in the Land Surveyors Regulation Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 127, p. 386; </para><para>Laws 1905, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 295; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5685; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 141, &#167; 1, p. 606; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5015; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-1601; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 16, p. 154; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-1601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1901; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 170, &#167; 1, p. 747; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 127, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 512, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 821, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 76, &#167; 543; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 622, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB138, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB200, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB791, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Engineers and Architects Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-3401.</para><para><emphasis>Land Surveyors Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,108.01.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>