<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id23">
<sectno id="id24">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id25" statutenumber="23-1734"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id27">23-1734</statuteno><catchline id="id28">Deputy sheriff;
removal, suspension, reduced in rank or grade; procedure; grievance; procedure.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) Any deputy sheriff
may be removed, suspended with
or without pay, or reduced in either rank or grade or both rank
and grade by the sheriff, after appointment or promotion is complete, by an
order in writing, stating specifically the reasons therefor. Such order shall
be filed with the sheriff's office merit commission, and a copy thereof shall be furnished to the
person so removed, suspended, or reduced. Any person so removed, suspended with or without pay, or reduced
in either rank or grade or both rank and grade may, within ten days after
presentation to him or her of the order of removal, suspension with or without pay, or reduction, appeal to
the commission from such order. The commission shall, within two weeks after the filing of such appeal, hold a hearing
thereon, and thereupon fully hear and determine the matter, and either affirm,
modify, or revoke such order. The appellant shall be entitled to appear personally,
produce evidence, and have counsel or
other representation and a public hearing. The finding and decision
of the commission shall be certified to the sheriff and shall forthwith be
enforced and followed, but under no condition shall the employee who has appealed
to the commission be permanently removed, suspended with or without pay, or reduced in rank until
such finding and decision of the commission is so certified to the sheriff.</para>
<para>(b) This subsection
does not apply to a deputy sheriff during his or her probationary period.</para>
<para>(2) Any deputy sheriff may grieve a violation of an employment
contract, a personnel rule, a state or local law, or a written departmental
policy or procedure to the commission. The commission shall hear the grievance
at the next regularly scheduled meeting, or the commission may, at its discretion,
set a special meeting to hear the grievance. If the deputy sheriff is subject
to a labor agreement, all applicable procedures in the agreement shall be
followed prior to the matter being heard by the commission. In all other cases,
the matter shall be grieved, in writing, to the commission within fifteen
calendar days after the date the deputy sheriff became
aware of the occurrence giving rise to the grievance. After hearing or reviewing
the grievance, the commission shall issue a written order either affirming
or denying the grievance. Such order shall be delivered to the parties to
the grievance or their counsel or
other representative within seven calendar days after the date
of the hearing or the submission of the written grievance.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1969, c. 140, &#167; 14, p. 646; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 222, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB158, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>This section does not become operative until a deputy sheriff has been reduced in either rank or grade or both by the sheriff; it does not become operative until the sheriff acts. The commissioner's authority, under this section, to modify the action of the sheriff does not permit him to increase the punishment imposed by the sheriff. Freese and Johnson v. County of Douglas, 210 Neb. 521, 315 N.W.2d 638 (1982).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>