<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1704.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1704.01</statuteno><catchline>Sheriff; deputies; appointment; oath; duties.</catchline><para>The sheriff may appoint such number of deputies as he or she sees fit for whose acts he or she will be responsible. The sheriff may not appoint the county treasurer, clerk, register of deeds, or surveyor as deputy.</para><para>The appointment shall be in writing and revocable in writing by the sheriff. Both the appointment and revocation shall be filed and kept in the office of the county clerk.</para><para>The deputy shall take the same oath as the sheriff which shall be endorsed upon and filed with the certificate of appointment. The sheriff may require a bond of the deputy.</para><para>In the absence or disability of the sheriff, the deputy shall perform the duties of the sheriff pertaining to the office, but when the sheriff is required to act in conjunction with or in place of another officer, the deputy cannot act in the sheriff's place. No deputy shall act as constable while deputy sheriff.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1866, c. 15, &#167; 4, p. 127; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5738; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5067; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 43, &#167; 1, p. 158; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 84-804; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1981), &#167; 84-804; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 821, &#167; 7. </para></source><annotation><para>Deputy sheriff, acting as jailer is public officer, and county board cannot contract with him for different compensation than fixed by law. Scott v. Scotts Bluff County, 106 Neb. 355, 183 N.W. 573 (1921).</para><para>County board must fix number and compensation of sheriff's deputies, under act requiring board to furnish sheriff with such deputies as they deem necessary, but sheriff has power to appoint. State ex rel. Rohrs v. Harris, 100 Neb. 745, 161 N.W. 253 (1917).</para><para>When office of sheriff was a fee office, a deputy sheriff was required to look to fees for his salary. Power v. Douglas County, 75 Neb. 734, 106 N.W. 782 (1906).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>