<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1303"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1303</statuteno><catchline>Warrants; funds transfer systems; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) The county clerk shall not issue any county warrants except upon claims approved by the county board. Every warrant issued shall be numbered consecutively as allowed from July 1 to June 30, corresponding with the fiscal year of the county. The county clerk shall maintain records including the date, amount, and number of each warrant, the name of the person to whom a warrant is issued, and the date a warrant is returned as canceled. The records shall be made accessible to the public for viewing, in either an electronic or printed format.</para><para>(2)(a) The county clerk shall develop and implement a system of warrant preparation and issuance by electronic or mechanical means which is compatible with the funds transfer system established by the county treasurer pursuant to subsection (6) of this section.</para><para>(b) Warrant includes an order issued by the chairperson of the county board and countersigned by the county clerk directing that the county treasurer make payment in a specified amount to a specified payee by the use of a dual signature negotiable instrument as provided for in subsections (3) and (4) of this section, an electronic funds transfer system, a telephonic funds transfer system, funds transfers as provided in article 4A, Uniform Commercial Code, a mechanical funds transfer system, or any other funds transfer system established by the county treasurer.</para><para>(3) The chairperson of the county board shall sign each warrant or shall cause each warrant to be signed in his or her behalf either personally, by delegation of authority, or by facsimile or electronic signature. The signature of the chairperson of the county board shall signify that the payment intended by a warrant bearing such signature is proper under the appropriate laws of the state and resolutions of the county.</para><para>(4) The county clerk shall countersign all warrants issued by the chairperson of the county board either personally, by delegation of authority, or by facsimile or electronic signature.</para><para>(5) The county treasurer shall, if requested by the county clerk or the county board, establish procedures and processes for facsimile or electronic signature of warrants.</para><para>(6) The county treasurer may establish and operate an electronic funds transfer system, a telephonic funds transfer system, funds transfers as provided for in article 4A, Uniform Commercial Code, a mechanical funds transfer system, or any other funds transfer system for the payment of funds from and the deposit of receipts into the county treasury. Such system as established by the county treasurer shall employ internal control safeguards and after meeting such safeguards shall be deemed to satisfy any signature requirements. The use of an electronic funds transfer system, a telephonic funds transfer system, funds transfers as provided for in article 4A, Uniform Commercial Code, a mechanical funds transfer system, or any other funds transfer system established by the county treasurer shall not create any rights that would not have been created had an order, drawn by the chairperson of the county board upon the county treasurer directing the latter to pay a specified amount to a specified payee by the use of a dual signature negotiable instrument as provided for in subsections (3) and (4) of this section, been used as the payment medium.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 75, p. 374; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5607; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4926; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-1003; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1303; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 74, &#167; 1, p. 235; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 86, &#167; 13. </para></source><annotation><para>Clerk cannot draw warrants except as ordered. State ex rel. Conger v. Maccuaig, 8 Neb. 215 (1879).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>