<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-1204.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1204.01</statuteno><catchline>Deputies; special; when; compensation.</catchline><para>The county attorney of any county may, under the direction of the district court, procure such assistance in any investigation or appearance or the trial of any person charged with a crime which is a felony, as he may deem necessary for the trial thereof, and such assistant or assistants shall be allowed such compensation for said services as the court shall determine, to be paid by order of the county treasurer, upon presenting to said board the certificate of the district judge before whom said cause was tried certifying to services rendered by such assistant or assistants and the amount of compensation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1885, c. 40, &#167; 6, p. 217; </para><para>Laws 1893, c. 2, &#167; 1, p. 64; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 8, &#167; 1, p. 57; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5599; </para><para>Laws 1917, c. 108, &#167; 1, p. 278; </para><para>Laws 1919, c. 62, &#167; 1, p. 169; </para><para>Laws 1921, c. 232, &#167; 1, p. 830; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4916; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 41, &#167; 1, p. 156; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 116, &#167; 2, p. 326; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-904; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 90, &#167; 14, p. 302; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1204; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 73, &#167; 2, p. 233; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 72, &#167; 2, p. 230; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 62, &#167; 5, p. 200; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 42, &#167; 1(2), p. 144; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 165, &#167; 1, p. 741.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Appointment of special counsel</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Effect of change of venue</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Appointment of special counsel</emphasis></para><para>In the prosecution of a felony case, the question of appointment of assistant counsel to aid the prosecution is addressed to the sound discretion of the court. Jackson v. State, 133 Neb. 786, 277 N.W. 92 (1938).</para><para>Application for appointment of counsel to assist in prosecution of criminal case is addressed to the sound discretion of the trial court and error cannot be predicated thereon in absence of showing of abuse of discretion. Dobry v. State, 130 Neb. 51, 263 N.W. 681 (1935).</para><para>Attorney may be appointed to assist in prosecution of felony, within discretion of court, on application of county attorney, and is not error in absence of showing abuse of discretion. Barr v. State, 114 Neb. 853, 211 N.W. 188 (1926); Baker v. State, 112 Neb. 654, 200 N.W. 876 (1924); Smith v. State, 109 Neb. 579, 191 N.W. 687 (1922).</para><para>Assistant attorney need not qualify and give bond nor take oath as deputy county attorney. Gragg v. State, 112 Neb. 732, 201 N.W. 338 (1924); Bush v. State, 62 Neb. 128, 86 N.W. 1062 (1901).</para><para>Court may appoint attorney in prosecution of misdemeanor. Goemann v. State, 100 Neb. 772, 161 N.W. 421 (1917).</para><para>It is the duty of the court to select impartial prosecutor to assist county attorney. Rogers v. State, 97 Neb. 180, 149 N.W. 318 (1914).</para><para>Attorney appointed to assist in prosecution may be nonresident but must qualify. Goldsberry v. State, 92 Neb. 211, 137 N.W. 1116 (1912).</para><para>Order permitting assistance of one employed privately should not be entered. McKay v. State, 90 Neb. 63, 132 N.W. 741 (1911).</para><para>Appointment after jury is passed for cause but before any peremptory challenges are used is valid. Johns v. State, 88 Neb. 145, 129 N.W. 247 (1910).</para><para>Appointment of counsel to assist in prosecution should be made before commencement of trial. Knights v. State, 58 Neb. 225, 78 N.W. 508 (1899).</para><para><emphasis>2. Effect of change of venue</emphasis></para><para>Attorney employed by county attorney to assist in prosecution is required to follow case on change of venue. Sands v. Frontier County, 42 Neb. 837, 60 N.W. 1017 (1894).</para><para>County from which venue is changed is liable for compensation of counsel appointed to assist in prosecution. Fuller v. Madison County, 33 Neb. 422, 50 N.W. 255 (1891).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>An application for attorney fees and expenses must be granted where the record demonstrates that the amount requested was reasonable and there is no evidence or indication otherwise that the amount is unreasonable. This section does not create a presumption of validity regarding attorney fees and expenses. Schirber v. State, in re Patrick Thomas, 254 Neb. 1002, 581 N.W.2d 873 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>