<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1219"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1219</statuteno><catchline>County attorney; deputy county attorney; failure to fulfill continuing legal education requirements; commission; investigate; duties.</catchline><para>When it comes to the attention of the commission that a county attorney or deputy county attorney has not fulfilled the required number of hours of annual mandatory continuing legal education, including instruction providing a working knowledge of electronic speed measurement principles and instruction on the investigation and prosecution of crimes against children, required by section 23-1217, it shall investigate such failure to comply in order to determine whether or not such failure was willful or negligent. If the commission determines that the failure to comply was willful or negligent, it shall refer the matter to the Attorney General for action under section 23-1220. If the commission determines that the failure to comply was not willful or negligent, it shall permit the county attorney or deputy county attorney to make up all outstanding hours of continuing legal education, including instruction providing a working knowledge of electronic speed measurement principles and instruction on the investigation and prosecution of crimes against children. In doing so, the commission shall establish a deadline by which such hours must be undertaken and completed. In making up any outstanding hours of continuing legal education, including instruction providing a working knowledge of electronic speed measurement principles and instruction on the investigation and prosecution of crimes against children under this section, such hours shall be in addition to those hours which are annually required under section 23-1217.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 790, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1246, &#167; 5. </para></source></law></legaldoc>