<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id253">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id255"  statutenumber="23-1827"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id257">23-1827</statuteno><catchline id="id258">Organ and tissue
donations; preliminary investigation; access to information; release of organs
or tissues; exception; presence for removal procedure.</catchline><para>(1)
A coroner shall conduct a preliminary investigation of a decedent within the
coroner's jurisdiction as soon as possible after notification by the hospital
in which such decedent is located or the hospital to which such decedent is
being transported. The coroner may designate the coroner's physician or another
physician to conduct the preliminary investigation.</para>
<para>(2) The preliminary investigation shall be completed within
a time period that is compatible with the preservation and recovery of organs
or tissues for the purpose of transplantation.</para>
<para>(3) The coroner may request and shall have access to all
necessary information including copies of medical records, laboratory test
results, X-rays, and other diagnostic results. The information shall be provided
as expeditiously as possible, through reasonable means, to permit the preliminary
investigation to be completed within a time period compatible with the preservation
and recovery of organs or tissues for the purpose of transplantation.</para>
<para>(4) Upon completion of the preliminary investigation, the
coroner shall release all organs or tissues which have been donated or may
yet be donated pursuant to the Revised Uniform
Anatomical Gift Act except those that the coroner reasonably believes contain
evidence of the proximate cause or means of death. If the coroner reasonably
believes that a specific organ or tissue contains evidence of the proximate
cause or means of death and the organ or tissue is otherwise subject to recovery
as a donated organ or tissue pursuant to the Revised Uniform Anatomical Gift Act, the coroner
or his or her designee shall be present for the removal procedure (a) to make
a final determination that allows the recovery of the organs and tissues to
proceed, (b) to request a biopsy, or (c) to deny removal of such organ or
tissue if the coroner determines such organ or tissue contains evidence of
the proximate cause or means of death. After a preliminary investigation is
completed under this section, all organs or tissues compatible for transplantation,
except any organs or tissues for which the coroner has denied recovery, may
be recovered pursuant to the Revised Uniform
Anatomical Gift Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB246, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB1036, &#167; 25.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Revised Uniform Anatomical Gift Act,</emphasis> see section 71-4824.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>