<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id6" statutenumber="23-1701.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1701.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Candidate for sheriff; appointee; requirements; sheriff; attend Sheriff's Certification Course; exception; continuing education; violation; penalty.</catchline><para>(1) Any candidate for the office of sheriff and any sheriff appointed under subsection (3) of section 23-1701 shall possess a law enforcement officer certificate or diploma issued by the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice. A standardized letter issued by the director of the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center certifying that the candidate or appointee was duly issued such certificate or diploma shall be filed by a candidate with the candidate filing form required by section 32-607 and by an appointee with the contract entered into under section 23-1701.</para><para>(2) Each sheriff shall attend the Sheriff's Certification Course conducted by the Nebraska Law Enforcement Training Center and obtain a certificate awarded by the Nebraska Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice attesting to satisfactory completion of such course within eight months after taking office unless such sheriff has already been awarded a certificate by the commission attesting to satisfactory completion of such course or unless such sheriff can demonstrate to the Nebraska Police Standards Advisory Council that his or her previous training and education is such that he or she will professionally discharge the duties of the office. Any sheriff in office prior to July 19, 1980, shall not be required to obtain a certificate awarded by the commission attesting to satisfactory completion of the Sheriff's Certification Course but shall otherwise be subject to this section.</para><para>(3) Each sheriff shall attend continuing education as provided in section 81-1414.07 each year following the first year of such sheriff's term of office.</para><para>(4) Unless a sheriff is able to show good cause for not complying with subsection (2) or (3) of this section or obtains a waiver of the training requirements from the council, any sheriff who violates subsection (2) or (3) of this section shall be punished by a fine equal to such sheriff's monthly salary. Each month in which such violation occurs shall constitute a separate offense.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1980, LB 628, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 971, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 75, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB817, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB924, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB51, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB894, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>