<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id16">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id18" statutenumber="23-1901.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1901.01</statuteno><catchline id="id21">County surveyor;
residency; appointed from another county;
when; term.</catchline><para>(1) A
person need not be a resident of the county when he or she files
for election as county surveyor, but if elected as county surveyor, such person
shall reside in a county for which he or she holds office.</para>
<para>(2) In a
county having a population of less than one hundred fifty thousand inhabitants
in which the voters have voted against the election of a county surveyor pursuant
to section 32-525 or in which no county surveyor has been elected and qualified, the
county board of such county shall appoint a
competent surveyor either on a full-time or part-time basis from any other
county of the State of Nebraska to such office. In making such appointment, the county board shall negotiate
a contract with the surveyor, such contract shall specify the responsibility of the
appointee to carry out the statutory duties of the office of county surveyor
and shall specify the compensation of the surveyor for the performance of such duties, which compensation
shall not be subject to section 33-116. A county surveyor appointed under this subsection shall serve
the same term as that of an elected surveyor.</para>
<para>(3) A person appointed to the office of
county surveyor in any county shall not be required to reside
in the county of appointment.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 45, &#167; 1, p. 162; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 115, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 127, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 812, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB946, &#167; 2.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>