<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1704"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1704</statuteno><catchline>Assistants; power to summon.</catchline><para>The sheriff and his deputies are conservators of the peace, and to keep the same, to prevent crime, to arrest any person liable thereto, or to execute process of law, they may call any person to their aid; and, when necessary, the sheriff may summon the power of the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 119, p. 385; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5656; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4983; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-1404; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1704.</para></source><annotation><para>City police officers may not make warrantless misdemeanor arrests outside their jurisdiction. State v. Tingle, 239 Neb. 558, 477 N.W.2d 544 (1991).</para><para>A sheriff has the power to summon to his assistance in the arrest of felons police officers of the cities of the second class under this section. Henning v. City of Hebron, 186 Neb. 381, 183 N.W.2d 756 (1971).</para><para>Sheriff has authority to call a private citizen into service to help capture prisoner. Anderson v. Bituminous Casualty Co., 155 Neb. 590, 52 N.W.2d 814 (1952).</para><para>Persons summoned as posse are not strictly deputies and sheriff is not liable to them for compensation, if entitled to any. Power v. Douglas County, 75 Neb. 734, 106 N.W. 782 (1906).</para><para>Duties of sheriff as conservator of peace are applicable to chief of police in metropolitan city. Moores v. State ex rel. Dunn, 71 Neb. 522, 99 N.W. 249 (1904), 115 Am. S.R. 605 (1904).</para><para>This section authorizes a deputy sheriff to summon a State Patrol trooper and a city police officer to assist in arresting a suspected intoxicated driver. Once summoned, those persons become de facto deputies. State v. Rodgers, 2 Neb. App. 360, 509 N.W.2d 668 (1993).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>