<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1301"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1301</statuteno><catchline>County clerk; office; duties; residency.</catchline><para>The county clerk shall keep his or her office at the county seat; shall attend the sessions of the county board; shall keep the seal, records, and papers of the board; and shall sign the record of the proceedings of the board and attest the same with the county seal. After the period of time specified by the State Records Administrator pursuant to the Records Management Act, the county clerk may transfer such record of the proceedings of the board to the State Archives of the Nebraska State Historical Society for permanent preservation.</para><para>A county clerk elected after November 1986 need not be a resident of the county when he or she files for election as county clerk, but a county clerk shall reside in a county for which he or she holds office.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1879, &#167; 73, p. 374; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5605; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 4924; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-1001; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1301; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 224, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 812, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 31. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Records Management Act,</emphasis> see section 84-1220.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Failure by a public governing body, as defined under section 84-1409, R.R.S.1943, to take and record a roll call vote on an action, as required by section 84-1413(2), R.S.Supp.,1980, grants any citizen the right to sue for the purpose of having the action declared void. In this case such failure could not be later corrected by a nunc pro tunc order because there was no showing that a roll call vote on the disputed action was actually taken, and even if it was the record showed it was not recorded until over a year later. Sections 23-1301, R.R.S.1943, and 23-1302, R.R.S.1943, make it the duty of the county clerk to record proceedings of the board of county commissioners. State ex rel. Schuler v. Dunbar, 208 Neb. 69, 302 N.W.2d 674 (1981).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>