<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-1911" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Annual Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>23-1911</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Surveys; records; contents; available to public.</catchline><para>The county surveyor shall record all surveys, for permanent purposes, made by him or her, as required by sections 81-8,121 to 81-8,122.02. Such record shall set forth the names of the persons making the application for the survey, for whom the work was done, and a statement showing it to be an official county survey or resurvey. The official records, other plats, and field notes of the county surveyor's office shall be deemed and considered public records. Any agent or authority of the United States, the State Surveyor or any deputy state surveyor of Nebraska, or any surveyor registered pursuant to the Land Surveyors Regulation Act shall at all times, within reasonable office or business hours, have free access to the surveys, field notes, maps, charts, records, and other papers as provided for in sections 23-1901 to 23-1913. In all counties, where no regular office is maintained in the county courthouse for the county surveyor of that county, the county clerk shall be custodian of the official record of surveys and all other permanent records pertaining to the office of county surveyor.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1913, c. 43, &#167; 9, p. 144; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 5695; </para><para>C.S.1922; </para><para>&#167; 5025; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 26-1611; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 44, &#167; 1, p. 227; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 26-1611; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-1911; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 127, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB138, &#167; 3. </para><effectivedate>August 30, 2015</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Land Surveyors Regulation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,108.01.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>An agreement as to boundary line is binding upon all parties having notice, though it may not be true line. Lynch v. Egan, 67 Neb. 541, 93 N.W. 775 (1903); Egan v. Light, 4 Neb. Unof. 127, 93 N.W. 859 (1903).</para><para>Where, on a line of the same survey and between remote corners, there is a variance between the measurement of the length of the whole line and the length of the line called for, excess or deficiency should be distributed equally unless one of the quarter sections is fractional, in which latter case excess is distributed proportionately. Brooks v. Stanley, 66 Neb. 826, 92 N.W. 1013 (1902).</para><para>In determining lines, testimony of party who located the line from government monuments then in existence is preferable to surveyor's testimony, who subsequently located a different line. Baty v. Elrod, 66 Neb. 735, 92 N.W. 1032 (1903), affirmed on rehearing 66 Neb. 744, 97 N.W. 343 (1903).</para><para>Government corners, if ascertained, will control all other surveys; if lost, they may be established by witnesses; if no witnesses, government field notes will control. Clark v. Thornburg, 66 Neb. 717, 92 N.W. 1056 (1902).</para><para>Government corners control field notes at time of survey and also field notes, courses, and distances of subsequent survey; as to lost corners, field notes will control. Knoll v. Randolph, 3 Neb. Unof. 599, 92 N.W. 195 (1902).</para><para>Surveyor need not follow original order of survey and his location of section corner will not be rejected in absence of proof of mistake or error. Shrake v. Laflin, 3 Neb. Unof. 489, 92 N.W. 184 (1902).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>