<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-2310"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2310</statuteno><catchline>Defined contribution benefit; employer account, defined; state investment officer; duties.</catchline><para>(1) For a member employed and participating in the retirement system prior to January 1, 2003, who has elected not to participate in the cash balance benefit, a member's share of the fund arising from the county contributions shall be known as his or her employer account. Prior to January 1, 1981, as of any January 1 a member's employer account shall be equal to his or her account as of the next preceding January 1, increased by one hundred percent of any amounts deducted from the member's compensation since the next preceding January 1 in accordance with section 23-2307. As of January 1, 1982, a member's employer account shall be equal to the account as of January 1, 1981, increased by one hundred percent of the amounts deducted from the member's compensation for the first nine months of the year and one hundred fifty percent for the final three months of the year in accordance with section 23-2307. As of January 1, 1983, and each year thereafter, the member's employer account shall be equal to the account as of the next preceding January 1 increased by one hundred fifty percent of the amounts deducted from the member's compensation since the next preceding January 1 in accordance with section 23-2307. The member's employer account shall be increased by any interest allocated under the provisions of the guaranteed investment contract and any gains on investments and reduced by any losses on investments, any expense charges under the guaranteed investment contract or other investments, and any expense charges incurred in connection with administering the retirement system in excess of those provided for in section 23-2319.01, except that a member who ceased being an employee since the next preceding January 1 may have his or her employer account reduced in accordance with such section. On and after July 1, 1999, the employer account shall be equal to the sum of the assets of the accounts created by the board pursuant to section 23-2310.05.</para><para>(2) On and after January 1, 1997, and until July 1, 1999, the state investment officer shall invest the employer account, and, after July 1, 1999, upon maturity, the state investment officer shall invest the employer account funds which have been invested in guaranteed investment contracts prior to January 1, 1997. On and after July 1, 1999, the employer account shall be invested pursuant to section 23-2310.05. The state investment officer shall invest or reinvest the funds in securities and investments the nature of which individuals of prudence, discretion, and intelligence acquire or retain in dealing with the property of another, and if the state investment officer has special skills or is appointed on the basis of representations of special skills or expertise, he or she is under a duty to use such skills.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 94, &#167; 10, p. 406; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 462, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 313, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 347, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1057, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 687, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 9.</para></source><annotation><para>At no time did the Legislature intend that a county make contributions of 250 percent of the amounts deducted from the compensation paid to the members of its retirement system. Hoiengs v. County of Adams, 254 Neb. 64, 574 N.W.2d 498 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>