<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-2511"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2511</statuteno><catchline>Employee; discharged, suspended, demoted; appeal; hearing; order; effect.</catchline><para>The commission shall, within two weeks after receipt of the notice of appeal, hold a public hearing thereon at which the employee shall be entitled to appear personally, be represented by counsel, cross-examine witnesses and produce evidence. The commission shall have the authority to affirm, modify or revoke the order appealed from, and the finding and the decision of the commission shall be certified to the department head who issued the order, and the finding and decision of the commission shall be binding on all parties concerned. In the event of an appeal to the commission, no order affecting an employee shall become permanent until the finding and decision of the commission shall be certified as provided in this section. Notwithstanding any other provision of sections 23-2501 to 23-2516, an employee affected by an order may request transfer to another department governed by sections 23-2501 to 23-2516 with the consent of the commission and the department head of such other department.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 921, &#167; 11. </para></source><annotation><para>A plain reading of the statutes which govern the appeal process from a county commission does not reveal an express or implied legislative intent to limit objections on appeal to those claims presented to the administrative tribunal. Although appeals through administrative channels are preferred and encouraged, procedural due process defenses should not be waived if timely raised in the first judicial tribunal to review the administrative action. Ashby v. Civil Serv. Comm. of Douglas County, 241 Neb. 988, 492 N.W.2d 849 (1992).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>