<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id79">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id81" statutenumber="23-2307"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2307</statuteno><catchline id="id84">Retirement system;
members; contribution; amount; county pay.</catchline><para>Each
employee who is a member of the retirement system shall pay to the county
or have picked up by the county a sum equal to four and one-half percent of
his or her compensation for each pay period. The contributions, although designated as employee contributions,
shall be paid by the county in lieu of employee contributions. The
county shall pick up the employee contributions required by this section for
all compensation paid on or after January 1, 1985, and the contributions so
picked up shall be treated as employer contributions pursuant to section 414(h)(2) of the Internal Revenue Code in
determining federal tax treatment under the code and shall not be included as gross income
of the employee until such time as they are distributed or made available.
The county shall pay these employee contributions from the same source of
funds which is used in paying earnings to the employee. The county shall pick
up these contributions by a compensation deduction through a reduction in
the cash compensation of the employee. Employee contributions picked up shall
be treated for all purposes of the County Employees Retirement Act in the
same manner and to the extent as employee contributions made prior to the
date picked up.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 94, &#167; 7, p. 405; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 459, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 218, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 347, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1057, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 31; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 186, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 4.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>