<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-2518.03" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2518.03</statuteno><catchline>Transfer of employees; sick leave; annual leave; vacation leave; other benefits; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) The state or a political subdivision shall transfer all accrued sick leave of the transferred employee up to the maximum number of accumulated hours for sick leave allowed by the county personnel system. The state or political subdivision shall reimburse the county for twenty-five percent of the value of the accrued sick leave hours based on the straight-time rate of pay for the employee.</para><para>(2) The transferred employee may transfer the maximum amount of accrued annual leave earned as an employee of the state or a political subdivision allowed by the county personnel system. The state or a political subdivision shall reimburse the county for one hundred percent of the value of the hours of accrued annual leave transferred.</para><para>(3) No transferred employee shall lose any accrual rate value of his or her sick leave and vacation leave as a result of becoming a county employee, and a transferred employee may credit years of service with the state or a political subdivision toward the accrual rate for sick leave and vacation leave plans. When accrued sick leave and vacation leave for a transferred employee are at a greater rate value than allowed by the county's sick leave and vacation leave plans, the state or political subdivision shall pay the county the difference between the value of the benefits allowed by the county and the state or political subdivision based on, at the time of the transfer, twenty-five percent of the employee's straight-time rate of pay for the sick leave and one hundred percent of the employee's straight-time rate of pay for vacation leave. A state or political subdivision shall reimburse the county not later than one year after the transfer is complete.</para><para>(4) The transferred employee shall not receive any additional accrual rate value for county benefits until the employee meets the qualifications for the increased accrual rates pursuant to the county's requirements.</para><para>(5) The transferred employee shall receive credit for time of service with the state or a political subdivision toward participation, coverage by insurance programs for the county, and the waiting period for medical insurance coverage provided by the county.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 11.</para></source></law></legaldoc>