
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id132" statutenumber="23-2319"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2319</statuteno><catchline id="id135">Termination of employment; termination benefit; vesting; certain required minimum distributions; election authorized.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in section 42-1107, upon termination of employment, except for retirement or disability, and after filing an application with the board, a member may receive:</para><para>(a) If not vested, a termination benefit equal to the amount of his or her employee account or member cash balance account as of the date of final account value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the lump-sum or first annuity payment made at any time after termination but no later than the required beginning date; or</para><para>(b) If vested, a termination benefit equal to (i) the amount of his or her member cash balance account as of the date of final account value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the lump-sum or first annuity payment made at any time after termination but no later than the required beginning date or (ii)(A) the amount of his or her employee account as of the date of final account value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the lump-sum or first annuity payment made at any time after termination but no later than the required beginning date plus (B) the amount of his or her employer account as of the date of final account value payable in a lump sum or an annuity with the lump-sum or first annuity payment made at any time after termination but no later than the required beginning date.</para><para>(c) The member cash balance account or employer and employee accounts of a terminating member shall be retained by the board, and the termination benefit shall be deferred until a valid application for benefits has been received.</para><para>(2) At the option of the terminating member, any lump sum of the employer account or member cash balance account or any annuity payment provided under subsection (1) of this section shall commence as of the first of the month at any time after such member has terminated his or her employment with the county and no later than the required beginning date. Such election by the terminating member shall be made at any time prior to the commencement of the lump-sum or annuity payments.</para><para>(3) Members of the retirement system shall be vested after a total of three years of participation in the system as a member pursuant to section 23-2306, including vesting credit. If an employee retires pursuant to section 23-2315, such employee shall be fully vested in the retirement system.</para><para>(4) A participant or beneficiary who would have been required to receive required minimum distributions for 2009 but for the enactment of section 401(a)(9)(H) of the Internal Revenue Code, and who would have satisfied that requirement by receiving distributions that are either equal to the 2009 required minimum distributions or one or more payments in a series of substantially equal distributions, including the 2009 required minimum distribution, made at least annually and expected to last for the life or life expectancy of the participant, the joint lives or joint life expectancy of the participant and the participant's designated beneficiary, or for a period of at least ten years, shall receive those distributions for 2009 unless the participant or beneficiary chooses not to receive such distributions. Participants and beneficiaries shall be given the opportunity to elect to stop receiving the distributions described in this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 94, &#167; 19, p. 408; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 32, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 47, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 216, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 60, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 417, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 1306, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1273, &#167; 16; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 28; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 366, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1054, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>