<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id95">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id97" statutenumber="23-2315"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2315</statuteno><catchline id="id100">Retirement system;
retirement; when; conditions; application for benefits; deferment of payment;
board; duties; certain required
minimum distributions; election authorized.</catchline><para>(1)
Upon filing an application for benefits with the board, an employee may elect
to retire at any time after attaining the age of fifty-five or an employee
may retire as a result of disability at any age.</para>
<para>(2) The member shall specify in the application for benefits
the manner in which he or she wishes to receive the retirement benefit under
the options provided by the County Employees Retirement Act. Payment under
the application for benefits shall be made (a) for annuities, no sooner than
the annuity start date, and (b) for other distributions, no sooner than the
date of final account value.</para>
<para>(3) Payment of any benefit provided under the retirement
system may not be deferred later than April 1 of the year following the year
in which the employee has both attained at least age seventy and one-half
years and terminated his or her employment with the county.</para>
<para>(4) The board shall make reasonable efforts to locate the
member or the member's beneficiary and distribute benefits by the required
beginning date as specified by section 401(a)(9) of the Internal Revenue Code
and the regulations issued thereunder. If the board is unable to make such
a distribution, the benefit shall be distributed pursuant to the Uniform Disposition
of Unclaimed Property Act and no amounts may be applied to increase the benefits
any member would otherwise receive under the County Employees Retirement Act.</para>
<para>(5) A participant
or beneficiary who would have been required to receive required minimum distributions
for 2009 but for the enactment of section 401(a)(9)(H) of the Internal Revenue
Code, and who would have satisfied that requirement by receiving distributions
that are either equal to the 2009 required minimum distributions or one or
more payments in a series of substantially equal distributions, including
the 2009 required minimum distribution, made at least annually and expected
to last for the life or life expectancy of the participant, the joint lives
or joint life expectancy of the participant and the participant's designated
beneficiary, or for a period of at least ten years, shall receive those distributions
for 2009 unless the participant or beneficiary chooses not to receive such
distributions. Participants and beneficiaries shall be given the opportunity
to elect to stop receiving the distributions described in this subsection.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1965, c. 94, &#167; 15, p. 407; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 47, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 391, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 287, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 311, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 60, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 296, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1076, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB263, &#167; 6.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Uniform Disposition of Unclaimed Property Act,</emphasis> see section 69-1329.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>