 <?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-2531" amended="yes" ><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2531</statuteno><catchline>Discrimination; prohibited; other prohibited acts.</catchline><para>(1) Discrimination against any person in recruitment, examination, appointment, training, promotion, retention, discipline, or any other aspect of personnel administration because of political or religious opinions or affiliations or because of race, national origin, or other nonmerit factors shall be prohibited. Discrimination on the basis of age or sex or physical disability shall be prohibited unless specific age, sex, or physical requirements constitute a bona fide occupational qualification necessary to proper and efficient administration. The rules and regulations shall provide for appeals in cases of alleged discrimination to the personnel policy board whose determination shall be binding upon a finding of discrimination.</para><para>(2) No person shall make any false statement, certificate, mark, rating, or report with regard to any test, certification, or appointment made under the County Civil Service Act or in any manner commit or attempt to commit any fraud preventing the impartial execution of the act and the rules and regulations promulgated pursuant to the act.</para><para>(3) No person shall, directly or indirectly, give, render, pay, offer, solicit, or accept any money, service, or other valuable consideration for or on account of any appointment, proposed appointment, promotion, or proposed promotion to, or any advantage in, a position in the classified service.</para><para>(4) No employee of the personnel office, examiner, or other person shall defeat, deceive, or obstruct any person in his or her right to examination, eligibility, certification, or appointment under the act, or furnish to any person any special or secret information for the purpose of affecting the rights or prospects of any persons with respect to employment in the classified service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1974, LB 995, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 808, &#167; 20. </para></source></law></legaldoc>