<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-2537"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2537</statuteno><catchline>Personnel policy board; members; terms; removal; officers; meetings.</catchline><para>(1) A personnel policy board may be created by resolution of the county board. The members of a personnel policy board shall include one elected county official chosen by the elected county officials other than the members of the county board, one county board member chosen by the county board, one member chosen by the employees who are not described in subdivisions (1) through (8) of section 23-2536, one lay member chosen by the elected county officials, and one lay member chosen by the county board. All members shall serve four-year terms, except of the members first chosen, the elected county official and the county board member shall serve one-year terms, the lay member chosen by the county board shall serve a two-year term, the lay member chosen by the elected county officials shall serve a three-year term, and the member chosen by the employees shall serve a four-year term. Each member of the board shall hold office until his or her successor is appointed and qualified. Any person appointed to fill a vacancy occurring prior to the expiration of a term shall be appointed in the same manner for the remainder of the term.</para><para>(2) A majority of the county board and elected county officials may remove any member of the personnel policy board for nonattendance at three meetings.</para><para>(3) A personnel policy board shall elect a chairperson from among its members. A board shall meet at such time and place as shall be specified by call of the chairperson or the county personnel officer. At least one meeting shall be held quarterly. Three members shall constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. Board members shall serve without compensation but shall receive reimbursement for actual and necessary expenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 212, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 124, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>