<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-2510" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2510</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Employee; discharged, suspended, demoted; order filed with commission; copy to employee; appeal.</catchline><para id="id00">Any employee may be discharged, suspended, or demoted in rank or compensation by his or her department head by a written order which shall specifically state the reasons therefor. Such order shall be filed with the commission, and a copy of such order shall be served upon the employee personally or by leaving it at his or her usual place of residence. Any employee so affected may, within ten days after service of the order, appeal such order to the commission. Notice of such appeal shall be in writing, signed by the employee appealing, and delivered to any member of the commission. The delivery of the notice of appeal shall be sufficient to perfect an appeal, and no other act shall be deemed necessary to confer jurisdiction of the commission over the appeal. In the event any employee is discharged, suspended, or demoted prior to the formation of the commission, such employee may appeal the order to the commission within ten days after the formation of the commission in the manner provided in this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 921, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB786, &#167; 12. </para></source><annotation><para>Pursuant to this section, the civil service commission is authorized to hear employee appeals from decisions where an employee is discharged, suspended, or demoted in rank or compensation by the employee's department head by a written order. The Legislature has authorized the commission to hear only those appeals which meet the requirements of this section. Douglas Cty. Bd. of Comrs. v. Civil Serv. Comm. of Douglas Cty., 263 Neb. 544, 641 N.W.2d 55 (2002).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>