<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id37">
<sectno id="id38" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id39" statutenumber="23-2309.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id41">23-2309.01</statuteno><catchline id="id42">Defined contribution
benefit; employee account; investment options; procedures; administration.</catchline><para>(1) Each member employed and participating in the retirement
system prior to January 1, 2003, who has elected not to participate in the
cash balance benefit, shall be allowed to allocate all contributions to his
or her employee account to various investment options. The investment options
shall include, but not be limited to, the following:</para>
<para>(a) An investor select account which shall be invested under
the direction of the state investment officer with an asset allocation and
investment strategy substantially similar to the investment allocations made
by the state investment officer for the defined benefit plans under the retirement
systems described in subdivision (1)(a) of section 84-1503. Investments shall
most likely include domestic and international equities, fixed income investments,
and real estate, as well as potentially additional asset classes;</para>
<para>(b) A stable return account which shall be invested by or
under the direction of the state investment officer in one or more guaranteed
investment contracts;</para>
<para>(c) An equities account which shall be invested by or under
the direction of the state investment officer in equities;</para>
<para>(d) A balanced account which shall be invested by or under
the direction of the state investment officer in equities and fixed income
instruments;</para>
<para>(e) An index fund account which shall be invested by or under
the direction of the state investment officer in a portfolio of common stocks
designed to closely duplicate the total return of the Standard and Poor's
500 Index;</para>
<para>(f) A fixed income account which shall be invested by or under
the direction of the state investment officer in fixed income instruments;</para>
<para>(g) A money market account which shall be invested by or under
the direction of the state investment officer in short-term fixed income securities;
and</para>
<para>(h) Beginning July 1, 2006, an age-based account which shall
be invested under the direction of the state investment officer with an asset
allocation and investment strategy that changes based upon the age of the
member. The board shall develop an account mechanism that changes the investments
as the employee nears retirement age. The asset allocation and asset classes
utilized in the investments shall move from aggressive, to moderate, and then
to conservative as retirement age approaches.</para>
<para>If a member fails to select an option or combination of options,
all of his or her funds shall be placed in the option described in subdivision
(b) of this subsection. Each member shall be given a detailed current description
of each investment option prior to making or revising his or her allocation.</para>
<para>(2) Members of the retirement system may allocate their contributions
to the investment options in percentage increments as set by the board in
any proportion, including full allocation to any one option. A member under
subdivision (1) of section 23-2321 or his or her beneficiary may transfer
any portion of his or her funds among the options, except for restrictions
on transfers to or from the stable return account pursuant to rule or regulation.
The board shall adopt and promulgate rules and regulations for changes of
a member's allocation of contributions to his or her accounts after his or
her most recent allocation and for transfers from one investment account to
another.</para>
<para>(3) The board shall develop a schedule for the allocation
of administrative costs of maintaining the various investment options and
shall assess the costs so that each member pays a reasonable fee as determined
by the board.</para>
<para>(4) In order to carry out this section, the board may enter
into administrative services agreements for accounting or record-keeping services.
No agreement shall be entered into unless the board determines that it will
result in administrative economy and will be in the best interests of the
county and its participating employees.</para>
<para>(5) The state, the board, the state investment officer, the
members of the Nebraska Investment Council, or the county shall not be liable
for any investment results resulting from the member's exercise of control
over the assets in the employee account.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1985, LB 347, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 549, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 833, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 847, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 703, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1200, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 407, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 503, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1147, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167;  3.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2010</operativedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>