<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id92">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id94" statutenumber="23-2319.01">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2319.01</statuteno><catchline id="id97">Termination
of employment; account forfeited; when; County Employer Retirement Expense
Fund; created; investment.</catchline><para>(1) For a member who
has terminated employment and is not vested, the balance of the member's employer
account or employer cash balance account shall be forfeited. The forfeited
account shall be credited to the County Employees Retirement Fund and shall
first be used to meet the expense charges incurred by the retirement board
in connection with administering the retirement system, which charges shall
be credited to the County Employees Defined Contribution Retirement Expense
Fund, if the member participated in the defined contribution option, or to
the County Employees Cash Balance Retirement Expense Fund, if the member participated
in the cash balance option, and the remainder, if any, shall then be used
to reduce the county contribution which would otherwise be required to fund
future service retirement benefits or to restore employer accounts or employer
cash balance accounts. No forfeited amounts shall be applied to increase the
benefits any member would otherwise receive under the County Employees Retirement
Act.</para>
<para>(2)(a) If a member ceases
to be an employee due to the termination of his or her employment by the county
and a grievance or other appeal of the termination is filed, transactions
involving forfeiture of his or her employer account or employer cash balance
account and, except as provided
in subdivision (b) of this subsection, transactions for payment of benefits
under sections 23-2315 and 23-2319 shall be suspended pending
the final outcome of the grievance or other appeal.</para>
<para>(b) If a member elects
to receive benefits payable under sections 23-2315 and 23-2319 after a grievance
or appeal is filed, the member may receive an amount up to the balance of
his or her employee account or member cash balance account or twenty-five
thousand dollars payable from the employee account or member cash balance
account, whichever is less.</para><para>(3) The County
Employer Retirement Expense Fund is created. The fund shall be administered
by the Public Employees Retirement Board. The fund shall consist of any reduction
in a county contribution which would otherwise be required to fund future
service retirement benefits or to restore employer accounts or employer cash
balance accounts referred to in subsection (1) of this section. The fund shall
be established and maintained separate from any funds held in trust for the
benefit of members under the county employees retirement system. Expenses
incurred as a result of a county depositing amounts into the fund shall be
deducted prior to any additional expenses being allocated. Any remaining amount
shall be allocated in accordance with section 23-2319.02. Any money in the
fund available for investment shall be invested by the state investment officer
pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the Nebraska State Funds
Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 624, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1200, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 7.</para><operativedate>July 1, 2011</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>