<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id57">
<sectno id="id58" opdate="July 1, 2010">Sec. 4.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id59" statutenumber="23-2310.04"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id61">23-2310.04</statuteno><catchline id="id62">County Employees
Defined Contribution Retirement Expense Fund; County Employees Cash Balance
Retirement Expense Fund; created; use; investment.</catchline><para>(1)
The County Employees Defined Contribution Retirement Expense Fund is created.
The fund shall be credited with money from the retirement
system assets and income sufficient to pay the pro rata share of administrative
expenses incurred as directed by the board for the proper administration of
the County Employees Retirement Act and necessary in connection with the administration
and operation of the retirement system, except as provided in sections 23-2308.01,
23-2309.01, and
23-2310.05. Any money in the fund available for investment shall be invested
by the state investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion
Act and the Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
<para>(2) The County Employees Cash Balance Retirement Expense Fund
is created. The fund shall be credited with money forfeited pursuant to section
23-2319.01 and with money from the retirement system assets and income sufficient
to pay the pro rata share of administrative expenses incurred as directed
by the board for the proper administration of the County Employees Retirement
Act and necessary in connection with the administration and operation of the
retirement system, except as provided in sections 23-2308.01, 23-2309.01, and 23-2310.05. Any
money in the fund available for investment shall be invested by the state
investment officer pursuant to the Nebraska Capital Expansion Act and the
Nebraska State Funds Investment Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 623, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 1200, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 408, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Capital Expansion Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1269.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska State Funds Investment Act,</emphasis> see section 72-1260.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>