<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id6" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="23-2308.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>23-2308.01</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Cash balance
benefit; election; effect; administrative services agreements; authorized.</catchline>
<para>(1) It is the intent of the Legislature that, in order to
improve the competitiveness of the retirement plan for county employees, a
cash balance benefit shall be added to the County Employees Retirement Act
on and after January 1, 2003. Each member who is employed and participating
in the retirement system prior to January 1, 2003, may either elect to continue
participation in the defined contribution benefit as provided in the act prior
to January 1, 2003, or elect to participate in the cash balance benefit as
set forth in this section. The member shall make the election prior to January
1, 2003, or on or after November 1, 2007, but before January 1, 2008. If no
election is made prior to January 1, 2003, or on or after November 1, 2007,
but before January 1, 2008, the member shall be treated as though he or she
elected to continue participating in the defined contribution benefit as provided
in the act prior to January 1, 2003. Members who elect to participate in the
cash balance benefit on or after November 1, 2007, but before January 1, 2008,
shall commence participation in the cash balance benefit on January 1, 2008.
Any member who made the election prior to January 1, 2003, does not have to
reelect the cash balance benefit on or after November 1, 2007, but before
January 1, 2008. A member employed and participating in the retirement system
prior to January 1, 2003, who terminates employment on or after January 1,
2003, and returns to employment prior to having a five-year break in service
shall participate in the cash balance benefit as set forth in this section.</para>
<para>(2) For a member employed and participating in the retirement
system beginning on and after January 1, 2003, or a member employed and participating
in the retirement system on January 1, 2003, who, prior to January 1, 2003,
or on or after November 1, 2007, but before January 1, 2008, elects to convert
his or her employee and employer accounts to the cash balance benefit:</para>
<para>(a)  Except as provided in subdivision (2)(b)
of section 23-2319.01, the employee cash balance account shall,
at any time, be equal to the following:</para>
<para>(i) The initial employee account balance, if any, transferred
from the defined contribution plan account described in section 23-2309; plus</para>
<para>(ii) Employee contribution credits deposited in accordance
with section 23-2307; plus</para>
<para>(iii) Interest credits credited in accordance with subdivision
(19) of section 23-2301; plus</para>
<para>(iv) Dividend amounts credited in accordance with subdivision
(4)(c) of section 23-2317; and</para>
<para>(b) The employer cash balance account shall, at any time,
be equal to the following:</para>
<para>(i) The initial employer account balance, if any, transferred
from the defined contribution plan account described in section 23-2310; plus</para>
<para>(ii) Employer contribution credits deposited in accordance
with section 23-2308; plus</para>
<para>(iii) Interest credits credited in accordance with subdivision
(19) of section 23-2301; plus</para>
<para>(iv) Dividend amounts credited in accordance with subdivision
(4)(c) of section 23-2317.</para>
<para>(3) In order to carry out the provisions of this section,
the board may enter into administrative services agreements for accounting
or record-keeping services. No agreement shall be entered into unless the
board determines that it will result in administrative economy and will be
in the best interests of the counties and their participating employees. The
board may develop a schedule for the allocation of the administrative services
agreements costs for accounting or record-keeping services and may assess
the costs so that each member pays a reasonable fee as determined by the board.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2002, LB 687, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 451, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 364, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 366, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1019, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB328, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB188, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB950, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB509, &#167; 6.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>