<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id00" statutenumber="23-3406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3406</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Public defender; contract; terms.</catchline><para>(1) The contract negotiated between the county board and the contracting attorney shall specify the categories of cases in which the contracting attorney is to provide services.</para><para>(2) The contract negotiated between the county board and the contracting attorney shall be awarded for at least a two-year term. Removal of the contracting attorney short of the agreed term may be for good cause only.</para><para>(3) The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney may specify a maximum allowable caseload for each full-time or part-time attorney who handles cases under the contract. Caseloads shall allow each lawyer to give every client the time and effort necessary to provide effective representation.</para><para>(4) The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney shall provide that the contracting attorney be compensated at a minimum rate which reflects the following factors:</para><para>(a) The customary compensation in the community for similar services rendered by a privately retained counsel to a paying client or by government or other publicly paid attorneys to a public client;</para><para>(b) The time and labor required to be spent by the attorney; and</para><para>(c) The degree of professional ability, skill, and experience called for and exercised in the performance of the services.</para><para>(5) The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney shall provide that the contracting attorney may decline to represent clients with no reduction in compensation if the contracting attorney is assigned more cases which require an extraordinary amount of time and preparation than the contracting attorney can competently handle.</para><para>(6) The contract between the contracting attorney and the county board shall provide that the contracting attorney shall receive at least ten hours of continuing legal education annually in the area of criminal law. The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney shall provide funds for the continuing legal education of the contracting attorney in the area of criminal law.</para><para>(7) The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney shall require that the contracting attorney provide legal counsel to all clients in a professional, skilled manner consistent with minimum standards set forth by the American Bar Association and the Canons of Ethics for Attorneys in the State of Nebraska. The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney shall provide that the contracting attorney shall be available to eligible defendants upon their request, or the request of someone acting on their behalf, at any time the Constitution of the United States or the Constitution of Nebraska requires the appointment of counsel.</para><para>(8) The contract between the county board and the contracting attorney shall provide for reasonable compensation over and above the normal contract price for cases which require an extraordinary amount of time and preparation, including capital cases.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 885, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1989), &#167; 29-1826; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 822, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB268, &#167; 1; </para><para>Referendum 2016, No. 426. </para><note>The changes made to section 23-3406 by Laws 2015, LB 268, section 1, have been omitted because of the vote on the referendum at the November 2016 general election.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>