<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3604"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3604</statuteno><catchline>Sewerage disposal system and plant; authorized; county; powers; vote by city or village governing body; when required.</catchline><para>(1) Any county in this state may own, construct, equip, and operate a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants for the treatment, purification, and disposal, in a sanitary manner, of liquid and solid wastes, sewage, and night soil or extend or improve any existing sanitary sewer system for the purpose of meeting the future needs of planned commercial or industrial users. The authority granted to a county under the provisions of the County Industrial Sewer Construction Act shall extend to the acquisition, leasing, or contracting for the use of a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants, and the county shall exercise this authority in the same manner as provided in the act for the construction, installation, improvement, or extension of a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants. A county is authorized to contract for the performance of any act or function provided for in the act with regard to the construction, installation, improvement, or extension of a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants or for the acquisition, leasing, or contracting for the use of a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants, except for such acts or functions as are governmental in nature.</para><para>(2) No county shall exercise the authority granted by the act within the boundaries of any incorporated city or village or outside the boundaries of the county. When more than fifty percent of the proposed length of a sewerage disposal system project will be located within the area of a city or village's declared extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction, the authority granted by the act shall not be exercised by a county without prior approval of the proposed project by a vote of the governing body of the city or village.</para><para>(3) Any county may acquire by gift, grant, purchase, or condemnation the necessary lands for the purposes authorized by the act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc>