<legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3618"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3618</statuteno><catchline>County board; adopt rules and regulations; connection to system; penalty; usage fees; permit; fee.</catchline><para>(1) The county board may adopt and promulgate rules and regulations governing the use, operation, and control of such sewerage disposal system and plant or plants, including the authority to compel all proper connections and to provide a penalty not to exceed one hundred dollars for any obstruction or injury to any sewer or part thereof or for failure to comply with the rules and regulations adopted and promulgated. If, after ten days' notice by certified mail or publication in a newspaper of general circulation, a property owner fails to make such connections and comply with such rules and regulations as may be ordered in accordance with this section, the county board may order such connection to be made and assess the cost of the connection against the property benefited in the same manner as special taxes are levied for other purposes.</para><para>(2) The county board may establish usage fees to be paid to it for the use of such sewerage disposal system and plant or plants by each person, firm, or corporation whose premises are served thereby. The county board may contract with another party for the billing and collection of such usage fees. If the usage fee so established is not paid when due, such sum may be recovered by the county in a civil action or it may be certified to the county assessor and assessed against the premises served and collected or returned in the same manner as other county taxes are certified, assessed, collected, and returned.</para><para>(3) The county board shall require the issuance of a permit for any property owner to connect with any sewer and the payment of a fee for the permit and connection as determined by the county board, which fee shall be paid prior to issuance of any such permit. The county board shall also require the issuance of a permit to connect with any sewer and payment of a connection fee by any developer payable at the time of filing a plat for the development, which fee shall be paid prior to issuance of such permit.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 18. </para></source></law></legaldoc>