<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="23-3803"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3803</statuteno><catchline>Program for management of black-tailed
prairie dogs; county; finding required; powers; discontinuance of program;
collection of unpaid assessments.</catchline><para>(1) A county may adopt by resolution and carry out a coordinated
program for the management of black-tailed prairie dogs on property within
the county consistent with the Black-Tailed Prairie Dog Management Act. When
a county adopts such a resolution, the county shall assume the authority and
duties provided in the act and the act shall be applicable to persons owning
or controlling property within the county.</para>
<para>(2) A black-tailed prairie
dog management plan shall include a finding by the county board of adverse
impacts of unmanaged colonies within the county and the necessity to exercise
the authority made available under the Black-Tailed Prairie Dog Management
Act. Such management plan shall include a listing of the methods for management
of colonies to be used for purposes which are consistent with the act. Such
management plan shall not conflict with any state management plan for black-tailed
prairie dogs or any rules or regulations adopted and promulgated pursuant
to the Nongame and Endangered Species Conservation Act and shall not conflict
with any state or federal recovery plan for endangered or threatened species.</para>
<para>(3) A county may cooperate
and coordinate with the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of the
United States Department of Agriculture, the Game and Parks Commission, the
United States Fish and Wildlife Service, and other local, state, and national
agencies and organizations, public or private, to prepare a coordinated program
for the control and management of black-tailed prairie dogs and to carry out
its duties and responsibilities under the Black-Tailed Prairie Dog Management
Act.</para><para>(4)
A county may by resolution discontinue a coordinated program for the management
of black-tailed prairie dogs. If such a program is discontinued, any unpaid
assessments against landowners for costs of black-tailed prairie dog management
shall continue to be collected pursuant to the Black-Tailed Prairie Dog Management
Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB473, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nongame and Endangered Species Conservation Act,</emphasis> see section 37-801.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>