<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-3632"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3632</statuteno><catchline>Urbanizing area planning commission; members; terms; vacancies.</catchline><para>The urbanizing area planning commission shall consist of six members. Three members shall be chosen by the county board from the membership of the county planning commission. Three members shall be chosen by the mayor with the approval of the governing body of the city or village from the regular membership of the planning commission of the city or village within whose area of future growth and development is located the territory which is the subject of the application. In the event that the territory which is the subject of the application is located in more than one area of future growth and development, the members of the urbanizing area planning commission shall be chosen from the city or village within whose area of future or growth and development more than fifty percent of the territory which is the subject of the plat, as measured by area, is located. The members of the urbanizing area planning commission shall serve without compensation for two-year terms. Initial appointments shall be made within thirty days after the date upon which the county board formally adopts a map designating and delineating the area of future growth and development of each city and village in the county pursuant to section 23-3610. Members shall hold office until their successors are appointed and qualified. Vacancies shall be filled by appointment by the person or body which made the original designation, and the vacancy shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 32. </para></source></law></legaldoc>