<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id63">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id65" statutenumber="23-3505"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3505</statuteno><catchline id="id68">Board of trustees; meetings; bylaws, rules, and regulations;
employees; filing required; other duties.</catchline>
<para>The board of
trustees shall:</para><para>(1) Hold meetings at least once each month and keep a complete record
of all of its proceedings;</para><para>(2) Adopt bylaws, rules, and regulations
for its own guidance and for the governance of a facility. The board of trustees
shall file such bylaws, rules, and regulations with the county board;</para>
<para>(3) Employ
or contract for an administrator of a facility, fix the administrator's compensation,
and review the administrator's job performance on at least an annual basis.
The administrator shall oversee the day-to-day operations of the facility
and its employees;</para><para>(4) If a facility maintains a medical staff, adopt and approve medical
staff bylaws that govern the medical staff of the facility, approve the appointment
of a qualified medical staff, and oversee the quality of medical care and
services provided at the facility;</para><para>(5) Manage and control a facility's funds
in accordance with guidelines established for political subdivisions by the
Nebraska Investment Council and invest such funds in investments as permitted
for counties in the State of Nebraska;</para><para>(6) Fix the price to be charged to patients
admitted to a facility for care and treatment;</para><para>(7) Establish charity-care
policies for free treatment or financial assistance for care provided by a
facility;</para><para>(8) Procure and pay premiums on any and all insurance policies required
for the prudent management of a facility, including, but not limited to, general
liability, professional malpractice liability, workers' compensation, vehicle
liability, and directors' and officers' liability; and</para>
<para>(9) On or before
July 15 of each year:</para><para>(a) File with the county board a report of its proceedings with
reference to a facility and a statement of all receipts and expenditures during
the year; and</para><para>(b) Certify the amount necessary, if any, to maintain and improve
a facility for the ensuing year.</para><para>The treasurer of the board of trustees or
his or her designee shall receive and pay out all money under the control
of the board of trustees as ordered by the board and report such expenditures
and receipts to the county board as required by subdivision (9)(a) of this
section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 44, &#167; 5, p. 210; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 114, &#167; 5, p. 450; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 121, &#167; 5, p. 389; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 134, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 23-343.04; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB995, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>April 6, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>