<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3633"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3633</statuteno><catchline>Urbanizing area planning commission; jurisdiction; powers and duties.</catchline><para>After the county board formally adopts a map designating and delineating the area of future growth and development of each city and village pursuant to section 23-3610, the urbanizing area planning commission shall assume jurisdiction of any matter within the jurisdiction of a county planning commission under sections 23-114 to 23-114.05, 23-168.01 to 23-168.04, 23-172 to 23-174, 23-174.02, 23-373, and 23-376 which arises from the application of an owner of real property seeking approval from the county to subdivide, plat, or lay out the real property in building lots, any of which are intended for use in whole or in part for the construction of structures to be used for any residential purposes, for which the owner has indicated his or her intent to seek approval for the eventual connection to the county sewerage disposal system and plant or plants developed under the provisions of the County Industrial Sewer Construction Act. The jurisdiction of the urbanizing area planning commission is restricted to such portions of the areas of future growth and development of the cities and villages as are outside of their areas of formal jurisdiction for zoning and platting purposes. All powers, duties, responsibilities, and functions of the county planning commission shall be assumed and exercised by the urbanizing area planning commission with regard to matters within its jurisdiction as defined by the act. Actions of the urbanizing area planning commission taken with regard to matters arising within the area of its jurisdiction shall be treated for all purposes as if made by the county planning commission.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 33. </para></source></law></legaldoc>