<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id22">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government and Officers" id="id24" statutenumber="23-3502"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3502</statuteno><catchline id="id27">Board of trustees;
membership; vacancy; county
board serve as board of trustees; terms; removal.</catchline>
<para>(1) When a county with a population
of three thousand six hundred inhabitants or
more and less than two hundred thousand inhabitants or with a taxable value
of the taxable property of twenty-eight million six hundred thousand dollars
or more establishes a facility as provided by section 23-3501, the county board of
the county shall appoint a board of trustees.</para>
<para>(2) In counties having
a population of two hundred thousand inhabitants or more, the county board
of the county having a facility, in lieu of appointing a board of trustees
of such facility, may elect to serve as the board of trustees of such facility.
If the county board makes such election, the county board shall assume all
the duties and responsibilities of the board of trustees of the facility,
including those set forth in sections 23-3504 and 23-3505. Such election shall
be evidenced by the adoption of a resolution by the county board.</para>
<para>(3)(a) The board of trustees appointed pursuant to this
section shall consist of three, five, seven,
or nine members as fixed by the county board.</para>
<para>(b) When the board is first established:</para>
<para>(i) If the county provides for a three-member
board, one member shall be appointed for a term of two years,
one for four years, and one for six years from the date such
member is appointed.
Thereafter, as the members' terms expire, members shall be appointed for terms
of six years;</para>
<para>(ii) If
the county board provides for a five-member board, one additional member shall
be appointed for four years and one for six years. If the
board is changed to a five-member board, the three members who are serving
as such trustees at the time of a change from a three-member to a five-member
board shall each complete his or her respective term of office. The two additional
members shall be appointed by the county board, one for a term of four years
and one for a term of six years. Thereafter, as the
members' terms expire, members shall be appointed for terms of
six years;</para>
<para>(iii) If
the county board provides for a seven-member board, one additional member
shall be appointed for two years and one for four years. If the
board is changed to a seven-member board, the three or five members who are
serving as such trustees at the time of the change shall each complete his
or her respective term of office. The two or four additional members shall
be appointed by the county board. If two additional members are appointed,
one shall be appointed for four years and one for six years. If four additional
members are appointed, one shall be appointed for two years, two for four
years, and one for six years. Thereafter,
as the members' terms expire, members shall be appointed for terms of six
years; and</para>
<para>(iv) If the
county board provides for a nine-member board, one additional member shall
be appointed for two years and one for six years. If the board is changed
to a nine-member board, the three, five, or seven members who are serving
as such trustees at the time of the change shall each complete his or her
respective term of office. The two, four, or six additional members shall
be appointed by the county board. If two additional members are appointed,
one shall be appointed for two years and one for six years. If four additional
members are appointed, two shall be appointed for two years, one for four
years, and one for six years. If six additional members are appointed, two
shall be appointed for two years, two for four years, and two for six years.
Thereafter, as the members' terms expire, members shall be appointed for terms
of six years.</para><para>(4)(a) All members of the board of trustees shall be residents of
the county.</para><para>(b) In
any county having a population of more than three hundred thousand inhabitants,
a minimum of one member of the board of trustees shall reside
outside the corporate limits of the city in which such facility or facilities
are located. In any county having a population of more than three hundred
thousand inhabitants, if only one member of the board of trustees resides
outside the corporate limits of the city in which the facility is located and the residence
of the member is annexed by the city, he or she shall be allowed to complete
his or her term of office but shall not be eligible for reappointment.</para>
<para>(c) The trustees shall, within
ten days after their appointment, qualify by taking the oath of county officers as provided in section 11-101 and
by furnishing a bond, if required
by the county board, in an amount to be fixed by the county board.</para>
<para>(d) Any person who has been excluded from participation
in a federally funded health care program or is included in a federal exclusionary
data base shall be ineligible to serve as a trustee.</para>
<para>(5) The board of trustees shall elect
a trustee to serve as chairperson, one as secretary, and one as
treasurer. The board shall
make such elections at each annual board meeting.</para>
<para>(6)(a) When a member is absent from
three consecutive board meetings, either
regular or special, without
being excused by the remaining members of the board, his or her office shall
become vacant and a new member shall be appointed by the county board to fill
the vacancy for the unexpired term of such member pursuant to subdivision (6)(b) of this section.</para>
<para>(b) Any member of such board may at any time be removed from
office by the county board for
any reason. Vacancies shall be filled in substantially the same
manner as the original appointments are made. The person appointed to fill
such a vacancy shall hold office for the unexpired term of the member that he or she has replaced.</para>
<para>(7) The county board shall
consult with the existing board of trustees regarding the skills and qualifications
of any potential appointees to the board pursuant to this section prior to
appointing any new trustee.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 44, &#167; 2, p. 208; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 53, &#167; 1, p. 185; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 64, &#167; 2, p. 284; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 113, &#167; 3, p. 443; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 114, &#167; 2, p. 447; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 121, &#167; 2, p. 386; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 293, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 481, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 103; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 685, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 260, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 703, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 134, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 122, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1991, &#167; 23-343.01; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 212, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1062, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB995, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>April 6, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>