<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-3107"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3107</statuteno><catchline>County board or purchasing agent; administrative duties.</catchline><para>The county board or purchasing agent, subject to the approval of the county board, shall: (1) Prescribe the manner in which personal property shall be purchased, delivered, and distributed; (2) prescribe dates for making estimates, the future period which they are to cover, the form in which they are submitted, and the manner of their authentication; (3) revise forms from time to time as conditions warrant; (4) provide for the transfer to and between county departments and agencies of personal property which is surplus with one department or agency but which may be needed by another or others; (5) dispose of by sale personal property which has been declared by the county board to be surplus and which is obsolete or not usable by the county. Such property with a value of less than two thousand five hundred dollars may be sold without competitive bidding. Property with a value of two thousand five hundred dollars or more shall be sold through competitive bidding; (6) prescribe the amount of cash deposit or bond to be submitted with a bid on a contract and the amount of deposit or bond to be given for the performance of a contract, if the amount of the bond is not specifically provided by law; and (7) prescribe the manner in which claims for personal property or services delivered to any department or agency of the county shall be submitted, approved, and paid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 6, p. 228; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-324.04; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-324.04; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 393, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 828, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 41, &#167; 2. </para></source></law></legaldoc>