<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id82">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id84" statutenumber="23-3508"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3508</statuteno><catchline id="id87">County board;
bonds; purpose;
terms; levy; limitation; procedure
to exceed.</catchline><para>(1) The county board in
counties in this state in which a facility has been established as provided in section
23-3501 may, by a majority vote of the board, issue and sell bonds of the
county in such sums as the county board may deem advisable to defray the cost
of improvements or additions thereto, equipment, and other property deemed necessary for operation of the
facility.</para>
<para>(2) Such
bonds shall (a) be payable in not to exceed thirty years after the
date of issuance, (b) bear interest payable annually or semiannually, and
(c) contain an option to the county to pay all or any part thereof at any
time after five years after the date of issuance.
When such bonds have been issued under this section or section 23-3501, the
county board shall cause to be levied and collected annually a tax upon all
of the taxable property of such county sufficient to pay the interest and
principal of the bonds as the interest and principal become
due and payable. If the county
board deems it appropriate, the county board may submit to the electors of
such county at a general or special election the question of whether to exceed
the tax limitation set forth in Article VIII, section 5, of the Constitution
of Nebraska or any other applicable statutory levy limitation.</para>
<para>(3) Any taxes
levied to pay bonds issued under this section or section 23-3501 shall be
kept in a separate fund in the county treasury. Any such bonds shall not be
deemed to be payable from the general fund of the county.</para>
<para>(4) This section
shall not apply to any bond or other indebtedness authorized by the board
of trustees pursuant to section 23-3504.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 44, &#167; 8, p. 210; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 38, &#167; 2, p. 131; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 114, &#167; 8, p. 451; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 121, &#167; 8, p. 390; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 157, &#167; 1, p. 729; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 51, &#167; 83, p. 327; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 560, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 798, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1991, &#167; 23-343.07; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB995, &#167; 6.</para></source><annotation><para>Two alternative methods of defraying the cost of improvements or additions are provided. Armstrong v. Board of Supervisors of Kearney County, 153 Neb. 858, 46 N.W.2d 602 (1951).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>