<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-3504"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3504</statuteno><catchline>Board of trustees; bylaws, rules, and regulations, adopt; facility funds; improvements and equipment; control; powers.</catchline><para>The board of trustees of such facility as provided by section 23-3501 shall make, adopt, and file with the county board such bylaws, rules, and regulations for its guidance and for the government of such facility as may be deemed expedient for the economical and equitable conduct of the facility. The board of trustees shall have the exclusive control of the expenditures of all money collected to the credit of the fund for such facility. After the original construction of such facility, the board of trustees shall have exclusive control over any and all improvements or additions thereto and equipment, including the authority to contract, subject to ratification by the county board, for any improvements or additions thereto and equipment. No such improvement, addition, or equipment shall cost more than fifty percent of the current replacement cost of such existing facility and equipment unless the proposition is submitted to the voters of such county at a general election or a special election called for such purpose and approved by a vote of the majority of the electors voting on the proposition at such election. The board of trustees shall also have exclusive control, supervision, care, and custody of the grounds, rooms, and buildings purchased, constructed, leased, or set apart for such purposes. The board of trustees shall have power to pay all current bills, claims, and salaries of all employees of such facility by an order upon its treasurer, signed by the superintendent of such facility and countersigned by the chairperson and secretary of the board of trustees. Facsimile signatures of the superintendent and board members may be used to sign such orders. The board of trustees shall have power to lease such facility and equipment to a charitable nonprofit organization upon such terms and conditions as may be agreed, but no such facility or equipment shall be leased unless authorized by the voters of such county at a general election or a special election called for such purpose and approved by a majority vote of the electors voting on such proposition at any such election. The board of trustees shall also have the following powers: (1) To expend hospital operating funds for the reimbursement of the reasonable expenses of persons interviewed or retained for employment or medical staff appointment; and (2) all powers and authority granted to the boards of nonprofit corporations under the Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act, except to the extent that those powers are inconsistent with the Hospital Authorities Act, the Nebraska Local Hospital District Act, and sections 23-3501 to 23-3527 or are specifically prohibited by law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1945, c. 44, &#167; 4, p. 209; </para><para>Laws 1949, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 130; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 50, &#167; 1, p. 168; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 114, &#167; 4, p. 449; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 102, &#167; 1, p. 424; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 121, &#167; 4, p. 388; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 171, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 260, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 798, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1991, &#167; 23-343.03; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 366, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 681, &#167; 193. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Hospital Authorities Act,</emphasis> see section 23-3579.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Local Hospital District Act,</emphasis> see section 23-3528.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Nonprofit Corporation Act,</emphasis> see section 21-1901.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Cost of improvements or additions is limited to fifty percent of original cost. Armstrong v. Board of Supervisors of Kearney County, 153 Neb. 858, 46 N.W.2d 602 (1951).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>