<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id311" statutenumber="23-3526"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3526</statuteno><catchline id="id314">Retirement plan; authorized; reports.</catchline><para>(1) The board of trustees of each facility, as provided by section 23-3501, shall, upon approval of the county board, have the power and authority to establish and fund a retirement plan for the benefit of its full-time employees. The plan may be funded by any actuarially recognized method approved by the county board. Employees participating in the plan may be required to contribute toward funding the benefits. The facility shall pay all costs of establishing and maintaining the plan. The plan may be integrated with old age and survivor's insurance.</para><para>(2) Beginning December 31, 1998, through December 31, 2017:</para><para>(a) The chairperson of the board of trustees of a facility with a retirement plan established pursuant to this section and section 401(a) of the Internal Revenue Code shall file with the Public Employees Retirement Board an annual report on such plan and shall submit copies of such report to the Auditor of Public Accounts. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. The annual report shall be in a form prescribed by the Public Employees Retirement Board and shall contain the following information for each such retirement plan:</para><para>(i) The number of persons participating in the retirement plan;</para><para>(ii) The contribution rates of participants in the plan;</para><para>(iii) Plan assets and liabilities;</para><para>(iv) The names and positions of persons administering the plan;</para><para>(v) The names and positions of persons investing plan assets;</para><para>(vi) The form and nature of investments;</para><para>(vii) For each defined contribution plan which is not administered by a retirement system under the County Employees Retirement Act, a full description of investment policies and options available to plan participants; and</para><para>(viii) For each defined benefit plan which is not administered by a retirement system under the County Employees Retirement Act, the levels of benefits of participants in the plan, the number of members who are eligible for a benefit, and the total present value of such members' benefits, as well as the funding sources which will pay for such benefits.</para><para>If a plan which is not administered by a retirement system under the County Employees Retirement Act contains no current active participants, the chairperson may file in place of such report a statement with the Public Employees Retirement Board indicating the number of retirees still drawing benefits, and the sources and amount of funding for such benefits; and</para><para>(b) If such retirement plan is a defined benefit plan which was open to new members on January 1, 2004, in addition to the reports required by section 13-2402, the board of trustees shall cause to be prepared an annual report for each retirement plan which is not administered by a retirement system under the County Employees Retirement Act, and the chairperson shall file the same with the Public Employees Retirement Board and the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee of the Legislature and submit to the Auditor of Public Accounts a copy of such report. The Auditor of Public Accounts may prepare a review of such report pursuant to section 84-304.02 but is not required to do so. If the board of trustees does not submit a copy of the report to the Auditor of Public Accounts within six months after the end of the plan year, the Auditor of Public Accounts may audit, or cause to be audited, the facility. All costs of the audit shall be paid by the facility. The report shall consist of a full actuarial analysis of each such retirement plan established pursuant to this section which is not administered by a retirement system under the County Employees Retirement Act. The analysis shall be prepared by an independent private organization or public entity employing actuaries who are members in good standing of the American Academy of Actuaries, and which organization or entity has demonstrated expertise to perform this type of analysis and is unrelated to any organization offering investment advice or which provides investment management services to the retirement plan. The report to the Nebraska Retirement Systems Committee shall be submitted electronically.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1977, LB 346, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 23-343.121; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 795, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB474, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB759, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB415, &#167; 17. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County Employees Retirement Act,</emphasis> see section 23-2331.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>