
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3806"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3806</statuteno><catchline>Notices for management of colonies; form; publication; hearing; failure to comply with notice; powers of county board; costs; lien; appeal.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Notices for management of colonies shall consist of two kinds: General notice and individual notices, which notices shall be on a form prescribed by this section.</para><para>(b) General notice shall be published by the county board of each county that has adopted a coordinated program for the management of black-tailed prairie dogs under section 23-3803 in one or more newspapers of general circulation in the county on or before May 1 of each year or at such other times as the county board may determine.</para><para>(c) Whenever any county board of a county that has adopted a coordinated program for the management of black-tailed prairie dogs under section 23-3803 finds that a colony, or any portion of a colony, has expanded onto adjacent property and the owner of the adjacent property objects to such expansion and the county board determines that it is necessary to secure more prompt or definite management of a colony than is accomplished by the general published notice, it shall cause to be served individual notice, upon the owner of record of the property upon which the colony is located, by certified mail at his or her last-known address, of recommended methods of when and how black-tailed prairie dogs are to be managed.</para><para>(d) The county board shall use the following form for all individual notices:</para><para> .......... County Board</para><para>OFFICIAL NOTICE</para><para>Information received by the county board, including from an onsite investigation, indicates the existence of an unmanaged black-tailed prairie dog colony on property owned by you at: ................................. . The method of management recommended by the county board is as follows: ................................................ . Other appropriate management methods are acceptable if approved by the county board.</para><para>State law specifies a duty of each person who owns or controls property within a county that has adopted a coordinated program for the management of black-tailed prairie dogs under section 23-3803 to manage black-tailed prairie dog colonies present upon his or her property to prevent the expansion of colonies to adjacent property unless the owner of the adjacent property waives objection in writing to such expansion. You must provide notice and evidence to the county board within sixty days after the date specified at the bottom of this notice that appropriate management as specified in this notice, or alternative management that is approved by the board, has been initiated. If services for the management of black-tailed prairie dogs are not available within the sixty-day period specified in this notice, you may satisfy this notice by providing evidence that you have arranged for management to occur when available. If such notice and evidence are not received by the county board within sixty days after the date specified at the bottom of this notice, the county board or its agent may enter upon your property for the purpose of taking the appropriate management measures. Costs for the management activities performed by the county board shall be at the expense of the owner of the property and shall become a lien on the property.</para><para>If the county board receives a written request from you within fifteen days after the date specified at the bottom of this notice, you are entitled to a hearing before the county board to challenge this notice.</para><para>County Board</para><para>Dated ................... </para><para>(2) Upon the written request of any landowner served with an individual notice pursuant to subsection (1) of this section received within fifteen days after the date specified by such notice, the county board shall hold an informal public hearing to allow such landowner an opportunity to address the county board's notice.</para><para>(3) Following the hearing, the county board may affirm, modify, or rescind such notice. If, upon expiration of the sixty-day period specified on the notice required by subdivision (1)(d) of this section, the landowner has not complied with the notice and has not requested a hearing pursuant to subsection (2) of this section, the county board may cause proper management methods to be used on such property and shall advise the record landowner of the cost incurred in connection with such operation. The cost of any such management shall be at the expense of the landowner.</para><para>(4) Amounts collected under this section shall be deposited to the black-tailed prairie dog management fund of the county board if such fund has been created by the county board or, if no such fund has been created, then to the county general fund.</para><para>(5) Any action of the county board taken pursuant to this section may be appealed to any court having jurisdiction.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB473, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB805, &#167; 11. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>