<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3630"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3630</statuteno><catchline>Owners of real property; subdivide or plat property; connection to system or plant; duty to inform; failure to inform; effect; county board; duties.</catchline><para>After the county board formally adopts its resolution of intent to develop a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants pursuant to section 23-3605, any owner of real property seeking approval from the county to subdivide, plat, or lay out the real property in building lots, any of which are intended for use in whole or in part for the construction of structures to be used for any residential purpose, shall at the time of application for approval inform the county if the owner intends to seek approval for connection of such lots or any proposed structures on them to a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants constructed under the County Industrial Sewer Construction Act. Any owner failing to inform the county of his or her intent to seek approval for connection to the sewerage disposal system or plant or plants at the time of application for a plat shall be barred from applying for a connection to the sewerage disposal system and plant or plants for any lot or any structure used for any residential purpose on such platted lots for a period of three years from the date such plat was finally approved and recorded. Such bar shall extend to any successor in interest of such owner in the platted lots during the same period of time. During the period between the date of adoption of the county board's resolution of intent to develop a sewerage disposal system and plant or plants and the date upon which the county board formally adopts a map designating and delineating the area of future growth and development of each city and village in the county pursuant to section 23-3610, the county board shall not approve any application for the platting of any territory whose owner has indicated an intent to seek approval for the eventual connection to the sewerage disposal system and plant or plants of any lots or any structures placed on such lots to be used for residential purposes. Such applications shall be treated as if filed on the date upon which the county board formally adopts a map designating and delineating the area of future growth and development of each city and village in the county pursuant to section 23-3610.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 30. </para></source></law></legaldoc>