<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government and Officers" statutenumber="23-3610"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3610</statuteno><catchline>Public hearing; adoption of map; disputed area; county board; duties.</catchline><para>(1) The county board shall hold a public hearing on each disputed area pursuant to such notice as set out in section 23-3609. Within fifteen days after the completion of such public hearings, the county board shall formally adopt a map designating and delineating the boundaries of the area of future growth and development of each city or village within the county.</para><para>(2) Over all territory regarding which there is no dispute between any cities or villages as to inclusion in their respective areas of future growth and development, the county board shall accept the recommended delineations of the cities and villages and incorporate them without amendment into its formal map.</para><para>(3) When any cities or villages involved in a dispute over the inclusion of territory within their respective areas of future growth and development reach an agreement on the allocation of the disputed territory and inform the county board of such agreement prior to the board's final action to adopt a formal map, the county board shall accept the agreement on the allocation and incorporate the agreed-upon delineation without amendment into its formal map.</para><para>(4) In determining any disputes on the allocation of territory not otherwise resolved by agreement between disputing cities and villages and in making its formal delineations with regard to such territory, the county board shall base its decision on the relative likelihood of the disputed area coming within the jurisdiction of the cities or villages for zoning or platting purposes based on (a) growth and land development patterns and (b) documented population and economic growth trends. The county board shall place the disputed area within the area of future growth and development of the city or village which would, based upon such factors, be the most likely city or village to first assume jurisdiction over such territory for zoning or platting purposes.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1994, LB 1139, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>