<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-35,120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-35,120</statuteno><catchline>Hospital authority; bonds; holders; contract with state; powers.</catchline><para>(1) The State of Nebraska covenants and agrees with the holders of bonds issued by an authority that the state will not limit or alter the rights vested by sections 23-3579 to 23-35,120 in an authority to acquire, maintain, construct, reconstruct, and operate hospitals; to establish and collect such rates, rentals, charges, and fees as may be convenient or necessary to produce sufficient revenue to meet the expense of maintenance and operation of such hospitals and to fulfill the terms of any agreements made with holders of bonds of the authority. The state will also not in any way impair the rights and remedies of the bondholders until the bonds together with interest thereon and with interest on any unpaid installments of interest, and all costs and expenses in connection with any action or proceedings by or on behalf of the bondholders, are fully met and discharged. The provisions of sections 23-3579 to 23-35,120 and of the proceedings authorizing bonds thereby shall constitute a contract with the holders of said bonds.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding any other provision of the Hospital Authorities Act to the contrary, in addition to any other powers which an authority has, an authority may engage in the financing of any hospital or the refinancing of any indebtedness incurred to finance a hospital, whether or not incurred prior to or after March 27, 1979, by issuing its bonds pursuant to a plan of financing involving an acquisition or commitment to acquire or use any federally guaranteed security or securities and may enter into any agreement which it deems necessary or desirable in order to effectuate any such plan. For the purposes of this section, federally guaranteed security shall mean any direct obligation of the United States of America or any obligation the payment of principal of and interest on which are fully or partially guaranteed by the United States of America, whether or not secured by other collateral, and shall include, without limitation, any security guaranteed by the Government National Mortgage Association under section 306(g) of the National Housing Act, 12 U.S.C. 1721(g). The provisions of section 23-35,113, shall not apply in the case of any such financing or refinancing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 54, &#167; 47; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 441, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 23-343.120. </para></source></law></legaldoc>