<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3595"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3595</statuteno><catchline>Hospital authority; board of trustees; duties.</catchline><para>All hospitals operated directly by an authority and not operated or leased as lessee by a nonprofit person, firm, partnership, limited liability company, association, or corporation shall be operated by the board of trustees of such authority according to the best interests of the public health, and the board of trustees shall make and enforce all rules, regulations, and bylaws necessary for the administration, government, protection, and maintenance of such hospitals and all property belonging thereto and may prescribe the terms upon which patients may be admitted thereto. Such hospitals shall not be required to contract with counties or with agencies thereof to provide care for indigent county patients at below the cost for care. In fixing the basic room rates for such hospitals, the board of trustees shall establish such basic room rates as will, together with other income and revenue available for such purpose and however derived, permit each such hospital to be operated upon a self-supporting basis. In establishing basic room rates for such hospital, the board of trustees shall give due consideration to at least the following factors: Costs of administration, operation, and maintenance of such hospitals; the cost of making necessary repairs and renewals thereto; debt service requirements; the creation of reserves for contingencies; and projected needs for expansion and for the making of major improvements. Minimum standards of operation for such hospitals, at least equal to those set by the Department of Health and Human Services, shall be established and enforced by the board of trustees.</para><para>In the case of hospitals financed with the proceeds of bonds issued by an authority, but not operated directly by an authority, the board of trustees shall require that the financing documents contain covenants of the operators of such hospitals to establish rates at least sufficient to pay costs of administration, operation, and maintenance of such hospitals, the cost of making necessary repairs and renewals thereto, and to provide for debt service requirements, the creation of reserves for contingencies, and projected needs for expansion and the making of major improvements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1971, LB 54, &#167; 20; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1382, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 801, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 23-343.93; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 165; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 58; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB296, &#167; 25.</para></source></law></legaldoc>