
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3211" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3211</statuteno><catchline>Law enforcement officer, Nebraska National Guard member, or judge; residential address; withheld from public; application; form; county assessor and register of deeds; duty.</catchline><para>(1) Unless requested in writing, the county assessor and register of deeds shall withhold from the public the residential address of a law enforcement officer, a member of the Nebraska National Guard acting pursuant to subdivision (3) of section 55-182, or a judge who applies to the county assessor in the county of his or her residence. The application shall be in a form prescribed by the county assessor and shall include the applicant's name and address and the parcel identification number for his or her residential address. A law enforcement officer shall include in the application his or her law enforcement identification number. A member of the Nebraska National Guard shall include in the application proof of his or her status as a member, in a manner prescribed by the county assessor. A judge shall include in the application the name of the specific court of which he or she is a judge. The county assessor shall notify the register of deeds regarding the receipt of a complete application. The county assessor and the register of deeds shall withhold the address of a law enforcement officer, member of the Nebraska National Guard, or judge who complies with this section for five years after receipt of a complete application. The officer, member, or judge may renew his or her application every five years upon submission of an updated application.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, judge includes the judge or magistrate judge of any court located in this state, including any county court, any district court, the Court of Appeals, the Nebraska Workers' Compensation Court, any separate juvenile court, the Supreme Court, and any federal court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2017, LB624, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB152, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB1178, &#167; 1. </para><effectivedate>July 21, 2022</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>