<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3113</statuteno><catchline>Purchasing agent or staff; financial interest prohibited; penalty; county board; limitation.</catchline><para>(1) Neither the county purchasing agent nor any member of his or her office staff, if any, shall be financially interested in or have any personal beneficial interest, either directly or indirectly, in any contract or purchase order for any personal property or services used by or furnished to any office, officer, department, or agency of the county government, nor shall such purchasing agent or a member of his or her staff, if any, receive directly or indirectly, from any person, firm, or corporation to which any contract or purchase order may be awarded, by rebate, gift, or otherwise, any money, anything of value whatsoever, or any promise, obligation, or contract for future reward or compensation. Any county purchasing agent or any member of his or her office staff, if any, who violates any of the provisions of the County Purchasing Act shall, upon conviction thereof, be guilty of a Class IV felony. All contracts or agreements in violation of this section are declared unlawful and shall be wholly void as an obligation against the county.</para><para>(2) If there is no purchasing agent, the county board acting pursuant to the County Purchasing Act shall be subject to section 49-14,103.01.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 9, p. 230; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-324.07; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 370, &#167; 15; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-324.07; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 393, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 548, &#167; 10. </para></source></law></legaldoc>