<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3519"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3519</statuteno><catchline>Adjoining counties; certification of taxes; levy; limitation; disposition of proceeds.</catchline><para>The board of trustees of any such facility organized under section 23-3515 shall, each year, fix the amount of money for the proposed budget statement as may be deemed sufficient and necessary for the operation of such facility during the following calendar year. After the adoption of the budget statement and on or before July 15 of each year, the board of trustees of such facility shall certify to the county board of the county in which such facility is located the amount of the tax which may be levied under the facility's adopted budget statement to be received from taxation. Such county board may apportion such amount among the counties concerned in proportion to the taxable valuation of all taxable property and shall certify to each county its share of such amount.</para><para>Each county may levy a tax sufficient to raise the amount so certified to it, and the county treasurer shall transmit the proceeds of such tax to the treasurer of the county in which such facility is located for credit to the facility fund.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 64, &#167; 7, p. 287; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 114, &#167; 17, p. 456; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 121, &#167; 16, p. 394; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 145, &#167; 28, p. 689; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 9, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 107; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 798, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1991, &#167; 23-343.19; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 114; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1240, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 366, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1085, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1114, &#167; 49.</para></source></law></legaldoc>