
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="County Government And Officers" id="id5" statutenumber="23-3104"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3104</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Terms, defined.</catchline><para>As used in the County Purchasing Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</para><para>(1) Mobile equipment means all vehicles propelled by any power other than muscular, including, but not limited to, motor vehicles, off-road designed vehicles, motorcycles, passenger cars, self-propelled mobile homes, truck-tractors, trucks, cabin trailers, semitrailers, trailers, utility trailers, and road and general-purpose construction and maintenance machinery not designed or used primarily for the transportation of persons or property, including, but not limited to, ditchdigging apparatus, asphalt spreaders, bucket loaders, leveling graders, earthmoving carryalls, power shovels, earthmoving equipment, and crawler tractors;</para><para>(2) Personal property includes, but is not limited to, supplies, materials, mobile equipment, and equipment used by or furnished to any county officer, office, department, institution, board, or other agency of the county government. Personal property does not include election ballots;</para><para>(3) Services means any and all services except telephone, telegraph, postal, and electric light and power service, other similar services, and election contractual services; and</para><para>(4) Purchasing or purchase means the obtaining of personal property or services by sale, lease, or other contractual means. Purchase also includes contracting with sheltered workshops for products or services as provided in Chapter 48, article 15. Purchasing or purchase does not include any purchase or lease of personal property or services by a facility established under section 23-3501 or by or on behalf of a county coroner.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 57, &#167; 5, p. 228; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 23-324.03; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1983), &#167; 23-324.03; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 393, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 602, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 828, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 41, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB628, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB995, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB458, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>