<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="County Government And Officers" statutenumber="23-3530"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>23-3530</statuteno><catchline>Hospital districts; petition; contents; signatures required; valuation required.</catchline><para>Whenever the formation of a local hospital district is desired, a petition stating (1) the name of the proposed district, (2) the location of the hospital to be maintained by such proposed district, and (3) the territory to be included within it, which territory should be contiguous, may be presented to the county board of the county in which the land or a greater portion of the land in the proposed district is situated. Such petitions shall be signed by at least ten percent of the resident freeholders whose names appear on the current tax schedules in the office of the county assessor and who appear to reside within the suggested boundaries of the proposed district. The minimum taxable valuation of all taxable property within such proposed district shall be eight million six hundred thousand dollars. Parts of a voting precinct may be included in the proposed district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 83, &#167; 2, p. 375; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 115, &#167; 1, p. 458; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 103, &#167; 1, p. 426; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 108; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1987), &#167; 23-343.21; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 115. </para></source><annotation><para>County board in which the land or greater portion of land in proposed district is appropriate tribunal to determine if lands have been properly included. Syfie v. Tri-County Hospital Dist., 186 Neb. 478, 184 N.W.2d 398 (1971).</para><para>Harm from fractionating territories of counties under this section insufficient to constitute violation of Article I, section 25, or Article VIII, section 1, Constitution of Nebraska. Shadbolt v. County of Cherry, 185 Neb. 208, 174 N.W.2d 733 (1970).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>