<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-701"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-701</statuteno><catchline>Joinder of claims.</catchline><para>A party asserting a claim to relief as an original claim, counterclaim, cross-claim, or third-party claim may join, either as independent or as alternate claims, as many claims, legal or equitable, as the party has against an opposing party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 87, p. 407; </para><para>Laws 1867, &#167; 3, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7657; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8601; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-701; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-701; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 234, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Same transaction</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Contracts</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Trustees</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Recovery of property</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Other actions</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Same transaction</emphasis></para><para>For application of res judicata a petition in quantum meruit is a restatement of the earlier cause of action on express contract where both petitions are based on same services. Vantage Enterprises, Inc. v. Caldwell, 196 Neb. 671, 244 N.W.2d 678 (1976).</para><para>Damages for loss of possession of lease and loss of crops could be joined. Dinkel v. Hagedorn, 156 Neb. 419, 56 N.W.2d 464 (1953).</para><para>In suit to enjoin nuisance, damages may be recovered. Brchan v. The Crete Mills, 155 Neb. 505, 52 N.W.2d 333 (1952).</para><para>Plaintiff may unite a cause of action growing out of breach of promise to marry, and another in damages for seduction, where both causes arise out of the same transaction. Ryan v. Oswald, 134 Neb. 265, 278 N.W. 508 (1938).</para><para>Malicious prosecution and false imprisonment arising out of same transaction may be joined. Scott v. Flowers, 60 Neb. 675, 84 N.W. 81 (1900).</para><para>Causes of action in tort, all growing out of and connected with the same transaction, may be joined. Dinges v. Riggs, 43 Neb. 710, 62 N.W. 74 (1895).</para><para><emphasis>2. Contracts</emphasis></para><para>Amendment of petition allowed to include action in quantum meruit with action on express contract. Associated Wrecking v. Wiekhorst Bros., 228 Neb. 764, 424 N.W.2d 343 (1988).</para><para>Agreement to pay principal of debt at one time and interest thereon at another gives rise to separate causes of action which plaintiff may join or not at his pleasure. Peters v. Meyer, 131 Neb. 847, 270 N.W. 312 (1936).</para><para>Action on quantum meruit may be joined with action on express contract. Stout v. Omaha, L. &amp; B. Ry. Co., 97 Neb. 816, 151 N.W. 295 (1915).</para><para>Action to foreclose mortgage and on unsecured note cannot be joined. McCague Sav. Bank v. Croft, 80 Neb. 702, 115 N.W. 315 (1908).</para><para>Action to foreclose mortgage and for deficiency judgment may be joined. Commercial Nat. Bank of Omaha v. Grant, 73 Neb. 435, 103 N.W. 68 (1905).</para><para>Action to correct official bond and for damages for breach of bond may be joined. Stewart v. Carter, 4 Neb. 564 (1876).</para><para><emphasis>3. Trustees</emphasis></para><para>Action to enforce trust agreement under which defendant purchased plaintiff's property at judicial sale, and action based upon alleged invalidity of sale may be joined. Williams v. Lowe, 4 Neb. 382 (1876).</para><para><emphasis>4. Recovery of property</emphasis></para><para>Under prior law, under subsection (6) of this section, plaintiff may seek rents and profits in an ejectment action. Wicker v. Waldemath, 238 Neb. 515, 471 N.W.2d 731 (1991).</para><para>Action for conversion of corporate assets may be joined with one for statutory liability of stockholders on account of failure to publish notice of amount of corporate indebtedness. Malm v. Stock, 99 Neb. 374, 156 N.W. 656 (1916).</para><para>Action by stockholder to enforce lien for money ordered paid by court in setting aside fraudulent conveyance to officers, and for appointment of receiver may be joined. Ponca Mill Co. v. Mikesell, 55 Neb. 98, 75 N.W. 46 (1898).</para><para>Actions to recover illegal fees and for statutory penalty were joinable. Phoenix Ins. Co. v. King, 52 Neb. 562, 72 N.W. 855 (1897).</para><para>Ejectment and action for rents and profits may be joined. Fletcher v. Brown, 35 Neb. 660, 53 N.W. 577 (1892); Harrall v. Gray, 12 Neb. 543, 11 N.W. 851 (1882).</para><para><emphasis>5. Other actions</emphasis></para><para>Causes of action involving different defendants cannot be joined unless each cause affects all defendants and they have a joint or common liability or interest. Gould v. Orr, 244 Neb. 163, 506 N.W.2d 349 (1993); S.I.D. No. 272 of Douglas County v. Marquardt, 233 Neb. 39, 443 N.W.2d 877 (1989).</para><para>Under the provisions of sections 25-701 and 25-702, R.R.S.1943, the joinder in a single action of the cause against an uninsured motorist with the insurer carrying the uninsured motorist coverage for the claimant is not permissible. Eich v. State Farm Mut. Automobile Ins. Co., 208 Neb. 714, 305 N.W.2d 621 (1981).</para><para>If the plaintiff does not choose to unite several causes of action in one petition and the defendant does not successfully require joinder, there is no legal requirement that distinct causes of action be joined in one suit. Suhr v. City of Scribner, 207 Neb. 24, 295 N.W.2d 302 (1980).</para><para>Plaintiff cannot join an individual cause of action with a representative cause of action. Niklaus v. Abel Construction Co., 164 Neb. 842, 83 N.W.2d 904 (1957).</para><para>Causes of action under the Fair Labor Standards Act may be united in one action. Archer v. Musick, 147 Neb. 1018, 25 N.W.2d 908 (1947).</para><para>Cause which might have been joined may be added by amendment. Freeman v. Webb, 21 Neb. 160, 31 N.W. 656 (1887).</para><para>Actions against the principal and sureties on separate bonds for a default of the official occurring after the execution of the second bond may be properly joined. Holeran v. School Dist. No. 17, Adams County, 10 Neb. 406, 6 N.W. 472 (1880).</para><para>Damages for breach of covenant and for quiet enjoyment of lease may be joined. Herpolsheimer v. Funke, 1 Neb. Unof. 471, 95 N.W. 688 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>