<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-204"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-204</statuteno><catchline>Actions other than for the recovery of real property.</catchline><para>Civil actions, other than for the recovery of real property, can only be brought within the following periods, after the cause of action shall have accrued.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 9, p. 395; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7566; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8509; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-204; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-204.</para></source><annotation><para>Cause of action to establish right to pension accrued at time fireman was totally and permanently disabled. Barney v. City of Lincoln, 144 Neb. 537, 13 N.W.2d 870 (1944).</para><para>Cause of action "accrued" when buyer acknowledged and promised to pay balance. W. T. Rawleigh Co. v. Smith, 142 Neb. 527, 7 N.W.2d 80 (1942).</para><para>Action by a husband for damages on account of assault and battery committed on wife must be brought within one year after cause of action occurred. Markel v. Glassmeyer, 137 Neb. 243, 288 N.W. 821 (1939).</para><para>The defense of statute of limitations is personal privilege of debtor, and can only be made by persons standing in his place. Neill v. Burke, 81 Neb. 125, 115 N.W. 321 (1908).</para><para>When not apparent on face of petition that action is barred, statute must be pleaded as a defense, or it is waived. Hanna v. Emerson, 45 Neb. 708, 64 N.W. 229 (1895).</para><para>Time may be extended by part payment or written acknowledgment. Lee, Fried &amp; Co. v. Brugmann, 37 Neb. 232, 55 N.W. 1053 (1893); Rolfe v. Pilloud, 16 Neb. 21, 19 N.W. 615 (1884).</para><para>Promise by one joint debtor will not toll statute as to other joint debtors. Mayberry v. Willoughby, 5 Neb. 368 (1877).</para><para>Under this and other statutes of limitations suit against employer to enforce agreement made in 1893 to deliver corporate stock was barred, in view of lapse of time, change in value, and repudiation of trust. Reed v. Fairmont Creamery Co., 37 F.2d 332 (8th Cir. 1929).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>