<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-401</statuteno><catchline>Local actions involving real estate.</catchline><para>All actions to recover damages for any trespass upon or any injury to real estate shall be brought only in the county where such real estate or some part thereof is situated, but such actions may be brought against corporations owning or operating any line of railroad in the state in any county where service of summons can be had, and all actions for the following causes must be brought in the county in which the subject of the action is situated, except as provided in section 25-402: (1) For the recovery of real property or of an estate or interest therein; (2) for the partition of real property; and (3) for the sale of real property under a mortgage lien or other encumbrance or charge.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 51, p. 401; </para><para>Laws 1889, c. 29, &#167; 1, p. 376; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 167, &#167; 1, p. 543; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7612; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8555; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-401; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-401.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For provisions on designation of defendants,</emphasis> see section 25-312.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Trespass</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Foreclosure</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Damages</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. General</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Trespass</emphasis></para><para>Jurisdiction of action to enjoin trespass on land is vested in district court for county in which land is situated. Fenster v. Isley, 143 Neb. 888, 11 N.W.2d 822 (1943).</para><para>Action for damages for trespass upon real estate can be brought alone in county where lands are located. Jacobson v. Lynn, 54 Neb. 794, 75 N.W. 243 (1898).</para><para><emphasis>2. Foreclosure</emphasis></para><para>Action to foreclose a real estate mortgage must be brought in county where land lies. Boehmer v. Heimen, 138 Neb. 376, 293 N.W. 237 (1940).</para><para>In foreclosure of real estate mortgage, a court having jurisdiction over subject matter, under its broad equity powers, may determine the rights of all persons claiming any interest therein, when properly before it. Department of Banking v. Stenger, 132 Neb. 576, 272 N.W. 403 (1939).</para><para>Action to foreclose real estate mortgage may be brought only in district court sitting in county where mortgaged realty, or some part thereof, is situated. Prudential Ins. Co. v. Bliss, 123 Neb. 578, 243 N.W. 842 (1932).</para><para>Action to establish equitable mortgage on real estate is properly brought in county where land is located. Miles v. Martin, 103 Neb. 261, 171 N.W. 907 (1919).</para><para>Action to foreclose mortgage can only be brought in county where land is situated. Eayrs v. Nason, 54 Neb. 143, 74 N.W. 408 (1898).</para><para><emphasis>3. Damages</emphasis></para><para>Drainage district may be sued to recover damages for injury to real estate in county where real estate or some part thereof is situated. Cooper v. Sanitary Dist. No. 1 of Lancaster County, 146 Neb. 412, 19 N.W.2d 619 (1945).</para><para>Action for damages for injury to realty may be brought only in county where realty is situated. Triplett v. Western Public Service Co., 128 Neb. 835, 260 N.W. 387 (1935).</para><para>Action for damage to land by drainage ditch must be brought in county where land is located. Dryden v. Peru Bottom Drain. Dist., 99 Neb. 837, 158 N.W. 54 (1916).</para><para>Action for injury to land from overflow by negligent construction of bridge is transitory. Omaha &amp; R. V. Ry. Co. v. Brown, 29 Neb. 492, 46 N.W. 39 (1890).</para><para><emphasis>4. General</emphasis></para><para>The district court for the county wherein real estate is situated is not without jurisdiction to hear and determine actions to quiet title to, or partition same. Page v. Buchfinck, 196 Neb. 135, 242 N.W.2d 610 (1976).</para><para>District court has jurisdiction to entertain action to quiet title even though construction of will is required. Hahn v. Verret, 143 Neb. 820, 11 N.W.2d 551 (1943).</para><para>Venue of action to establish that title to land held by plaintiff is held by him in trust, and that the terms of the trust require a sale thereof before an accounting can be had, is the county in which the land lies. Stuckey v. Stuckey, 143 Neb. 610, 10 N.W.2d 458 (1943).</para><para>Mandamus action is properly brought to compel an irrigation district to build a bridge across one of its canals in county where land is, even though irrigation district is situated and has its principal office or place of business in another county. State ex rel. Johnson v. Central Nebraska Public Power &amp; Irr. Dist., 140 Neb. 471, 300 N.W. 379 (1941).</para><para>Where one of two courts having concurrent jurisdiction takes cognizance of a case and thereafter loses jurisdiction over the res, the other is no longer deprived of its right to assume jurisdiction over it. Lincoln Joint Stock Land Bank v. Fuller, 132 Neb. 677, 273 N.W. 14 (1937).</para><para>Accounting suit was properly brought even though it involved real estate situated in another county. Lincoln Safe Deposit Co. v. Yeast, 117 Neb. 344, 220 N.W. 573 (1928).</para><para>Action to contest city bond election and enjoin bonds must be brought in county where election is held. Russell v. City of Indianola, 105 Neb. 207, 179 N.W. 927 (1920).</para><para>Action to quiet title must be brought in county where land lies. Rakow v. Tate, 93 Neb. 198, 140 N.W. 162 (1913).</para><para>Interest includes any right, title or estate in, or lien on land. Johnson v. Samuelson, 82 Neb. 201, 117 N.W. 470 (1908).</para><para>Action by wife to appropriate land of nonresident husband for alimony may be brought where land is. Rhoades v. Rhoades, 78 Neb. 495, 111 N.W. 122 (1907).</para><para>Action of ejectment may be brought against nonresident and service obtained by publication. Lantry v. Parker, 37 Neb. 353, 55 N.W. 962 (1893).</para><para>If action affects title or possession of real estate, action should be brought in county where land lies. Pacific Ry. Co. v. Perkins, 36 Neb. 456, 54 N.W. 845 (1893).</para><para>Service by publication may be had in actions brought under this section where any or all of the defendants reside out of the state. Brown v. Rice, 30 Neb. 236, 46 N.W. 489 (1890).</para><para>This section does not prevent action being brought against railroad in county where it has property or credits, under other provisions of this article. Atchison, T. &amp; S. F. Ry. Co. v. Drayton, 292 F. 15 (8th Cir. 1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>