<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-402"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-402</statuteno><catchline>Local actions involving real estate located in more than one county.</catchline><para>If the real property, the subject of the action, be an entire tract, and situated in two or more counties, or if it consists of separate tracts situated in two or more counties, the action may be brought in any county in which any tract or part thereof is situated, unless it be an action to recover the possession thereof. And if the property be an entire tract, situated in two or more counties, an action to recover the possession thereof may be brought in either of such counties; but if it consists of separate tracts in different counties, the possession of such tracts must be recovered by separate actions brought in the counties where they are situated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 52, p. 401; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7613; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8556; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-402.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For provisions on designation of defendants,</emphasis>  see section 25-312.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The district court for the county wherein real estate is situated is not without jurisdiction to hear and determine actions to quiet title to, or partition same. Page v. Buchfinck, 196 Neb. 135, 242 N.W.2d 610 (1976).</para><para>Where none of the defendants have or claim any interest adverse to plaintiff in the property situated in the county in which the action is brought, the court has no jurisdiction over land of such defendants in another county. Lippincott v. Wolski, 147 Neb. 930, 25 N.W.2d 747 (1947).</para><para>An action to foreclose a mortgage on the entire tract may be brought in any county in which any part thereof is situated. State Bank of Nebraska v. Green &amp; Redick, 11 Neb. 303, 9 N.W. 36 (1881).</para><para> Section is discussed. Atchison, T. &amp; S. F. Ry. Co. v. Drayton, 292 F. 15 (8th Cir. 1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>