<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id48">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id50" statutenumber="25-505.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>25-505.01</statuteno><catchline id="id53">Service of
summons; methods; State Court
Administrator; maintain list.</catchline><para>(1) Unless
otherwise limited by statute or by the court, a plaintiff may elect to have
service made by any of the following methods:</para>
<para>(a) Personal service which shall be made by leaving the summons
with the individual to be served;</para>
<para>(b) Residence service which shall be made by leaving the summons
at the usual place of residence of the individual to be served, with some
person of suitable age and discretion residing therein;</para>
<para>(c) Certified mail service which shall be made by (i) within
ten days of issuance, sending the summons to the defendant by certified mail
with a return receipt requested showing to whom and where delivered and the
date of delivery, and (ii) filing with the court proof of service with the
signed receipt attached; or</para>
<para>(d) Designated
delivery service which shall be made by (i) within ten days of issuance, sending
the summons by a designated delivery service to the defendant, (ii) obtaining
a signed delivery receipt showing to whom and where delivered and the date
of delivery, and (iii) filing with the court proof of service with a copy
of the signed delivery receipt attached. As used in this subdivision, a designated
delivery service means a delivery service designated as such pursuant to 26
U.S.C. 7502(f) and a signed delivery receipt includes an electronic or facsimile
receipt with an image of the recipient's signature.</para><para>(2) Failure to make service by the method elected by the plaintiff
does not affect the validity of the service.</para>
<para>(3) The State
Court Administrator shall maintain on the web site of the Supreme Court a
list of designated delivery services.</para></amendatorysection>
</section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 22; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 845, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB669, &#167; 7.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Workers' compensation cases,</emphasis> manner of service, see sections 48-174, 48-175, 48-175.01, and 48-190.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Plaintiff may elect to have service made by any of the methods specified in the statute. West Town Homeowners Assn. v. Schneider, 221 Neb. 674, 380 N.W.2d 265 (1986).</para><para>Personal service at work rather than at home, despite the designation on the praecipe of where service should be effected, is nonetheless valid service. Hatcher v. McShane, 12 Neb. App. 239, 670 N.W.2d 638 (2003).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>