<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-304"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-304</statuteno><catchline>Parties to actions.</catchline><para>An executor, administrator, guardian, trustee of an express trust, a person with whom or in whose name a contract is made for the benefit of another, or a person expressly authorized by statute, may bring an action without joining the person for whose benefit it is prosecuted. Officers may sue and be sued in such name as is authorized by law and official bonds may be sued upon the same way. Assignees of choses in action assigned for the purpose of collection may sue on any claim assigned in writing.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 32, p. 398; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 166, &#167; 1, p. 509; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7585; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8528; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-304; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-304; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 19, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Assignees</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Executors, administrators, and guardians</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Trustees</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Officers</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Contracts made for benefit of another</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>6. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Assignees</emphasis></para><para>An assignee of a chose in action to whom the legal title has been assigned for the purpose of collection is a proper party plaintiff and may maintain an action as the real party in interest. Archer v. Musick, 147 Neb. 1018, 25 N.W.2d 908 (1947).</para><para>An assignee of a chose in action assigned for collection is a proper party plaintiff but is not the real party in interest as to the cause of action. Archer v. Musick, 147 Neb. 344, 23 N.W.2d 323 (1946).</para><para>Action is properly brought by assignee of creditor. Seybolt v. Waters, 109 Neb. 99, 189 N.W. 980 (1922).</para><para><emphasis>2. Executors, administrators, and guardians</emphasis></para><para>Plaintiff, describing himself as guardian, presumed to sue in representative capacity. Bennett v. Bennett, 65 Neb. 432, 91 N.W. 409 (1902), affirmed on rehearing 65 Neb. 441, 96 N.W. 994 (1903).</para><para>Federal court had jurisdiction on ground of diversity of citizenship by Kansas resident, even though plaintiff had been appointed administratrix by Nebraska court. Janzen v. Goos, 302 F.2d 421 (8th Cir. 1962).</para><para><emphasis>3. Trustees</emphasis></para><para>When certain devisees under will appoint a trustee who brings action in their behalf, they are all bound thereby. Glissmann v. McDonald, 128 Neb. 693, 260 N.W. 182 (1935).</para><para>Trustee for bondholders is entitled to maintain appeal. Roebling's Sons Co. v. Nebraska Elec. Co., 106 Neb. 255, 183 N.W. 546 (1921).</para><para>Trustee for minor son of insured, so designated as beneficiary in policy, may bring action thereon. Ward v. Bankers Life Co., 99 Neb. 812, 157 N.W. 1017 (1916).</para><para>Where trustee refuses to carry out terms of trust, parties beneficially interested may maintain action to enforce trust and obtain benefit thereunder. Goble v. Swobe, 64 Neb. 838, 90 N.W. 919 (1902).</para><para>Trustee of express trust, who is obligee on injunction bond, may maintain action thereon in own name. Gyger v. Courtney, 59 Neb. 555, 81 N.W. 437 (1900).</para><para>Consignor of goods is not trustee of an express trust. Union Pacific Ry. Co. v. Metcalf &amp; Wood, 50 Neb. 452, 69 N.W. 961 (1897).</para><para>County is proper party to bring an action analogous to that of trustee for all funds, except those of the county proper, where county treasurer is in default. Thorne v. Adams County, 22 Neb. 825, 36 N.W. 515 (1888).</para><para><emphasis>4. Officers</emphasis></para><para>School district treasurer or successor may maintain action for recovery of district's money deposited in bank. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Nemaha County Bank, 124 Neb. 883, 248 N.W. 650 (1933).</para><para>Tax Commissioner exercising constitutional powers as the real party in interest, in absence of express statutory prohibition, is authorized to carry on proceedings in the name of the state. State v. Odd Fellows Hall Assn., 123 Neb. 440, 243 N.W. 616 (1932).</para><para>Action may be brought in name of bank as plaintiff, although it is in hands of State Bank Superintendent. First State Bank of Herrick v. Conant, 117 Neb. 562, 221 N.W. 691 (1928).</para><para>State Board may bring action where authorized by statute. State ex rel. Board of Transportation v. Missouri P. Ry. Co., 29 Neb. 550, 45 N.W. 785 (1890).</para><para><emphasis>5. Contracts made for benefit of another</emphasis></para><para>Action may be brought by person in whose name a contract was made for benefit of another. Brown v. Globe Laboratories, Inc., 165 Neb. 138, 84 N.W.2d 151 (1957).</para><para>Party in whose name contract is made for benefit of another may bring action without joining such other person. Coe v. Nebraska B. &amp; I. Co., 110 Neb. 322, 193 N.W. 708 (1923).</para><para>This section constitutes exception to statutory rule that all parties united in interest must join as plaintiffs. Owner of fractional interest in real estate is proper plaintiff in action upon contract executed in his name for benefit of all interests. O'Shea v. North American Hotel Co., 109 Neb. 317, 191 N.W. 321 (1922).</para><para>Person holding legal title, although property is in fact owned by another, may maintain action in own name. Chamberlain v. Woolsey, 66 Neb. 149, 95 N.W. 38 (1903).</para><para>Party, holding legal title to chose in action for the benefit of another, may sue in own name. Meeker v. Waldron, 62 Neb. 689, 87 N.W. 539 (1901).</para><para>Where legal title was taken in name of plaintiff, suit was authorized by her for wrongful sale of land. Alexander v. Overton, 36 Neb. 503, 54 N.W. 825 (1893).</para><para>Where contract is made for benefit of another, action can be maintained in name of contracting party. Ley v. Miller, 28 Neb. 822, 45 N.W. 174 (1890).</para><para>Where a promissory note is made to an agent in his own name as promisee, he may maintain an action thereon without joining the person beneficially interested in the note. Stoll v. Sheldon, 13 Neb. 207, 13 N.W. 201 (1882).</para><para><emphasis>6. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>An agreement requiring the purchase of construction fund warrants, regardless of the holder of the warrants, may be enforced by the party that made the agreement and is authorized to make the demand for purchase. Chiles, Heider &amp; Co. v. Pawnee Meadows, 217 Neb. 315, 350 N.W.2d 1 (1984).</para><para>Under this section, Nebraska has not recognized "consent" as being an exception to the requirement under section 25-301, R.R.S.1943, that an action be prosecuted by the real party in interest. Redding v. Gibbs, 203 Neb. 727, 280 N.W.2d 53 (1979).</para><para>The Attorney General may bring an action for a declaratory judgment challenging the constitutionality of a statute which the Tax Commissioner proposes to implement and enforce. State ex rel. Meyer v. Peters, 188 Neb. 817, 199 N.W.2d 738 (1972).</para><para>Tenant who had settled with landowner for landowner's share of loss was entitled to recover the entire damages caused to crops by defendant. Ristine v. Geigy Agricultural Chemicals, 188 Neb. 550, 198 N.W.2d 199 (1972).</para><para>Party in whose name contract was made could bring action for violation of Installment Loan Act. McNish v. Grand Island Finance Co., 164 Neb. 543, 83 N.W.2d 13 (1957); McNish v. General Credit Corp., 164 Neb. 526, 83 N.W.2d 1 (1957).</para><para>Attorney General may bring action of injunction under Installment Loan Act without joining borrowers as parties. State ex rel. Beck v. Associates Discount Corp., 162 Neb. 683, 77 N.W.2d 215 (1956).</para><para>Person for whom bond was tendered did not fall within exceptions. Summit Fidelity &amp; Surety Co. v. Nimtz, 158 Neb. 762, 64 N.W.2d 803 (1954).</para><para>The real party in interest is the person entitled to the avails of the suit. Uptegrove v. Metropolitan Life Ins. Co. of N. Y., 145 Neb. 51, 15 N.W.2d 220 (1944).</para><para>Defendant interposing counterclaim was not real party in interest where loss, if any, would fall on owner of bonds not joined as defendant in the action. Continental Nat. Bank of Lincoln v. Wilkinson, 124 Neb. 675, 247 N.W. 604 (1933).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>