<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-528"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-528</statuteno><catchline>Personal service upon appointed resident agent; appointment invalidates constructive service, when.</catchline><para>It shall be lawful for any person, association or corporation, owning or claiming any interest in or lien upon any real estate lying within this state, to make and file in the office of the register of deeds of the county in which such real estate is situated an appointment, in writing, of some person, who shall be a resident of the county in which said lands lie, upon whom process may be served in any suit, action or proceeding, concerning or affecting such real estate, to which such owner or claimant shall be made a party. Such appointment shall be acknowledged in the manner provided by law for the acknowledgment of deeds, and shall specifically describe the lands affected by such appointment. From and after the filing of such appointment as herein provided, service of any writ, summons, order or notice, in any suit, action or proceeding, concerning or affecting such real estate, shall be made upon the person so appointed and designated in such manner as may be provided by law for the service of process upon persons found in this state, and shall be held and taken to be a valid and effectual service upon such owner or claimant. A copy of such appointment, or of the record thereof, duly certified by the said register of deeds, shall be deemed sufficient evidence thereof. No service made by publication shall be valid in respect to any such owner or claimant, who shall have filed an appointment under the provisions of this article; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> such appointment may be at any time revoked by such owner or claimant, but such revocation shall be in writing duly acknowledged, and shall specifically describe the lands affected by such appointment, and filed and recorded in the office of the register of deeds of the county in which any such real property is situated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 17; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7649; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8593; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 65, &#167; 1, p. 227; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-528; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-528.</para></source></law></legaldoc>