<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id6" statutenumber="25-410"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>25-410</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Transfer of actions; clerk of transferor court; duties; clerk of transferee court; duties; certain support orders; how treated.</catchline><para>(1) For the convenience of the parties and witnesses or in the interest of justice, a district court of any county, the transferor court, may transfer any civil action to the district court of any other county in this state, the transferee court. The transfer may occur before or after the entry of judgment, and there shall be no additional fees required for the transfer.</para><para>(2) To transfer a civil action, the transferor court shall order transfer of the action to the specific transferee court requested. The clerk of the transferor court shall file with the transferee court within ten days after the entry of the transfer order a certification of the case file and costs. The clerk of the transferor court shall certify any judgment and payment records of such judgments in the action maintained by the transferor court. </para><para>(3) Upon the filing of such documents by the clerk of the transferor court, the clerk of the transferee court shall enter any judgment in the action on the judgment index of the transferee court. The judgment, once filed and entered on the judgment index of the transferee court, shall be a lien on the property of the debtor in any county in which such judgment is filed. Transfer of the action shall not change the obligations of the parties under any judgment entered in the action regardless of the status of the transfer.</para><para>(4) If the transferred civil action involves a support order that has payment records maintained by the Title IV-D Division as defined in section 43-3341, the transferor court order shall notify the division to make the necessary changes in the support payment records. Support payments shall commence in the transferee court on the first day of the month following the order of transfer, payments made prior to such date shall be considered payment on a judgment entered by the transferor court, and payments made on and after such date shall be considered payment on a judgment entered by the transferee court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 61, p. 402; </para><para>G.S.1873, c. 57, &#167; 61, p. 532; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7621; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8564; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-410; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-410; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 576, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 6. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For disqualification of judge,</emphasis> see sections 24-723.01, 24-739, and 24-740.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Abuse of discretion</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Bias or prejudice</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Authority to transfer actions</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Abuse of discretion</emphasis></para><para>Where record does not show abuse of discretion, a ruling on motion to transfer hereunder will not be disturbed. Johnsen v. Parks, 189 Neb. 712, 204 N.W.2d 804 (1973).</para><para>Failure to grant change of venue in equity case was immaterial on appeal, since case was for trial de novo in reviewing court. Lippincott v. Lippincott, 144 Neb. 486, 13 N.W.2d 721 (1944).</para><para>Where only showing made in support of motion for change of venue is affidavit which was not offered in evidence and was not incorporated in bill of exceptions, error cannot be predicated on appeal from order overruling motion. Dunlap v. Loup River Public Power Dist., 136 Neb. 11, 284 N.W. 742 (1939).</para><para>Supreme Court will not disturb ruling of lower court on motion for change of venue unless abuse of discretion is shown. Markel v. Glassmeyer, 132 Neb. 716, 273 N.W. 33 (1937).</para><para>Ruling should not be disturbed on appeal unless discretion is abused. Boyd v. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co., 97 Neb. 238, 149 N.W. 818 (1914).</para><para>Unless abuse of discretion is shown, ruling on motion should not be disturbed. Hinton v. Atchison &amp; Nebraska R. R. Co., 83 Neb. 835, 120 N.W. 431 (1909).</para><para><emphasis>2. Bias or prejudice</emphasis></para><para>Where fair and impartial trial cannot be had, court must change; if fair trial cannot be had in adjoining county, change should be made to other county in district. Gandy v. Bissell's Estate, 81 Neb. 102, 115 N.W. 571 (1908).</para><para>Ruling will not be reversed unless prejudice is shown by clear and convincing evidence. State v. Smith, 77 Neb. 824, 110 N.W. 557 (1906).</para><para>Judge is not disqualified to sit in contempt case to try violation of own order. Back v. State, 75 Neb. 603, 106 N.W. 787 (1906).</para><para>Court on own motion cannot transfer case for trial to another county. Lefferts v. Bell, 57 Neb. 248, 77 N.W. 680 (1898).</para><para>This section does not authorize district court, on its own motion, to order a change of venue. Fisk v. Thorpe, 51 Neb. 1, 70 N.W. 498 (1897).</para><para>Bias or prejudice of judge preventing fair and impartial trial is ground for change. Le Hane v. State, 48 Neb. 105, 66 N.W. 1017 (1896).</para><para>When it appears that a fair and impartial trial cannot be had where suit is pending, change of venue should be granted. Omaha S. Ry. Co. v. Todd, 39 Neb. 818, 58 N.W. 289 (1894).</para><para><emphasis>3. Authority to transfer actions</emphasis></para><para>A court which never acquires jurisdiction permitting it to act has no authority to transfer venue. Jackson v. Jensen, 225 Neb. 671, 407 N.W.2d 758 (1987).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>