<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-316" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-316</statuteno><catchline>Company, partnership, or unincorporated association; member's individual property; how subjected to satisfaction of judgment.</catchline><para>If the plaintiff, in any judgment so rendered against any company or partnership, seeks to charge the individual property of the persons composing such company or firm, it shall be lawful for the plaintiff to file a bill in equity against the several members thereof, setting forth his or her judgment and the insufficiency of the partnership property to satisfy the same, and to have a decree for the debt and an award of execution against all such persons or any of them as may appear to have been members of such company, association, or firm.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 27, p. 397; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7597; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8540; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-316; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-316; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1115, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>As a condition precedent to bringing an action against individual partners to satisfy the debts of a partnership, this section contemplates that there must be a prior judgment against the partnership. Security State Bank v. McCoy, 219 Neb. 132, 361 N.W.2d 514 (1985).</para><para>The right of action preserved by this section is assignable in like manner and with like effect as other choses in action. Wood v. Carter, 67 Neb. 133, 93 N.W. 158 (1903).</para><para>A member of an unincorporated religious society not founded for the purpose of gain or pecuniary profit is not individually liable for its debts, unless he authorized the incurring of the obligation or subsequently ratified the same. First Nat. Bank of Plattsmouth v. Rector, 59 Neb. 77, 80 N.W. 269 (1899).</para><para>To entitle plaintiff to recover from individual partner, it was necessary to allege and prove that the partnership property was insufficient to satisfy the judgment. Ruth v. Lowrey &amp; Upton, 10 Neb. 260, 4 N.W. 977 (1880).</para><para>A fundamental condition precedent to the bringing of a bill in equity pursuant to this section against individual partners is a prior judgment against the partnership. Under the doctrine of res judicata, an order by a bankruptcy court allowing an administrative expense claim is a prior judgment within the meaning of this section. Metco, Inc. v. Huffman, 2 Neb. App. 506, 511 N.W.2d 780 (1994). </para></annotation></law></legaldoc>