<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-219"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-219</statuteno><catchline>Actions upon liability created by federal statute.</catchline><para>All actions upon a liability created by a federal statute, other than a forfeiture or penalty, for which actions no period of limitations is provided in such statute shall be commenced within three years next after the cause of action shall have accrued.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 49, &#167; 1, p. 200; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-219.</para></source><annotation><para>Claim for reimbursement from estate of recipient of old age assistance did not accrue until death of recipient. Boone County Old Age Assistance Board v. Myhre, 149 Neb. 669, 32 N.W.2d 262 (1948).</para><para>This section was applicable to federal civil rights claim of former guidance counselor in action against school district on allegations dismissal was due to his race and his exercise of First Amendment rights. Chambers v. Omaha Public School Dist., 536 F.2d 222 (8th Cir. 1976).</para><para>Summons issued before time allowed by statute of limitations has expired will give court jurisdiction even though served after time has expired. Sandobal v. Armour &amp; Co., 429 F.2d 249 (8th Cir. 1970).</para><para>Under former law, section 43-666, R.R.S.1943, is not sufficiently analogous to 20 U.S.C. section 1415 for its statute of limitation to apply to actions under that federal statute. However, the statute of limitations under either section 25-212 or 25-219, R.R.S.1943, appears to be more appropriate. Monahan v. State of Neb., 491 F.Supp. 1074 (D. Neb. 1980).</para><para>The statute of limitation for commencement of suits under the federal civil rights act, which guarantees equal rights under the law, is the three-year statute of limitation set by this section. Metcalf v. Omaha Steel Casting Co., 476 F.Supp. 870 (D. Neb. 1979).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>