<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-311"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-311</statuteno><catchline>Joinder of plaintiffs.</catchline><para>All persons may join in one action as plaintiffs if they assert any right to relief jointly, severally, or in the alternative in respect of or arising out of the same transaction, occurrence, or series of transactions or occurrences and if any question of law or fact common to all these persons will arise in the action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 40, p. 399; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7592; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8535; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-311; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-311; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 234, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Joinder</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Joinder</emphasis></para><para>Multiple plaintiffs may join in one suit to enjoin a nuisance so long as the alleged nuisance interferes with the rights of each plaintiff joined; however, multiple plaintiffs seeking monetary damages for an alleged nuisance would be misjoined where any one plaintiff has no interest in the monetary relief demanded by each of the other plaintiffs. Goeke v. National Farms, Inc., 245 Neb. 262, 512 N.W.2d 626 (1994).</para><para>Mortgagees of cattle were proper party plaintiffs with owner in suit on indemnity bond of livestock commission company. Oss v. Hartford Accident &amp; Indemnity Co., 130 Neb. 311, 264 N.W. 897 (1936).</para><para>To authorize joinder of parties as defendants, they must be under joint liability or claiming some right in subject matter of action. Stull Bros. v. Powell, 70 Neb. 152, 97 N.W. 249 (1903).</para><para>Successive mortgagees, merely as such, and even though possession has not been had on any of the mortgages, may join in replevying the property. Trompen v. Yates, 66 Neb. 525, 92 N.W. 647 (1902).</para><para>City may join as party plaintiff in tax foreclosure proceedings by county, but is not required to do so. County of Lancaster v. Rush, 35 Neb. 119, 52 N.W. 837 (1892).</para><para>Two parties having separate and distinct claims to the possession of the same property may unite such claims and in their joint or combined names maintain an action of replevin therefor. Earle v. Burch, 21 Neb. 702, 33 N.W. 254 (1887).</para><para>Tenants in common may join in an action for the possession of real estate held by one without title. Mattis v. Boggs, 19 Neb. 698, 28 N.W. 325 (1886).</para><para>An attorney who has perfected his lien upon money due from defendant in a pending action has such an interest therein to be made a coplaintiff. Reynolds v. Reynolds, 10 Neb. 574, 7 N.W. 322 (1880).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Interested parties may appeal to district court from action of county superintendent in dissolving school district. Board of Education v. Winne, 177 Neb. 431, 129 N.W.2d 255 (1964).</para><para>Objection that plaintiff has no legal capacity to sue must be made, if at all, by party to suit. Miller v. Willis, 15 Neb. 13, 16 N.W. 840 (1883).</para><para>In an action brought upon a judgment against a principal debtor, in behalf of a surety who has paid off and satisfied the same and taken an assignment thereof, the original plaintiffs are not proper parties. Eaton v. Lambert, 1 Neb. 339 (1871).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>