<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-209"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-209</statuteno><catchline>Actions on official or judicial bonds.</catchline><para>An action upon the official bond or undertaking of an executor, administrator, guardian, sheriff, or any other officer, or upon the bond or undertaking given in attachment, injunction, or in any case whatever required by statute can only be brought within ten years.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 14, p. 396; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7571; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8514; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-209; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-209.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Official bonds</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Official bonds</emphasis></para><para>Action on county treasurer's bond was commenced within time permitted by this section. City of Bellevue v. Western Surety Co., 184 Neb. 678, 171 N.W.2d 772 (1969).</para><para>Bond of chairman of Board of Public Works is an official bond within meaning of this section. Neisius v. Henry, 143 Neb. 273, 9 N.W.2d 163 (1943).</para><para>In suit against city officer and surety on bond to recover excess salary paid, all amounts paid more than ten years prior to date of filing suit are barred. Neisius v. Henry, 142 Neb. 29, 5 N.W.2d 291 (1942).</para><para>Statute of limitations on action on official bond of clerk of district court is ten years. Thurston County v. Farley, 128 Neb. 756, 260 N.W. 397 (1935).</para><para>Actions on official bonds may be brought within ten years after the cause of action accrues. United States Fidelity &amp; Guaranty Co. v. McLaughlin, 76 Neb. 310, 109 N.W. 390 (1906).</para><para>Action on official bond is not barred until expiration of ten years from time action accrues. Bantley v. Baker, 61 Neb. 92, 84 N.W. 603 (1900).</para><para>Action on official bond of county judge is barred in ten years after cause of action accrued. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. Ry. Co. v. Philpott, 56 Neb. 212, 76 N.W. 550 (1898).</para><para>County treasurers are within the general designation "any other officer," and actions upon their bonds are brought within the provisions of this section. Alexander v. Overton, 22 Neb. 227, 34 N.W. 629 (1887).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>The statute of limitations on action on statutorily required grain dealer's bond is 10 years. Stock v. Meissner, 217 Neb. 56, 348 N.W.2d 426 (1984).</para><para>Where bond was not applicable on the date the plaintiff's cause of action accrued, this section was inapplicable. Stock v. Meissner, 209 Neb. 636, 309 N.W.2d 86 (1981).</para><para>The limitation does not begin to run on a guardian's bond until he has obtained approval of his final account and been discharged by probate court. Sherwood v. Merchants Mut. Bonding Co., 193 Neb. 262, 226 N.W.2d 761 (1975).</para><para>Where amended petition introduces new causes of action which are barred by statute of limitations, such new allegations cannot be the basis of a recovery, but this rule does not apply to allegations contained in the original petition which are repeated in the amended petition. Streight v. First Trust Co. of Omaha, 133 Neb. 340, 275 N.W. 278 (1937).</para><para>Action accrues on official bond of a county judge when he fails to pay to his successor in office, on the expiration of his term, any money in his possession due to an heir or other person, which has not been paid to the person entitled thereto. Ericsson v. Streitz, 132 Neb. 692, 273 N.W. 17 (1937).</para><para>Action on appeal bond is governed by this section and is not barred until after ten years. Crum v. Johnson, 3 Neb. Unof. 826, 92 N.W. 1054 (1902).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>