<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-320"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-320</statuteno><catchline>Permissive joinder of defendants.</catchline><para>All persons may be joined in one action as defendants if there is asserted against them jointly, severally, or in the alternative any right to relief in respect of or arising out of the same transaction, occurrence, or series of transactions or occurrences and if any question of law or fact common to all defendants will arise in the action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 44, p. 399; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7601; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8544; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-320; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-320; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 234, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>The maker and guarantor of a note are not liable upon the same obligation, so as to be sued together. Ayres v. West, 86 Neb. 297, 125 N.W. 583 (1910); Mowery v. Mast, 9 Neb. 445, 4 N.W. 69 (1880).</para><para>Parties who are severally liable upon a written contract may be impleaded in one action thereon. Champlin Bros. v. Sperling, 84 Neb. 633, 121 N.W. 976 (1909).</para><para>Any or all of persons severally liable on promissory note may be included in action at option of plaintiff. Palmer v. McFarlane, 73 Neb. 178, 102 N.W. 256 (1905).</para><para>Where written guarantee constitutes endorsement also, maker and endorsers may be sued jointly in action on note. Weitz v. Wolfe, 28 Neb. 500, 44 N.W. 485 (1890).</para><para>Maker and several endorsers may be sued together in one action. Pearson v. Kansas Mfg. Co., 14 Neb. 211, 15 N.W. 346 (1883).</para><para>Joinder of several defendants under state statute, notwithstanding several liability, does not create joint liability so as to preclude removal to federal court by nonresident defendant. Des Moines Elevator &amp; Grain Co. v. Underwriters' Grain Assn., 63 F.2d 103 (8th Cir. 1933).</para><para>Statute does not prevent removal to federal court of action on note; statute does not make obligations, which are several, joint. Stewart v. Nebraska Tire &amp; Rubber Co., 39 F.2d 309 (8th Cir. 1930), affirming Stewart v. Heisler, 32 F.2d 519 (N.D. Iowa 1929).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>