<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="no" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure"  statutenumber="25-227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-227</statuteno><catchline>Action to enforce obligation to pay certificate of deposit; when.</catchline><para>(1) For purposes of this section:</para><para>(a) Account agreement means one or more written instruments that establish when a certificate of deposit is payable;</para><para>(b) Certificate of deposit means a deposit or share account at a depository institution that:</para><para>(i) Is payable by the depository institution at the expiration of a specified time; and</para><para>(ii) May be transferable or nontransferable, negotiable or nonnegotiable, and renewable or nonrenewable;</para><para>(c) Depository institution means a state-chartered or federally chartered financial institution located in this state that is authorized to maintain certificates of deposit; and</para><para>(d) Maturity date means the time specified in an account agreement when a certificate of deposit is first payable, without taking into account any agreement regarding renewals.</para><para>(2) Subject to subsection (3) of this section, an action to enforce the obligation of a depository institution to pay all or part of the balance of a certificate of deposit shall be commenced by the earlier of:</para><para>(a) The time that an action to enforce an obligation under subsection (e) of section 3-118, Uniform Commercial Code, must be commenced if the certificate of deposit is subject to such section; or</para><para>(b) Seven years after the later of:</para><para>(i) The maturity date of the certificate of deposit;</para><para>(ii) The due date of the certificate of deposit indicated in the depository institution's last written notice of renewal of the certificate of deposit, if any;</para><para>(iii) The date of the last written communication from the depository institution recognizing the depository institution's obligation with respect to the certificate of deposit; or</para><para>(iv) The last day of the taxable year for which a person identified in the certificate of deposit last reported interest income earned on the certificate of deposit on a federal or state income tax return.</para><para>(3) Notwithstanding subsection (2) of this section, an action to enforce the obligation of a depository institution to pay all or part of the balance of an automatically renewing certificate of deposit in existence on July 1, 2008, shall be commenced by the later of:</para><para>(a) Seven years after the later of:</para><para>(i) The maturity date of the certificate of deposit;</para><para>(ii) The due date of the certificate of deposit indicated in the depository institution's last written notice of renewal of the certificate of deposit, if any;</para><para>(iii) The date of the last written communication from the depository institution recognizing the depository institution's obligation to pay the certificate of deposit; or</para><para>(iv) The last day of the taxable year for which a person identified in the certificate of deposit last reported interest income earned on the certificate of deposit on a federal or state income tax return; or</para><para>(b) One year after July 1, 2008.</para><para>(4) This section applies to all certificates of deposit that are in existence on or after July 1, 2008.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2008, LB151, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>An action commenced on November 30, 2009, was time barred by this section, because it was past the 7 years after the maturity date of the certificate of deposit and more than a year since July 1, 2008. Swift v. Norwest Bank-Omaha West, 285 Neb. 619, 828 N.W.2d 755 (2013).</para><para>The maturity date of a certificate of deposit was 9 months after the date issued, and the maturity date did not extend for 9 additional months every time the certificate of deposit automatically renewed. Swift v. Norwest Bank-Omaha West, 285 Neb. 619, 828 N.W.2d 755 (2013).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
