<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-516.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-516.01</statuteno><catchline>Service; voluntary appearance; defenses.</catchline><para>(1) The voluntary appearance of the party is equivalent to service.</para><para>(2) A defense of lack of jurisdiction over the person, insufficiency of process, or insufficiency of service of process may be asserted only under the procedure provided in the pleading rules adopted by the Supreme Court. If any of those defenses are asserted either by motion or in a responsive pleading and the court overrules the defense, an objection that the court erred in its ruling will be waived and not preserved for appellate review if the party asserting the defense either (a) thereafter files a demand for affirmative relief by way of counterclaim, cross-claim, or third-party claim or (b) fails to dismiss a demand for such affirmative relief that was previously filed. If any of those defenses are asserted either by motion or in a responsive pleading and the court overrules the defense, an objection that the court erred in its ruling on any issue, except the objection that the party is not amenable to process issued by a court of this state, will be waived and not preserved for appellate review if the party asserting the defense thereafter participates in proceedings on any issue other than those defenses.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 32; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 15. </para></source><annotation><para>A voluntary appearance is the equivalent to service that waives a defense of insufficient service or process if the party requests general relief from the court on an issue other than sufficiency of service or process, or personal jurisdiction. Carlson v. Allianz Versicherungs-AG, 287 Neb. 628, 844 N.W.2d 264 (2014).</para><para>A voluntary appearance signed the day before a complaint or petition is filed waives service of process if filed simultaneously with or after the petition. Johnson v. Johnson, 282 Neb. 42, 803 N.W.2d 420 (2011).</para><para>A voluntary appearance of a party is equivalent to service and, in effect, is another mode of service. Nebraska Methodist Health Sys. v. Dept. of Health, 249 Neb. 405, 543 N.W.2d 466 (1996).</para><para>Intended defendant's father, who bore same name as defendant without distinction of "Sr." or "Jr.," had no obligation to assert affirmative defense of lack of jurisdiction or insufficient service either in answer or by motion, in plaintiff's action for personal injuries, as grounds for permitting plaintiff to serve intended defendant rather than dismissing complaint with prejudice; trial court acquired personal jurisdiction over father when father was served, and there was no objection to service of summons on father. Rudd v. Debora, 20 Neb. App. 850, 835 N.W.2d 765 (2013).</para><para>An action stood dismissed by operation of law upon the passing of 6 months after the filing of the petition, where the defendants were not served process and their voluntary appearances were entered more than 6 months after the date the petition was filed. Vopalka v. Abraham, 9 Neb. App. 285, 610 N.W.2d 433 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>