<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-213"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>25-213</statuteno><catchline>Tolling of statutes of limitation; when.</catchline><para>Except as provided in sections 76-288 to 76-298, if a person entitled to bring any action mentioned in Chapter 25, the Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act, the Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act, the State Contract Claims Act, the State Tort Claims Act, the State Miscellaneous Claims Act, or the Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act, except for a penalty or forfeiture, for the recovery of the title or possession of lands, tenements, or hereditaments, or for the foreclosure of mortgages thereon, is, at the time the cause of action accrued, within the age of twenty years, a person with a mental disorder, or imprisoned, every such person shall be entitled to bring such action within the respective times limited by Chapter 25 after such disability is removed. For the recovery of the title or possession of lands, tenements, or hereditaments or for the foreclosure of mortgages thereon, every such person shall be entitled to bring such action within twenty years from the accrual thereof but in no case longer than ten years after the termination of such disability. Absence from the state, death, or other disability shall not operate to extend the period within which actions in rem are to be commenced by and against a nonresident or his or her representative.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 17, p. 396; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7576; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8519; </para><para>Laws 1925, c. 64, &#167; 2, p. 221; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-213; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-213; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 243, &#167; 12, p. 766; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1049, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 949, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1984, LB 692, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1177, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 864, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB339, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB680, &#167; 10. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Hospital-Medical Liability Act,</emphasis> see section 44-2855.</para><para><emphasis>Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 13-901.</para><para><emphasis>State Contract Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,302.</para><para><emphasis>State Miscellaneous Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,294.</para><para><emphasis>State Tort Claims Act,</emphasis> see section 81-8,235.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act,</emphasis> see section 25-3501.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Minors</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Mental disabilities</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Nonresidents</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Minors</emphasis></para><para>Under this section, a person is within the age of 20 years until he or she becomes 21 years old. Carruth v. State, 271 Neb. 433, 712 N.W.2d 575 (2006).</para><para>Subsection (2) of section 25-224 is not tolled by a person's status as a minor pursuant to this section. Budler v. General Motors Corp., 268 Neb. 998, 689 N.W.2d 847 (2004).</para><para>One is within the age of 20 for purposes of this section until he or she becomes 21 years old. Brown v. Kindred, 259 Neb. 95, 608 N.W.2d 577 (2000).</para><para>Mere fact of imprisonment does not toll the statute of limitations for a medical malpractice action. Gordon v. Connell, 249 Neb. 769, 545 N.W.2d 722 (1996).</para><para>One is "within the age of twenty years" until he or she becomes 21 years old. Lawson v. Ford Motor Co., 225 Neb. 725, 408 N.W.2d 256 (1987).</para><para>Suspension of the statute of limitations in accordance with this section inures to the exclusive and personal benefit of the infant, and not to the benefit of the infant's parent. Macku v. Drackett Products Co., 216 Neb. 176, 343 N.W.2d 58 (1984).</para><para>Workmen's Compensation Act makes no exception in favor of minor dependents as to limitation for filing claims, and action brought by minors under this act are governed by its provisions and not by general statute of limitations. Ray v. Sanitary Garbage Co., 134 Neb. 178, 278 N.W. 139 (1938).</para><para>Statute is not tolled by minority of heirs where it commenced to run in lifetime of ancestor. McNeill v. Schumaker, 94 Neb. 544, 143 N.W. 805 (1913).</para><para>Minor may bring action to recover interest in real estate within ten years after arriving at majority. Albers v. Kozeluh, 68 Neb. 522, 94 N.W. 521 (1903), former judgment adhered to 68 Neb. 529, 97 N.W. 646 (1903).</para><para>Time for bringing of action by minor against county for defect in highway under special statute is not extended by this section. Swaney v. Gage County, 64 Neb. 627, 90 N.W. 542 (1902).</para><para>This section tolls the running of the time limitation under section 25-222 until an infant reaches the age of majority. Hatfield v. Bishop Clarkson Memorial Hosp., 679 F.2d 1258 (8th Cir. 1982).</para><para><emphasis>2. Mental disabilities</emphasis></para><para>Insanity means such condition of mental derangement which actually prevents the sufferer from understanding and protecting his or her legal rights. Sacchi v. Blodig, 215 Neb. 817, 341 N.W.2d 326 (1983).</para><para>In the case of recovery of real estate this section gives an incompetent ten years after disability is removed to bring action. In re Estate of Montgomery, 133 Neb. 153, 274 N.W. 487 (1937).</para><para>Statute does not commence to run against the owner of real property confined in an asylum for the insane at the time of a tax lien foreclosure, and who continues to be mentally incompetent after his discharge from the hospital, until he has been sufficiently restored to his mental powers to be able to comprehend that he was owner of the property and able to take some action to protect his rights with reference thereto. Walter v. Union Real Estate Co., 107 Neb. 144, 185 N.W. 323 (1921).</para><para>Fact that statute tolls limitation period during insanity does not deny prosecution of action for insane person by guardian during period of insanity. Wirth v. Weigand, 85 Neb. 115, 122 N.W. 714 (1909).</para><para>A mental disorder within the meaning of this section is an incapacity which disqualifies one from acting for the protection of one's rights. Anonymous v. St. John Lutheran Church, 14 Neb. App. 42, 703 N.W.2d 918 (2005).</para><para>A person with a mental disorder is one who suffers from a condition of mental derangement which actually prevents the sufferer from understanding his or her legal rights or from instituting legal action. Anonymous v. St. John Lutheran Church, 14 Neb. App. 42, 703 N.W.2d 918 (2005).</para><para>A person with a mental disorder is one who suffers from a condition of mental derangement which actually prevents the sufferer from understanding his or her legal rights or from instituting legal action. Vergara v. Lopez-Vasquez, 1 Neb. App. 1141, 510 N.W.2d 550 (1993).</para><para><emphasis>3. Nonresidents</emphasis></para><para>Absence from state will not extend time in which foreclosure of real estate mortgage may be brought against nonresident. Brainard v. Hall, 137 Neb. 491, 289 N.W. 845 (1940).</para><para>Absence from state does not operate to extend the period within which mechanic lien foreclosure shall be commenced. Pickens v. Polk, 42 Neb. 267, 60 N.W. 566 (1894).</para><para>Absence from state does not extend time for foreclosure of mortgage. Merriam v. Goodlett, 36 Neb. 384, 54 N.W. 686 (1893).</para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Political Subdivisions Tort Claims Act including one-year notice of claim requirement and two-year limitation for bringing action held constitutional. Campbell v. City of Lincoln, 195 Neb. 703, 240 N.W.2d 339 (1976).</para><para>This section does not toll the statutes of limitations for the benefit of executors or administrators. Sherwood v. Merchants Mut. Bonding Co., 193 Neb. 262, 226 N.W.2d 761 (1975).</para><para>Statute runs against married woman during coverture. Watkins v. Adamson, 113 Neb. 715, 204 N.W. 816 (1925).</para><para>Courts of equity have inherent powers to refuse relief after undue and inexcusable delay, independent of statute of limitations. Hawley v. Von Lanken, 75 Neb. 597, 106 N.W. 456 (1906).</para><para>Suit to quiet title is action in rem, within this section. Lantry v. Parker, 37 Neb. 353, 55 N.W. 962 (1893).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>