<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-519"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-519</statuteno><catchline>Service by publication; how made; contents.</catchline><para>The publication shall be made once in each week for three successive weeks in some newspaper printed in the county where the complaint is filed if there is any printed in such county and, if there is not, in some newspaper printed in this state of general circulation in that county. It shall contain a summary statement of the claim for relief of the complaint, mention the court wherein it is filed, and notify the person or persons thus to be served when they are required to answer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 79, p. 405; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7642; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8585; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-519; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-519; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 47, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 299, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 16. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For publication of legal notices,</emphasis> see sections 25-2227, 25-2228, 33-141, and 33-142.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. How made</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Contents</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. How made</emphasis></para><para>In the case of substitute service by publication under this section, service is not "made" until the third publication, and prior to the third publication, a defendant is "not served" under section 25-217. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co. v. Allstate Ins. Co., 268 Neb. 439, 684 N.W.2d 14 (2004).</para><para>Where service by publication has been approved, a defendant is not served within 6 months from the date the petition was filed under section 25-217 unless the third publication under this section has occurred within 6 months from the date the petition was filed. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co. v. Allstate Ins. Co., 268 Neb. 439, 684 N.W.2d 14 (2004).</para><para>Publication seven times in semi-weekly newspaper was not sufficient in foreclosure of tax lien. Davis v. American Inv. &amp; Trust Co., 94 Neb. 427, 143 N.W. 464 (1913).</para><para>Publications need not be on same day of week; "week" defined. Burr v. Finch, 91 Neb. 417, 136 N.W. 72 (1912).</para><para>Notice must be published in all regular issues during week. Smith v. Potter, 90 Neb. 298, 133 N.W. 437 (1911); Claypool v. Robb, 90 Neb. 193, 133 N.W. 178 (1911).</para><para>Notice takes place of summons; publication requiring defendant to answer on second Monday is irregular and may be set aside on motion. Calkins v. Miller, 55 Neb. 601, 75 N.W. 1108 (1898).</para><para>Four weekly publications are sufficient. Taylor v. Coots, 32 Neb. 30, 48 N.W. 964 (1891); Fouts v. Mann, 15 Neb. 172, 18 N.W. 64 (1883).</para><para>Notice requiring defendant to answer in forenoon is valid; but has whole day to answer. Armstrong v. Middlestadt, 22 Neb. 711, 36 N.W. 151 (1888).</para><para>Notice once each week for four successive weeks is completed upon distribution of last publication. Davis v. Huston, 15 Neb. 28, 16 N.W. 820 (1883).</para><para><emphasis>2. Contents</emphasis></para><para>Publication notice must contain a summary statement of the object and prayer of the petition, mention the court wherein it is filed, and notify the person or persons to be served when they are required to answer. Coffin v. Maitland, 146 Neb. 477, 20 N.W.2d 310 (1945).</para><para>Plaintiff's cause of action is not required to be set out in notice. Smith v. Potter, 92 Neb. 39, 137 N.W. 854 (1912).</para><para>Notice stating that action was for "partition" of lands was sufficient without reciting "partition or sale." McCormick v. Paddock, 20 Neb. 486, 30 N.W. 602 (1886).</para><para>Notice in attachment containing general description of property attached is not void. Grebe v. Jones, 15 Neb. 312, 18 N.W. 81 (1883).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Notice to nonresident herein complied with this section. Armstrong v. Bates, 94 Neb. 462, 143 N.W. 477 (1913).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>