<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id94">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id96" statutenumber="25-510.02">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2011</bookinfo><statuteno>25-510.02</statuteno><catchline id="id99">Service on
state or political subdivision.</catchline><para>(1) The State
of Nebraska, any state agency as defined in section 81-8,210, and any employee
of the state as defined in section 81-8,210 sued in an official capacity may
be served by leaving the summons at the office of the Attorney General with
the Attorney General, deputy attorney general, or someone designated in writing
by the Attorney General, or by certified mail or designated delivery service addressed to
the office of the Attorney General.</para>
<para>(2) Any county, city, or village of this state may be served
by personal, residence, certified
mail, or designated delivery service
upon the chief executive officer or
clerk.</para>
<para>(3) Any political subdivision of this state, as defined in
subdivision (1) of section 13-903, other than a county, city, or village,
may be served by personal, residence, certified
mail, or designated delivery service
upon the chief executive officer, clerk, secretary, or other official whose
duty it is to maintain the official records, or any member of the governing
board or body, or by certified mail or
designated delivery service to the principal office of the political
subdivision.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 27; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB669, &#167; 12.</para></source><annotation><para>When this section applies, a summons must be served on the Attorney General in order to institute judicial review under the Administrative Procedure Act, sections 84-901 through 84-920. Concordia Teachers College v. Neb. Dept. of Labor, 252 Neb. 504, 563 N.W.2d 345 (1997).</para><para>This section provides the acceptable methods of service of summons upon the Attorney General, but although some discretion is granted as to the mode of service, no discretion is granted as to the entity to be served. Nebraska Methodist Health Sys. v. Dept. of Health, 249 Neb. 405, 543 N.W.2d 466 (1996).</para><para>When this section applies, in order to institute judicial review under the Administrative Procedure Act, service must be had on the Attorney General. Becker v. Nebraska Acct. &amp; Disclosure Comm., 249 Neb. 28, 541 N.W.2d 36 (1995).</para><para>In cases in which this section applies, a summons must be served on the Attorney General in order to institute judicial review under the Administrative Procedure Act. Glass v. Nebraska Dept. of Motor Vehicles, 248 Neb. 501, 536 N.W.2d 344 (1995).</para><para>Pursuant to subsection (1), when a party commences an action against the State, that party's service must be served in one of the four following ways to be effective: (1) By leaving summons at the Attorney General's office with the Attorney General, (2) by leaving summons at the Attorney General's office with a deputy attorney general, (3) by leaving summons at the Attorney General's office with someone designated in writing by the Attorney General to receive summons, or (4) by sending summons by certified mail addressed to the Attorney General's office. Twiss v. Trautwein, 247 Neb. 535, 529 N.W.2d 24 (1995).</para><para>Pursuant to this section, the Attorney General must be served on behalf of the committee and that service may be accomplished by one of the methods for which provision is made in subsection (1). Ray v. Nebraska Crime Victim's Reparations Comm., 1 Neb. App. 130, 487 N.W.2d 590 (1992).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>
