<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-913"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-913</statuteno><catchline>Motion to strike pleadings and papers from files; notice, when.</catchline><para>Motions to strike pleadings and papers from the files may be made with or without notice, as the court or judge shall direct.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 577, p. 495; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7729; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8673; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-913; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-913.</para></source><annotation><para>Motions to strike filed under this section are aimed at petitions filed in violation of a court's order or a rule of practice or procedure prescribed either by statute or by the court in which the petition is filed. Motions to strike under this section may also be filed when a party declines to amend the petition or refuses to follow the court's orders. Nuss ex rel. Estate of Nuss v. Alexander, 257 Neb. 36, 595 N.W.2d 263 (1999).</para><para>A motion to strike a petition is not a substitute for a demurrer or a motion to strike or make more definite and certain, and may be directed only to a petition filed in violation of a court's order or a rule of practice or procedure prescribed either by statute or by the court in which the petition is filed. Hecker v. Ravenna Bank, 237 Neb. 810, 468 N.W.2d 88 (1991).</para><para>Petition may be stricken on motion if fatal defects extend to the pleading as a whole, or if the plaintiff, in filing it, ignored an order of court. Ferson v. Armour &amp; Co., 109 Neb. 648, 192 N.W. 125 (1923).</para><para>This section, as construed by the Supreme Court of Nebraska, applies in actions at law in federal courts, and petition failing to state cause of action may be stricken on motion. Jack v. Armour &amp; Co., 291 F. 741 (8th Cir. 1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>