<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-520.01" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-520.01</statuteno><catchline>Service by publication; mailing of published notice; requirements; waiver; when mailing not required.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (3) of this section, in any action or proceeding of any kind or nature, as defined in section 25-520.02, where a notice by publication is given as authorized by law, a party instituting or maintaining the action or proceeding with respect to notice or such party's attorney shall within five days after the first publication of notice send by United States mail a copy of such published notice or, if applicable, the notice described in subsection (4) of this section, to each and every party appearing to have a direct legal interest in such action or proceeding whose name and post office address are known to such party or attorney.</para><para>(2) Proof by affidavit of the mailing of such notice shall be made by the party or such party's attorney and shall be filed with the officer with whom filings are required to be made in such action or proceeding within ten days after mailing of such notice. Such affidavit of mailing of notice shall further be required to state that such party and such party's attorney, after diligent investigation and inquiry, were unable to ascertain and do not know the post office address of any other party appearing to have a direct legal interest in such action or proceeding other than those to whom notice has been mailed in writing.</para><para>(3) It shall not be necessary to serve the notice prescribed by this section upon any competent person, fiduciary, partnership, or corporation, who has waived notice in writing, has entered a voluntary appearance, or has been personally served with summons or notice in such proceeding.</para><para>(4) In the case of a lien for a special assessment imposed by any city or village, in lieu of sending a copy of published notice, the city or village may instead send by United States mail, to each and every party appearing to have a direct legal interest in such action or proceeding whose name and post office address are known to the city or village or its attorney, a notice containing the amount owed, the date due, and the date the board of equalization meets in case of an appeal.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 80, &#167; 1, p. 325; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 97, &#167; 1, p. 416; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB58, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Notice not required</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Notice not required</emphasis></para><para>First cousins of testator were not prima facie heirs-at-law, and hence were not required to be notified by mail of pending probate of will. Estate of Colman v. Redford, 179 Neb. 270, 137 N.W.2d 822 (1965).</para><para>Notice by mail is not required to be given to the holder of a claim for unliquidated damages. Farmers Co-op. Mercantile Co. v. Sidner, 175 Neb. 94, 120 N.W.2d 537 (1963).</para><para>Notice by mail was not required to be given to property owner of intention by municipality to pass resolution of necessity for constructing sewer system. Jones v. Village of Farnam, 174 Neb. 704, 119 N.W.2d 157 (1963).</para><para>Notice was not required to be sent to all owners of land within school district of proceedings to change boundaries thereof. Lindgren v. School Dist. of Bridgeport, 170 Neb. 279, 102 N.W.2d 599 (1960).</para><para>A decedent's potential liability for an automobile accident, without establishment of liability and amount of damages, does not constitute a direct legal interest in the estate such that notice by mail must be sent to the potential creditor. Mach v. Schmer, 4 Neb. App. 819, 550 N.W.2d 385 (1996).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Because the appellant did not file an affidavit that complied with this section, the appellant's constructive service was improper and the district court lacked personal jurisdiction over the appellee. Francisco v. Gonzalez, 301 Neb. 1045, 921 N.W.2d 350 (2019).</para><para>Section 30-2483 requires notice to be sent to the Department of Health and Human Services under certain circumstances. To comply with this requirement, notice must be sent in accordance with this section. In re Estate of Cushing, 283 Neb. 571, 810 N.W.2d 741 (2012).</para><para>The 3-year limitations period of section 30-2485(a)(2) applied to the Department of Health and Human Services' Medicaid estate recovery claim because the personal representative failed to send notice to the department within 5 days of the date on which notice to creditors was first published, as required by section 30-2483 and this section. In re Estate of Cushing, 283 Neb. 571, 810 N.W.2d 741 (2012).</para><para>The requirements of this section apply to a publication of notice given under section 25-1529 governing sales on execution. KLH Retirement Planning v. Okwumuo, 263 Neb. 760, 642 N.W.2d 801 (2002).</para><para>County court which obtained jurisdiction of res of estate upon filing of petition retains jurisdiction until service of notice is perfected or until matter is abandoned. Fischer v. Lingle, 195 Neb. 108, 237 N.W.2d 110 (1975).</para><para>A mortgagor in a foreclosure proceeding is not entitled to personal service of the published notice of sale. Hollstein v. Adams, 187 Neb. 781, 194 N.W.2d 216 (1972).</para><para>Copy of notice, mailed hereunder, that a will and codicil are being offered for probate is sufficient to put party upon inquiry as to documents offered. Flint v. Panter, 187 Neb. 615, 193 N.W.2d 279 (1970).</para><para>This section does not apply to notice of dissolution of corporation. Christensen v. Boss, 179 Neb. 429, 138 N.W.2d 716 (1965).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>