<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-403.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-403.02</statuteno><catchline>Venue; residency; determination.</catchline><para>For purposes of venue, the following definitions shall apply:</para><para>(1) Any private corporation organized under the laws of this state and any foreign corporation authorized to transact business in this state is a resident of any county in which it has its registered office or other office or is doing business. A foreign corporation not authorized to transact business in this state is not a resident of this state;</para><para>(2) A partnership sued in its firm name is a resident of any county in which any partner resides or in which the partnership has an office or is doing business. If all partners are nonresidents of this state and the partnership does not have an office or do business in this state, the partnership is not a resident of this state;</para><para>(3) A voluntary unincorporated association sued in its own name is a resident of any county in which the association has an office or in which any officer of the association resides. If it has no office in this state and no officer resides in this state, the voluntary unincorporated association is not a resident of this state; and</para><para>(4) A limited liability company organized under the laws of this state and any foreign limited liability company authorized to transact business in this state is a resident of any county in which it has its registered office or other office or is doing business. A foreign limited liability company not authorized to transact business in this state is not a resident of this state.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1986, LB 529, &#167; 24; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 166. </para></source></law></legaldoc>