<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2004, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-329" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-329</statuteno><catchline>Intervention; judgment; costs.</catchline><para>The court shall determine upon the intervention at the same time that the action is decided, and if the claim of the intervenor is not sustained, the intervenor shall pay all costs of the intervention.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1887, c. 100, &#167; 2, p. 655; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7610; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8553; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-329; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-329; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1115, &#167; 16.</para></source><annotation><para>District court may rule on sufficiency of petition of intervention before trial. Kirchner v. Gast, 169 Neb. 404, 100 N.W.2d 65 (1959).</para><para>Costs are taxed to interveners and relators where they are unsuccessful in a mandamus case. State ex rel. Nelson v. Butler, 145 Neb. 638, 17 N.W.2d 683 (1945).</para><para>Determination whether intervener has an actual interest in the subject of the controversy is a necessary preliminary question for the trial court's decision and is determinable when the action is finally decided. Drainage Dist. No. 1 of Lincoln County v. Kirkpatrick-Pettis Co., 140 Neb. 530, 300 N.W. 582 (1941).</para><para>Intervention was unknown at common law and is creature of statute. Geis v. Geis, 125 Neb. 394, 250 N.W. 252 (1933).</para><para>Section should be liberally construed, but intervener must plead and prove actual interest or be regarded as mere interloper. Parker v. City of Grand Island, 115 Neb. 892, 215 N.W. 127 (1927).</para><para>A person may intervene as matter of right before trial. In re Estate of Keller, 101 Neb. 115, 162 N.W. 511 (1917).</para><para>Petition of intervener cannot be dismissed until determination on merits. Montgomery v. Dresher, 97 Neb. 112, 149 N.W. 314 (1914).</para><para>Petition may be dismissed without prejudice. Lincoln Upholstering Co. v. Baker, 82 Neb. 592, 118 N.W. 321 (1908).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>