<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-703"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-703</statuteno><catchline>Consolidation of actions; motion and notice.</catchline><para>Whenever two or more actions are pending in the same court which might have been joined, the defendant may, on motion and notice to the adverse party, require him to show cause why the same shall not be consolidated, and if no such cause be shown, the said several actions shall be consolidated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 150, p. 416; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7659; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8603; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-703; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-703.</para></source><annotation><para>If the plaintiff does not choose to unite several causes of action in one petition and the defendant does not successfully require joinder, there is no legal requirement that distinct causes of action be joined in one suit. Suhr v. City of Scribner, 207 Neb. 24, 295 N.W.2d 302 (1980).</para><para>Right of consolidation under this section is dependent upon an application by a defendant. Bruno v. Kramer, 176 Neb. 597, 126 N.W.2d 885 (1964).</para><para>Two or more actions pending in the same court which might have been joined, may, upon application, be consolidated. Peters v. Meyer, 131 Neb. 847, 270 N.W. 312 (1936).</para><para>Consolidating actions for trial is inherent power of equity court. Butler v. Secrist, 84 Neb. 85, 120 N.W. 1109 (1909).</para><para>Where plaintiffs who should have joined bring separate actions, motion to consolidate is proper. Downey v. Coykendall, 81 Neb. 648, 116 N.W. 503 (1908).</para><para>Actions must be such as might have been joined. Weeks v. Wheeler, 41 Neb. 200, 59 N.W. 554 (1894).</para><para>Plaintiff is not required to join distinct claims in one action but may be required to consolidate actions. Beck v. Devereaux, 9 Neb. 109, 2 N.W. 365 (1879).</para><para>Five actions on separate policies and an action to enjoin encumbrances on three more policies may be consolidated. Equitable Life Assur. Soc. v. Wert, 102 F.2d 10 (8th Cir. 1939).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>