<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1245"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1245</statuteno><catchline>Affidavit; before whom made; attorney at law not disqualified.</catchline><para>An affidavit may be made in and out of this state before any person authorized to take depositions, and must be authenticated in the same way. An attorney at law who is attorney for a party in any proceedings in any court of this state shall not be disqualified as the person before whom the affidavit is made by reason of such representation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 371, p. 455; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7937; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8879; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1245; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1245; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 121, &#167; 1, p. 457. </para></source><annotation><para>Affidavits are not improper or excludable because notarized by one who is attorney of record. Frazier, Inc. v. 20th Century Builders, Inc., 188 Neb. 618, 198 N.W.2d 478 (1972).</para><para>Affidavits verified before attorneys for state held competent after being reverified before authorized officer. Baker v. State, 112 Neb. 654, 200 N.W. 876 (1924).</para><para>Attorney in case is not competent to act as notary in taking affidavit to be used on hearing. Maroosis v. Catalano, 98 Neb. 284, 152 N.W. 559 (1915); Horkey v. Kendall, 53 Neb. 522, 73 N.W. 953 (1898).</para><para>Objections to use of affidavit as evidence are not required to be made in the manner provided for interposing objections to depositions. Malcom Savings Bank v. Cronin, 80 Neb. 231, 116 N.W. 150 (1908).</para><para>Affidavit must have attached certificate of officer before whom taken that oath was administered. Sebesta v. Supreme Court of Honor, 77 Neb. 249, 109 N.W. 166 (1906).</para><para>Affidavit taken before notary of a sister state or foreign government was properly received. Browne v. Palmer, 66 Neb. 287, 92 N.W. 315 (1902).</para><para>There must be authentication by both seal and signature. Holmes v. Crooks, 56 Neb. 466, 76 N.W. 1073 (1898).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>