<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1063"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1063</statuteno><catchline>Temporary injunction; issuance; grounds.</catchline><para>When it appears by the complaint that the plaintiff is entitled to the relief demanded, and such relief or any part thereof consists in restraining the commission or continuance of some act, the commission or continuance of which during the litigation would produce great or irreparable injury to the plaintiff, or when, during the litigation, it appears that the defendant is doing, or threatens, or is about to do, or is procuring or suffering to be done, some act in violation of the plaintiff's rights respecting the subject of the action and tending to render the judgment ineffectual, a temporary injunction may be granted to restrain such act, subject to the limitations of sections 25-1062 to 25-1080. It may also be granted in any case specially authorized by statute.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 251, p. 435; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7792; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8736; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1063; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 29, &#167; 3, p. 134; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-1063; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1063; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 20.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Grounds</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Grounds</emphasis></para><para>Installment Loan Act specially provides for a temporary injunction. State ex rel. Beck v. Associates Discount Corp., 162 Neb. 683, 77 N.W.2d 215 (1956).</para><para>Where part of relief sought is to enjoin disposal of notes given for property, action may be brought in county where notes are held in escrow, and summons sent to other county. Bushee v. Keller, 96 Neb. 736, 148 N.W. 902 (1914).</para><para>Landowner will be enjoined from building fence without useful purpose, to annoy neighbor. Bush v. Mockett, 95 Neb. 552, 145 N.W. 1001 (1914).</para><para>Authorities should not ordinarily be enjoined from constructing necessary drains along highways. Wachter v. Lange, 94 Neb. 290, 143 N.W. 207 (1913).</para><para>Injunctions will be granted against repeated or continued acts of trespass. Ayers v. Barnett, 93 Neb. 350, 140 N.W. 634 (1913); Munger v. Yeiser, 80 Neb. 285, 114 N.W. 166 (1907); Jacobson v. Van Boening, 48 Neb. 80, 66 N.W. 993 (1896); Shaffer v. Stull, 32 Neb. 94, 48 N.W. 882 (1891).</para><para>Injunction is proper to protect enjoyment of easement. Ballinger v. Kinney, 87 Neb. 342, 127 N.W. 239 (1910).</para><para>Injunction is properly granted to restrain enforcement of void order taxing costs and remove cloud on title. Weiler v. Fischer, 86 Neb. 614, 126 N.W. 296 (1910).</para><para>Injunction will lie to restrain intruder interfering with incumbent of office. Hotchkiss v. Keck, 86 Neb. 322, 125 N.W. 509 (1910).</para><para>Injunction does not lie to prevent passage of city or village ordinance. Chicago, R. I. &amp; P. Ry. Co. v. City of Lincoln, 85 Neb. 733, 124 N.W. 142 (1910).</para><para>Injunction is proper to restrain road overseer taking land for road prior to condemnation proceedings. Johnson v. Peterson, 85 Neb. 83, 122 N.W. 683 (1909).</para><para>Injunction is proper to prevent collection of exempt wages under order of garnishment. Jones v. Union P. R. R. Co., 84 Neb. 121, 120 N.W. 946 (1909).</para><para>Injunction is proper to restrain use of premises as disorderly house. Seifert v. Dillon, 83 Neb. 322, 119 N.W. 686 (1909).</para><para>Injunction will be granted against waste by tenant for years or by his servants. Hayman v. Rownd, 82 Neb. 598, 118 N.W. 328 (1908).</para><para>Injunction will not lie to restrain commission of single act of trespass. Cox v. Sheen, 82 Neb. 472, 118 N.W. 125 (1908).</para><para>Injunction lies to restrain public officer from illegally creating debt or obligation. Roberts v. Thompson, 82 Neb. 458, 118 N.W. 106 (1908).</para><para>Injunction will be granted to restrain illegal assessment of special taxes by city council. Barkley v. City of Lincoln, 82 Neb. 181, 117 N.W. 398 (1908).</para><para>Injunction is not proper to restrain breach of contract where terms are in doubt or uncertain. Platte County Independent Tel. Co. v. Leigh Independent Tel. Co., 80 Neb. 41, 113 N.W. 799 (1907).</para><para>Injunction will be allowed to prevent removal of buildings and fences. Lynch v. Egan, 67 Neb. 541, 93 N.W. 775 (1903); Pohlman v. Evangelical Lutheran Trinity Church, 60 Neb. 364, 83 N.W. 201 (1900).</para><para>Injunction lies to prevent the obstruction or interference with irrigation ditch. Castle Rock Irrig. Canal &amp; Water Power Co. v. Jurisch, 67 Neb. 377, 93 N.W. 690 (1903); Park v. Ackerman, 60 Neb. 405, 83 N.W. 173 (1900).</para><para>Mandamus allowed in proper case to compel vacation. State ex rel. Cohn v. Jessen, 66 Neb. 515, 92 N.W. 584 (1902); Reynolds v. Graves, 66 Neb. 17, 92 N.W. 144 (1902).</para><para>Where plain and adequate remedy may be had by motion in original proceedings, injunction to stay proceedings will not lie. Carson v. Jansen, 65 Neb. 423, 91 N.W. 398 (1902).</para><para>Injunction will, in proper case, be allowed to prevent nuisance. Lowe v. Prospect Hill Cemetery Assn., 58 Neb. 94, 78 N.W. 488 (1899); Farrell v. Cook, 16 Neb. 483, 20 N.W. 720 (1884).</para><para>Injunction should not be allowed to restrain enforcement of judgment when plaintiff has negligently failed to make defense at law. Losey v. Neidig, 52 Neb. 167, 71 N.W. 1067 (1897).</para><para>Injunction is not proper remedy to test legality of municipal organization. Osborn v. Village of Oakland, 49 Neb. 340, 68 N.W. 506 (1896).</para><para>Injunction will be allowed against unlawful establishing of highway through plaintiff's land. Welton v. Dickson, 38 Neb. 767, 57 N.W. 559 (1894).</para><para>Injunction is not proper to restrain collection of taxes for mere irregularity. Touzalin v. City of Omaha, 25 Neb. 817, 41 N.W. 796 (1889).</para><para>Injunction cannot be used to control discretion of public officer. School Dist. No. 1 of Red Willow Co. v. Wheeler, 25 Neb. 199, 41 N.W. 143 (1888).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Injunction can issue against void occupation tax. Best &amp; Co., Inc. v. City of Omaha, 149 Neb. 868, 33 N.W.2d 150 (1948).</para><para>Enforcement of rights should be sought by peaceable legal procedure, not by force or stealth. Wallace v. Kruzer, 95 Neb. 615, 146 N.W. 984 (1914).</para><para>Restraining order is in aid only, and not part of main action. State ex rel. Keefe v. Graves, 82 Neb. 282, 117 N.W. 717 (1908).</para><para>"Irreparable injury" defined. Cole v. Manners, 76 Neb. 454, 107 N.W. 777 (1906); Eidemiller Ice Co. v. Guthrie, 42 Neb. 238, 60 N.W. 717 (1894).</para><para>Injunction does not lie to enforce bare legal right. Mohat v. Hutt, 75 Neb. 732, 106 N.W. 659 (1906).</para><para>Affidavits must set forth the acts constituting the violation; general allegation not sufficient. Back v. State, 75 Neb. 603, 106 N.W. 787 (1906).</para><para>Power of district court to punish for contempt discussed. Lowe v. Prospect Hill Cemetery Assn., 75 Neb. 85, 106 N.W. 429 (1905); Zimmerman v. State, 46 Neb. 13, 64 N.W. 375 (1895).</para><para>Order of court without jurisdiction, or in excess of powers is void. State ex rel. Ellingsworth v. Carlson, 72 Neb. 837, 101 N.W. 1004 (1904).</para><para>It is the duty of judge sitting at chambers to fix amount of supersedeas bond on entry of order of dissolution or modification. State ex rel. Plattsmouth Tel. Co. v. Baker, 62 Neb. 840, 88 N.W. 124 (1901); State ex rel. Downing v. Greene, 48 Neb. 327, 67 N.W. 162 (1896).</para><para>There is a distinction between order of injunction and temporary restraining order. State ex rel. Plattsmouth Tel. Co. v. Baker, 62 Neb. 840, 88 N.W. 124 (1901).</para><para>Petition should disclose with definiteness and particularity the threatened injury. Wabaska Elec. Co. v. City of Wymore, 60 Neb. 199, 82 N.W. 626 (1900); State Bank of Neb. of Seward v. Rohren, 55 Neb. 223, 75 N.W. 543 (1898).</para><para>One who knowingly disobeys injunction, though he would have been entitled to vacate order, is liable to punishment for contempt. Hydock v. State, 59 Neb. 296, 80 N.W. 902 (1899); Zimmerman v. State, 46 Neb. 13, 64 N.W. 375 (1895); Wilber v. Woolley, 44 Neb. 739, 62 N.W. 1095 (1895).</para><para>Adequate remedy at law discussed. Bankers Life Ins. Co. v. Robbins, 53 Neb. 44, 73 N.W. 269 (1897); Welton v. Dickson, 38 Neb. 767, 57 N.W. 559 (1894).</para><para>Order may be dissolved on security. State ex rel. Downing v. Greene, 48 Neb. 327, 67 N.W. 162 (1896); State ex rel. Beecher v. Wakeley, 28 Neb. 431, 44 N.W. 488 (1890).</para><para>Restraining order ceases to be operative on the expiration of the date fixed by its terms. State ex rel. Downing v. Greene, 48 Neb. 327, 67 N.W. 162 (1896).</para><para>Pleadings must state facts; threatened acts must be alleged. Blakeslee v. Missouri P. Ry. Co., 43 Neb. 61, 61 N.W. 118 (1894); Lininger v. Glenn, 33 Neb. 187, 49 N.W. 1128 (1891).</para><para>A mandatory injunction should not be granted except to prevent failure of justice, and only when right is clearly established. Buettgenbach v. Gerbig, 2 Neb. Unof. 889, 90 N.W. 654 (1902).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>