<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section id="id173"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id175" statutenumber="25-1130"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno id="id177">25-1130</statuteno><catchline id="id178">Reference by court order; when allowed.</catchline><para>When the parties do not consent, the court may, upon application of either, or of its own motion, direct a reference in any equity matter to a referee appointed by the court. The court shall direct a reference to a referee only when caseload and time constraints require such reference, and a referee shall not be appointed to conduct any hearing involving an issue of law and not equity that could result in the exercise of the right to a trial before a jury.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 299, p. 444; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7868; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8813; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1130; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1130; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 11.</para></source><annotation><para>Trial court can make a reference of an accounting to a referee. Corn Belt Products Co. v. Mullins, 172 Neb. 561, 110 N.W.2d 845 (1961).</para><para>Interlocutory order that plaintiff is entitled to account is unnecessary. Bennett v. Baum, 90 Neb. 320, 133 N.W. 439 (1911).</para><para>Right to jury cannot be defeated because of issues as to equitable rights. Yager v. Exchange Nat. Bank of Hastings, 52 Neb. 321, 72 N.W. 211 (1897).</para><para>Purely legal action cannot be referred, except on consent of parties. Kinkaid v. Hiatt, 24 Neb. 562, 39 N.W. 600 (1888).</para><para>Court may refer in partition without consent for taking of account. Mills v. Miller, 3 Neb. 87 (1873).</para><para>Where equitable counterclaim is filed in legal action it is not error to overrule general objection to reference of whole cause. Brown v. Keith, 1 Neb. Unof. 649, 96 N.W. 59 (1901).</para></annotation>  </law></legaldoc>