<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1125</statuteno><catchline>Five-sixths verdict; jurors to sign.</catchline><para>In all trials in civil actions in any court in this state, a verdict shall be rendered if five-sixths or more of the members of the jury concur therein, and such verdict shall have the same force and effect as though agreed to by all members of the jury; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that a verdict concurred in by less than all members of the jury shall not be rendered until the jury shall have had an opportunity for deliberation and consideration of the case for a period of not less than six hours after the same is submitted to said jury. If a verdict be concurred in by all the members of the jury, the foreman alone may sign it, but if rendered by a less number, such verdict shall be signed by all the jurors who shall agree to the verdict.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 124, &#167; 1, p. 534; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8808; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1125.</para></source><annotation><para>A juror is free to deliberate and vote on each issue presented to the jury, even if the juror has dissented from the majority on a previous issue. Gourley v. Nebraska Methodist Health Sys., 265 Neb. 918, 663 N.W.2d 43 (2003).</para><para>Even though a juror, who disagreed on the question of who was liable, provided the 10th vote necessary on the damages and apportionment questions, the verdict was valid. Gourley v. Nebraska Methodist Health Sys., 265 Neb. 918, 663 N.W.2d 43 (2003).</para><para>Length of time devoted to meals cannot be shown to prove that jury did not deliberate six hours. Cartwright &amp; Wilson Constr. Co. v. Smith, 155 Neb. 431, 52 N.W.2d 274 (1952).</para><para>The presumption is in favor of the regularity of the proceeding of the district court and that the jury deliberated six hours before returning the verdict by ten jurors. Lovelace v. Boatsman, 113 Neb. 145, 202 N.W. 418 (1925).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>