<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1017"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1017</statuteno><catchline>Order of attachment; effect; lien of consignee; interest and other costs; how computed.</catchline><para>An order of attachment binds the property attached from the time of service, and the garnishee shall stand liable to the plaintiff in attachment for all property, money, and credits in his hands, or due from him to defendant, from the time he is served with the written notice mentioned in section 25-1011, notwithstanding the money or debt owing by such garnishee, and which is sought to be attached, may be payable at the place of residence of a nonresident defendant; but where the property is attached in the hands of a consignee, his lien thereon shall not be affected by the attachment.</para><para>At the time of the issuance of the order of attachment, all interest and other costs due, as of that date, shall be computed. All interest and other costs which accrue after such date shall be specified on a per day basis or such other basis for assessment as may exist. Upon delivery of the attached property by the garnishee, such garnishee shall not be liable for interest or costs other than those specified in the order of attachment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 212, p. 427; </para><para>Laws 1911, c. 168, &#167; 4, p. 546; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7746; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8690; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1017; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1017; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 102, &#167; 2, p. 425; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 670, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Scope of lien</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Priorities</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Scope of lien</emphasis></para><para>Proceedings in garnishment are in the nature of notice of attachment to party in possession who becomes trustee. Crawford State Bank v. Murphy, 142 Neb. 795, 7 N.W.2d 762 (1943).</para><para>Debt owing by one Illinois corporation to another on contract payable in that state may, by attachment and garnishment in Nebraska, be subjected to payment of debt owing to resident of Iowa. Morrison v. Illinois C. R. R. Co., 101 Neb. 49, 161 N.W. 1032 (1917).</para><para>Lien of garnishment of debt due insolvent is subject to bankruptcy law. Hall v. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co., 88 Neb. 20, 128 N.W. 645 (1910).</para><para>Attachment lien merges in judgment lien. Lincoln Upholstering Co. v. Baker, 82 Neb. 592, 118 N.W. 321 (1908).</para><para>Lien is not lost by taking money judgment without order for sale. Coulson v. Saltsman, 71 Neb. 495, 98 N.W. 1055 (1904).</para><para>Plaintiff does not acquire full lien but right to hold garnishee personally liable for property or value. Benedict v. T. L. V. Land &amp; Cattle Co., 66 Neb. 236, 92 N.W. 210 (1902).</para><para>Lien by garnishment may attach to property held by fraudulent grantee of debtor. Glover v. Hargadine-McKittrick Dry Goods Co., 62 Neb. 483, 87 N.W. 170 (1901).</para><para>Attachment creditors of grantee of fraudulent conveyance acquire no valid lien against creditors of grantor. Westervelt v. Hagge, 61 Neb. 647, 85 N.W. 852 (1901).</para><para>Plaintiff by service of writ becomes entitled to all rights of defendant against garnishee. Cahn v. Carpless Co., 61 Neb. 512, 85 N.W. 538 (1901); Chamberlain Banking House v. Reliance Ins. Co., 59 Neb. 195, 80 N.W. 822 (1899).</para><para>Plaintiff has lien only to extent of defendant's actual interest. Barnes v. Cox, 58 Neb. 675, 79 N.W. 550 (1899); Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. First Nat. Bank of Omaha, 58 Neb. 548, 78 N.W. 1064 (1899).</para><para>Lien of attachment on insolvent bank is not vacated by appointment of receiver. Arnold v. Weimer, 40 Neb. 216, 58 N.W. 709 (1894).</para><para>Garnishment does not affect vendor's rights of stoppage in transit. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. Painter &amp; Sons, 15 Neb. 394, 19 N.W. 488 (1884).</para><para>Deed executed after attachment levied is subject to judgment. Wright v. Smith, 11 Neb. 341, 7 N.W. 537 (1881).</para><para><emphasis>2. Priorities</emphasis></para><para>Garnishment is subject to prior bona fide assignments of debt. Cockins v. Bank of Alma, 84 Neb. 624, 122 N.W. 16 (1909).</para><para>Rights of holder of prior unrecorded deed stated. Naudain v. Fullenwider, 72 Neb. 221, 100 N.W. 296 (1904).</para><para>Attachment lien is prior to rights of vendor under unrecorded conditional sale contract. New Home Sewing Machine Co. v. Beals, 44 Neb. 816, 62 N.W. 1092 (1895).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>This section is designed to supplement and implement general attachment statute. Insurance Co. of North America v. Maxim's of Nebraska, 178 Neb. 274, 132 N.W.2d 885 (1965).</para><para>Lien may be enforced by creditor's bill. Hargreaves v. Tennis, 63 Neb. 356, 88 N.W. 486 (1901).</para><para>Officer holding personal property under lawful attachment levy may be charged as garnishee and the property bound from the time of the service of summons in garnishment on him. Pitkin v. Burnham, 62 Neb. 385, 87 N.W. 160 (1901).</para><para>Purchaser after attachment is bound by adjudication as to validity of attachment. Nagle v. First Nat. Bank of Omaha, 57 Neb. 552, 77 N.W. 1074 (1899).</para><para>Property is in custody of law after garnishee is summoned. Meyer v. Miller, 51 Neb. 620, 71 N.W. 315 (1897).</para><para>Judgment debtor may be garnished; but not under writ from another court. Scott v. Rohman, 43 Neb. 618, 62 N.W. 46 (1895).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>