<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1660"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1660</statuteno><catchline>Jurors; how summoned; notice; deadlines, applicability.</catchline><para>(1) The summons of grand and petit jurors for the courts of this state shall be served by the jury commissioner, the clerk of such court, or any other person authorized by the court by delivering such summons by first-class mail or personal service or through a jury management system to the person whose name has been drawn.</para><para>(2)(a) If the jury commissioner uses the two-step qualifying and summoning system, the summons shall be delivered not less than ten days before the day such juror is to appear as a juror in such court.</para><para>(b) If the jury commissioner uses the one-step qualifying and summoning system, the summons shall be delivered:</para><para>(i) Not less than ten days before the first day of the jury term, if the jury commissioner is summoning jurors for service throughout the jury term; or</para><para>(ii) Not less than ten days before the day such juror is to appear as a juror in such court, if the jury commissioner is summoning a juror for service on a specific jury panel.</para><para>(c) The deadlines in this subsection shall not apply to summons delivered to extra jurors pursuant to section 25-1665 or tales jurors pursuant to section 25-1666. Summons to such jurors shall be delivered at the earliest possible time under the circumstances and as directed by the judge or judges.</para><para>(3)(a) If the jury commissioner uses the two-step qualifying and summoning system, a summons sent under this section shall include the day, time, place, and name of the court where the juror is to report for jury service.</para><para>(b) If the jury commissioner uses the one-step qualifying and summoning system, a summons sent under this section shall include such details as to the day, time, place, and name of the court where the juror is to report for jury service as are known at the time the summons is sent along with additional instructions regarding the manner in which the juror shall contact the court or will be notified by the court of any additional details.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167;&#167; 661, 662, p. 510; </para><para>Laws 1885, c. 97, &#167; 1, p. 381; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8141; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 148, &#167; 1, p. 318; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9076; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1606; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1606; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 72, &#167; 3, p. 225; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 242, &#167; 18, p. 831; </para><para>Laws 1982, LB 677, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 25-1606; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 17. </para></source><annotation><para>This section was cited as illustrative of service of process by registered mail. Blauvelt v. Beck, 162 Neb. 576, 76 N.W.2d 738 (1956).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>