<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1105"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1105</statuteno><catchline>Issues of fact triable to court.</catchline><para>All other issues of fact shall be tried by the court, subject to its power to order any issue or issues to be tried by a jury, or referred as provided in this code.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 281, p. 441; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7844; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8788; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1105.</para></source><annotation><para>Claims brought under this section may be equitable in nature, and in such case the court may submit questions of fact to the jury, but the jury's determination is only an advisory one. In re Estate of Layton, 212 Neb. 518, 323 N.W.2d 817 (1982).</para><para>Appeals in guardianship matters are heard de novo in Supreme Court. Cass v. Pense, 155 Neb. 792, 54 N.W.2d 68 (1952).</para><para>Contest over sufficiency of election by widow to take under statute was triable de novo in Supreme Court. In re Estate of Bergren, 154 Neb. 289, 47 N.W.2d 582 (1951).</para><para>In suits not triable by jury as of right, a verdict of a jury is advisory only. In re Guardianship of Warner, 137 Neb. 25, 288 N.W. 39 (1939).</para><para>Jury cannot be demanded on adverse possession issue in suit to quiet title. Krumm v. Pillard, 104 Neb. 335, 177 N.W. 171 (1920).</para><para>Verdict in equity case on issue of fact is advisory only. Bank of Stockham v. Alter, 61 Neb. 359, 85 N.W. 300 (1901).</para><para>Issues in equity causes are triable to the court without a jury. Smith v. Perry, 52 Neb. 738, 73 N.W. 282 (1897).</para><para>Power of court of equity to obtain verdict of jury on issues of fact is preserved by the code. Omaha Fire Ins. Co. v. Thompson, 50 Neb. 580, 70 N.W. 30 (1897).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>