<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts Civil Procedure" id="id16" statutenumber="25-1647"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1647</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Jury commissioner; designation; salary; expenses; duties; salary increase, when effective.</catchline><para>(1) In each county of the State of Nebraska, the clerk of the district court shall serve as the jury commissioner.</para><para>(2) In counties having a population in excess of one hundred seventy-five thousand inhabitants, the judges of the district court within such counties shall determine whether the clerk of the district court will receive additional compensation to perform the duties of jury commissioner. The amount of any such additional compensation shall be fixed by the judges of the district court in an amount not to exceed three thousand dollars per annum.</para><para>(3) In all counties the necessary expenses incurred in the performance of the duties of jury commissioner shall be paid by the county board of the county out of the general fund, upon proper claims approved by one of the district judges in the judicial district and duly filed with the county board.</para><para>(4) In all counties the jury commissioner shall prepare and file the annual inventory statement with the county board of the county of all county personal property in his or her custody or possession, as provided in sections 23-346 to 23-350.</para><para>(5) This section shall be so interpreted as to effectuate its general purpose, to provide, in the public interest, adequate compensation for the jury commissioner and to permit a change in such salary as soon as the change may become operative under the Constitution of Nebraska.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 248, &#167; 1, p. 568; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9095; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1625; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 65, &#167; 5, p. 178; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 20, p. 159; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-1625; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1625; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 62, &#167; 9, p. 202; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 72, &#167; 6, p. 227; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 113, &#167; 1, p. 352; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 547, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 527, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 234, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 19, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB169, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 25-1625; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB922, &#167; 2. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2023</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Statutory procedure for selection and impaneling of juries in a county the size of Douglas is provided. Maher v. State, 144 Neb. 463, 13 N.W.2d 641 (1944).</para><para>Jury commissioner act indicates modern trend against advance disclosure of names of jurors. Fetty v. State, 118 Neb. 169, 223 N.W. 955 (1929).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>