<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1405"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1405</statuteno><catchline>Death of party; cessation of powers of personal representative; right of action surviving to or against successor; revivor.</catchline><para>Where one of the parties to an action dies, or his powers as a personal representative cease, before the judgment, if the right of action survives in favor of or against his representatives or successor, the action may be revived, and proceed in their names.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 458, p. 470; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8026; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8967; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1405.</para></source><annotation><para>Where there is no probate and no personal representative of the original plaintiff, the action may be revived in the names of the heirs-at-law of the original plaintiff. Spradlin v. Myers, 200 Neb. 559, 264 N.W.2d 658 (1978).</para><para>Section is not applicable as to revivor sought by executor of widow's estate in claim for widow's allowance. In re Samson's Estate, 142 Neb. 556, 7 N.W.2d 60 (1942).</para><para>Where party plaintiff dies before judgment, action can no longer proceed in his name but must be revived. Vogt v. Daily, 70 Neb. 812, 98 N.W. 31 (1904).</para><para>Action to recover support for child born out of wedlock may be revived in name of county. Dodge County v. Kemnitz, 28 Neb. 224, 44 N.W. 184 (1889).</para><para>Because inmate's cause of action against the State for allegedly violating his constitutional rights did not survive his death, it could not be revived. Fitzgerald v. Clarke, 9 Neb. App. 898, 621 N.W.2d 844 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>