<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1541"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1541</statuteno><catchline>Sale of lands or tenements; reversal of judgment; title of purchaser; restitution.</catchline><para>If any judgment or judgments, in satisfaction of which any lands or tenements are sold, shall at any time thereafter be reversed, such reversal shall not defeat or affect the title of the purchaser or purchasers; but, in such case, restitution shall be made by the judgment creditor, of the money for which such lands or tenements were sold, with lawful interest from the day of sale.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 508, p. 480; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8087; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9023; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1541; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1541.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Reversal of judgment</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Bona fide purchaser</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Reversal of judgment</emphasis></para><para>There is no sale as contemplated by the statute until order of confirmation is entered and time for superseding the order has elapsed and, where defendant appeals from order confirming sale, said order being superseded, and judgment is reversed, an order may be entered quashing the levy and vacating the sale. Baxter v. National Mortgage Loan Co., 130 Neb. 256, 264 N.W. 675 (1936).</para><para>Payment of judgment made by defendant to avoid sale of his property on execution does not waive his right to appeal. Burke v. Dendinger, 120 Neb. 594, 234 N.W. 405 (1931).</para><para>Upon reversal of judgment which has been executed, it is duty of court to compel restitution. Hier v. Anheuser-Busch Brewing Assn., 60 Neb. 320, 83 N.W. 77 (1900).</para><para>Title of stranger through sale under judgment is not defeated by subsequent reversal of judgment. Manfull v. Graham, 55 Neb. 645, 76 N.W. 19 (1898).</para><para>Where judgment creditor purchases at execution sale on judgment which is subsequently reversed, it is his duty to make restitution. Nelson v. City of Beatrice, 2 Neb. Unof. 47, 96 N.W. 288 (1901).</para><para><emphasis>2. Bona fide purchaser</emphasis></para><para>Bona fide purchaser under decree of partition, no fraud being shown, is protected hereunder although judgment is thereafter reversed. Schleuning v. Tatro, 122 Neb. 3, 238 N.W. 741 (1931).</para><para>Only good faith purchaser is protected. Pauley v. Knouse, 109 Neb. 716, 192 N.W. 195 (1923).</para><para>Purchaser defined; one who made bona fide contract to purchase land sold under erroneous judgment is protected to extent of money paid, with interest. Coon v. O'Brien, 107 Neb. 427, 186 N.W. 340 (1922).</para><para>One who purchases knowing that proceedings are fraudulent, and that he is assisting in the fraud, does not get good title. Coates v. O'Connor, 102 Neb. 602, 168 N.W. 102 (1918), rehearing denied 102 Neb. 606, 169 N.W. 239 (1918).</para><para>Bona fide purchaser under judicial decree is protected by this section, though judgment is thereafter reversed. Kazebeer v. Nunemaker, 82 Neb. 732, 118 N.W. 646 (1908).</para><para>Purchaser should recover from redemptioner purchase money paid. Hitchcock County v. Cole, 80 Neb. 375, 114 N.W. 276 (1907).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>