<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id26">
<sectno id="id27" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id28" statutenumber="25-1628"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id30">25-1628</statuteno><catchline id="id31">Jury list; how
made up.</catchline><para>(1) At least once each calendar year,
the officer having charge of the election records shall furnish to the jury
commissioner a complete list of the names, dates of birth, addresses,
and motor vehicle operator license numbers or state identification card numbers of
all registered electors nineteen years of age or older in the county. The
Department of Motor Vehicles shall make available to each jury commissioner
each December a list in magnetic, optical, digital, or other electronic format
mutually agreed to by the jury commissioner and the department containing
the names, dates of birth, addresses, and motor vehicle operator license numbers
or state identification card numbers of all licensed motor vehicle
operators and state identification card holders nineteen years of age or older
in the county. The jury commissioner may request such a list of licensed motor
vehicle operators and state identification card holders from the county treasurer
if the county treasurer has an automated procedure for developing such lists.
If a jury commissioner requests similar lists at other times from the department,
the cost of processing such lists shall be paid by the county which the requesting
jury commissioner serves.</para>
<para>(2) Upon receipt of both lists described in subsection (1)
of this section, the jury commissioner shall combine the separate lists and
attempt to reduce duplication to the best of his or her ability to produce
a master list. In counties having a population of seven thousand
inhabitants or more, the jury commissioner shall produce a master list at
least once each calendar year. In counties having a population of three thousand inhabitants but less
than seven thousand inhabitants,
the jury commissioner shall produce a master list at least once every two
calendar years. In counties
having a population of less than three thousand inhabitants, the jury commissioner
shall produce a master list at least once every five calendar years.</para>
<para>(3) The proposed juror list shall be derived by selecting
from the master list the name of the person whose numerical order on such
list corresponds with the key number and each successive tenth name thereafter.
The jury commissioner shall certify that the proposed juror list has been
made in accordance with sections 25-1625 to 25-1637.</para>
<para>(4) Any duplication of names on a master list shall not be
grounds for quashing any panel pursuant to section 25-1637 or for the disqualification
of any juror.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 248, &#167; 4, p. 569; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9098; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1628; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1628; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 88, &#167; 1, p. 337; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 11, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 113, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 82, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 19, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 402, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 3.</para></source><annotation><para>A defendant in a criminal case is not entitled to a proportionate number of his race on the jury. State v. Gutierrez, 187 Neb. 383, 191 N.W.2d 164 (1971).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>