<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1093.02"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1093.02</statuteno><catchline>Affidavit; filing; service; temporary order; effect; hearing; when.</catchline><para>Upon the filing of such affidavit and request for delivery, if the defendant with full knowledge of the allegations and effect of the plaintiff's request agrees that such delivery in replevin be had, he may execute a voluntary, intelligent, and knowing waiver under oath of his rights to notice and hearing, in which event the court shall order that all further proceedings shall be suspended and the property being replevied delivered to the plaintiff forthwith, otherwise upon the filing of such affidavit and request for delivery required by section 25-1093.01, the court shall issue a temporary order addressed to the defendant that he shall hold the property described in the affidavit in his possession, unimpaired and unencumbered, and in all respects in the same state and condition as at the time of receipt of the order, until further order of the court. The temporary order shall also notify such defendant that if he fails to comply with the temporary order he shall be subject to the full contempt powers of the court. Attached to such temporary order shall be a notice that a hearing will be had and specifying the date, time, and place of such hearing, at which hearing will be determined plaintiff's right to possession of the goods described in plaintiff's affidavit and request for delivery, pending final determination of the merits. At such hearing the defendant shall be required to show cause why the possession of the goods should not be delivered to the plaintiff. Unless otherwise determined and ordered by the court, the date of such hearing shall be seven days after service of the order upon the defendant, but in no event later than fourteen days after service.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 474, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1976, LB 859, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>A temporary order entered pursuant to this provision, which requires the defendant in replevin action to hold the property unimpaired and unencumbered until hearing which must take place within fourteen days after service and at which court determines plaintiff's right to possession pending final resolution on the merits, results in a deprivation of property rights sufficient to trigger due process protection. Lewis Service Center, Inc. v. Mack Financial Corp., 696 F.2d 66 (8th Cir. 1982).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>