<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-1224"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1224</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Subpoena; to whom directed; production of documents, information, or tangible things; Supreme Court; powers.</catchline><para>(1) A subpoena commanding an individual to appear and testify at a trial or deposition may command that at the same time and place specified in the subpoena for the individual to appear and testify, the individual must produce designated documents, electronically stored information, or tangible things in the individual's possession, custody, or control. The scope of a command to produce documents, electronically stored information, or tangible things pursuant to this section is governed by the rules of discovery in civil cases.</para><para>(2) The Supreme Court may promulgate a rule for discovery in civil cases that specifies the procedures to be followed when a party seeks to serve a deposition subpoena that commands the individual to produce designated documents, electronically stored information, or tangible things in the individual's possession, custody, or control. Any such rule shall not conflict with the laws governing such matters.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 351, p. 452; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7916; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8858; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1224; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1224; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB509, &#167; 2. </para><effectivedate>August 24, 2017</effectivedate></source><annotation><para>A DNA sample is not documentary in nature and is not discoverable under this section. State v. McKinney, 273 Neb. 346, 730 N.W.2d 74 (2007).</para><para>A subpoena duces tecum for trial imposes a duty upon the witness to bring with him sought-after matter under his control that the law requires him to produce as evidence. City of Omaha v. American Theater Corp., 189 Neb. 441, 203 N.W.2d 155 (1973).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>