<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1678"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1678</statuteno><catchline>Juries; proceedings stayed; jury panel or list quashed; grounds; procedures; new list, order for.</catchline><para>(1) A party may move to stay the proceedings, to quash the entire jury panel or jury list, or for other appropriate relief on the ground of substantial failure to comply with the Jury Selection Act in selecting the grand or petit jury. Such motion shall be made within seven days after the moving party discovered or by the exercise of diligence could have discovered the grounds for such motion, and in any event before the petit jury is sworn to try the case.</para><para>(2) Upon a motion filed under subsection (1) of this section containing a sworn statement of facts which, if true, would constitute a substantial failure to comply with the Jury Selection Act, the moving party is entitled to present, in support of the motion, the testimony of the jury commissioner or the clerk, any relevant records and papers not public or otherwise available which were used by the jury commissioner or the clerk, and any other relevant evidence. If the court determines that in selecting either a grand jury or a petit jury there has been a substantial failure to comply with the Jury Selection Act, the court shall stay the proceedings pending the selection of the jury in conformity with the act, quash an entire jury panel or jury list, or grant other appropriate relief.</para><para>(3) The procedures prescribed by this section are the exclusive means by which the state, a person accused of a crime, or a party in a civil case may challenge a jury on the ground that the jury was not selected in conformity with the Jury Selection Act.</para><para>(4) The contents of any records or papers used by the jury commissioner or the clerk in connection with the selection process and not made public under the Jury Selection Act shall not be disclosed, except in connection with the preparation or presentation of a motion under subsection (1) of this section, until after all persons on the jury list have been discharged. The parties in a case may inspect, reproduce, and copy the records or papers at all reasonable times during the preparation and pendency of a motion under subsection (1) of this section.</para><para>(5) Whenever the entire jury list is quashed, the court shall make an order directing the jury commissioner to draw a new key number in the manner provided in section 25-1653 and prepare a new master key list in the manner provided in section 25-1654. The jury commissioner shall qualify and summon jurors from the new master key list as provided in the Jury Selection Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 248, &#167; 13, p. 577; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9108; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1637; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1637; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 102, &#167; 3, p. 425; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 234, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 113, &#167; 4; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 25-1637; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 35. </para><operativedate>January 1, 2021</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (1) of this section, an objection pertaining to a failure to comply with Batson requirements must be made before the jury is sworn to try the case. An objection challenging prosecution's strike of juror because of race must be made prior to swearing of jury. State v. Covarrubias, 244 Neb. 366, 507 N.W.2d 248 (1993).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>