<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1064"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1064</statuteno><catchline>Temporary injunctions and restraining orders; courts and judges empowered to issue; conditions; temporary restraining order granted without notice; requirements; actions involving irrigation water; notice, how given.</catchline><para>(1) The injunction may be granted at the time of commencing the action or at any time afterward before judgment by the Court of Appeals or the Supreme Court or any judge thereof. No restraining order or temporary injunction should be granted at the time of the commencement of the action if the relief demanded involves the delivery of irrigation water and the Director of Natural Resources, as defined in section 25-1062.01, is a party except in accordance with the procedure prescribed in subsection (5) of this section.</para><para>(2) No temporary injunction may be granted without notice to the adverse party.</para><para>(3) Any judge of the district court, except when the relief demanded involves the delivery of irrigation water and the director is a party, may grant a temporary restraining order without notice to the adverse party or his or her attorney only if (a) it clearly appears from specific facts shown by affidavit that immediate and irreparable injury, loss, or damage will result to the applicant before the adverse party or his or her attorney can be heard in opposition and (b) the applicant or his or her attorney certifies to the court in writing the efforts, if any, which have been made to give such notice and the reasons supporting the applicant's claim that such notice shall not be required.</para><para>Every temporary restraining order granted without notice shall: (i) Be endorsed with the date and hour of issuance; (ii) be filed immediately in the office of the clerk of the district court and entered of record; (iii) define the injury and state why the injury is irreparable and why the order was granted without notice; and (iv) expire by its terms within such time after entry, not to exceed ten days, as the court fixes unless within such fixed time period the order, for good cause shown, is extended for a like period or unless the party against whom the order is directed consents to an extension for a longer period. The reasons for the extension shall be entered of record. If a temporary restraining order is granted without notice, the motion for a temporary injunction shall be heard at the earliest possible time in the district court and shall take precedence over all matters except older matters of the same character. When the motion for a temporary injunction comes up for hearing, the party who obtained the temporary restraining order shall proceed with the application for a temporary injunction, and if he or she does not do so, the district court shall dissolve the temporary restraining order. On two days' notice to the party who obtained the temporary restraining order without notice or on such shorter notice to such party as the district court may prescribe, the adverse party may appear and move for the dissolution or modification of the order, and in that event, the court shall proceed to hear and determine such motion as expeditiously as the ends of justice require.</para><para>(4) In the absence from the county of the district judges, any judge of the county court, except when the relief demanded involves the delivery of irrigation water and the director is a party, may grant a temporary restraining order without notice to the adverse party or his or her attorney only if (a) it clearly appears from specific facts shown by affidavit that immediate and irreparable injury, loss, or damage will result to the applicant before the adverse party or his or her attorney can be heard in opposition and (b) the applicant or his or her attorney certifies to the court in writing the efforts, if any, which have been made to give such notice and the reasons supporting the applicant's claim that such notice shall not be required. The judge of the county court shall direct that reasonable notice be given to the party against whom the temporary restraining order is issued to attend at a specified time or place before the district court or any judge thereof to show cause why a temporary injunction should not be issued.</para><para>Every temporary restraining order granted without notice shall: (i) Be endorsed with the date and hour of issuance; (ii) be filed immediately in the office of the clerk of the district court and entered of record; (iii) define the injury and state why the injury is irreparable and why the order was granted without notice; and (iv) expire by its terms within such time after entry, not to exceed ten days, as the judge of the county court fixes unless within such fixed time period the order, for good cause shown, is extended by the district court for a like period or unless the party against whom the order is directed consents to an extension for a longer period. The reasons for the extension shall be entered of record.</para><para>(5) The Supreme Court or any judge thereof, the Court of Appeals or any judge thereof, the district court or any judge thereof, or a judge of the county court, if and when he or she has jurisdiction, shall have no power, when the relief demanded involves the delivery of irrigation water and the director is a party, to grant a restraining order or temporary injunction at the time of the commencement of the action, except when notice by either registered or certified letter has been mailed seventy-two hours prior to the time of hearing to the director and the division supervisor in the water division created by section 61-212 in which the action is brought and, in the manner provided in section 25-1062.01, to all appropriators whose rights to the delivery of irrigation water might in any manner be affected, of the time and place of the hearing. At the hearing on the restraining order or temporary injunction, the director, appropriators, or riparian owners shall be entitled to be heard, in person or by their attorney or attorneys, on the question of whether the restraining order should be granted and, if so, in what amount the bond or undertaking is to be fixed.</para><para>(6) Any person, natural or artificial, injured or likely to be injured by the granting of a restraining order may intervene in the action at any stage of the proceedings and become a party to the litigation if it involves the delivery of irrigation water and the director is a party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 252, p. 435; </para><para>Laws 1913, c. 65, &#167; 1, p. 198; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7793; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8737; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1064; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 29, &#167; 4, p. 134; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-1064; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1064; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 260; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 242, &#167; 15, p. 828; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 365, &#167; 2, p. 1232; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 516, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 44; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 900, &#167; 66. </para></source><annotation><para>Notwithstanding section 24-517(5), the district court has jurisdiction in injunctive actions to enforce zoning ordinances. Village of Springfield v. Hevelone, 195 Neb. 37, 236 N.W.2d 811 (1975).</para><para>Supreme Court may grant a temporary injunction in proceedings by state under Installment Loan Act. State ex rel. Beck v. Associates Discount Corp., 162 Neb. 683, 77 N.W.2d 215 (1956).</para><para>District judge has power to allow temporary injunction, notwithstanding provisions of this section. State ex rel. Hahler v. Grimes, 96 Neb. 719, 148 N.W. 942 (1914).</para><para>Affidavit not stating Supreme Judges were absent is sufficient to allow county judge to act, latter cannot issue perpetual injunction. State ex rel. Minden-Edison Light &amp; Power Co. v. Dungan, 89 Neb. 738, 132 N.W. 305 (1911).</para><para>County judge may grant temporary restraining order if district judge is absent. State ex rel. Downing v. Greene, 48 Neb. 327, 67 N.W. 162 (1896).</para><para>Violation of injunction allowed by county judge is contempt for district court. Wilber v. Woolley, 44 Neb. 739, 62 N.W. 1095 (1895).</para><para>County judge cannot punish for contempt of violation of restraining order. Johnson v. Bouton, 35 Neb. 898, 53 N.W. 995 (1892).</para><para>Judge of Supreme Court may grant temporary injunction. Calvert v. State, 34 Neb. 616, 52 N.W. 687 (1892).</para><para>District judge cannot grant injunction out of district unless judge therein is absent or unable to act; injunction void. Ellis v. Karl, 7 Neb. 381 (1878).</para><para>Order granted by county judge before petition filed is valid, where both filed forthwith. Commercial State Bank of Crawford v. Ketcham, 3 Neb. Unof. 839, 92 N.W. 998 (1902).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>