<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1029"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1029</statuteno><catchline>Garnishment; property; delivery into court; bond in lieu of delivery.</catchline><para>If the garnishee answers that, at the time of the service of the summons and interrogatories upon him or her, he or she was possessed of any property of the defendant or was indebted to him or her, the court may order the delivery of such property and the payment of the amount owing by the garnishee into court; or the court may permit the garnishee to retain the property or the amount owing, upon the execution of an undertaking to the plaintiff by one or more sufficient sureties to the effect that the amount shall be paid or the property forthcoming as the court may direct. If the garnishee presents to the court, by affidavit or otherwise, specific facts demonstrating that no sureties are necessary to insure that the amount owing by the garnishee shall be paid, or the property forthcoming, the court may allow the undertaking to be executed by the garnishee alone.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 224, p. 430; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7758; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8702; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1029; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1029; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 67, &#167; 6, p. 204; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 101, &#167; 3, p. 423; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 597, &#167; 11. </para></source><annotation><para>Where original judgment on which garnishment proceedings are based is made ineffective by bankruptcy of judgment debtor, the garnishment summons and power and rights thereunder cease; garnishee is released from liability on summons although court made no order. Savard v. Physicians Casualty Co., 124 Neb. 627, 247 N.W. 567 (1933).</para><para>In absence of fraud or collusion, no garnishable debt arises from contract for personal services paid for in advance. Salyers Auto Co. v. De Vore, 116 Neb. 317, 217 N.W. 94 (1927).</para><para>Where garnishment proceedings are void, money should be returned to garnishee. Yeiser v. Cathers, 73 Neb. 317, 102 N.W. 612 (1905).</para><para>Judgment debtor is liable to process of garnishment when the two actions are brought in the same court. Scott v. Rohman, 43 Neb. 618, 62 N.W. 46 (1895).</para><para>Garnishee, not making full disclosure, is liable over to creditor. Smith v. Ainscow, 11 Neb. 476, 9 N.W. 646 (1881).</para><para>Garnishee, not making full disclosure, defendant have judgment, if appeal is taken. Dolby v. Tingley, 9 Neb. 412, 2 N.W. 866 (1879).</para><para>Liability of garnishee is to be determined by status of fund when answer is taken. First Nat. Bank of Pawnee City v. Manning, 2 Neb. Unof. 3, 95 N.W. 1128 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>