<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1090"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1090</statuteno><catchline>Inconclusive decree; appointment of master; disposition of property; orders; appeal.</catchline><para>When a decree is rendered in a suit in which a receiver has been appointed and such decree does not finally determine the rights of the parties, any one of them may apply to the court for the possession of the property and proceeds thereof in the receiver's hands. If such application is resisted, the matter may be referred to a master to take and report to the court the testimony of the parties. Upon the filing of the report, the court shall, by its order, award the possession of the property and the proceeds thereof to the party entitled thereto, and thereupon the receiver shall surrender the property and the proceeds thereof to such party. All orders appointing receivers, giving them further directions, and disposing of the property may be appealed to the Court of Appeals in the same manner as final orders and decrees.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 275, p. 439; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7819; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8763; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1090; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1090; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 46. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For appeals to Court of Appeals,</emphasis> see section 25-1911 et seq.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Appeal</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Supersedeas</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Appeal</emphasis></para><para>
An order appointing a receiver is a final, appealable order. Floral Lawns Memorial Gardens Assn. v. Becker, 284 Neb. 532, 822 N.W.2d 692 (2012).</para><para>The appointment of a receiver may be treated as a final order. Robertson v. Southwood, 233 Neb. 685, 447 N.W.2d 616 (1989).</para><para>An order confirming a sale by a receiver is a final order from which an appeal can be taken. Lewis v. Gallemore, 173 Neb. 441, 113 N.W.2d 595 (1962).</para><para>This section was incorporated by reference in procedure for liquidation of insolvent banks. State ex rel. Sorensen v. Nebraska State Bank of Bloomfield, 124 Neb. 449, 247 N.W. 31 (1933).</para><para>Order of court appointing receiver is final and appealable hereunder. State ex rel. Sorensen v. State Bank of Minatare, 123 Neb. 109, 242 N.W. 278 (1932).</para><para>Statute authorizes appeal from order appointing receiver; appointment of receiver sustained. Howell v. Poff, 122 Neb. 793, 241 N.W. 548 (1932).</para><para>Order to receiver to sell real estate is appealable. State ex rel. German Sav. Bank v. Fawcett, 58 Neb. 371, 78 N.W. 636 (1899).</para><para>Objections are available on appeal from final decree. Seeds Dry-Plate Co. v. Heyn Photo-Supply Co., 57 Neb. 214, 77 N.W. 660 (1898).</para><para>Bank may appeal from order directing suit against its stockholders. State v. German Savings Bank, 50 Neb. 734, 70 N.W. 221 (1897).</para><para>Appointment is final order; appealable before final judgment. McCord, Brady &amp; Co. v. Weil, 33 Neb. 868, 51 N.W. 300 (1892).</para><para>A summary judgment in a receiver's favor finding that he is not liable to an intervenor for a claim is a "direction" to a receiver from which an appeal is allowable; such summary judgment is "final" because it fully and completely determines the dispute between the intervenor and the receiver. Sutton v. Killham, 19 Neb. App. 842, 820 N.W.2d 292 (2012).</para><para><emphasis>2. Supersedeas</emphasis></para><para>Whether order may be superseded is discretionary with court, and court may fix terms and conditions thereof. Lowe v. Riley, 57 Neb. 252, 77 N.W. 758 (1898).</para><para>Order appointing receiver cannot be superseded pending appeal, as matter of right. State ex rel. Heinzelman v. Stull, 49 Neb. 739, 69 N.W. 101 (1896).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>