<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id168" statutenumber="25-1129"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1129</statuteno><catchline id="id171">Reference by consent; when allowed.</catchline><para>All or any of the issues in the action, whether of fact or law or both, may be referred to a referee upon the written consent of the parties or upon their oral consent in court entered upon the record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 298, p. 444; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7867; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8812; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1129; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1129; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB1014, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 15. </para></source><annotation><para>A referee's factual findings are entitled to some deference, but no such deference is owed to the referee's conclusions or recommendations. Becher v. Becher, 299 Neb. 206, 908 N.W.2d 12 (2018).</para><para>The question of the defendant's agency was within the issue of receivership and therefor within the authority given the referee, and the filing of a supplemental report which recommended appointment of a receiver was proper in this case. Beavers v. Graham, 209 Neb. 556, 308 N.W.2d 826 (1981).</para><para>Special master appointed by court is a referee. Gentsch, Inc. v. Burnett, 173 Neb. 820, 115 N.W.2d 446 (1962).</para><para>Supreme Court has inherent power to refer original cases. State ex rel. Broatch v. Moores, 56 Neb. 1, 76 N.W. 530 (1898).</para><para>Party participating in proceedings before referee is estopped to deny consent to reference. Morris v. Haas, 54 Neb. 579, 74 N.W. 828 (1898).</para><para>Court will presume consent was given to action to a referee when record fails to show that objections were made. Hosford v. Stone, 6 Neb. 378 (1877).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>