<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-12,112"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-12,112</statuteno><catchline>Admissibility of reproduced records in evidence; destruction of records; approval.</catchline><para>If any business, institution, member of a profession or calling, or department or agency of government in the regular course of business or activity has kept or recorded any memorandum, writing, entry, print, representation, or combination thereof of any act, transaction, occurrence, or event and in the regular course of business has caused any or all of the same to be recorded, copied, or reproduced by any photographic, photostatic, optical imagery, microfilm, microcard, miniature photographic, optical disk, or other process which accurately reproduces or forms a durable medium for so reproducing the original, the original may be destroyed in the regular course of business unless held in a custodial or fiduciary capacity or unless its preservation is required by law and, with respect to agencies or departments of government, if the State Records Administrator approves such destruction. Such reproduction, when satisfactorily identified, is as admissible in evidence as the original itself in any judicial or administrative proceeding whether the original is in existence or not and an enlargement or facsimile of such reproduction is likewise admissible in evidence if the original reproduction is in existence and available for inspection under direction of the court. The introduction of a reproduced record, enlargement, or facsimile does not preclude admission of the original.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1951, c. 56, &#167; 1, p. 188; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 105, &#167; 6, p. 481; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 25, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 980, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Credit union records,</emphasis> see section 21-1737.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Copy of memorandum from Postmaster General regarding early retirement opportunities was admissible hereunder. Corn v. Corn, 190 Neb. 383, 208 N.W.2d 678 (1973).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>