<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1293"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1293</statuteno><catchline>Public seal affixed to copy of written law or public writing; effect; unwritten law; how proved.</catchline><para>The public seal of the state or county affixed to a copy of a written law or other public writing, is also admissible as evidence of such law or writing respectively; the unwritten law of any other state or government may be proved as fact by parol evidence, and also by the books of reports of cases adjudged in their courts.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 420, p. 463; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7986; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8927; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1293; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1293.</para></source><annotation><para>Where no evidence was given as to marriage laws of sister state where common law marriage was alleged to have occurred, law of this state at time marriage was alleged to have taken place was applicable. Forshay v. Johnston, 144 Neb. 525, 13 N.W.2d 873 (1944).</para><para>This section provides a method for proof of unwritten law of foreign states by parol evidence or reports of adjudicated cases. Banks v. Metropolitan Life Ins. Co., 142 Neb. 823, 8 N.W.2d 185 (1943).</para><para>Common law of sister state may be proved by books of reports of decisions of her courts. Steinke v. Dobson, 90 Neb. 616, 134 N.W. 169 (1912).</para><para>Public seal of another state, affixed to copy of written law, is admissible as evidence of such law. Rieck v. Griffin, 74 Neb. 102, 103 N.W. 1061 (1905).</para><para>Except as to statute, law of another state is proper subject of expert testimony. Barber v. Hildebrand, 42 Neb. 400, 60 N.W. 594 (1894).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>