<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1419"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1419</statuteno><catchline>Death of parties after judgment; revivor in name of representatives of deceased.</catchline><para>If either or both the parties die after judgment, and before satisfaction thereof, their representatives, real or personal, or both, as the case may require, may be made parties to the same, in the same manner as is prescribed for reviving actions before judgment; and such judgment may be rendered and execution awarded as might or ought to be given or awarded against the representatives real or personal, or both, of such deceased party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 472, p. 472; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8040; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8981; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1419; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1419.</para></source><annotation><para>To be a lien upon land descending to heirs of deceased judgment debtor, judgment must be revived against heirs, not against administrator. Dougherty v. White, 112 Neb. 675, 200 N.W. 884 (1924).</para><para>Proceedings should not be in name of administrator unless he has succeeded to right of deceased. Vogt v. Binder, 76 Neb. 361, 107 N.W. 383 (1906).</para><para>Execution is void unless judgment is revived after plaintiff's death. Vogt v. Daily, 70 Neb. 812, 98 N.W. 31 (1904).</para><para>Fact that one or more parties cannot be found will not abate action as against those found and properly served. Clark v. Commercial Nat. Bank of Columbus, 68 Neb. 764, 94 N.W. 958 (1903).</para><para>The word "manner" does not include the element of time. Bankers' Life Ins. Co. v. Robbins, 59 Neb. 170, 80 N.W. 484 (1899).</para><para>Administrator may prosecute error proceedings without order of revivor. Webster v. City of Hastings, 56 Neb. 245, 76 N.W. 565 (1898).</para><para>If judgment is joint, liability must be revived in that form. Fox v. Abbott, 12 Neb. 328, 11 N.W. 303 (1882).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>