<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts Civil Procedure" id="id28" statutenumber="25-1654"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1654</statuteno><catchline id="id31">Combined list; master key list; how produced.</catchline><para>(1) Each December, the Department of Motor Vehicles shall make available to each jury commissioner a list in magnetic, optical, digital, or other electronic format mutually agreed to by the jury commissioner and the department containing the names, dates of birth, addresses, and motor vehicle operator license numbers or state identification card numbers of all licensed motor vehicle operators and state identification card holders nineteen years of age or older in the county. If a jury commissioner requests similar lists at other times from the department, the cost of processing such lists shall be paid by the county which the requesting jury commissioner serves. Upon request of the jury commissioner, the election commissioner or county clerk having charge of the election records shall furnish to the jury commissioner a complete list of the names, dates of birth, addresses, and motor vehicle operator license numbers or state identification card numbers of all registered voters nineteen years of age or older in the county.</para><para>(2) When required pursuant to subsection (3) of this section or when otherwise necessary or as directed by the judge or judges, the jury commissioner shall create a combined list by merging the separate lists described in subsection (1) of this section and reducing any duplication to the best of his or her ability.</para><para>(3) In counties having a population of seven thousand inhabitants or more, the jury commissioner shall produce a combined list at least once each calendar year. In counties having a population of three thousand inhabitants but less than seven thousand inhabitants, the jury commissioner shall produce a combined list at least once every two calendar years. In counties having a population of less than three thousand inhabitants, the jury commissioner shall produce a combined list at least once every five calendar years.</para><para>(4) The jury commissioner shall then create a master key list by selecting from the combined list the name of the person whose numerical order on such list corresponds with the key number and each successive tenth name thereafter. The jury commissioner shall certify that the master key list has been made in accordance with the Jury Selection Act.</para><para>(5) Any unintentional duplication of names on a combined list or master key list shall not be grounds for quashing any panel or jury list pursuant to section 25-1678 or for the disqualification of any juror.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 248, &#167; 4, p. 569; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9098; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1628; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1628; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 88, &#167; 1, p. 337; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 11, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 113, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 111, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 82, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 19, &#167; 5; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 402, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 3; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 25-1628; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 11. </para></source><annotation><para>A defendant in a criminal case is not entitled to a proportionate number of his race on the jury. State v. Gutierrez, 187 Neb. 383, 191 N.W.2d 164 (1971).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>