<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-1121"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1121</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Special verdicts; when allowed; procedure; filing; record.</catchline><para id="id00">In every action for the recovery of money only or specific real property, the jury, in their discretion, may render a general or special verdict. In all other cases the court may direct the jury to find a special verdict, in writing, upon all or any of the issues and in all cases may instruct them, if they render a general verdict, to find upon particular questions of fact to be stated in writing, and may direct a written finding thereon. The special verdict or finding must be filed with the clerk and entered upon the record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 293, p. 443; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7860; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8804; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1121; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1121; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 13. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Special verdict</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Trial court discretion</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Special verdict</emphasis></para><para>Under circumstances of case, rendition of special verdict was proper. Baum v. County of Scotts Bluff, 172 Neb. 225, 109 N.W.2d 295 (1961).</para><para>Special findings, based upon conflicting evidence, will not be disturbed. Norfolk Beet-Sugar Co. v. Hight, 59 Neb. 100, 80 N.W. 276 (1899).</para><para><emphasis>2. Trial court discretion</emphasis></para><para>Trial court may submit special verdict in negligence action. Carlson v. Hanson, 166 Neb. 96, 88 N.W.2d 140 (1958).</para><para>Court may direct submission of special issues to jury, or jury may render special verdict without direction from the court. McGrew Machine Co. v. One Spring Alarm Clock Co., 124 Neb. 93, 245 N.W. 263 (1932).</para><para>Submission of special findings is within the discretion of trial court. Buel v. Chicago, R. I. &amp; P. Ry. Co., 81 Neb. 430, 116 N.W. 299 (1908); American Fire Ins. Co. v. Landfare, 56 Neb. 482, 76 N.W. 1068 (1898); Phoenix Ins. Co. v. King, 52 Neb. 562, 72 N.W. 855 (1897); Hedrick v. Strauss, Uhlman &amp; Guthman, 42 Neb. 485, 60 N.W. 928 (1894); Reed v. McRill, 41 Neb. 206, 59 N.W. 775 (1894).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>This section has no application to criminal trials. State v. Bradley, 210 Neb. 882, 317 N.W.2d 99 (1982).</para><para>Quotient verdict is not void in absence of previous agreement that it should be controlling. Herbert v. Katzberg, 104 Neb. 395, 177 N.W. 650 (1920).</para><para>Objection that special findings are not signed is waived unless made before they are received and recorded. Thompson v. Thompson, 49 Neb. 157, 68 N.W. 372 (1896).</para><para>It is error for court to enter judgment on general verdict when material special findings are returned unanswered. Sandwich Enterprise Co. v. West, 42 Neb. 722, 60 N.W. 1012 (1894); Doom v. Walker, 15 Neb. 339, 18 N.W. 138 (1884).</para><para>In absence of abuse of discretion, refusal to submit special findings is not error. Atchison, T. &amp; S. F. Ry. Co. v. Lawler, 40 Neb. 356, 58 N.W. 968 (1894).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>