<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1542"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1542</statuteno><catchline>Judgment lien; when lost.</catchline><para>No judgment on which execution has not been taken out and levied before the expiration of five years after its entry shall operate as a lien upon the estate of any debtor to the preference of any other bona fide judgment creditor or purchaser, but when judgment has been or may be rendered in the Court of Appeals or Supreme Court and any special mandate awarded to the district court to carry the same into execution, the lien of the judgment creditor shall continue for five years after the first day of the next term of the district court to which such mandate may be directed. Nothing in this section shall be construed to defeat the lien of any judgment creditor who fails to take out execution and cause a levy to be made as provided in this section when such failure is occasioned by appeal, proceedings in error, or injunction or by a vacancy in the office of sheriff and coroner or the inability of such officers until one year after such disability is removed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 509, p. 480; </para><para>Laws 1901, c. 81, &#167; 1, p. 474; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8088; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9024; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1542; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1542; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 50; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 921, &#167; 13. </para></source><annotation><para>To preserve priority of judgment lien against bona fide creditor or purchaser, actual levy of execution must be made. Hein v. W. T. Rawleigh Co., 167 Neb. 176, 92 N.W.2d 185 (1958).</para><para>Lien of foreclosure decree is not lost by failure to have order of sale issued within five years. Jenkins Land &amp; Live Stock Co. v. Kimsey, 99 Neb. 308, 156 N.W. 499 (1916).</para><para>Priority of a judgment lien may be continued as against other bona fide judgment creditors and purchasers only by the issuance of an execution and an actual levy within the time limited by statute. Glenn v. Glenn, 79 Neb. 68, 112 N.W. 321 (1907).</para><para>An appeal by judgment defendant does not in absence of a supersedeas, operate to prolong lien of judgment. Harvey v. Godding, 77 Neb. 289, 109 N.W. 220 (1906).</para><para>Lien of judgment created by mandate of Supreme Court continues for five years. Medland v. Van Etten, 75 Neb. 794, 106 N.W. 1022 (1906).</para><para>Right of judgment creditor to execution is a substantial one and can only be taken away by some act done in compliance with law. Halmes v. Dovey, 64 Neb. 122, 89 N.W. 631 (1902).</para><para>Execution levied but returned unsatisfied before sale by order of plaintiff prevents judgment from becoming dormant. Godman v. Boggs, 12 Neb. 13, 10 N.W. 403 (1881).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>