<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1937"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1937</statuteno><catchline>Appeals; general procedure.</catchline><para>When the Legislature enacts a law providing for an appeal without providing the procedure therefor, the procedure for appeal to the district court shall be the same as for appeals from the county court to the district court in civil actions. Trial in the district court shall be de novo upon the issues made up by the pleadings in the district court. Appeals from the district court to the Court of Appeals shall be taken in the same manner provided by law for appeals from the district court in civil cases. This section shall not apply if the Administrative Procedure Act otherwise provides.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1963, c. 138, &#167; 1, p. 515; </para><para>Laws 1988, LB 352, &#167; 26; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 732, &#167; 66.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Administrative Procedure Act,</emphasis> see section 84-920.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>When a decision regarding a conditional use or special exception permit is appealed under section 23-114.01(5) and a trial is held de novo under this section, the findings of the district court shall have the effect of a jury verdict and the court's judgment will not be set aside by an appellate court unless the court's factual findings are clearly erroneous or the court erred in its application of the law. Egan v. County of Lancaster, 308 Neb. 48, 952 N.W.2d 664 (2020).</para><para>Subsection (5) of section 23-114.01 provides for a right of appeal to the district court from a decision by the county planning commission or county board of commissioners or supervisors, without setting forth any procedure for prosecuting the appeal. Therefore, the appeal procedure in this section is also implicated. In re Application of Olmer, 275 Neb. 852, 752 N.W.2d 124 (2008).</para><para>This section provides for appeal when a statute confers the right to appeal but fails to prescribe the procedure. Hawkins v. City of Omaha, 261 Neb. 943, 627 N.W.2d 118 (2001).</para><para>This section provides the procedure for appeal when a statute confers a right to appeal, but fails to prescribe the procedure therefor. Prucha v. Kahlandt, 260 Neb. 366, 618 N.W.2d 399 (2000).</para><para>This section and others cited provide for appeals from action of county superintendent in school reorganization case. Schroeder v. Oeltjen, 184 Neb. 8, 165 N.W.2d 81 (1969).</para><para>Remedy by appeal under this section is not exclusive. Moser v. Turner, 180 Neb. 635, 144 N.W.2d 192 (1966).</para><para>This section provides the procedure for appeal when right of appeal is given but procedure is not provided. School Dist. of Wilbur v. Pracheil, 180 Neb. 121, 141 N.W.2d 768 (1966).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>