<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-1521"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1521</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Intervening claimants; proceedings to ascertain title.</catchline><para id="id00">If the officer, by virtue of any writ of execution issued from any court of record in this state, shall levy the same on any goods and chattels claimed by any person other than the defendant, such officer shall give notice in writing to the court, in which shall be set forth the names of the plaintiff and defendant, together with the name of the claimant. At the same time such officer shall furnish the court with a schedule of the property claimed. Immediately upon the filing of such notice and schedule, the court shall determine the right of the claimant to the property in controversy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 486, p. 474; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8062; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9003; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1521; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1521; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 131; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 226, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 26. </para></source><annotation><para>Sheriff does not receive additional compensation for services under this section. Muinch v. Hull, 181 Neb. 571, 149 N.W.2d 527 (1967).</para><para>Failure of sheriff to comply with this section, when property is claimed by third person, does not fix liability on sheriff. Miller v. Crosson, 131 Neb. 88, 267 N.W. 145 (1936).</para><para>Sheriff may bring suit hereunder to try claim to personal property attached by him. Leadabrand v. State, 121 Neb. 836, 238 N.W. 656 (1931).</para><para>An intervening claimant does not have a statutory right to a jury trial pursuant to the provisions of this section through section 25-1523. Eli's, Inc. v. Commercial Lithographing, Inc., 8 Neb. App. 752, 601 N.W.2d 795 (1999).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>