<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-1303"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1303</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Transcript of judgment to other county; effect.</catchline><para id="id00">The transcript of a judgment of any district court in this state may be filed in the office of the clerk of the district court in any county. Such transcript, when so filed and entered on the judgment index, shall be a lien on the property of the debtor in any county in which such transcript is so filed, in the same manner and under the same conditions only as in the county where such judgment was rendered, and execution may be issued on such transcript in the same manner as on the original judgment. Such transcript shall at no time have any greater validity or effect than the original judgment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 1, p. 158; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7796; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8937; </para><para>Laws 1929, c. 83, &#167; 1, p. 332; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1303; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1303; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 19. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>County court judgment,</emphasis> transcript to district court for lien, see section 25-2721.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Federal court judgments are liens on real estate only in county where rendered unless transcript is filed in other counties. Rathbone Co. v. Kimball, 117 Neb. 229, 220 N.W. 244 (1928).</para><para>Transcript filed in other county can only be vacated in suit to set aside original judgment; applies in suits to remove cloud on title. State ex rel. Long v. Westover, 107 Neb. 593, 186 N.W. 998 (1922).</para><para>Motion to revive judgment of district court must be made in court where rendered. Case Threshing Mach. Co. v. Edmisten, 85 Neb. 272, 122 N.W. 891 (1909).</para><para>Judgment in county court, regardless of amount, may be transcripted to any county in state. Cabon v. Gruenig, 18 Neb. 562, 26 N.W. 253 (1886).</para><para>Transcript of justice judgment must be filed in district court of county where judgment was rendered. Pemberton v. Pollard, 18 Neb. 435, 25 N.W. 582 (1885).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>