<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1306"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1306</statuteno><catchline>Dissolution of lien; deposit; bond; appellate proceedings.</catchline><para>In all cases wherein the judgment of any court, for payment of money only, which may be a general lien on property of the judgment debtor, and the debtor proposes to take proceedings in error or by appeal for review of such judgment, he may deposit in the court in which such judgment is rendered the full sum of such judgment, interest and costs, there to abide until termination of such appellate proceedings, and may file bond in such sum as the court or judge thereof may determine, with sureties to the approval of the clerk of such court, conditioned to pay interest on the judgment debt and costs to accrue in event the judgment be affirmed. On such payment being made, and such bond filed and approved, the general lien of the judgment shall be dissolved.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1893, c. 42, &#167; 1, p. 383; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7999; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8940; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1306; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1306.</para></source><annotation><para>This section provides for filing of petition and answer in an appeal under this section. School Dist. of Wilber v. Pracheil, 180 Neb. 121, 141 N.W.2d 768 (1966).</para><para>Under Nebraska law, which applies to a foreign judgment after the judgment is filed in Nebraska, once a party appeals a monetary judgment for money only and files a supersedeas bond which is approved by the court in which judgment was rendered, the general lien resulting from the judgment is dissolved. Anderson v. Werner Enters., Inc., 7 Neb. App. 294, 581 N.W.2d 104 (1998).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>