<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id16" statutenumber="25-1625"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1625</statuteno><catchline id="id19">Jury commissioner;
designation; salary; expenses; duties.</catchline><para>(1) In each county
of the State of Nebraska there shall be a jury commissioner.</para>
<para>(2) In counties having a population of not more than seventy-five thousand
inhabitants, the clerk of the district court shall be jury commissioner ex
officio.</para>
<para>(3) In counties having a population of more than seventy-five thousand,
and not more than two hundred thousand inhabitants, the jury commissioner
shall be a separate office in the county government or the duties may be performed,
when authorized by the judges of the district court within such counties,
by the election commissioner. The jury commissioner shall receive an annual
salary of not less than twelve hundred dollars.</para>
<para>(4) In counties having a population in excess of two hundred thousand
inhabitants, the judges of the district court within such counties shall determine
whether the clerk of the district court will perform the duties of jury commissioner
without additional compensation or the election commissioner will be jury
commissioner ex officio.</para>
<para>(5) In all counties the necessary expenses incurred in the performance
of the duties of jury commissioner shall be paid by the county board of the
county out of the general fund, upon proper claims approved by one of the
district judges in the judicial district and duly filed with the county board.</para>
<para>(6) In all counties the jury commissioner shall prepare and file the
annual inventory statement with the county board of the county of all county
personal property in his or her custody or possession, as provided in sections
23-346 to 23-350.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1915, c. 248, &#167; 1, p. 568; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9095; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1625; </para><para>Laws 1931, c. 65, &#167; 5, p. 178; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 20, p. 159; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-1625; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1625; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 62, &#167; 9, p. 202; </para><para>Laws 1953, c. 72, &#167; 6, p. 227; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 113, &#167; 1, p. 352; </para><para>Laws 1971, LB 547, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 527, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 234, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 19, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB169, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For designation of election commissioner in counties having a population in excess of one hundred thousand inhabitants,</emphasis> see section 32-207.</para><para><emphasis>For designation of election commissioner in counties having a population of twenty thousand to one hundred thousand inhabitants,</emphasis> see section 32-211.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Statutory procedure for selection and impaneling of juries in a county the size of Douglas is provided. Maher v. State, 144 Neb. 463, 13 N.W.2d 641 (1944).</para><para>Jury commissioner act indicates modern trend against advance disclosure of names of jurors. Fetty v. State, 118 Neb. 169, 223 N.W. 955 (1929).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>