<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1139"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1139</statuteno><catchline>Taking and noting of exceptions; unnecessary, when.</catchline><para>Every litigant in any court or in any proceeding to which he is a party before any judge, magistrate, referee, board or tribunal, shall be deemed and taken, both in the trial court and before such judge, magistrate, referee, board or tribunal as well on appeal or error therefrom, as excepting to any judgment, order or other ruling, including the giving or refusal of instructions to the jury, made by such court, judge, magistrate, referee, board or tribunal at any stage of the case or proceeding, that is material and prejudicial to the substantial rights of the litigant and he shall not be required in order to preserve his rights actually to take, or to cause to be noted upon the record, any such exception.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167;&#167; 308, 309, 310, 312, and 313, p. 446; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 11; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7877; </para><para>Laws 1915, c. 147, &#167; 1, p. 317; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8822; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1139; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1139.</para></source><annotation><para>An instruction to which no exception is noted on the record when given may be reviewed on appeal, former rule having been changed by statute. Derr v. Gunnell, 127 Neb. 708, 256 N.W. 725 (1934).</para><para>Bill of exceptions was sufficient hereunder to protect rights of accused. Scott v. State, 121 Neb. 232, 236 N.W. 608 (1931).</para><para>Order of court in foreclosure suit, after evidence concluded, requiring defendant to file first brief, must be taken as excepted to, under this section. Quesner v. Novotny, 113 Neb. 827, 205 N.W. 566 (1925).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>