<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-1223"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1223</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Trial subpoena; deposition subpoena; issuance; statement required; by whom served; forms.</catchline><para>(1) Upon the request of a party to a civil action or proceeding, a subpoena may be issued to command a person to testify at a trial or deposition. The term trial in reference to a subpoena includes a hearing at which testimony may be taken.</para><para>(2) The clerk or a judge of the court in which the action or proceeding is pending shall issue a trial subpoena upon the request of a party. An attorney, as an officer of the court, may issue and sign a trial subpoena on behalf of the court if the attorney is authorized to practice in the court. An attorney who issues a subpoena must file a copy of the subpoena with the court on the day the subpoena is issued.</para><para>(3) A person before whom a deposition may be taken may issue a deposition subpoena on behalf of the court in which the action or proceeding is pending. An attorney, as an officer of the court, may issue and sign a deposition subpoena on behalf of the court if the attorney is authorized to practice in the court.</para><para>(4) A subpoena shall state the name of the court from which it is issued, the title of the action, and the case number and shall command each person to whom it is directed to appear and testify at the time and place specified in the subpoena.</para><para>(5) Except as provided in subsection (6) of this section, a trial subpoena that is issued in a civil action or proceeding (a) at the request of an agency of state government or (b) pursuant to section 25-2304 shall contain the following statement: As a witness in [insert name of court], you are entitled to receive a witness fee in the amount of [insert amount from section 33-139] for each day that you are required to be in court and, if you live more than one mile from the courthouse, you are also entitled to receive mileage at the rate that state employees receive. Ask the lawyer or party who subpoenaed you or the clerk of the court for information about what you should do to receive the fees and mileage to which you are entitled.</para><para>(6) A trial subpoena in a civil action or proceeding that commands testimony by an employee of the State of Nebraska or a political subdivision thereof or a privately employed security guard, under the circumstances described in section 33-139.01, shall contain the following statement: As a witness in [insert name of court], you are entitled to be compensated for your actual and necessary expenses if you are required to travel outside of your county of residence to testify. Ask the lawyer or party who subpoenaed you or the clerk of the court for information about what you should do to receive compensation, if any, to which you are entitled.</para><para>(7) Any other trial subpoena in a civil action or proceeding shall contain the following statement: As a witness in [insert name of court], you are entitled to receive a witness fee in the amount of [insert amount from section 33-139] for each day that you are required to be in court and, if you live more than one mile from the courthouse, you are also eligible to receive mileage at the rate that state employees receive. You should have received your witness fee for one day with this subpoena. Ask the lawyer or party who subpoenaed you or the clerk of the court for information about what you should do to receive the additional fees, if any, and mileage to which you are entitled.</para><para>(8) The Supreme Court may promulgate forms for subpoenas for use in civil and criminal actions and proceedings. Any such forms shall not be in conflict with the laws governing such matters.</para><para>(9) A subpoena may be served by a sheriff or constable. It may also be served by a person who is twenty-one years of age or older and who is not a party to the action or proceeding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 350, p. 452; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7915; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8857; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1223; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1223; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB509, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB912, &#167; 12. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>