<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1560"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1560</statuteno><catchline>Exempt wages; interstate business; attachment or garnishment by method to avoid exemption laws; unlawful.</catchline><para>It is hereby declared unlawful for any creditor of, or other holder of any evidence of debt, book account, or claim of any name or nature against any laborer, servant, clerk, or other employee, of any corporation, firm or individual in this state engaged in interstate business, for the purpose below stated, to sell, assign, transfer, or by any means dispose of any such claim, book account, bill, or debt of any name or nature whatever, to any person or persons, firm, corporation or institution, or to institute, in this state or elsewhere, or prosecute any suit or action for any such claim or debt against any such laborer, servant, clerk or employee by any process seeking to seize, attach, or garnish the wages of such person or persons earned within sixty days prior to the commencement of such proceeding, for the purpose of avoiding the effect of the laws of the State of Nebraska concerning exemptions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1889, c. 25, &#167; 1, p. 369; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8107; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9043; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1561; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1560.</para></source><annotation><para>Nonresident cannot claim benefits of this and following sections. McCormack v. Tincher, 77 Neb. 857, 110 N.W. 547 (1906).</para><para>Act, of which this section was part, is constitutional. Gordon Bros. v. Wageman, 77 Neb. 185, 108 N.W. 1067 (1906).</para><para>Foreign corporations are subject to operation of act; exemption laws where wages earned apply. Singer Mfg. Co. v. Fleming, 39 Neb. 679, 58 N.W. 226 (1894).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>