<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1907"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1907</statuteno><catchline>Proceedings in error; effect; supersedeas bond.</catchline><para>No proceedings to reverse, vacate, or modify any judgment rendered, or final order made, by any court inferior to the district court shall operate as a stay of execution unless the judge or clerk of the court in which the judgment was rendered or order made shall take and approve a written undertaking to the defendant in error, executed on the part of the plaintiff in error, by one or more sufficient sureties. The undertaking shall be conditioned that the plaintiff will pay all the costs which have accrued or may accrue on such proceedings in error, together with the amount of any judgment that may be rendered against such plaintiff in error, either on the further trial of the case, after the judgment of the court below shall have been set aside or reversed, or upon and after the affirmation thereof in the district court. No proceedings shall operate as a stay of execution on judgments of restitution rendered in actions for the forcible entry and detention, or the forcible detention only, of lands and tenements, unless the undertaking shall be further conditioned for the payment to the defendant in error of all money or sums of money that has or have accrued or may accrue to the defendant from the plaintiff in error for the use, occupation or rent of the lands and tenements in controversy, in case the judgment sought to be reversed shall be affirmed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 593, p. 499; </para><para>Laws 1871, &#167; 1, p. 110; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8181; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9133; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1907; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1907; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 71, &#167; 1, p. 227; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 138.</para></source><annotation><para>Supersedeas bond may be filed in district court in proceedings in error from county court to district court. In re Berg's Estate, 139 Neb. 99, 296 N.W. 460 (1941).</para><para>Bond is necessary to stay execution but not to obtain review. Welton v. Beltezore, 17 Neb. 399, 23 N.W. 1 (1885).</para><para>An appeal from a special assessment by a metropolitan‑class city taken as specified in section 14‑813 means that proceedings from a district court shall be the same as an appeal from a county board, and under this section, that means appeal is taken by petition in error and the review is solely of the record made before the tribunal whose action is being reviewed. Jackson v. Board of Equal. of City of Omaha, 10 Neb. App. 330, 630 N.W.2d 680 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>