<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1082"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1082</statuteno><catchline>Notice of application for appointment; service.</catchline><para>No receiver shall be appointed except in a suit actually commenced and pending, and after notice to all parties to be affected thereby, of the time and place of the application, the names of the proposed receiver, and of his or her proposed sureties, and of the proposed sureties of the applicant. Such notice shall state upon what papers the application is based, and be served at least five days before the proposed hearing upon the adverse party in the manner provided for service of a summons in a civil action or upon the adverse party's attorney in the manner provided for service of a notice on an attorney.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 267, p. 438; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7811; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8755; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 49, &#167; 1, p. 199; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1082; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 17, &#167; 1, p. 96; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-1082; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1082; </para><para>Laws 1983, LB 447, &#167; 40.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Notice</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Notice</emphasis></para><para>Validity of order of appointment of bank receiver cannot be collaterally questioned, where receiver was appointed pursuant to notice and qualified and performed legal duties. Brownell v. Adams, 121 Neb. 304, 236 N.W. 750 (1931).</para><para>Where action for foreclosure of mortgage and application for receiver combined in one petition, and defendant joins issue, no other notice is required. Lackey v. Yekel, 113 Neb. 382, 203 N.W. 542 (1925).</para><para>Court is without power to appoint even temporary receiver for solvent corporation without notice to stockholders, where officers, who were the only parties notified, are charged with misuse of corporate powers. Furrer v. Nebraska Bldg. &amp; Inv. Co., 108 Neb. 698, 189 N.W. 359 (1922).</para><para>Where record shows judge made appointment prior to date set in notice it is void. Gibson v. Sexson, 82 Neb. 475, 118 N.W. 77 (1908).</para><para>Appointment without notice is void. Smiley v. Sioux Beet Syrup Co., 71 Neb. 581, 99 N.W. 263 (1904); Johnson v. Powers, 21 Neb. 292, 32 N.W. 62 (1887).</para><para>Service of notice may be made on attorney of record, who may waive time required by statute, and authorize court to proceed to immediate hearing. Murphy v. Fidelity Mutual Fire Ins. Co., 69 Neb. 489, 95 N.W. 1022 (1903).</para><para>Statutory notice may be waived. Veith v. Ress, 60 Neb. 52, 82 N.W. 116 (1900).</para><para>Notice is waived where appointment is opposed on other grounds. Farmers &amp; Merchants Bank of Holstein v. German Nat. Bank of Lincoln, 59 Neb. 229, 80 N.W. 820 (1899).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>This section contains conditions precedent to valid appointment of a receiver. Gentsch, Inc. v. Burnett, 173 Neb. 820, 115 N.W.2d 446 (1962).</para><para>It is error for a trial court in a foreclosure action to appoint a receiver for defendant's homestead interest in real estate. Federal Credit Co. v. Reynolds, 132 Neb. 495, 272 N.W. 397 (1937).</para><para>This section applies to appointment of receivers for banks. Holcomb v. Tierney, 79 Neb. 660, 113 N.W. 204 (1907).</para><para>Action must be one in which main relief sought is independent of receivership. Mann v. German-American Investment Co., 70 Neb. 454, 97 N.W. 600 (1903).</para><para>Court may permit amendments of pleading upon notice. McCord, Brady &amp; Co. v. Weil, 29 Neb. 682, 46 N.W. 152 (1890).</para><para>"Parties to be affected" means those having interest in possession or immediate custody of property or immediate disposition of rents and profits therefrom. Chambers v. Barker, 2 Neb. Unof. 523, 89 N.W. 388 (1902).</para><para>Petition need not propose name of person as receiver. Defects in notice are waived by appearance. Robertson v. Ostrom, 1 Neb. Unof. 200, 95 N.W. 469 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>