<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1292"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1292</statuteno><catchline>Abstracts of title and title insurance policy; when used as evidence; certification.</catchline><para>(1) Any party to a civil action who may desire to use in evidence at the trial any abstract of title to real estate shall, not less than seven days prior to the date of trial, notify the adverse party by written notice addressed to such party's counsel of record and deposit such abstract in the office of the clerk of the district court of the county in which such action is pending for examination by such adverse party. Such abstract of title, if certified to and issued by a registered abstracter, shall be received in evidence as prima facie evidence of the existence of the record of deeds, mortgages, and other instruments, conveyances, or liens affecting the real estate mentioned in such abstract and that such record is as described in such abstract. If such abstract is successively certified to by abstracters who were bonded under section 76-506 prior to November 18, 1965, registered under sections 76-509 to 76-528 on or after November 18, 1965, but prior to March 26, 1985, or registered under the Abstracters Act, the same shall be received in evidence without further foundation.</para><para>(2) A title insurance policy issued by a title insurer licensed to issue such policy by the State of Nebraska shall also be received in court as prima facie evidence of the ownership, liens, mortgages, easements, and all other corporeal as well as incorporeal hereditaments to such real estate, the existence of which are indicated in such title insurance policy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1887, c. 64, &#167; 3, p. 566; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7985; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8926; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1292; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1292; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 453, &#167; 21, p. 1446; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 47, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 235, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Abstracters Act,</emphasis> see section 76-535.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Abstracts of title, when proper foundation has been laid, are admissible in evidence. Worm v. Crowell, 165 Neb. 713, 87 N.W.2d 384 (1958).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>