<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1072"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1072</statuteno><catchline>Enforcement; disobedience; punishment.</catchline><para>An injunction granted by a judge may be enforced as the act of the court. Disobedience of an injunction may be punished as a contempt by the court, or by any judge who might have granted it in vacation. An attachment may be issued by the court or judge, upon being satisfied by affidavit of the breach of the injunction, against the party guilty of the same; and he may be required, in the discretion of the court or judge, to pay a fine not exceeding two hundred dollars, for the use of the county, to make immediate restitution to the party injured, and give further security to obey the injunction; or, in default thereof, he may be committed to close custody, until he shall fully comply with such requirements, or be otherwise legally discharged.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 260, p. 436; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7801; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8745; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1072; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1072.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Enforcement</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Enforcement</emphasis></para><para>In a civil contempt proceeding, a district court has inherent power to order compensatory relief when a contemnor has violated its order or judgment; overruling <emphasis type="italic">Kasparek v. May,</emphasis> 174 Neb. 732, 119 N.W.2d 512 (1963). Smeal Fire Apparatus Co. v. Kreikemeier, 279 Neb. 661, 782 N.W.2d 848 (2010).</para><para>In determining whether a party is in contempt of an order, a court may not expand an earlier order's prohibitory or mandatory language beyond a reasonable interpretation considering the purposes for which the order was entered. Smeal Fire Apparatus Co. v. Kreikemeier, 279 Neb. 661, 782 N.W.2d 848 (2010).</para><para>A party who disobeys an injunction may be required, in the discretion of the court, to make immediate restitution to the party injured. Kasparek v. May, 178 Neb. 425, 133 N.W.2d 614 (1965).</para><para>Violation of injunction against unlawful practice of law could be punished as contempt of court. State ex rel. Beck v. Lush, 170 Neb. 376, 103 N.W.2d 136 (1960).</para><para>Operators of motion picture theatres who had been enjoined from operating lottery referred to as "bank night" were guilty of contempt by carrying on similar scheme known as "prosperity night." State ex rel. Hunter v. Omaha Motion Picture Exhibitors Assn., 139 Neb. 312, 297 N.W. 547 (1941).</para><para>Disobedience of an injunction must be willful before a breach thereof may be punished as a contempt. Whipple v. Nelson, 138 Neb. 514, 293 N.W. 382 (1940).</para><para>Information must be specific; court may fine and imprison; judge at chambers cannot imprison. Back v. State, 75 Neb. 603, 106 N.W. 787 (1906).</para><para>Judge in vacation may punish for contempt. Nebraska Children's Home Society v. State, 57 Neb. 765, 78 N.W. 267 (1899).</para><para>Void injunction is not enforceable by contempt proceedings; is only voidable contra. Wilber v. Woolley, 44 Neb. 739, 62 N.W. 1095 (1895).</para><para><emphasis>2. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>A court of equity has the power to interpret its own injunctive decree if a party later claims that a provision is unclear. Smeal Fire Apparatus Co. v. Kreikemeier, 279 Neb. 661, 782 N.W.2d 848 (2010).</para><para>This section is invalid and unenforceable as a limitation upon the inherent power of the court to punish for contempt. State ex rel. Beck v. Frontier Airlines, Inc., 174 Neb. 172, 116 N.W.2d 281 (1962).</para><para>Procedure is authorized for punishment for violation of mandatory injunction. Meier v. Nelsen, 156 Neb. 666, 57 N.W.2d 273 (1953).</para><para>One who is in privity with party enjoined and has knowledge of the injunction is bound thereby. Wilcox v. Ashford, 131 Neb. 338, 268 N.W. 81 (1936).</para><para>Conviction under contempt proceedings can be reviewed in Supreme Court only by filing petition in error. Gentle v. Pantel Realty Co., 120 Neb. 630, 234 N.W. 574 (1931).</para><para>Contempt proceeding is in nature of criminal action; reviewable on error. Zimmerman v. State, 46 Neb. 13, 64 N.W. 375 (1895).</para><para>A county judge has no power to commit for contempt a party who has violated an injunction allowed by him in an action in district court. Johnson v. Bouton, 35 Neb. 898, 53 N.W. 995 (1892).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>