<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1565"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1565</statuteno><catchline>Discovery of property of debtor; order to appear and answer.</catchline><para>At any time after the entry of judgment against the judgment debtor, or one of several debtors in the same action, the judgment creditor is entitled to an order from the county court or the district court of the county (1) in which the debtor resides, (2) if the debtor does not reside in the state, where judgment was rendered, or (3) in which a transcript of judgment has been filed, requiring the debtor to appear and answer concerning his or her property before the judge of such court or a referee appointed by the judge of such court at a time and place specified in the order within the county to which the order was issued.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 533, p. 487; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8112; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9048; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1566; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1565; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 134; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1059, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 1207, &#167; 7. </para></source><annotation><para>Provisions of the code pertaining to compulsory discovery do not relate to the subject of pleading. Marshall v. Rowe, 126 Neb. 817, 254 N.W. 480 (1934).</para><para>Making of order is authorized only after return of execution unsatisfied. Clarke v. Nebraska Nat. Bank, 57 Neb. 314, 77 N.W. 805 (1899).</para><para>Proceedings in aid of execution were designed to take the place of bill of discovery. Clarke v. Nebraska Nat. Bank, 49 Neb. 800, 69 N.W. 104 (1896).</para><para>Execution must issue to lay foundation for contempt proceedings. Hawthorne v. State, 45 Neb. 871, 64 N.W. 359 (1895).</para><para>Affidavit is unnecessary to obtain order; it is sufficient if execution is returned unsatisfied. English v. Smith, 1 Neb. Unof. 670, 96 N.W. 60 (1901).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>