<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1285"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1285</statuteno><catchline>Judicial records of Nebraska and federal courts; how proved.</catchline><para>A judicial record of this state, or of any other federal court of the United States, may be proved by producing the original or a copy thereof, certified by the clerk or the clerk's designee or the person having the legal custody thereof, authenticated by his or her seal of office, if there is one.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 413, p. 462; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7978; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8919; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1285; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1285; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB449, &#167; 1.</para></source><annotation><para>A certified copy of judgment of prior conviction in any federal court or in a court of this state is sufficient proof thereof. State v. Micek, 193 Neb. 379, 227 N.W.2d 409 (1975).</para><para>Judgment of justice, including copy of complaint embodied therein, was established by competent proof. Osborne v. State, 115 Neb. 65, 211 N.W. 179 (1926).</para><para>Judicial record, if properly certified, is admissible to prove its own existence. Sheibley v. Fales, 81 Neb. 795, 116 N.W. 1035 (1908).</para><para>Orders or judgments of court of general jurisdiction may be pleaded without alleging jurisdictional facts. Lear v. Brown County, 77 Neb. 230, 109 N.W. 174 (1906).</para><para>Records of sister state may be examined to determine court's jurisdiction. Fall v. Fall, 75 Neb. 104, 106 N.W. 412 (1905), judgment vacated 75 Neb. 120, 113 N.W. 175 (1907).</para><para>Transcript of proceedings, duly certified, of United States court, is competent evidence, though presiding judge failed to sign journal. Stacks v. Crawford, 63 Neb. 662, 88 N.W. 852 (1902).</para><para>Recitals in judgment record kept by clerk of district court of transcript from county court are not competent to prove judgment. Burge v. Gandy, 41 Neb. 149, 59 N.W. 359 (1894).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>