<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1026"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1026</statuteno><catchline>Garnishee; answer; interrogatories; filing fee; costs.</catchline><para>The garnishee shall answer, under oath, all the interrogatories put to him touching the property of every description and credits of the defendant in his possession or under his control at the time of the service of the summons and interrogatories, and he shall disclose truly the amount owing by him to the defendant, whether due or not, and, in case of a corporation, any stock therein held by or for the benefit of the defendant, at the time of the service of the summons and interrogatories. The fee for filing of answer may be taxed and collected in the same manner as other costs in such proceedings.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 221, p. 429; </para><para>Laws 1877, &#167; 1, p. 10; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7755; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8699; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1026; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1026; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 67, &#167; 3, p. 203; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 101, &#167; 2, p. 423. </para></source><annotation><para>A garnishee who serves as the plan administrator for a judgment debtor's employee benefit plan must comply with this section and disclose any property of the judgment debtor that it possesses or controls, regardless of whether the property is subject to garnishment. Florence Lake Investments v. Berg, 312 Neb. 183, 978 N.W.2d 308 (2022).</para><para>As a general rule, a garnishee owes a duty to act in good faith and answer fully and truthfully all proper interrogatories presented to him. Petersen v. Central Park Properties, 275 Neb. 220, 745 N.W.2d 884 (2008).</para><para>Failure to tender garnishee fee excuses failure to appear but does not discharge garnishee from liability. Crawford State Bank v. Murphy, 142 Neb. 795, 7 N.W.2d 762 (1943).</para><para>After stating substance of this section, comment made that while garnishee appeared in person to answer questions, he did not file written answer. Hilton v. Clements, 137 Neb. 791, 291 N.W. 483 (1940).</para><para>Stock of domestic corporation for which certificate has been issued and delivered to purchaser is deemed to be in possession of corporation subject to attachment or garnishment proceedings. Danbom v. Danbom, 132 Neb. 858, 273 N.W. 502 (1937).</para><para>A nonresident whose property has been seized under a writ of attachment may, without making a general appearance, demand relief to which want of jurisdiction entitles him. McCartney v. McCartney, 128 Neb. 671, 260 N.W. 184 (1935).</para><para>After judgment, summons in garnishment from one county to another in aid of execution, is unauthorized. Hinds State Bank v. Loffler, 113 Neb. 110, 202 N.W. 465 (1925).</para><para>Section applies to all garnishment proceedings; unless fees are tendered, garnishee need not appear. Chicago, B. &amp; Q. R. R. Co. v. Van Cleave, 52 Neb. 67, 71 N.W. 971 (1897).</para><para>Where garnishee after answer receives notice of assignment made before levy, he should make supplemental answer. Coleman v. Scott, 27 Neb. 77, 42 N.W. 896 (1889).</para><para>Prepayment is waived by appearance and answer without objection. Pope v. Kingman &amp; Co., 2 Neb. Unof, 184, 96 N.W. 519 (1901).</para><para>Where insurance company denies indebtedness to judgment debtor in answer to garnishee summons, judgment creditor should be remitted to action for unsatisfactory disclosure. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co. v. Mackechnie, 114 F.2d 728 (8th Cir. 1940).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>