<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1933"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1933</statuteno><catchline>Costs; how taxed.</catchline><para>When a judgment, decree or final order is reversed, vacated or modified, the court may render judgment for all costs against the appellee or appellees or some of them, or may direct that each party pay his own costs or apportion the costs among parties or direct that judgment for costs abide the event of a new trial as, in its discretion, the equities of the cause may require.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1907, c. 162, &#167; 5, p. 496; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8205; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9158; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1933; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1933.</para></source><annotation><para>Upon modification of judgment, Supreme Court is authorized to apportion costs. Metropolitan Utilities Dist. v. City of Omaha, 171 Neb. 609, 107 N.W.2d 397 (1961).</para><para>Costs can only be taxed against parties to the litigation. Ludwig v. Board of County Commissioners of Sarpy County, 170 Neb. 600, 103 N.W.2d 838 (1960).</para><para>Where appellant obtained reversal in part, all costs in Supreme Court could be taxed to appellee. Ricenbaw v. Kraus, 157 Neb. 723, 61 N.W.2d 350 (1953).</para><para>On reversal, Supreme Court may tax costs as the equities of the cause require. Stocker v. Wells, 155 Neb. 472, 52 N.W.2d 284 (1952).</para><para>When a judgment is reversed on appeal to Supreme Court, the court in its discretion may render judgment for all costs in favor of one party, direct each party to pay his own costs, apportion the costs among the parties, or direct that costs abide the event of a new trial. Rehn v. Bingaman, 152 Neb. 171, 40 N.W.2d 673 (1950).</para><para>If appellant seeks reversal and appellee consents thereto, Supreme Court will ordinarily tax costs to appellee. In re Estate of Simon, 149 Neb. 382, 31 N.W.2d 231 (1948).</para><para>Interest on amount paid for bill of exceptions is not allowable as costs until entry of mandate on appeal. Nemaha Valley Drainage Dist. No. 2 v. Stocker, 95 Neb. 663, 146 N.W. 936 (1914).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>