<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1067"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1067</statuteno><catchline>Injunctions; security.</catchline><para>No injunction, unless provided by special statute, shall operate until the party obtaining the same shall give an undertaking, executed by one or more sufficient sureties, who shall justify as provided in sections 25-2222 and 25-2223. The undertaking shall be approved by the clerk of the court granting such injunction, in an amount to be fixed by the court or judge allowing the same, to secure to the party enjoined the damages he may sustain, if it be finally decided that the injunction ought not to have been granted.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 255, p. 435; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7796; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8740; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1067; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 29, &#167; 7, p. 136; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-1067; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1067.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>State officers and departments,</emphasis> not required to give injunction bond, see section 25-21,216.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Filing and approval of bond</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Effect of order</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Dissolution of order</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Suit on bond</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>5. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Filing and approval of bond</emphasis></para><para>Injunction is not effective for any purpose until bond is given and approved. Johnson v. Bouton, 35 Neb. 898, 53 N.W. 995 (1892).</para><para>If bond is not given, adverse party may disregard order. Baker v. Meisch, 29 Neb. 227, 45 N.W. 685 (1890).</para><para><emphasis>2. Effect of order</emphasis></para><para>Dissolution of injunction is adjudication that same ought not to have been granted; sureties cannot complain that order is broader than application. Gibson v. Reed, 54 Neb. 309, 75 N.W. 1085 (1898).</para><para><emphasis>3. Dissolution of order</emphasis></para><para>Where injunction against collection of judgment was dissolved, measure of damages in suit on bond was reduction in amount collectible, not amount of judgment. Stull Bros. v. Beddeo, 78 Neb. 119, 112 N.W. 315 (1907).</para><para>When order is dissolved, action accrues on bond; striking cause from files for failure to revive, dissolves. Humfeldt v. Moles, 63 Neb. 448, 88 N.W. 655 (1902).</para><para>Expenses of unsuccessful attempt to dissolve injunction are not recoverable. Pollock v. Whipple, 57 Neb. 82, 77 N.W. 355 (1898).</para><para>Attorney's fees for dissolution of restraining order are generally not recoverable. Carnes v. Heimrod, 45 Neb. 364, 63 N.W. 809 (1895).</para><para><emphasis>4. Suit on bond</emphasis></para><para>A party enjoined may recover damages on a temporary injunction bond only if it be finally decided that the injunction ought not to have been granted. State ex rel. Douglas v. Ledwith, 204 Neb. 6, 281 N.W.2d 729 (1979).</para><para>In absence of statute authorizing court to assess damages resulting to defendant from issuance of restraining order on dissolving such order, defendant must resort to independent action on plaintiff's bond. Higgins v. Adelson, 131 Neb. 820, 270 N.W. 502 (1936).</para><para>Voluntary dismissal entitles defendant to sue on bond. Gyger v. Courtney, 59 Neb. 555, 81 N.W. 437 (1900).</para><para><emphasis>5. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Attorneys' fees cannot be recovered as damages in suit on bond where injunction proceedings are only auxiliary to main case. Williams v. Hallgren, 149 Neb. 621, 31 N.W.2d 737 (1948).</para><para>Attorney's fees in trial of case are not recoverable on bond where injunction is ancillary; limited to fees for dissolving injunction. Darling v. McBride, 86 Neb. 481, 125 N.W. 1088 (1910).</para><para>No action can be maintained on temporary injunction bond until final decree in cause wherein bond is given. Johnson v. Bouton, 56 Neb. 626, 77 N.W. 57 (1898).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>