<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1563.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1563.01</statuteno><catchline>Stock, pension, or similar plan or contract; exempt from certain process; when.</catchline><para>In bankruptcy and in the collection of a money judgment, the following benefits shall be exempt from attachment, garnishment, or other legal or equitable process and from all claims of creditors: To the extent reasonably necessary for the support of the debtor and any dependent of the debtor, an interest held under a stock bonus, pension, profit-sharing, or similar plan or contract payable on account of illness, disability, death, age, or length of service unless:</para><para>(1) Within two years prior to bankruptcy or to entry against the individual of a money judgment which thereafter becomes final, such plan or contract was established or was amended to increase contributions by or under the auspices of the individual or of an insider that employed the individual at the time the individual's rights under such plan or contract arose; or</para><para>(2) Such plan or contract does not qualify under section 401(a), 403(a), 403(b), 408, or 408A of the Internal Revenue Code.</para><para>For purposes of this section, unless the context otherwise requires, insider shall have the meaning provided in 11 U.S.C. 101.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 335, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 574, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 23, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Individual Retirement Accounts are generally protected from attachment and garnishment to the extent the funds contained therein are reasonably necessary for the support of the debtor or any dependent of the debtor. Novak v. Novak, 245 Neb. 366, 513 N.W.2d 303 (1994).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>