<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-1301.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1301.01</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Civil judgment or final order; duty of clerk; exception.</catchline><para id="id00">Within three working days after the entry of any civil judgment or final order, except judgments by default when service has been obtained by publication or interlocutory orders styled as judgments, the clerk of the court shall send the judgment or final order by United States mail or by service through the court's electronic case management system to each party whose address appears in the records of the action or to the party's attorney or attorneys of record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1961, c. 111, &#167; 2, p. 350; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 186, &#167; 1, p. 778; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 124, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 43, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB1028, &#167; 4. </para></source><annotation><para>Where notice of judgment was mailed late, to an attorney no longer representing defendant and to an address where defendant could not be reached, the notification of judgment statute was not complied with, and is additional evidence to permit vacation of a default judgment. Tietsort v. Ranne, 200 Neb. 651, 264 N.W.2d 860 (1978).</para><para>Where judgment of dismissal was entered and no notice was given by the clerk to the parties, the proper proceeding to correct omissions of the clerk is by motion and notice. Pofahl v. Pofahl, 196 Neb. 347, 243 N.W.2d 55 (1976).</para><para>This section has no application to the filing of the report of appraisers with the county judge in eminent domain proceedings. Weiner v. State, 179 Neb. 297, 137 N.W.2d 852 (1965).</para><para>Sending of notice by post card is required as to ruling on motion for new trial where such ruling is a prerequisite to an appeal. Simmons v. Lincoln, 176 Neb. 71, 125 N.W.2d 63 (1963).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>