<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1532"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1532</statuteno><catchline>Sale upon execution; deed to purchaser.</catchline><para>The sheriff or other officer who, upon such writ or writs of execution, shall sell lands and tenements, or any part thereof, shall make to the purchaser or purchasers thereof as good and sufficient a deed of conveyance of lands and tenements sold as the person or persons against whom such writ or writs of execution were issued could have made of the same at the time they became liable to the judgment, or at any time thereafter.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 499, p. 478; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8078; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9014; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1532; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1532.</para></source><annotation><para>Sheriff's deed of homestead on judgment against husband alone will not divest debtor of title. Van Doren v. Wiedeman, 68 Neb. 243, 94 N.W. 124 (1903).</para><para>Unless decreed otherwise foreclosure transfers to purchaser every right and interest in the property of all parties to action. Hart v. Beardsley, 67 Neb. 145, 93 N.W. 423 (1903).</para><para>Where judgment is prematurely entered, error must be brought to attention of court entering it before action can be reviewed on appeal. Ley v. Pilger, 59 Neb. 561, 81 N.W. 507 (1900).</para><para>Purchaser at execution sale becomes vested with such title and right as were in the judgment debtor at the time the lien of the judgment attached. Orr v. Broad, 52 Neb. 490, 72 N.W. 850 (1897).</para><para>Where no supersedeas bond is filed, sale of property vests title in purchaser which is not affected by reversal of judgment. Green v. Hall, 43 Neb. 275, 61 N.W. 605 (1895).</para><para>On execution sale, owner retains title and is entitled to possession, rents and profits until final confirmation. Yeazel v. White, 40 Neb. 432, 58 N.W. 1020 (1894).</para><para>Successor to sheriff may make deed. Phillips v. Dawley, 1 Neb. 320 (1871).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>