<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1089"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1089</statuteno><catchline>Appointment of receiver without notice; void; suspension of order, when.</catchline><para>Every order appointing a receiver without the notice provided for herein shall be void, and every such order heretofore made, under which the appointee has not possessed himself of the property in question, shall be suspended until an order shall have been made and the bonds executed and filed in accordance with the provisions of sections 25-1081 to 25-1092.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 274, p. 439; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7818; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8762; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1089; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1089.</para></source><annotation><para>Requirement of giving of notice of application for receiver is mandatory, but may be waived. Modisett v. Campbell, 144 Neb. 222, 13 N.W.2d 126 (1944).</para><para>Statutory notice to interested parties is jurisdictional. Furrer v. Nebraska Bldg. &amp; Inv. Co., 108 Neb. 698, 189 N.W. 359 (1922).</para><para>Where record shows receiver was appointed before day set in notice, it is void and may be collaterally attacked. Gibson v. Sexson, 82 Neb. 475, 118 N.W. 77 (1908).</para><para>Taking possession of bank by receiver is sufficient notice to protect from collateral attack. Holcomb v. Tierney, 79 Neb. 660, 113 N.W. 204 (1907).</para><para>Appointment without notice is void not voidable. Smiley v. Sioux Beet Syrup Co., 71 Neb. 581, 99 N.W. 263 (1904); Johnson v. Powers, 21 Neb. 292, 32 N.W. 62 (1887).</para><para>Notice may be waived by resisting appointment on other grounds; court may appoint one not named, without further notice. Farmers &amp; Merchants Bank of Holstein v. German Nat. Bank of Lincoln, 59 Neb. 229, 80 N.W. 820 (1899).</para><para>Order, regular on its face, is prima facie valid, and protects receiver. Edee v. Strunk, 35 Neb. 307, 53 N.W. 70 (1892).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>