<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1912.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1912.01</statuteno><catchline>Appellate review; motion for new trial; when required.</catchline><para>(1) A motion for a new trial shall not be a prerequisite to obtaining appellate review of any issue upon which the ruling of the trial court appears in the record.</para><para>(2) When an action has been tried before a jury a motion for a new trial shall not be a prerequisite to obtaining appellate review of the sufficiency of the evidence, but a motion for a new trial shall be a prerequisite to obtaining appellate review of the issue of inadequate or excessive damages.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1982, LB 720, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>In order for any question as to the admissibility of evidence to be reviewed on appeal under subsection (1) of this section, the record must show that the objection was brought to the attention of the trial judge and ruled upon. State v. Blair, 227 Neb. 742, 419 N.W.2d 868 (1988).</para><para>A motion for a new trial is not a prerequisite to obtain review in most cases, but the timely filing of such a motion will extend the time within which a notice of appeal must be filed to a period of thirty days following the overruling of that motion. In re Interest of C.M.H. and M.S.H., 227 Neb. 446, 418 N.W.2d 226 (1988).</para><para>A motion for new trial is not required to obtain appellate review of any issue upon which the ruling of the trial court appears in the record. State v. Wright, 220 Neb. 847, 374 N.W.2d 26 (1985).</para><para>The Supreme Court acquires jurisdiction of an equitable appeal when the notice of appeal and docket fee are filed within one month of the judgment. Caro, Inc. v. Roby, 215 Neb. 897, 342 N.W.2d 182 (1983).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>