<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1657"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1657</statuteno><catchline>Juror qualification form; potential juror; complete; return; when.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, the jury commissioner shall deliver a juror qualification form to each potential juror drawn for jury service. The delivery may be by first-class mail or personal service or through a jury management system. The jury commissioner shall include instructions to complete and return the form to the jury commissioner within ten days after its receipt. The form may be returned to the jury commissioner by mail or through a jury management system.</para><para>(2)(a) In lieu of the juror qualification form delivery process described in subsection (1) of this section, a jury commissioner may send to a potential juror a notice or summons which includes instructions to complete a juror qualification form through a jury management system. The notice or summons may be sent by first-class mail or personal service or through a jury management system. The jury commissioner shall include instructions to complete and submit the juror qualification form within ten days after receipt of the notice or summons.</para><para>(b) If a potential juror fails to complete the qualification form as instructed within such ten days, the jury commissioner shall deliver to such potential juror, by first-class mail or personal service, a revised notice or summons and juror qualification form with instructions to complete and return the form to the jury commissioner within ten days after its receipt.</para><para>(3) The juror qualification form shall be in the form prescribed by the Supreme Court. Notarization of the juror qualification form shall not be required. If the potential juror is unable to complete the form, another person may do it for the potential juror and shall indicate that such other person has done so and the reason therefor.</para><para>(4) If it appears that there is an omission, ambiguity, or error in a returned form, the jury commissioner shall again send the form with instructions to the potential juror to make the necessary addition, clarification, or correction and to return the form to the jury commissioner within ten days after its second receipt.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 234, &#167; 12; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 105, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2016), &#167; 25-1629.01; </para><para>Laws 2020, LB387, &#167; 14. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>