<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1281"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1281</statuteno><catchline>Official records; photographic copies; admissibility; destruction of original records.</catchline><para>In all cases in which any instrument or document is required by law to be copied or recorded in any public record in any public office within the State of Nebraska, the officials having charge of the making of such records may employ the use of photographic processes for the reproduction of such instrument or document. This shall be done for the public records and shall be a true copy of the original instrument or document to be so recorded, and may likewise use any such photographic process for the making of certified copies of such public records; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> no such photographic processes shall be used for the making of permanent records until it shall have been demonstrated to the satisfaction of the officials having charge of such records and the State Records Administrator, that the processes to be used will produce an accurate and permanent record of the instrument or document to be recorded. Any such existing records when reproduced by such photographic processes may be destroyed by the official having charge of the same when approval is given by the State Records Administrator.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1911, c. 103, &#167; 1, p. 369; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 7974; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 8915; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1281; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1281; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 87, &#167; 1, p. 336; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 105, &#167; 5, p. 481. </para></source><annotation><para>Photostatic copies of county surveyor's records are admissible. Worm v. Crowell, 165 Neb. 713, 87 N.W.2d 384 (1958).</para><para>This section does not prevent courts from admitting photographs as secondary evidence; identification of photograph by one who took it not essential; correctness may be shown by knowledge and observation of witness. Nebraska State Bank of Republican City v. Walker, 111 Neb. 203, 196 N.W. 128 (1923).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>