<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-1557"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-1557</statuteno><catchline>Actions in which exemptions limited or not allowed.</catchline><para>Nothing in this chapter shall be so construed as to exempt any property in this state from execution or attachment for unpaid wages; for money due and owing by an attorney at law for money or other valuable consideration received by such attorney for any person or persons; or for enforcement of an award of or judgment for child support, alimony, or maintenance or a judgment for property division awarded to a former spouse.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 531, p. 486; </para><para>Laws 1869, &#167; 1, p. 66; </para><para>Laws 1887, c. 95, &#167; 1, p. 649; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8104; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9040; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-1558; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-1557; </para><para>Laws 1977, LB 60, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 372, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Judgment need not disclose nature of claim. Shreck v. Gilbert, 52 Neb. 813, 73 N.W. 276 (1897).</para><para>This section is not applicable to property exempt by homestead laws. Money due independent contractor is not "wages." Fox v. McClay, 48 Neb. 820, 67 N.W. 888 (1896).</para><para>Money due contractor furnishing his own and other labor is not exempt as wages. Henderson v. Nott, 36 Neb. 154, 54 N.W. 87 (1893).</para><para>"Necessaries of life" do not include goods furnished boarding house. Lehnoff v. Fisher, 32 Neb. 107, 48 N.W. 821 (1891).</para><para>Laborers' wages were exempt. Snyder v. Brune, 22 Neb. 189, 34 N.W. 364 (1887).</para><para>Proviso in this section does not limit value of specific property exemption under preceding section. Clay Center Bank v. McKelvie, 19 F.2d 308 (8th Cir. 1927).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>