<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2932"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2932</statuteno><catchline>Scope.</catchline><para>(a) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (b) or (c) of this section, the Uniform Mediation Act applies to a mediation in which:</para><para>(1) the mediation parties are required to mediate by statute or court or administrative agency rule or referred to mediation by a court, administrative agency, or arbitrator;</para><para>(2) the mediation parties and the mediator agree to mediate in a record that demonstrates an expectation that mediation communications will be privileged against disclosure; or</para><para>(3) the mediation parties use as a mediator an individual who holds himself or herself out as a mediator, or the mediation is provided by a person that holds itself out as providing mediation.</para><para>(b) The Uniform Mediation Act does not apply to a mediation:</para><para>(1) relating to the establishment, negotiation, administration, or termination of a collective-bargaining relationship;</para><para>(2) relating to a dispute that is pending under or is part of the processes established by a collective-bargaining agreement, except that the act applies to a mediation arising out of a dispute that has been filed with an administrative agency or court;</para><para>(3) conducted by a judge who might make a ruling on the case; or</para><para>(4) conducted under the auspices of:</para><para>(A) a primary or secondary school if all the parties and the mediator are students; or</para><para>(B) a correctional institution for youths or a juvenile center if all the parties and the mediator are residents of that institution.</para><para>(c) If the parties agree in advance in a signed record or a record of proceeding so reflects that all or part of a mediation is not privileged, the privileges under sections 25-2933 to 25-2935 do not apply to the mediation or part agreed upon. However, such sections apply to a mediation communication made by a person that has not received actual notice of the agreement before the communication is made.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 255, &#167; 3. </para></source></law></legaldoc>