<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,117"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,117</statuteno><catchline>Remaindermen; reversioners; rights and benefits.</catchline><para>Any person or persons having an interest in remainder or reversion in real estate shall be entitled to all the rights and benefits of sections 25-21,112 to 25-21,120.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 130, &#167; 6, p. 542; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5681; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 76-406; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-21,117.</para></source><annotation><para>Although a remainderman has the right to bring an action to quiet title, he is not required to do so to protect his estate in remainder from claim of adverse possession by grantee of life estate. Maxwell v. Hamel, 138 Neb. 49, 292 N.W. 38 (1940).</para><para>Remainderman may maintain action to quiet title before termination of life estate. Davis v. Davis, 107 Neb. 70, 185 N.W. 442 (1921); Naiman v. Bohlmeyer, 97 Neb. 551, 150 N.W. 829 (1915); First Nat. Bank of Perry, Iowa v. Pilger, 78 Neb. 168, 110 N.W. 704 (1907); Foree v. Stubbs, 41 Neb. 271, 59 N.W. 798 (1894).</para><para>Rule stated as to when statute commences to run against remainderman where adverse holder is a stranger holding by independent title not in privity with life tenant. Criswell v. Criswell, 101 Neb. 349, 163 N.W. 302 (1917); which overrules Bohrer v. Davis, 94 Neb. 367, 143 N.W. 209 (1913); McFarland v. Flack, 87 Neb. 452, 127 N.W. 375 (1910); Helming v. Forrester, 87 Neb. 438, 127 N.W. 373 (1910); Hobson v. Huxtable, 79 Neb. 334, 112 N.W. 658 (1907).</para><para>Statute of limitations will not run against remainderman in favor of life tenant until knowledge of adverse holding is brought home to the owner of the remainder. Maurer v. Reifschneider, 89 Neb. 673, 132 N.W. 197 (1911).</para><para>Minor has ten years after attaining majority in which to bring suit to quiet title against surviving widow claiming title. Draper v. Clayton, 87 Neb. 443, 127 N.W. 369 (1910).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>