<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00"  statutenumber="25-21,280"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,280</statuteno><catchline id="id00">School, educational service unit, early childhood education program, school nurse, medication aide, and nonmedical staff person; physician; health care professional; pharmacist; immunity; when.</catchline><para id="id00">(1) Any person employed by a school approved or accredited by the State Department of Education, employed by an educational service unit and working in a school approved or accredited by the department, or employed by an early childhood education program approved by the department who serves as a school nurse or medication aide or who has been designated and trained by the school, educational service unit, or program as a nonmedical staff person to implement the emergency response to life-threatening asthma or systemic allergic reactions protocols adopted by the school, educational service unit, or program shall be immune from civil liability for any act or omission in rendering emergency care for a person experiencing a potentially life-threatening asthma or allergic reaction event on school grounds, in a vehicle being used for school purposes, in a vehicle being used for educational service unit purposes, at a school-sponsored activity or athletic event, at a facility used by the early childhood education program, in a vehicle being used for early childhood education program purposes, or at an activity sponsored by the early childhood education program which results in damage or injury unless such damage or injury was caused by the willful or wanton act or omission of such employee.</para><para id="id00">(2) The individual immunity granted by subsection (1) of this section shall not extend to the school district, educational service unit, or early childhood education program and shall not extend to any act or omission of such employee which results in damage or injury if the damage or injury is caused by such employee while impaired by alcohol or any controlled substance enumerated in section 28-405.</para><para id="id00">(3) Any school nurse, such nurse's designee, or other designated adult described in section 79-224 shall be immune from civil liability for any act or omission described in such section which results in damage or injury unless such damage or injury was caused by the willful or wanton act or omission of such school nurse, nurse's designee, or designated adult.</para><para>(4) A physician or other health care professional may issue a non-patient-specific prescription for medication for response to life-threatening asthma or anaphylaxis to a school, an educational service unit, or an early childhood education program as described in subsection (1) of this section. The physician or other health care professional shall be immune from liability for issuing such prescription unless he or she does not exercise reasonable care under the circumstances in signing the prescription. In no circumstance shall a physician or other health care professional be liable for the act or omission of another who provides or in any way administers the medication prescribed by the physician or other health care professional.</para><para>(5) A pharmacist may dispense medication pursuant to a non-patient-specific prescription for response to life-threatening asthma or anaphylaxis to a school, an educational service unit, or an early childhood education program as described in subsection (1) of this section. The pharmacist shall be immune from liability for dispensing medication pursuant to a non-patient-specific prescription unless the pharmacist does not exercise reasonable care under the circumstances in dispensing the medication. In no circumstance shall a pharmacist be liable for the act or omission of another who provides or in any way administers the medication dispensed by the pharmacist.</para><para>(6) For purposes of this section, the name of the school, educational service unit, or early childhood education program shall serve as the patient name on the non-patient-specific prescription.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2004, LB 868, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2005, LB 361, &#167; 30; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1148, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB487, &#167; 1. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>