<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2210"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2210</statuteno><catchline>Clerk of district court; records; contents; appearance docket; general index; judgment record; transcripts from inferior courts; discharge of judgments.</catchline><para>On the appearance docket, the clerk of the district court shall enter all actions in the order in which they were brought, the date of the summons, the time of the return thereof by the officer and his or her return thereon, the time of filing the complaint or petition, and all subsequent pleadings. On the general index he or she shall enter the names of the parties to every suit, both direct and inverse, with the page and book where all proceedings in such action may be found. The judgment record shall contain the names of the judgment debtor and the judgment creditor, arranged alphabetically, the date of the judgment, the amount of the judgment, and the amount of costs, with the page and the book where the judgment may be found. Transcripts of judgments from county courts filed in the district court shall be entered upon the judgment record. Whenever any judgment is paid and discharged, the clerk shall enter such fact upon the judgment record in a column provided for that purpose.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 322, p. 448; </para><para>G.S.1873, c. 57, &#167; 322, p. 579; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8558; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9509; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2210; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2210; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 1, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 53.</para></source><annotation><para>On satisfactory proof that judgment has been paid, district court may order it discharged and canceled of record. Hopwood v. Hopwood, 169 Neb. 760, 100 N.W.2d 833 (1960).</para><para>Federal court judgment is lien only upon property in county where rendered, and not in other county, unless transcript is filed and entered upon judgment record there. Rathbone Co. v. Kimball, 117 Neb. 229, 220 N.W. 244 (1928).</para><para>Satisfaction of judgment entered on court record may be avoided by evidence that payment was not made or that it has become inoperative for equitable reason. Knaak v. Brown, 115 Neb. 260, 212 N.W. 431 (1927).</para><para>Court, on motion and satisfactory proof that judgment has been paid, may order it discharged and canceled of record. Manker v. Sine, 47 Neb. 736, 66 N.W. 840 (1896).</para><para>Judgment is sufficient, though not entered on general index. Hamilton v. Whitney, Clark &amp; Co., 19 Neb. 303, 27 N.W. 125 (1886).</para><para>Judgment must be properly indexed in alphabetical index. Metz v. State Bank of Brownville, 7 Neb. 165 (1878).</para><para>On motion and satisfactory proof that a judgment has been paid or satisfied, a district court may order such judgment discharged. Gutierrez v. Gutierrez, 5 Neb. App. 205, 557 N.W.2d 44 (1996).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>