<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id7">
<sectno id="id8">Sec. 2.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id9" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="25-21,291"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno>25-21,291</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes
of the Exploited Children's Civil Remedy Act:</para>
<para>(1) Access software
provider means a provider of software, including client or server software,
or enabling tools that do any one or more of the following: (a) Filter, screen,
allow, or disallow content; (b) pick, choose, analyze, or digest content;
or (c) transmit, receive, display, forward, cache, search, subset, organize,
reorganize, or translate content;</para>
<para>(2)
Aid or assist another with the creation, distribution, or active acquisition
of child pornography means help a principal in some appreciable manner with
the creation, distribution, or active acquisition of a visual depiction of
sexually explicit conduct which has a child as one of its participants or
portrayed observers. The term also includes knowingly employing, forcing,
authorizing, inducing, or otherwise causing a child to engage in any visual
depiction of sexually explicit conduct which has a child as one of its participants
or portrayed observers. No parent, stepparent, legal guardian, or person with
custody and control of a child, knowing the content thereof, may consent to
such child engaging in any visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct which
has a child as one of its participants or portrayed observers;</para>
<para>(3) Cable operator
means any person or group of persons (a) who provides cable service over a
cable system and directly or through one or more affiliates owns a significant
interest in such cable system or (b) who otherwise controls or is responsible
for, through any arrangement, the management and operation of such a cable
system;</para><para>(4) Child has the same meaning as in section 28-1463.02;</para>
<para>(5)
Create means to knowingly create, make, manufacture, direct, publish, finance,
or in any manner generate;</para><para>(6) Distribute means the actual, constructive,
or attempted transfer from one person, source, or location to another person,
source, or location. The term includes, but is not limited to, renting, selling,
delivering, displaying, advertising, trading, mailing, procuring, circulating,
lending, exhibiting, transmitting, transmuting, transferring, disseminating,
presenting, or providing any visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct
which has a child as one of its participants or portrayed observers;</para>
<para>(7) Interactive computer
service means any information service system or access software provider that
provides or enables computer access by multiple users to a computer server,
including specifically a service or system that provides access to the Internet
and such systems operated or services offered by libraries or educational
institutions;</para><para>(8) Participant means a child who appears in any visual depiction
of sexually explicit conduct and is portrayed or actively engaged in acts
of sexually explicit conduct appearing therein;</para><para>(9) Portrayed observer
means a child who appears in any visual depiction where sexually explicit
conduct is likewise portrayed or occurring within the child's presence or
in the child's proximity;</para><para>(10) Sexually explicit conduct has the same
meaning as in section 28-1463.02;</para><para>(11) Telecommunications service means the offering
of telecommunications for a fee directly to the public, or to such classes
of users as to be effectively available directly to the public, regardless
of the facilities used; and</para><para>(12) Visual depiction has the same meaning
as in section 28-1463.02.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB728, &#167;  2.</para><effectivedate>July 15, 2010</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>