<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,154"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,154</statuteno><catchline>Declaratory judgments; when refused.</catchline><para>The court may refuse to render or enter a declaratory judgment or decree where such judgment or decree, if rendered or entered, would not terminate the uncertainty or controversy giving rise to the proceeding.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 75, &#167; 6, p. 258; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-21,145; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-21,154.</para></source><annotation><para>The court may refuse to render or enter a declaratory judgment or decree where such judgment or decree, if rendered or entered, would not terminate the uncertainty or controversy giving rise to the proceeding. Omaha Pub. Power Dist. v. Nuclear Elec. Ins. Ltd., 229 Neb. 740, 428 N.W.2d 895 (1988); Arlington Oil Co. v. Hall, 130 Neb. 674, 266 N.W. 583 (1936); Smithberger v. Banning, 130 Neb. 354, 265 N.W. 10 (1936).</para><para>Where eminent domain proceeding was pending in which question of abandonment and its effect could be determined, action for declaratory judgment on claimed abandonment should have been dismissed. Zarybnicky v. County of Gage, 196 Neb. 210, 241 N.W.2d 834 (1976).</para><para>Discretionary power is conferred. Haynes v. Anderson, 163 Neb. 50, 77 N.W.2d 674 (1956).</para><para>One of the purposes of the act is to terminate the controversy that gave rise to the proceedings. Custer Public Power Dist. v. Loup River Public Power Dist., 162 Neb. 300, 75 N.W.2d 619 (1956).</para><para>Court will not render declaratory judgment where necessary parties have not been joined. Redick v. Peony Park, 151 Neb. 442, 37 N.W.2d 801 (1949).</para><para>Statute authorizing declaratory judgment is applicable only when all interested persons are made parties to the proceeding. Ben B. Wood Realty Co. v. Wood, 132 Neb. 817, 273 N.W. 493 (1937); Southern Nebraska Power Co. v. Village of Deshler, 130 Neb. 133, 264 N.W. 462 (1936).</para><para>Declaratory Judgments Act is applicable only where there is a present actual controversy and where justiciable issues are presented. Dobson v. Ocean Accident &amp; Guarantee Corp., 124 Neb. 652, 247 N.W. 789 (1933).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>