<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2606"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2606</statuteno><catchline>Hearing.</catchline><para>Unless otherwise provided by the agreement:</para><para>(a) The arbitrators shall appoint a time and place for the hearing and cause notification to the parties to be served personally or by registered or certified mail not less than ten days before the hearing. Appearance at the hearing waives such notice. The arbitrators may adjourn the hearing from time to time as necessary and, on request of a party and for good cause, or upon their own motion, may postpone the hearing to a time not later than the date fixed by the agreement for making the award unless the parties consent to a later date. The arbitrators may hear and determine the controversy upon the evidence produced notwithstanding the failure of a party duly notified to appear. The court on application may direct the arbitrators to proceed promptly with the hearing and determination of the controversy;</para><para>(b) The parties are entitled to be heard, to present evidence material to the controversy, and to cross-examine witnesses appearing at the hearing; and</para><para>(c) The hearing shall be conducted by all the arbitrators but a majority may determine any question and render a final award. If, during the course of the hearing, an arbitrator for any reason ceases to act, the remaining arbitrator or arbitrators appointed to act as neutrals may continue with the hearing and determination of the controversy.</para><para>Arbitration proceedings shall take place in the county designated in section 25-403.01 unless the parties otherwise agree at a time subsequent to the arising of the controversy.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 71, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 151, &#167; 4. </para></source>
<annotation><para>The lack of a formal notice of hearing in compliance with this section of the postponement of a hearing previously scheduled and correctly noticed did not invalidate an award where evidence supported the conclusion that the parties to the arbitration had actual notice of the postponed hearing in advance. Damrow v. Murdoch, 15 Neb. App. 920, 739 N.W.2d 229 (2007).</para><para>The trial court did not err in finding that lack of a formal notice under this section was an insufficient ground to vacate an arbitration award. Damrow v. Murdoch, 15 Neb. App. 920, 739 N.W.2d 229 (2007).</para></annotation>
</law></legaldoc>