<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2501" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2017</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2501</statuteno><catchline id="id00">Intent and purpose.</catchline><para id="id00">It is the intent and purpose of sections 25-2501 to 25-2506 to establish a uniform procedure to be used in acquiring private property for a public purpose by the State of Nebraska and its political subdivisions and by all privately owned public utility corporations and common carriers which have been granted the power of eminent domain. Such sections shall not apply to:</para><para id="id00">(1) Water transmission and distribution pipelines and their appurtenances and common carrier pipelines and their appurtenances;</para><para id="id00">(2) Public utilities and cities of all classes and villages when acquiring property for a proposed project involving the acquisition of rights or interests in ten or fewer separately owned tracts or when the acquisition is within the corporate limits of any city or village;</para><para id="id00">(3) Sanitary and improvement districts organized under sections 31-727 to 31-762 when acquiring easements for a proposed project involving the acquisition of rights or interests in ten or fewer separately owned tracts;</para><para id="id00">(4) Counties and municipalities which acquire property through the process of platting or subdivision or for street or highway construction or improvements;</para><para id="id00">(5) Common carriers subject to regulation by the Federal Railroad Administration of the United States Department of Transportation; or</para><para id="id00">(6) The Nebraska Department of Transportation when acquiring property for highway construction or improvements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 187, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 917, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 441, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 176, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2017, LB339, &#167; 81. </para><operativedate>July 1, 2017</operativedate></source><annotation><para>The purpose of the hearing provided for in the uniform procedure for acquiring property for public use is merely to explain the taking and to inform landowners of their procedural rights. Seward County Board of Commissioners v. City of Seward, 196 Neb. 266, 242 N.W.2d 849 (1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>