<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2301"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2301</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 25-2301 to 25-2310:</para><para>(1) Case includes any suit, action, or proceeding; and</para><para>(2) In forma pauperis means the permission given by the court for a party to proceed without prepayment of fees and costs or security.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1120, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 148, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 750, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 689, &#167; 2.</para></source><annotation><para>The "fees" specified in subsection (2) of this section do not include a party's attorney fees. State v. Ortega, 290 Neb. 172, 859 N.W.2d 305 (2015).</para><para>The plain language of the in forma pauperis statutes, taken as a whole, does not excuse a litigant who seeks the status of a pauper from paying the cost of a premium for a replevin bond pursuant to section 25-1098. Jacob v. Schlichtman, 261 Neb. 169, 622 N.W.2d 852 (2001).</para><para>Although jurisdiction is vested in an appellate court upon timely filing of a notice of appeal and an affidavit of poverty, some duties are still required of the lower court. This section requires the lower court to act if it determines that the allegations of poverty are untrue. In re Interest of Noelle F. &amp; Sarah F., 249 Neb. 628, 544 N.W.2d 509 (1996).</para><para>Generally, in the absence of good cause evident in the record, it is necessary for a party appealing to personally sign the affidavit in support of her or his motion to proceed in forma pauperis. Mere absence from the jurisdiction of the court from which the appeal is being taken, without more, does not show good cause for a party's failure to sign a poverty affidavit. In re Interest of T.W. et al., 234 Neb. 966, 453 N.W.2d 436 (1990).</para><para>As an alternative to depositing a docket fee, a person who is unable to pay the required fee may file an affidavit of poverty and proceed with an appeal in forma pauperis. State v. Hunter, 234 Neb. 567, 451 N.W.2d 922 (1990).</para><para>In order to perfect an appeal in forma pauperis, all that is necessary to confer jurisdiction on the Supreme Court is to file a notice of appeal and an affidavit signed by the appellant, as required by this section. In re Interest of N.L.B., 234 Neb. 280, 450 N.W.2d 676 (1990).</para><para>Courts must make specific findings of fact that establish the expected fees and costs and the ability of the appellant to pay those costs within the time required before denying the appellant in forma pauperis status for an appeal under this section. Fine v. Fine, 4 Neb. App. 101, 537 N.W.2d 642 (1995).</para><para>Where, after petitioner's appeal was dismissed by Nebraska Supreme Court for failure to deposit cash or bond and United States Supreme Court granted certiorari, sections 25-2301 to 25-2307 were enacted permitting appeal in forma pauperis, judgment was vacated, and cause remanded for reconsideration. Huffman v. Boersen, 406 U.S. 337 (1972).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>