<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id270"><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2744"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2744</statuteno><catchline>Discovery; expert; limitations; motion to modify.</catchline><para>(1) Except upon agreement of the parties or leave of court granted upon a showing of good cause, all discovery under the County Court Expedited Civil Actions Act must be completed no later than sixty days before trial.</para><para>(2) Except upon agreement of the parties or leave of court granted upon a showing of good cause, discovery under the act is subject to the following additional limitations:</para><para>(a) Each side shall serve no more than ten interrogatories on any other side;</para><para>(b) Each side shall serve no more than ten requests for production on any other side;</para><para>(c) Each side shall serve no more than ten requests for admission on any other side. This limit does not apply to requests for admission of the genuineness of documents that a party intends to offer into evidence at trial;</para><para>(d) One deposition of each party may be taken. With regard to corporations, partnerships, voluntary associations, or any other groups or entities named as a party, the entity or one officer, member, or employee of such entity may be deposed; and</para><para>(e) Each side may take the deposition of up to two nonparties.</para><para>(3) Each side is entitled to one expert, except upon agreement of the parties or leave of court granted upon a showing of good cause. A treating health care provider is counted as an expert for purposes of this subsection.</para><para>(4) A motion for leave of court to modify the limitations set forth in this section must be in writing and must set forth the proposed additional discovery or expert and the reasons establishing good cause.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB912, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>