<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2913"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2913</statuteno><catchline>Mediators and restorative justice facilitators; qualifications; compensation; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) Mediators and restorative justice facilitators of approved centers shall have completed at least thirty hours of basic mediation training, including conflict resolution techniques, neutrality, agreement writing, and ethics. An initial apprenticeship with an experienced mediator shall be required for at least three sessions for all mediators without prior mediation experience.</para><para>(2) In addition to the basic mediation training required under subsection (1) of this section:</para><para>(a) For disputes involving marital dissolution, parenting, or child custody, mediators of approved centers shall have additional training in family mediation; and</para><para>(b) For disputes involving harm done to others or the community, restorative justice facilitators of approved centers shall have additional restorative justice training that has been approved by the office. Such training should include, but not be limited to, topics such as restorative justice basics, trauma-informed practices, juvenile developmental characteristics, and crime victimization.</para><para>(3) An approved center may provide for the compensation of mediators and restorative justice facilitators, utilize the services of volunteer mediators and restorative justice facilitators, or utilize the services of both paid and volunteer mediators and restorative justice facilitators.</para><para>(4) The mediator or restorative justice facilitator shall provide an opportunity for the parties to achieve a mutually acceptable resolution of their dispute, in joint or separate sessions, as appropriate, including a reparation plan agreement regarding reparations through dialogue and negotiation. A mediator shall be impartial, neutral, and unbiased and shall make no decisions for the parties.</para><para>(5) The mediator or restorative justice facilitator shall officially terminate the process if the parties are unable to agree or if, in the judgment of the mediator, the agreement would be unconscionable. The termination shall be without prejudice to either party in any other proceeding.</para><para>(6) The mediator or restorative justice facilitator has no authority to make or impose any adjudicatory sanction or penalty upon the parties.</para><para>(7) The mediator or restorative justice facilitator shall be aware of and recommend outside resources to the parties whenever appropriate. The mediator or restorative justice facilitator shall advise participants to obtain legal review of agreements as necessary.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1991, LB 90, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB595, &#167; 13. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>