<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id864"><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2914.01"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2914.01</statuteno><catchline>Verbal, written, or electronic communication; confidentiality; privileged; disclosure; when; activities of juvenile; limit on evidence.</catchline><para>(1) Any verbal, written, or electronic communication made in or in connection with matters referred to a restorative justice program which relates to the controversy or dispute undergoing restorative justice and agreements resulting from the restorative justice program, whether made to the restorative justice facilitator, the staff of an approved center, a party, or any other person attending the restorative justice program, shall be confidential and privileged.</para><para>(2) No admission, confession, or incriminating information obtained from a juvenile in the course of any restorative justice program that is conducted in conjunction with proceedings under the Dispute Resolution Act or as directed by a court, including, but not limited to, school-based disciplinary proceedings, juvenile diversion, court-ordered detention, or probation, shall be admitted into evidence against such juvenile, except as rebuttal or impeachment evidence, in any future adjudication hearing under the Nebraska Juvenile Code or in any criminal proceeding. Such admission, confession, or incriminating information may be considered by a court at sentencing or by a juvenile court during disposition proceedings.</para><para>(3) Confidential communications and materials are subject to disclosure when all parties to the restorative justice program agree in writing to waive confidentiality regarding specific verbal, written, or electronic communications relating to the restorative justice program or the agreement.</para><para>(4) This section shall not apply if:</para><para>(a) A party brings an action against the restorative justice facilitator or approved center;</para><para>(b) The communication was made in furtherance of a crime or fraud;</para><para>(c) The communication is required to be reported under section 28-711 and is a new allegation of child abuse or neglect which was not previously known or reported; or</para><para>(d) This section conflicts with other legal requirements.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB595, &#167; 15. </para><effectivedate>September 1, 2019</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Juvenile Code,</emphasis> see section 43-2,129.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>