<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2141"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2141</statuteno><catchline>Parties defendant; joinder.</catchline><para>If the mortgage debt is secured by the obligation or other evidence of debt of any other person besides the mortgagor, the complainant may make such person a party to the action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 849, p. 543; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8258; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9211; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2143; </para><para>Laws 1933, c. 41, &#167; 2, p. 248; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-2143; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2141.</para></source><annotation><para>After mortgage foreclosure is completed, mortgagee may sue at law for deficiency without authorization of equity court wherein foreclosure was had. Federal Farm Mtg. Corp. v. Claussen, 138 Neb. 518, 293 N.W. 424 (1940).</para><para>Amendment of 1933 did not affect right of creditor to bring suit at law on note for deficiency remaining after foreclosure of mortgage has been completed. Federal Farm Mtg. Corp. v. Thiele, 137 Neb. 626, 290 N.W. 471 (1940); Federal Farm Mtg. Corp. v. Cramb, 137 Neb. 553, 290 N.W. 440 (1940).</para><para>Parties to indemnity agreement against loss on real estate mortgage are proper, though not necessary, parties to original foreclosure proceeding. First Trust Co. of Lincoln v. Airedale Ranch &amp; Cattle Co., 136 Neb. 521, 286 N.W. 766 (1939).</para><para>Holder of secured note transferring it without disclosing that he was agent is liable for deficiency. Thornton v. Farmers &amp; Merchants Nat. Bank of Fairbury, 117 Neb. 355, 220 N.W. 598 (1928).</para><para>Joining sureties on note secured by mortgage as defendants in foreclosure suit was proper. United States Trust Co. v. Miller, 116 Neb. 25, 215 N.W. 462 (1927).</para><para>Vendor becomes in effect surety if mortgagee elects to hold purchaser. Merriam v. Miles, 54 Neb. 566, 74 N.W. 861 (1898).</para><para>If conveyed subject to mortgage, purchaser is not liable for deficiency. Green v. Hall, 45 Neb. 89, 63 N.W. 119 (1895).</para><para>Purchaser agreeing to pay mortgage as part consideration may be sued at law or held liable on foreclosure. Reynolds v. Dietz, 39 Neb. 180, 58 N.W. 89 (1894).</para><para>Where purchaser assumes and agrees to pay mortgage, it is immaterial in foreclosure action whether vendor had mortgageable interest in premises. Bond v. Dolby, 17 Neb. 491, 23 N.W. 351 (1885).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>