<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2214"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2214</statuteno><catchline>Clerks of courts; general powers and duties.</catchline><para>The clerk of each of the courts shall exercise the powers and perform the duties conferred and imposed upon him by other provisions of this code, by other statutes and by the common law. In the performance of his duties he shall be under the direction of his court. It shall be the duty of the clerk of each of said courts to prepare and file the annual inventory statement with the county board of his county of all county personal property in his custody or possession, as provided in sections 23-346 to 23-350.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 889, p. 548; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8563; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9514; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2215; </para><para>Laws 1939, c. 28, &#167; 21, p. 159; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-2215; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2214.</para></source><annotation><para>Although the appellate court's mandate did not state that buyout payments were to be made to the clerk of the district court, the district court had authority to make such an order, because the proper place to pay a judgment is the clerk of the court in which the judgment is obtained. Robertson v. Jacobs Cattle Co., 292 Neb. 195, 874 N.W.2d 1 (2015).</para><para>Although the clerk of the district court is authorized to spread upon the court journal the proceedings had and relief granted by the court, and to that extent is responsible for entry of the judgment, such clerk has no authority to perform the judicial function of rendering a judgment. Building Systems, Inc. v. Medical Center, Ltd., 228 Neb. 168, 421 N.W.2d 773 (1988).</para><para>Where petition on appeal is filed in district court in compensation case, it is clerk's duty to issue summons, and place same in hands of proper officer for service, without praecipe being filed. McIntosh v. Standard Oil Co., 121 Neb. 92, 236 N.W. 152 (1931).</para><para>Supreme Court will not issue mandamus to clerk unless district court has refused. State ex rel. Fitzgerald v. Houseworth, 63 Neb. 658, 88 N.W. 858 (1902).</para><para>Money paid to clerk, pursuant to order or judgment of court, is received in official capacity, and sureties are liable for failure to account therefor. Bantley v. Baker, 61 Neb. 92, 84 N.W. 603 (1900).</para><para>Clerk of court is the proper custodian of money paid into court. Dirks v. Juel, 59 Neb. 353, 80 N.W. 1045 (1899).</para><para>Money paid to clerk in mortgage foreclosure proceeding before judgment was not received in official capacity. Commercial Inv. Co. v. Peck, 53 Neb. 204, 73 N.W. 452 (1897).</para><para>Mandamus will not lie in Supreme Court to compel clerk of district court to issue execution on judgment when no application for such order has been made to district court. State ex rel. Ogden v. Frank, 52 Neb. 553, 72 N.W. 857 (1897).</para><para>District court has jurisdiction to direct clerk in the performance of his official duties. State ex rel. Solmon v. Moores, 29 Neb. 122, 45 N.W. 278 (1890).</para><para>Clerks perform their duties under the direction of the court. State v. Wahrman, 11 Neb. App. 101, 644 N.W.2d 572 (2002).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>