<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2503"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2503</statuteno><catchline>Agency; notice; contents.</catchline><para>Any agency which proposes to acquire private property for a public purpose shall give notice of such proposed acquisition at least forty-five days before beginning negotiations for such acquisition. The notice shall be directed to each owner of property over or across which any right or interest is to be acquired and shall be deemed properly given if delivered personally or mailed by registered or certified mail addressed to the property owner and to the address shown on the tax records in the office of the county treasurer, except that such notice shall be sufficient if given to the administrator or executor of the estate of a deceased person, the trustee of a trust estate, the guardian of the estate of a minor or incompetent person, or a conservator. The notice shall (1) describe the property proposed to be acquired and the compensation to be given for such property, (2) include a statement of the authority for the acquisition, (3) include the nature of and necessity and purpose for which the land shall be used, (4) include the title, right, or interest in the property to be acquired, (5) specify the amount of property needed for the public purpose, (6) include the reasons for selecting the proposed location or route, and (7) state that if approval of any other agency is required, the condemner shall set forth which other agency's approval shall be necessary and, when the acquisition involves a highway, power line, telephone line, or similar project, shall include a map showing the proposed route to be followed by the project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1973, LB 187, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1978, LB 917, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 1105, &#167; 425. </para></source><annotation><para>A notice of acquisition sent to a landowner prior to beginning condemnation proceedings constitutes a privileged communication during statutorily required negotiations and, thus, may be excluded pursuant to section 27-408. In re Application of SID No. 384 of Douglas County, 259 Neb. 351, 609 N.W.2d 679 (2000).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>