<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,157"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,157</statuteno><catchline>Trial; issues of fact; how conducted.</catchline><para>When a proceeding under sections 25-21,149 to 25-21,164 involves the determination of an issue of fact, such issue may be tried and determined in the same manner as issues of fact are tried and determined in other civil actions in the court in which the proceeding is pending.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 75, &#167; 9, p. 258; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-21,148; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-21,157.</para></source><annotation><para>A party may not simply move the court for a declaratory judgment; no such summary proceeding is recognized in Nebraska. Breci v. St. Paul Mercury Ins. Co., 288 Neb. 626, 849 N.W.2d 523 (2014).</para><para>In a declaratory judgment action involving the determination of issues of fact, such issues may be tried and determined as in other civil actions. Millard Rur. Fire Prot. Dist. No. 1 v. City of Omaha, 226 Neb. 50, 409 N.W.2d 574 (1987).</para><para>Fact questions in a declaratory judgment action may be tried and determined as in other civil actions. OB-GYN v. Blue Cross, 219 Neb. 199, 361 N.W.2d 550 (1985).</para><para>Where a decision appealed from involves, at the outset, questions of fact, the parties are entitled to a jury trial, notwithstanding the fact that the action may have involved both questions of fact and of law. Hemenway v. MFA Life Ins. Co., 211 Neb. 193, 318 N.W.2d 70 (1982).</para><para>In a declaratory judgment action, issues of fact may be tried and determined as in other civil actions, and if the action would otherwise be an action at law and is tried to the court without a jury the trial court's findings have the effect of a jury verdict. Larutan Corp. v. Magnolia Homes Manuf. Co., 190 Neb. 425, 209 N.W.2d 177 (1973).</para><para>Where jury waived, judgment of trial court will not be set aside unless clearly wrong. Belek v. Travelers Ind. Co., 187 Neb. 470, 191 N.W.2d 819 (1971).</para><para>Issues of fact may be tried and determined as in other civil actions. American Standard Ins. Co. v. Tournor, 186 Neb. 585, 185 N.W.2d 267 (1971); United Services Automobile Assn. v. Hills, 172 Neb. 128, 109 N.W.2d 174 (1961); State Farm Mutual Auto. Ins. Co. v. Kersey, 171 Neb. 212, 106 N.W.2d 31 (1960).</para><para>An issue of fact may be submitted for determination by a jury. Hawkeye Casualty Co. v. Stoker, 154 Neb. 466, 48 N.W.2d 623 (1951).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>