<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2009" amended="yes" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2009</statuteno><catchline>Supreme Court, Court of Appeals, and county court judgments; laws applicable.</catchline><para>The provisions of Chapter 25 shall apply to the Supreme Court, Court of Appeals, and county court, so far as the same may be applicable to the judgments or final orders of such courts. The parties shall be limited to the same time in which to commence proceedings; and in estimating time, the county court shall, for such purpose, be considered as holding, in each year, a regular term of court commencing on January 1.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 610, p. 502; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8215; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9168; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2009; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 30, &#167; 1, p. 139; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 20-2009; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2009; </para><para>Laws 2006, LB 1115, &#167; 17. </para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Power</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Power</emphasis></para><para>A county court in the exercise of its probate jurisdiction is not bound by the statute which fixes its terms within which its jurisdiction in civil cases must be exercised. In re Reikofski Estate, 144 Neb. 735, 14 N.W.2d 379 (1944).</para><para>County court has power to vacate order in probate proceedings at subsequent term. In re Estate of Sheerer, 137 Neb. 374, 289 N.W. 529 (1940).</para><para>County court cannot vacate or modify judgment in civil cases beyond jurisdiction of justice after monthly term except as provided by statute. Stone v. Jensen, 118 Neb. 254, 224 N.W. 284 (1929).</para><para>Justices and county courts exercising justice jurisdiction are not empowered to vacate judgment after time to appeal has expired, nor to vacate fraudulent judgment after term. Carlson v. Ray, 104 Neb. 18, 175 N.W. 886 (1919).</para><para>County court may vacate probate procured by fraud and permit contest of will. In re Estate of Kelly, 103 Neb. 513, 172 N.W. 758 (1919), rehearing denied 103 Neb. 524, 175 N.W. 653 (1919).</para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para>This section makes proceedings to vacate or modify judgment at subsequent term applicable to Supreme and county courts. In re Estate of Jensen, 135 Neb. 602, 283 N.W. 196 (1939).</para><para>Law authorizing district court to vacate judgment cannot be invoked after judgment is pronounced regular by Supreme Court. Brandeen v. Beale, 117 Neb. 291, 220 N.W. 298 (1928).</para><para>Final order of county court in proceeding to set aside fraudulent judgment is reviewable by district court on appeal. Gainsforth v. Peterson, 114 Neb. 442, 207 N.W. 935 (1926).</para><para>Procedure to vacate judgment applies to county court in exercise of probate jurisdiction. Oakdale Heat &amp; Light Co. v. Seymour, 78 Neb. 50, 114 N.W. 643 (1908).</para><para><emphasis>3. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Statutory provision is exclusive. State v. State Journal Co., 77 Neb. 771, 111 N.W. 118 (1907).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>