<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2146"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2146</statuteno><catchline>Sale; proceeds; how applied.</catchline><para>The proceeds of every sale made under a decree in equity shall be applied to the discharge of the debt adjudged by such court to be due, and of the costs awarded, and if there be any surplus, it shall be brought into court for the use of the defendant, or of the persons entitled thereto, subject to the order of the court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 854, p. 543; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8263; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9216; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2148; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2146.</para></source><annotation><para>District court has jurisdiction over distribution of proceeds of mortgage foreclosure sale. Mauzy v. Elliott, 146 Neb. 865, 22 N.W.2d 142 (1946).</para><para>Where plaintiff bid in the property at foreclosure sale, he cannot apply interest coupons, not included in the decree, to reduce the surplus which he must pay into court above the amount due on his lien. DeMoulin Loan &amp; Inv. Co. v. McLain, 107 Neb. 858, 187 N.W. 123 (1922).</para><para>Court may bring in all necessary parties to complete distribution of surplus. Montague v. Marunda, 71 Neb. 805, 99 N.W. 653 (1904).</para><para>Sheriff is custodian of proceeds until confirmation; then it is his duty to pay to parties entitled. Craw v. Abrams, 68 Neb. 546, 94 N.W. 639 (1903), affirmed on rehearing 68 Neb. 553, 97 N.W. 296 (1903).</para><para>Junior mortgagee, not party to foreclosure, may claim surplus. Milligan v. Gallen, 64 Neb. 561, 90 N.W. 541 (1902).</para><para>There should be ratable application to all notes secured by mortgage though some were outlawed, where security is insufficient. Patrick v. National Bank of Commerce, 63 Neb. 200, 88 N.W. 183 (1901).</para><para>Entire proceeds of sale are subject to order of court until paid out. Conley v. State, 46 Neb. 187, 64 N.W. 708 (1895).</para><para>Officer selling property has no authority to sell on credit unless authorized by express terms of decree or statute. Hooper v. Castetter, 45 Neb. 67, 63 N.W. 135 (1895).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>