<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2125"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2125</statuteno><catchline>Ejectment; answer; contents.</catchline><para>It shall be sufficient in such action if the answer denies generally the title alleged in the complaint, or that the defendant withholds possession, as the case may be; but if the defendant denies the title of the plaintiff, possession by the defendant shall be taken as admitted. If the defendant does not defend for the whole premises, the answer shall describe the particular part for which defense is made.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 627, p. 505; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8240; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9193; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2125; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2125; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 31. </para></source><annotation><para>Defendant's general denials in an ejectment action are sufficient to raise the question of the defendant's equity in the property as a defense to the ejectment action. Miller v. Radtke, 230 Neb. 561, 432 N.W.2d 542 (1988).</para><para>Ejectment of a vendee may be granted as a remedy for violating the terms of a land contract only where the equities of the particular case justify such a disposition, where the property is of less value than the contract price, and where such a procedure would not offend against justice and equity. Miller v. Radtke, 230 Neb. 561, 432 N.W.2d 542 (1988).</para><para>In an ejectment action, where defendant presents an equitable defense, the case is tried, and reviewed, as an action in equity. Miller v. Radtke, 230 Neb. 561, 432 N.W.2d 542 (1988).</para><para>In enforcing a vendor's rights in a land contract, ejectment is a more severe disposition than is the remedy of strict foreclosure. Miller v. Radtke, 230 Neb. 561, 432 N.W.2d 542 (1988).</para><para>Under general denial, defendant may prove estoppel to defeat plaintiff's cause of action. Fitch v. Walsh, 94 Neb. 32, 142 N.W. 293 (1913).</para><para>Proof of adverse possession is admissible under general denial. Murray v. Romine, 60 Neb. 94, 82 N.W. 318 (1900).</para><para>Where answer denies title and right of possession, defendant may interpose defense of adverse possession. Fink v. Dawson, 52 Neb. 647, 72 N.W. 1037 (1897).</para><para>Defendant may interpose any number of defenses. Wanser v. Lucas, 44 Neb. 759, 62 N.W. 1108 (1895).</para><para>Defendant under general denial may prove any fact which will defeat plaintiff's cause of action. Staley v. Housel, 35 Neb. 160, 52 N.W. 888 (1892).</para><para>Statute of limitations is a defense. Gue v. Jones, 25 Neb. 634, 41 N.W. 555 (1889); Colvin v. Republican Valley Land Assn., 23 Neb. 75, 36 N.W. 361 (1888).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>