<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2145"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2145</statuteno><catchline>Deed of conveyance; effect; estate conveyed.</catchline><para>Deed shall thereupon be executed by such sheriff, which shall vest in the purchaser the same estate that would have vested in the mortgagee if the equity of redemption had been foreclosed, and no other or greater; and such deeds shall be as valid as if executed by the mortgagor and mortgagee, and shall be an entire bar against each of them and all parties to the suit in which the decree for such sale was made, and against their heirs respectively, and all persons claiming under such heirs.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 853, p. 543; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8262; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9215; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2147; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2145.</para></source><annotation><para>Confirmation of sale vests in purchaser estate that would have been vested in mortgagee if equity of redemption had been foreclosed. Mauzy v. Elliott, 146 Neb. 865, 22 N.W.2d 142 (1946).</para><para>The purchaser at a foreclosure sale buys all the interests of all parties to the suit. George v. Pracheil, 92 Neb. 81, 137 N.W. 880 (1912).</para><para>Deed transfers every right and interest in the property of all parties to action, unless otherwise provided. Arterburn v. Beard, 86 Neb. 733, 126 N.W. 379 (1910).</para><para>Deed is subject to rights of parties not served. Kerr v. McCreary, 84 Neb. 315, 120 N.W. 1117 (1909).</para><para>Deed conveys all interest of mortgagor, and grantee need not account to junior mortgagee, not party to action, where latter is not seeking to redeem. City of Lincoln v. Lincoln St. Ry. Co., 75 Neb. 523, 106 N.W. 317 (1906).</para><para>Foreclosure sale transfers to purchaser every right, title and interest of all the parties to the suit. Hart v. Beardsley, 67 Neb. 145, 93 N.W. 423 (1903).</para><para>Mortgagor retains legal title and substantial interest in mortgaged premises until confirmation of sale and execution of deed, and may redeem at any time before order of confirmation becomes final. United States Nat. Bank of Omaha v. Pamp, 83 F.2d 493 (8th Cir. 1936).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>