<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,156"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,156</statuteno><catchline>Pleadings; complaint; orders to show cause.</catchline><para>Further relief based on a declaratory judgment or decree may be granted whenever necessary or proper. The application therefor shall be by complaint to a court having jurisdiction to grant the relief. If the application is deemed sufficient, the court shall, on reasonable notice, require any adverse party whose rights have been adjudicated by the declaratory judgment or decree to show cause why further relief should not be granted forthwith.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 75, &#167; 8, p. 258; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-21,147; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-21,156; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 49. </para></source><annotation><para>When the plaintiff's pleadings in a declaratory judgment action put the defendant on notice of the remedy sought, a trial court may order relief which is clearly within the scope of its declaratory judgment. Conversely, when a plaintiff's requested relief is not clearly within the scope of a court's declaratory judgment, the court should grant such relief only for a plaintiff's concurrent or subsequent cause of action or the plaintiff's application for supplemental relief under this section. Wetovick v. County of Nance, 279 Neb. 773, 782 N.W.2d 298 (2010).</para><para>The trial court has the power to retain jurisdiction in order to grant further relief for the amounts of percentage rent as they may be determined each year until the expiration of the lease which was the subject of the declaratory judgment action. S.N. Mart, Ltd. v. Maurices Inc., 234 Neb. 343, 451 N.W.2d 259 (1990).</para><para>Judgment for amount due under contract may be obtained in a declaratory judgment action. Richardson v. Waterite Co., 169 Neb. 263, 99 N.W.2d 265 (1959).</para><para>Injunction against enforcing of city ordinance was properly refused. McNeil v. City of Omaha, 160 Neb. 301, 70 N.W.2d 83 (1955).</para><para>Injunctive relief deemed unnecessary. Omaha Nat. Bank v. Heintze, 159 Neb. 520, 67 N.W.2d 753 (1954).</para><para>Further relief may be granted to carry into effect declaratory judgment. Noble v. City of Lincoln, 158 Neb. 457, 63 N.W.2d 475 (1954).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>