<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,239"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,239</statuteno><catchline>Leased trucks, truck-tractors, and trailers; liability of owner for damages.</catchline><para>The owner of any truck, truck-tractor, whether with or without trailer, or trailer, leased for a period of less than thirty days or leased for any period of time and used for commercial purposes, shall be jointly and severally liable with the lessee and the operator thereof for any injury to or the death of any person or persons, or damage to or the destruction of any property resulting from the operation thereof in this state, except that the owner shall not be jointly and severally liable if there is in effect at the time the claim arises a valid liability insurance policy with coverage limits in the minimum amount of one million dollars per occurrence which is available to compensate any person with a claim arising out of the operation or use of the leased truck, truck-tractor, or trailer. This section shall not limit or reduce the owner's liability for his or her own acts or omissions which cause damage to any person or when the lessee is a related entity or by reason of any workers' compensation law.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 170, &#167; 1, p. 591; </para><para>R.R.S.1943, &#167; 39-7,135; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1988), &#167; 39-6,193; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 370, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 527, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Where the plaintiff's injury resulted from the operation of a truck outside the State of Nebraska, there was no finding of liability under this section. Erickson v. U-Haul Internat., 278 Neb. 18, 767 N.W.2d 765 (2009).</para><para>A minivan used primarily as a passenger vehicle is not a truck under this section. Philpot v. Aguglia, 259 Neb. 573, 611 N.W.2d 93 (2000).</para><para>This section held inapplicable in workmen's compensation case arising from use of hoist, not the truck. Vangreen v. Interstate Machinery &amp; Supply Co., 197 Neb. 29, 246 N.W.2d 652 (1976).</para><para>Section 39-6,193, imposing vicarious liability on owners-lessors of trucks is constitutional. Bridgeford v. U-Haul Co., 195 Neb. 308, 238 N.W.2d 443 (1976) (pursuant to Laws 1993, LB 370, section 7, language from section 39-6,193 was placed in section 25-21,239).</para><para>This section, imposing vicarious liability on owners-lessors of trucks for damages by lessees and operators of the leased trucks, is constitutional. Bridgeford v. U-Haul Co., 195 Neb. 308, 238 N.W.2d 443 (1976).</para><para>Section did not make lessee of trailer of lessor, and did not impute lessee's negligence to lessor under nonresident motor vehicle statute. Peterson v. U-Haul Co., 409 F.2d 1174 (8th Cir. 1969).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>