<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,187"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,187</statuteno><catchline>Contract or agreement; indemnity provision; against public policy; unenforceable; when; construction project; violation of safety practice; liability.</catchline><para>(1) In the event that a public or private contract or agreement for the construction, alteration, repair, or maintenance of a building, structure, highway bridge, viaduct, water, sewer, or gas distribution system, or other work dealing with construction or for any moving, demolition, or excavation connected with such construction contains a covenant, promise, agreement, or combination thereof to indemnify or hold harmless another person from such person's own negligence, then such covenant, promise, agreement, or combination thereof shall be void as against public policy and wholly unenforceable. This subsection shall not apply to construction bonds or insurance contracts or agreements.</para><para>(2) No professional architect, professional engineer, or professional land surveyor who is retained to perform professional services on a construction project and no employee of a professional architect, professional engineer, or professional land surveyor who is assisting or representing the professional architect, professional engineer, or professional land surveyor in the performance of professional services on a construction project shall be liable in tort for any case of personal injury to or death of any employee working on a construction project arising out of and in the course of employment on the construction project and occurring as a result of a violation of a safety practice by any third party unless the responsibility for supervision of safety practices has been assumed by contract or by other conduct. This subsection shall not be construed to establish, diminish, or abrogate any duty, standard of care, or liability of any person or individual except as expressly provided in this subsection.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 288, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1979), &#167; 25-1153; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 492, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Maintenance of a building, within the meaning of subsection (1) of this section, does not encompass the ordinary activities associated with management of commercial property. Kuhn v. Wells Fargo Bank of Neb., 278 Neb. 428, 771 N.W.2d 103 (2009).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>