<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2005"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2005</statuteno><catchline>District court judgment; vacation; existence of valid claim or defense a prerequisite; preservation of liens upon modification.</catchline><para>A judgment shall not be vacated on motion or complaint, until it is adjudged that there is a valid defense to the action in which the judgment is rendered, or, if the plaintiff seeks its vacation, that there is a valid cause of action; and when a judgment is modified, all liens and securities obtained under it shall be preserved to the modified judgment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 606, p. 501; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8211; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9164; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2005; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2005; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 29. </para></source><annotation><para>Prerequisite to vacation of judgment is showing of valid defense. Gasper v. Mazur, 157 Neb. 857, 62 N.W.2d 117 (1954).</para><para>Plaintiff seeking vacation of judgment after term must allege and prove valid cause of action. Morrill County v. Bliss, 125 Neb. 97, 249 N.W. 98 (1933).</para><para>Court must adjudge that cause of action is prima facie valid before it is authorized to take action on motion. Gavin v. Reed, 73 Neb. 237, 102 N.W. 455 (1905).</para><para>Mere showing of want of service of summons is not sufficient. Baldwin v. Burt, 54 Neb. 287, 74 N.W. 594 (1898).</para><para>Party seeking to vacate judgment after term must plead and prove valid cause or defense. Gilbert v. Marrow, 54 Neb. 77, 74 N.W. 420 (1898).</para><para>"Adjudged" means judicially determined. Western Assur. Co. of Toronto v. Klein, 48 Neb. 904, 67 N.W. 873 (1896).</para><para>Applicant must allege and prove valid defense or cause of action. Bond v. Wycoff, 42 Neb. 214, 60 N.W. 564 (1894).</para><para>Motion to vacate must be accompanied by answer. McBrien v. Riley, 38 Neb. 561, 57 N.W. 385 (1894).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>