<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2225"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2225</statuteno><catchline>Special statutory proceedings; procedure; how affected by this code.</catchline><para>Where, by general or special statute, a civil action, legal or equitable, is given and the mode of proceeding therein is prescribed, this code shall not affect the proceedings under such statute, until the Legislature shall otherwise provide; but in all such cases, as far as it may be consistent with the statute giving such action, and practicable under this code, the proceedings shall be conducted in conformity thereto. Where the statute designates by name or otherwise the kind of action, but does not prescribe the mode of proceedings therein, such action shall be commenced and prosecuted in conformity to this code; where the statute gives an action, but does not designate the kind of action, or prescribe the mode of proceeding therein, such action shall be held to be the civil action of this code and proceeded in accordingly.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 903, p. 550; </para><para>Laws 1867, &#167; 1, p. 71; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8574; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9525; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2226; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2225.</para></source><annotation><para>In a summary proceeding under section 32-624 before a district court judge, it was not an abuse of discretion to deny discovery. Nebraska Republican Party v. Shively, 311 Neb. 160, 971 N.W.2d 128 (2022).</para><para>During pendency of an appeal in district court in workmen's compensation case, plaintiff has the right to dismiss action without prejudice. Chilen v. Commercial Casualty Ins. Co., 135 Neb. 619, 283 N.W. 366 (1939).</para><para>Proceedings in election contest case should be in harmony with provisions of the code of civil procedure, except where controlled by specific provisions of special act. Swan v. Bowker, 135 Neb. 405, 281 N.W. 891 (1938).</para><para>In mandamus proceedings no pleading is authorized other than the writ and the answer; intervention should be denied. State ex rel. Randall v. Hall, 125 Neb. 236, 249 N.W. 756 (1933).</para><para>District court on filing of petition for appeal, will proceed in accordance with compensation act, and requirement of praecipe before issuance of summons does not apply. McIntosh v. Standard Oil Co., 121 Neb. 92, 236 N.W. 152 (1931).</para><para>Special proceeding before Supreme Court Justice to compel election commissioner to file nomination acceptance and place name on ballot is civil action, and must be brought in county where cause of action arose. State ex rel. Meissner v. McHugh, 120 Neb. 356, 233 N.W. 1 (1930).</para><para>Special divorce statute requires plaintiff to give actual notice to nonresident defendant whose address is known. Williams v. Williams, 101 Neb. 369, 163 N.W. 147 (1917).</para><para>Original actions in Supreme Court are governed by code. State v. State Journal Co., 77 Neb. 771, 111 N.W. 118 (1907).</para><para>Divorce is special proceeding. Eager v. Eager, 74 Neb. 827, 105 N.W. 636, 107 N.W. 254 (1905).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>