<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2137"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2137</statuteno><catchline>Complaint for foreclosure or satisfaction; where filed.</catchline><para>All complaints for the foreclosure or satisfaction of mortgages shall be filed in the district court where the mortgaged premises are situated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>R.S.1867, Code &#167; 845, p. 542; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 8254; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9207; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2139; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2137; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 32. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>For appointment of receiver,</emphasis> see sections 25-1081 to 25-1092.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>Action to foreclose real estate mortgage must be brought in county where real estate is situated. Boehmer v. Heinen, 138 Neb. 376, 293 N.W. 237 (1940).</para><para>Right to bring action at law on promissory note, secured by real estate mortgage, has not been abolished. Federal Farm Mtg. Corp. v. Thiele, 137 Neb. 626, 290 N.W. 471 (1940).</para><para>It is presumed that the law of Colorado regarding place of filing mortgage foreclosure actions is same as that of Nebraska in absence of proof to contrary. National Fidelity Life Ins. Co. v. Gordon, 130 Neb. 130, 264 N.W. 155 (1936).</para><para>Foreclosure was properly brought in county where land was located. Prudential Ins. Co. v. Bliss, 122 Neb. 561, 240 N.W. 766 (1932).</para><para>One holding interest in proceeds of sale because of rights possessed in the mortgage is necessary party in foreclosure suit. Webb v. Patterson, 114 Neb. 346, 207 N.W. 522 (1926).</para><para>A judicial foreclosure is not designed to remove the original mortgage lien and create a new and independent one; purpose of foreclosure decree was not to destroy lien of mortgages but to judicially recognize them. In re Black Ranches, Inc., 362 F.2d 8 (8th Cir. 1966).</para><para>Confirmation of sale under mortgage foreclosure after death of mortgagor is voidable but not void, and is not open to collateral attack. O'Connor v. Townsend, 87 F.2d 882 (8th Cir. 1937).</para><para>Mortgagor retains legal title and substantial interest in mortgaged real estate until confirmation of sale and execution of deed, and may redeem at any time before order of confirmation becomes final. United States Nat. Bank of Omaha v. Pamp, 83 F.2d 493 (8th Cir. 1936).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>