<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,185.08"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,185.08</statuteno><catchline>Civil actions to which contributory negligence is a defense; terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of sections 25-21,185.07 to 25-21,185.12:</para><para>(1) Claimant shall mean any person who brings or maintains an action described in section 25-21,185.07. If an action is brought through or on behalf of an estate, claimant shall mean the claimant's decedent. If an action is brought through or on behalf of a minor, claimant shall mean the minor;</para><para>(2) Economic damages shall mean monetary losses, including, but not limited to, medical expenses, loss of earnings and earning capacity, funeral costs, loss of use of property, costs of repair or replacement, costs of obtaining substitute domestic services, loss of employment, and loss of business or employment opportunities; and</para><para>(3) Noneconomic damages shall mean subjective, nonmonetary losses, including, but not limited to, pain, suffering, inconvenience, mental suffering, emotional distress, loss of society and companionship, loss of consortium, injury to reputation, and humiliation, but shall not include economic damages.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1992, LB 262, &#167; 2. </para></source><annotation><para>A request for inconvenience damages is subsumed within a plaintiff's request for mental pain and suffering damages, when the facts show that the plaintiff is actually seeking hedonic damages for the plaintiff's loss of enjoyment of life resulting from physical injuries. Golnick v. Callender, 290 Neb. 395, 860 N.W.2d 180 (2015).</para><para>Apart from an exception for anxiety damages associated with parasitic damages, a request for anxiety damages is usually subsumed with a plaintiff's request for mental pain and suffering damages. Golnick v. Callender, 290 Neb. 395, 860 N.W.2d 180 (2015).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>