<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,194"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,194</statuteno><catchline>Shoplifting; civil action authorized; conditions; limitations.</catchline><para>(1)(a) Any person who commits the crime of theft by shoplifting as provided in section 28-511.01 or whose conduct is described by section 28-511.01 or (b) the parents of a minor who commits the crime of theft by shoplifting as provided in section 28-511.01 or whose conduct is described by section 28-511.01 shall be liable to the owner of the merchandise in a civil action for:</para><para>(i) Actual property damage or loss sustained as a direct result of the incident of shoplifting, which may include, but shall not be limited to, full retail value, cost of repair, or cost of replacement of the merchandise;</para><para>(ii) Costs of maintaining the action; and</para><para>(iii) Reasonable attorney's fees if such owner has retained the services of an attorney in maintaining the action and the action is not in the Small Claims Court.</para><para>(2) A conviction under any statute or ordinance shall not be a condition precedent to maintaining an action under this section.</para><para>(3) Recovery under this section may be had in addition to, and shall not be limited by, any other provision of law which limits the liability of the parents for tortious conduct of a minor. The liability of the parents and the minor shall be joint and several.</para><para>(4) This section shall not prohibit or limit any other cause of action which the owner of merchandise may have against a person who unlawfully or wrongfully takes merchandise from the owner's store or retail establishment.</para><para>(5) Judgments, but not claims, arising under this section may be assigned.</para><para>(6) The fact that an owner of merchandise may commence an action under this section shall not limit the right of such owner to demand, in writing, that any person who is liable for damages and costs under this section remit such damages and costs prior to the commencement of an action.</para><para>(7) This section shall only apply to causes of action which accrue after August 30, 1987.</para><para>(8) For purposes of this section, minor shall mean any individual under seventeen years of age.</para><para>(9) Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, no parent shall be liable to the owner of merchandise in a civil action unless such minor is living with such parent at the time the conduct described by section 28-511.01 is committed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 536, &#167; 1. </para></source></law></legaldoc>