<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id443"><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2747"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2747</statuteno><catchline>Evidence; stipulation; document; objections; Nebraska Evidence Rules; applicability; health care provider report; form.</catchline><para>(1) Parties to an action under the County Court Expedited Civil Actions Act should stipulate to factual and evidentiary matters to the greatest extent possible.</para><para>(2) For purposes of the act, the court may overrule objections based on authenticity and hearsay to the admission of a document, notwithstanding the absence of testimony or certification from a custodian or other qualified witness, if:</para><para>(a) The party offering the document gives notice to all other parties of the party's intention to offer the document into evidence at least ninety days in advance of trial. The notice must be given to all parties together with a copy of any document intended to be offered;</para><para>(b) The document on its face appears to be what the proponent claims it is;</para><para>(c) The document on its face appears not to be hearsay or appears to fall within a hearsay exception set forth in Nebraska law; and</para><para>(d) The objecting party has not raised a substantial question as to the authenticity or trustworthiness of the document.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise specifically provided by the act, the Nebraska Evidence Rules are applicable to actions under the act.</para><para>(4) Nothing in subsection (2) of this section authorizes admission of a document that contains hearsay within hearsay, unless the court determines from the face of the document that each part of the combined statements conforms with a hearsay exception set forth in Nebraska law.</para><para>(5) Any authenticity or hearsay objections to a document as to which notice has been provided under subdivision (2)(a) of this section must be made within thirty days after receipt of the notice.</para><para>(6)(a) The report of any treating health care provider concerning the plaintiff may be used in lieu of deposition or in-court testimony of the health care provider, so long as the report offered into evidence is on a form adopted for such purpose by the Supreme Court and is signed by the health care provider making the report.</para><para>(b) The Supreme Court shall adopt a form for the purposes of subdivision (6)(a) of this section.</para><para>(c) Unless otherwise stipulated or ordered by the court, a copy of any completed health care provider report under subdivision (6)(a) of this section must be served on all parties at least ninety days in advance of trial. Any objections to the health care provider statement, including an objection that the statement is incomplete or does not otherwise comply with this subsection, must be made within thirty days after receipt of the statement. For good cause shown, the court may issue such orders regarding the health care provider report as justice may require, including an order permitting a health care provider to supplement the report.</para><para>(d) Any party against whom a health care provider report may be used has the right, at the party's own initial expense, to cross-examine by deposition the health care provider signing the report, and the deposition may be used at trial.</para><para>(e) The deposition of the health care provider and the discovery of facts or opinions held by an expert are not counted for purposes of the numerical limits of section 25-2744.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2020, LB912, &#167; 7. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Evidence Rules,</emphasis> see section 27-1103.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>