<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id124" statutenumber="25-2721"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2721</statuteno><catchline id="id127">Judgment; execution; lien on real estate; conditions.</catchline><para>(1) Any person having a judgment rendered by a county court may request the clerk of such court to issue execution on the judgment in the same manner as execution is issued upon other judgments rendered in the county court and direct the execution on the judgment to any county in the state. Such person may request that garnishment, attachment, or any other aid to execution be directed to any county without the necessity of filing a transcript of the judgment in the receiving county, and any hearing or proceeding with regard to such execution or aid in execution shall be heard in the court in which the judgment was originally rendered.</para><para>(2) Any person having a judgment rendered by a county court may cause a transcript thereof to be filed in the office of the clerk of the district court in any county of this state. When the transcript is so filed and entered upon the judgment index, such judgment shall be a lien on real estate in the county where the transcript is filed, and when the transcript is so filed and entered upon such judgment index, the clerk of such court may issue execution thereupon in like manner as execution is issued upon judgments rendered in the district court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>G.S.1873, c. 14, &#167; 18, p. 267; </para><para>R.S.1913, &#167; 1221; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 1144; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 27-532; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 24-532; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 39; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1985), &#167; 24-539; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 422, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 45. </para></source><annotation><para>Under subsection (2) of this section, a judgment rendered by a county court does not automatically become a lien on real estate. A judgment rendered by a county court is only a personal judgment against the debtor. In order for a county court's judgment to become a lien on real estate, it must be transcribed to a district court. Mousel Law Firm, P.C. v. The Townhouse, Inc., 259 Neb. 113, 608 N.W.2d 571 (2000).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>