<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id43">
<sectno id="id44" opdate="July 15, 2010">Sec. 5.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id45" statutenumber="25-2803">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno id="id47">25-2803</statuteno><catchline id="id48">Parties; representation.</catchline><para>(1) Parties in the Small Claims Court may be individuals,
partnerships, limited liability companies, corporations, unions, associations,
or any other kind of organization or entity.</para>
<para>(2) No party shall be represented by an attorney in the Small
Claims Court except as provided in sections 25-2804 and 25-2805.</para>
<para>(3) An individual shall represent himself or herself in the
Small Claims Court. A partnership shall be represented by a partner or one
of its employees. A limited liability company shall be represented by a member,
a manager, or one of its employees. A union shall be represented by a union
member or union employee. A corporation shall be represented by one of its
employees. An association shall be represented by one of its members or by
an employee of the association. Any other kind of organization or entity shall
be represented by one of its members or employees.</para>
<para>(4) Only a party, natural or otherwise, who has been a party
to the transaction with the defendant for which the claim is brought may file
and prosecute a claim in the Small Claims Court.</para>
<para>(5) No party may file an assigned claim in the Small Claims
Court.</para>
<para>(6) No party shall file more than two claims within any calendar
week nor more than ten claims in any calendar year in the Small Claims Court.
This subsection shall not apply to actions brought pursuant to section 25-21,194.</para>
<para>(7) Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, a
personal representative of a decedent's estate, a guardian, or a conservator
may be a party in the Small Claims Court.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 77, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 536, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1988, &#167; 24-523; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 174; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB712, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>