<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id949"><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id13" statutenumber="25-2701"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2026</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2701</statuteno><catchline id="id16">Rules of procedure; county court power to seal records; applicability of rules of civil procedure to Uniform Probate Code.</catchline><para>(1) All provisions in the rules and codes of criminal and civil procedure governing actions and proceedings in the district court not in conflict with statutes specifically governing procedure in county courts and related to matters for which no specific provisions have been made for county courts shall govern and apply to all actions and proceedings in the county court.</para><para>(2) County courts may seal records of a person as provided under sections 43-2,108.01 to 43-2,108.05.</para><para>(3) Unless specifically provided to the contrary in the Uniform Probate Code or unless inconsistent with its provisions, the rules and codes of civil procedure, including the rules concerning vacation of orders and appellate review, govern proceedings under this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1032, &#167; 28; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1985), &#167; 24-528; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB800, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2026, LB838, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>July 18, 2026</operativedate></source><annotation><para>As subsection (1) of this section makes clear, all provisions of the criminal and civil procedure code govern all actions in the county court. State v. Lebeau, 280 Neb. 238, 784 N.W.2d 921 (2010).</para><para>This section applies to the prosecution of city ordinances. State v. Lebeau, 280 Neb. 238, 784 N.W.2d 921 (2010).</para><para>On appeal from a county or municipal court, notice of appeal and bond must be filed within ten days after rendition of judgment and this period cannot be prolonged by filing a motion for new trial. Edward Frank Rozman Co. v. Keillor, 195 Neb. 587, 239 N.W.2d 779 (1976).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>