<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,113</statuteno><catchline>Parties as defendants; how designated; effect of decree.</catchline><para>In all actions to establish or quiet title to an estate in real estate, all persons in whose favor any interest, right, title, estate in, or lien upon such real estate appears of record shall be made defendants by the names by which they are designated on the record. When it is alleged in the complaint that there are persons who claim or appear to have some interest in, right or title to, or lien upon such property, and that the ownership of, interest in, right or title to, or lien upon such property of such persons does not appear of record in or by their respective names in the county wherein such property is situated, and that the plaintiff, after diligent investigation and inquiry, is unable to ascertain and does not know the names or whereabouts, if in this state, or the residence of such persons, there shall also be designated as defendants in such action "all persons having or claiming any interest in" (here inserting an accurate and definite description of the property involved) followed by the words "real names unknown". Judgments and decrees rendered in such actions after the defendants so impleaded and designated have been served as provided by statute, shall be conclusive against all defendants impleaded and designated by name, and also against all persons who are not in actual possession of such property, whose ownership of, interest in, rights or title to, or lien upon such property does not appear of record in or by their respective names in the county wherein such property is situated.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 130, &#167; 2, p. 541; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5677; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 76-402; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-21,113; </para><para>Laws 2002, LB 876, &#167; 45. </para></source><annotation><para>Parties in actual possession of land were not precluded from right to redeem from tax sale where service was had by publication. Thomas v. Flynn, 169 Neb. 458, 100 N.W.2d 37 (1959).</para><para>A decree in an action to quiet title against all persons having or claiming any interest in designated lands is conclusive against all persons not in possession and not record holders. State ex rel. Conkey v. Ryan, 136 Neb. 334, 285 N.W. 923 (1939).</para><para>Where law providing quieting title by making land defendant was complied with, it was not necessary to comply with previous law covering service on unknown heirs. Miller v. Ruzicka, 109 Neb. 152, 190 N.W. 216 (1922).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>