<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-21,120"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-21,120</statuteno><catchline>Trial; appeal.</catchline><para>The court shall try such cause in like manner as other equitable actions and shall enter therein such orders and decrees as the parties may be entitled to. Appeals from final orders may be had as in other actions.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 130, &#167; 9, p. 542; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 5684; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 76-409; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-21,120.</para></source><annotation><para>A quiet title action sounds in equity. Boundary disputes cannot be determined in a quiet title action. Rather, boundary disputes are properly brought as an action in ejectment or pursuant to section 34-301. Rush Creek Land &amp; Live Stock Co. v. Chain, 255 Neb. 347, 586 N.W.2d 284 (1998).</para><para>Since amendment of 1921, action to quiet title may be maintained by any person whether in actual possession or not, and cause is tried as an equitable action. Morse v. Cochran, 131 Neb. 424, 268 N.W. 307 (1936).</para><para>Defendant defeats action by proving no title or interest in plaintiff. Van Patten v. O'Brien, 88 Neb. 382, 129 N.W. 540 (1911).</para><para>As between rival homestead claimants, no finding of ownership can be made before patent is issued. Rupke v. Moran, 87 Neb. 316, 127 N.W. 127 (1910).</para><para>Maintenance of action by remainderman during life estate is permitted. Hobson v. Huxtable, 79 Neb. 334, 112 N.W. 658 (1907), judgment vacated on rehearing 79 Neb. 340, 116 N.W. 278 (1908).</para><para>Purpose of action is to obtain complete determination of question of title between parties. Dolen v. Black, 48 Neb. 688, 67 N.W. 760 (1896).</para><para>Plaintiff must show his interest is superior to defendant's if put in issue. McCauley v. Ohenstein, 44 Neb. 89, 62 N.W. 232 (1895).</para><para>Plaintiff should allege the nature, extent, and invalidity of defendant's title. McDonald v. Early, 15 Neb. 63, 17 N.W. 257 (1883).</para><para>In an action to quiet title, the plaintiff has the burden of proof and must recover upon the strength of his title. Vogel v. Bartels, 1 Neb. App. 1113, 510 N.W.2d 529 (1993).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>