<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2307"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2307</statuteno><catchline>Appellate briefs; costs; payment by county.</catchline><para>In any civil or criminal case in which a party is permitted to proceed in forma pauperis, on appeal the court shall direct that the expense of printing of the appellate briefs, if such printing is required by the court, be paid by the county in the same manner as other claims are paid.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1972, LB 1120, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1999, LB 689, &#167; 10.</para></source><annotation><para>The expense of photocopying is included in the expense of "printing", which is required under this section to be paid by the county when a party has been permitted to proceed in forma pauperis. Heathman v. Kenney, 263 Neb. 966, 644 N.W.2d 558 (2002).</para>
<para>A district court has jurisdiction to hear a motion for reimbursement of costs sought under this section, and an order entered thereon is appealable as a summary application in an action after judgment. State v. Patterson, 18 Neb. App. 255, 778 N.W.2d 756 (2010).</para>
<para>Neither this section nor Heathman v. Kenney, 263 Neb. 966, 644 N.W.2d 558 (2002), support a conclusion that a request for reimbursement of printing costs must be made during the pendency of the appeal. State v. Patterson, 18 Neb. App. 255, 778 N.W.2d 756 (2010).</para>
<para>The words "on appeal" in this section follow the requirement that a party be permitted to proceed in forma pauperis and precede the requirement that the county pay for printing of the appellate briefs; therefore, the logical interpretation is that the expense of printing of appellate briefs is to be reimbursed to a party who is allowed to proceed in forma pauperis on appeal. State v. Patterson, 18 Neb. App. 255, 778 N.W.2d 756 (2010).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>