<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2620"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2620</statuteno><catchline>Appeals.</catchline><para>(a) An appeal may be taken from:</para><para>(1) An order denying an application to compel arbitration made under section 25-2603;</para><para>(2) An order granting an application to stay arbitration made under subsection (b) of section 25-2603;</para><para>(3) An order confirming or denying confirmation of an award;</para><para>(4) An order modifying or correcting an award;</para><para>(5) An order vacating an award without directing a rehearing; or</para><para>(6) A judgment or decree entered pursuant to the provisions of the Uniform Arbitration Act.</para><para>(b) The appeal shall be taken in the manner and to the same extent as from orders or judgments in a civil action.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 71, &#167; 20.</para></source><annotation><para>An order compelling arbitration or staying judicial proceedings pending arbitration is a final order under the second category of section 25-1902. It affects a substantial right in an independent special proceeding because it disposes of all the issues presented. Kremer v. Rural Community Ins. Co., 280 Neb. 591, 788 N.W.2d 538 (2010).</para><para>The list of appealable arbitration orders under this section is not exclusive. Kremer v. Rural Community Ins. Co., 280 Neb. 591, 788 N.W.2d 538 (2010).</para>
<para>In reviewing a trial court's decision to vacate, modify, or confirm an arbitration award under Nebraska's Uniform Arbitration Act, an appellate court is obligated to reach a conclusion independent of the trial court's ruling regarding questions of law; however, the trial court's factual findings will not be set aside on appeal unless clearly erroneous. Aramark Uniform &amp; Career Apparel v. Hunan, Inc., 276 Neb. 700, 757 N.W.2d 205 (2008).</para><para>Under subsection (a)(5) of this section, an order which vacates an arbitrator's award without directing a rehearing is appealable, whereas an order which vacates an award and directs a rehearing is not appealable. Nebraska Dept. of Health &amp; Human Servs. v. Struss, 261 Neb. 435, 623 N.W.2d 308 (2001).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>