<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id19">
<sectno id="id20">Sec. 3.</sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id21" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="25-21,292"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo>
<statuteno>25-21,292</statuteno><catchline>Civil action authorized; recovery;
attorney's fees and costs; injunctive relief.</catchline><para>(1) Any participant or portrayed
observer in a visual depiction of sexually explicit conduct or his or her
parent or legal guardian who suffered or continues to suffer personal or psychological
injury as a result of such participation or portrayed observation may bring
a civil action against any person who knowingly and willfully (a) created,
distributed, or actively acquired such visual depiction while in this state
or (b) aided or assisted with the creation, distribution, or active acquisition
of such visual depiction while such person or the person aided or assisted
was in this state.</para>
<para>(2)
A plaintiff who prevails in a civil action brought pursuant to the Exploited
Children's Civil Remedy Act may recover his or her actual damages, which are
deemed to be a minimum of one hundred fifty thousand dollars, plus any and
all attorney's fees and costs reasonably associated with the civil action.
In addition to all other remedies available under the act, the court may also
award temporary, preliminary, and permanent injunctive relief as the court
deems necessary and appropriate.</para><para>(3) This section does not create a cause
of action if the participant was sixteen years of age or older at the time
the visual depiction was created and the participant willfully and voluntarily
participated in the creation of the visual depiction.</para><para>(4) No law enforcement officer
engaged in his or her law enforcement duties, governmental entity, provider
of interactive computer service, provider of telecommunications service, or
cable operator is subject to a civil action under the Exploited Children's
Civil Remedy Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2010, LB728, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>