<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id00" statutenumber="25-2706"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2020</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2706</statuteno><catchline id="id00">County court; certify proceedings to district court; when; avoidance of county court jurisdiction; recovery of costs prohibited.</catchline><para id="id00">The county court shall certify proceedings to the district court of the county in which an action is pending (1) when the pleadings or discovery proceedings indicate that the amount in controversy is greater than the jurisdictional amount in subdivision (5) of section 24-517 and a party to the action requests the transfer or (2) when the relief requested is exclusively within the jurisdiction of the district court. The county court shall file a certification of the case file and costs with the district court within ten days after entry of the transfer order. The action shall then be tried and determined by the district court as if the proceedings were originally brought in such district court, except that no new pleadings need be filed unless ordered by the district court.</para><para id="id00">If it is determined, upon adjudication, that the allegations of either party to such action are asserted with the intention solely of avoiding the jurisdiction of the county court, the offending party shall not recover any costs in the county court or the district court.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1983, LB 137, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 750, &#167; 2; </para><para>R.S.Supp.,1988, &#167; 24-302.01; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 422, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 69, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 269, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2018, LB193, &#167; 43. </para></source><annotation><para>This section does not require a district court to issue a new summons for service of process when an action has been certified to it from the county court under this section. Hunt v. Trackwell, 262 Neb. 688, 635 N.W.2d 106 (2001).</para><para>Plaintiff may not transfer jurisdiction of a case from county court to district court by simply filing the county court transcript in the district court. Collection Bureau of Grand Island, Inc. v. Fry, 9 Neb. App. 277, 610 N.W.2d 442 (2000).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>