<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2228" amended="yes"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2228</statuteno><catchline>Legal notices; how published.</catchline><para>(1) All legal publications and notices of whatever kind or character that may by law be required to be published a certain number of days or a certain number of weeks shall be legally published when they have been published in one issue in each week in a daily, semiweekly, or triweekly newspaper, such publication in such daily, semiweekly, or triweekly paper or papers to be made upon any one day of the week upon which such paper is published. Nothing in this section shall be construed as preventing the publication of such legal notices and publications in weekly newspapers. Any newspaper publishing such legal notices or publications as provided in this section shall be otherwise qualified under existing law to publish such notices or publications. All legal publications and all notices of whatever kind or character that may be required by law to be published a certain number of days or a certain number of weeks, shall be and hereby are declared to be legally published when they shall have been published once a week in a weekly, semiweekly, triweekly, or daily newspaper for the number of weeks, covering the period of publication. For the purpose of this section, when a newspaper is published regularly four or more times each week, it shall be deemed a daily newspaper.</para><para>(2) Beginning October 1, 2022, all legal publications and notices of whatever kind or character that may by law be required to be published a certain number of days or a certain number of weeks shall also be posted by the newspaper publishing such legal publications or notices on a statewide website established and maintained as a repository for such notices by a majority of Nebraska newspapers. A website posting or a failure to make such website posting under this subsection shall not affect the validity of the publication or notice published under subsection (1) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1917, c. 202, &#167; 1, p. 481; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 9528; </para><para>Laws 1923, c. 100, &#167; 1, p. 255; </para><para>Laws 1927, c. 63, &#167; 1, p. 225; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 20-2229; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 25-2228; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 47, &#167; 1, p. 198; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 299, &#167; 21; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB840, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>If a publication day falls upon a holiday, publication the preceding day complies with this section. Hollstein v. Adams, 187 Neb. 781, 194 N.W.2d 216 (1972).</para><para>This section supersedes and effectively abrogates contrary provision of statute and home rule charter. Skag-Way Department Stores, Inc. v. City of Grand Island, 176 Neb. 169, 125 N.W.2d 529 (1964).</para><para>Last part of section refers only to number of times notice is required to be published and not to duration of notice. Johnson v. Richards, 155 Neb. 552, 52 N.W.2d 737 (1952).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>