<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-2603"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>25-2603</statuteno><catchline>Proceedings to compel or stay arbitration.</catchline><para>(a) On application of a party showing an agreement described in section 25-2602.01 and the opposing party's refusal to arbitrate, the court shall order the parties to proceed with arbitration, but if the opposing party denies the existence of the agreement to arbitrate, the court shall proceed summarily to the determination of the issue so raised and shall order for the moving party, otherwise, the application shall be denied.</para><para>(b) On application, the court may stay an arbitration proceeding commenced or threatened on a showing that there is no agreement to arbitrate. Such an issue, when in substantial and bona fide dispute, shall be forthwith and summarily tried and the stay ordered if found for the moving party. If found for the opposing party, the court shall order the parties to proceed to arbitration.</para><para>(c) If an issue referable to arbitration under the alleged agreement is involved in an action or proceeding pending in a court having jurisdiction to hear applications under subsection (a) of this section, the application shall be made therein. Otherwise and subject to section 25-2619, such application may be made in any court of competent jurisdiction.</para><para>(d) Any action or proceeding involving an issue subject to arbitration shall be stayed if an order for arbitration or an application therefor has been made under this section or, if the issue is severable, the stay may be with respect thereto only. When the application is made in such action or proceeding, the order for arbitration shall include such stay.</para><para>(e) An order for arbitration shall not be refused on the ground that the claim in issue lacks merit or bona fides or because any fault or grounds for the claim sought to be arbitrated have not been shown.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1987, LB 71, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 151, &#167; 3. </para></source><annotation><para>Although this section specifies that the question of whether an agreement to arbitrate exists should be "summarily" tried, this section does not preclude the right to a jury trial in every circumstance. Omaha Cold Storage Terminals v. Patterson, 15 Neb. App. 548, 733 N.W.2d 219 (2007).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>