<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="25-3401"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>25-3401</statuteno><catchline>Prisoner; civil actions; in forma
pauperis litigation; limitation; finding by court that action was frivolous.</catchline>
<para>(1) For purposes of this
section:</para>
<para>(a) Civil action means
a legal action seeking monetary damages, injunctive relief, declaratory relief,
or any appeal filed in any court in this state that relates to or involves
a prisoner's conditions of confinement. Civil action does not include a motion
for postconviction relief or petition for habeas corpus relief;</para>
<para>(b) Conditions of confinement
means any circumstance, situation, or event that involves a prisoner's custody,
transportation, incarceration, or supervision;</para><para>(c) Correctional institution means
any state or local facility that incarcerates or detains any adult accused
of, charged with, convicted of, or sentenced for any crime;</para>
<para>(d) Frivolous means the
law and evidence supporting a litigant's position is wholly without merit
or rational argument; and</para><para>(e)
Prisoner means any person who is incarcerated, imprisoned, or otherwise detained
in a correctional institution.</para><para>(2)(a) A prisoner who has filed three or more civil
actions, commenced after July 19, 2012, that have been found to be frivolous
by a court of this state or a federal court for a case originating in this
state shall not be permitted to proceed in forma pauperis for any further
civil actions without leave of court. A court shall permit the prisoner to
proceed in forma pauperis if the court determines that the person is in danger
of serious bodily injury.</para><para>(b)
A court may include in its final order or judgment in any civil action a finding
that the action was frivolous.</para><para>(c) A finding under subdivision (2)(b) of this section
shall be reflected in the docket entries of the case.</para><para>(d) This subsection does not apply
to judicial review of disciplinary procedures in adult institutions administered
by the Department of Correctional Services governed by sections 83-4,109 to
83-4,123.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB793, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>