<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id137">
<sectno id="id138" opdate="August 30, 2009">Sec. 17.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" id="id139" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="25-3008"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno id="id141">25-3008</statuteno><catchline id="id142">Grant recipients;
requirements; application; audit.</catchline><para>(1) The Commission on Public Advocacy shall
establish guidelines for submission of applications for grants to provide
civil legal services to eligible low-income persons. To be eligible for a
grant under this section, a civil legal services provider shall:</para>
<para>(a) Be a nonprofit organization chartered in Nebraska;</para>
<para>(b) Employ or contract with attorneys admitted to practice
before the Nebraska Supreme Court and the United States District Courts;</para>
<para>(c) Have offices located throughout the state;</para>
<para>(d) Have as its principal purpose and mission the delivery
of civil legal services to eligible low-income persons who are residents of
Nebraska;</para>
<para>(e) Distribute its resources equitably throughout the state;</para>
<para>(f) Be a recipient of financial assistance for the delivery
of civil legal services from the Legal Services Corporation established by
the federal Legal Services Corporation Act, 42 U.S.C. 2996 et seq.; and</para>
<para>(g) Certify that any grant funds received pursuant to this
section will be used to supplement any existing funds used by the applicant
and that such funds will not replace other funds appropriated or awarded by
a state agency to provide civil legal services to any eligible low-income
person.</para>
<para>(2) A civil legal services provider seeking a grant under
this section shall file an application with the commission on forms provided by the commission. The application
shall include a place for the provider to certify to the commission that
it will provide free civil legal services to eligible low-income persons upon
receipt of a grant under this section.</para>
<para>(3) The commission shall
review the applications and determine which civil legal services providers
shall receive grants under this section and the amount of the grants. Grant
recipients shall use the grant funds to provide free civil legal services
to eligible low-income persons.</para>
<para>(4) An independent certified public accountant shall annually
audit the books and accounts of each grant recipient. The grant recipients
shall provide the results of such audit to the commission.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2006, LB 746, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB35, &#167; 17.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>