<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section id="id912"><amendatorysection chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure" statutenumber="25-3602"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>25-3602</statuteno><catchline>Terms, defined.</catchline><para>For purposes of the COVID-19 Liability Act:</para><para>(1) COVID-19 means the novel coronavirus identified as SARS-CoV-2, the disease caused by the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 or a virus mutating therefrom, and the health conditions or threats associated with the disease caused by the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 or a virus mutating therefrom;</para><para>(2) Federal public health guidance means and includes written or oral guidance related to COVID-19 issued by any of the following:</para><para>(a) The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention of the United States Department of Health and Human Services;</para><para>(b) The Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services of the United States Department of Health and Human Services; or</para><para>(c) The federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration; and</para><para>(3)(a) Person means:</para><para>(i) Any natural person;</para><para>(ii) Any sole proprietorship, partnership, limited liability partnership, corporation, limited liability company, business trust, estate, trust, unincorporated association, or joint venture;</para><para>(iii) The State of Nebraska and any political subdivision of the state;</para><para>(iv) Any school, college, university, institution of higher education, religious organization, or charitable organization; or</para><para>(v) Any other legal or commercial entity.</para><para>(b) Person includes an employee, director, governing board, officer, agent, independent contractor, or volunteer of a person listed in subdivision (3)(a) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2021, LB139, &#167; 2. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Health Care Crisis Protocol Act,</emphasis> see section 71-2701.</para> </crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>