<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id908"><amendatorysection statutenumber="25-3502" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2019</bookinfo><statuteno>25-3502</statuteno><catchline>Definitions.</catchline><para>In the Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act:</para><para>(1) Consent means affirmative, conscious, and voluntary authorization by an individual with legal capacity to give authorization.</para><para>(2) Depicted individual means an individual whose body is shown in whole or in part in an intimate image.</para><para>(3) Disclosure means transfer, publication, or distribution to another person. Disclose has a corresponding meaning.</para><para>(4) Identifiable means recognizable by a person other than the depicted individual:</para><para>(A) from an intimate image itself; or</para><para>(B) from an intimate image and identifying characteristic displayed in connection with the intimate image.</para><para>(5) Identifying characteristic means information that may be used to identify a depicted individual.</para><para>(6) Individual means a human being.</para><para>(7) Intimate image means a photograph, film, video recording, or other similar medium that shows:</para><para>(A) the uncovered genitals, pubic area, anus, or female post-pubescent nipple of a depicted individual; or</para><para>(B) a depicted individual engaging in or being subjected to sexual conduct.</para><para>(8) Person means an individual, estate, business or nonprofit entity, public corporation, government or governmental subdivision, agency, or instrumentality, or other legal entity.</para><para>(9) Sexual conduct includes:</para><para>(A) masturbation;</para><para>(B) genital, anal, or oral sex;</para><para>(C) sexual penetration of, or with, an object;</para><para>(D) bestiality; or</para><para>(E) the transfer of semen onto a depicted individual.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB680, &#167; 2. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>