<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id860"><amendatorysection statutenumber="25-3504" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>25-3504</statuteno><catchline>Exceptions to liability.</catchline><para>(a) In this section:</para><para>(1) Child means an unemancipated individual who is less than nineteen years of age.</para><para>(2) Parent means an individual recognized as a parent under law of this state other than the Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act.</para><para>(b) A person is not liable under the act if the person proves that disclosure of, or a threat to disclose, an intimate image was:</para><para>(1) made in good faith in:</para><para>(A) law enforcement;</para><para>(B) a legal proceeding; or</para><para>(C) medical education or treatment;</para><para>(2) made in good faith in the reporting or investigation of:</para><para>(A) unlawful conduct; or</para><para>(B) unsolicited and unwelcome conduct;</para><para>(3) related to a matter of public concern or public interest; or</para><para>(4) reasonably intended to assist the depicted individual.</para><para>(c) Subject to subsection (d) of this section, a defendant who is a parent, legal guardian, or individual with legal custody of a child is not liable under the act for a disclosure or threatened disclosure of an intimate image, as defined in subdivision (7)(A) of section 25-3502, of the child.</para><para>(d) If a defendant asserts an exception to liability under subsection (c) of this section, the exception does not apply if the plaintiff proves the disclosure was:</para><para>(1) prohibited by law other than the act; or</para><para>(2) made for the purpose of sexual arousal, sexual gratification, humiliation, degradation, or monetary or commercial gain.</para><para>(e) Disclosure of, or a threat to disclose, an intimate image is not a matter of public concern or public interest solely because the depicted individual is a public figure.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB680, &#167; 4. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>