<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id993"><amendatorysection statutenumber="25-3507" chaptername="Courts; Civil Procedure"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>25-3507</statuteno><catchline>Construction.</catchline><para>(a) In an action brought under the Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act, no provider or user of an interactive computer service shall be treated as a person disclosing any information provided by another information content provider unless the provider or user of such interactive computer service is responsible, in whole or in part, for the creation or development of the information provided through the Internet or any other interactive service.</para><para>(b) No provider or user of an interactive computer service shall be held liable under the act on account of:</para><para>(1) any action voluntarily taken in good faith to restrict access to or availability of material that the provider or user considers to be obscene, lewd, lascivious, filthy, excessively violent, harassing, or otherwise objectionable, whether or not such material is constitutionally protected; or</para><para>(2) any action taken to enable or make available to any information content provider or others the technical means to restrict access to material described in subdivision (b)(1) of this section.</para><para>(c) Nothing in the Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act shall be construed to impose liability on an interactive computer service for content provided by another person.</para><para>(d) The Uniform Civil Remedies for Unauthorized Disclosure of Intimate Images Act must be construed to be consistent with 47 U.S.C. 230, as such section existed on January 1, 2019.</para><para>(e) The act may not be construed to alter the law of this state on sovereign immunity.</para><para>(f) For purposes of this section, information content provider and interactive computer service have the same meanings as in 47 U.S.C. 230, as such section existed on January 1, 2019.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2019, LB680, &#167; 7. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>