<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-361"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-361</statuteno><catchline>Sewerage and drainage; connections; city may require; notice to property owners; construction by city; assessment of cost.</catchline><para>Whenever sewer connections for sewerage or drainage may be deemed necessary or advisable, whether within the corporate limits or within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of a city of the metropolitan class, the property owners shall be given thirty days from the publication of the ordinance ordering such improvements and connections to make such improvements and connections in conformity with approved plans to be kept on file by the city. The publication of such ordinance ordering such connections in the official newspaper shall be the only notice required to be given such property owners. Upon the failure or neglect of the property owners to construct such connections within the time fixed, the city shall cause such work to be done and shall contract for such construction with the lowest responsible bidder. The cost of construction, including superintendence and inspection, shall be assessed against the property to which such connections have been made as a special assessment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. III, &#167; 52, p. 455; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3605; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-353; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-361; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 30, &#167; 2, p. 184; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 62. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Person filing protest against special assessments before time fixed in notice for meeting of board thereby waives all defects in notice. Shannon v. City of Omaha, 73 Neb. 507, 103 N.W. 53 (1905), affirmed on rehearing 73 Neb. 514, 106 N.W. 592 (1906).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>