<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-105" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>14-105</statuteno><catchline id="id00">City council; powers; drainage of lots; duty of owner; special assessment.</catchline><para>The city council may require any and all lots or pieces of ground within the city to be drained, filled, or graded, and upon the failure of the owners of such lots or pieces of ground to comply with such requirements, after thirty days' notice in writing, the council may cause the lots or pieces of ground to be drained, filled, or graded, and the cost and expense thereof shall be levied upon the property so filled, drained, or graded and shall be equalized, assessed, and collected as a special assessment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. I, &#167; 5, p. 407; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3492; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-105; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-105; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB361, &#167; 1. </para></source><annotation><para>Owner of lot must have been requested to fill lot and failed to comply before cost of drainage can be assessed against lot. If nuisance is caused by negligence of city in grading, cost of filling or drainage cannot be assessed against the lot. Lasbury v. McCague, 56 Neb. 220, 76 N.W. 862 (1898).</para><para>This section in charter of 1887, authorizing cost of filling and draining to be assessed where nuisance existed, was held constitutional, and a valid exercise of police power. Horbach v. City of Omaha, 54 Neb. 83, 74 N.W. 434 (1898).</para><para>It is within police power of state to authorize a municipal corporation to fill lots within its limits so as to prevent stagnant water thereon and to assess cost against lots so filled. Patrick v. City of Omaha, 1 Neb. Unof. 250, 95 N.W. 477 (1901).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>