
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" id="id5" statutenumber="14-407"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-407</statuteno><catchline id="id8">Zoning; exercise of powers; planning board or official; notice to military installation; notice to neighborhood association.</catchline><para>(1) A city of the metropolitan class shall exercise the powers conferred by sections 14-401 to 14-418 through such appropriate planning board or official as exists in such city.</para><para>(2) When the city is considering the adoption or amendment of a zoning ordinance or the approval of the platting or replatting of any development of real estate, the city shall notify any military installation which is located within the corporate boundary limits or the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of the city if the city has received a written request for such notification from the military installation. The planning board shall deliver the notification to the military installation at least ten days prior to the meeting of the planning board at which the proposal is to be considered.</para><para>(3) When the city is considering the adoption or amendment of a zoning ordinance, except for an amendment that serves only to correct a misspelling or other typographical error, the city shall notify any registered neighborhood association whose area of representation is located in whole or in part within the area that will be included in such zoning ordinance. Each neighborhood association desiring to receive such notice shall register with the city the area of representation of such association and provide the name of and contact information for the individual designated to receive notice on behalf of such association and the requested manner of service, whether by email or first-class or certified mail. The registration shall be in accordance with any rules and regulations adopted and promulgated by the city. The planning board shall deliver the notification to the neighborhood association (a) in the manner requested by the neighborhood association and (b) at least ten days prior to the meeting of the planning board at which the proposal is to be considered.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 45, &#167; 7, p. 181; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-410; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-407; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 37, &#167; 2, p. 212; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB279, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2016, LB700, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2019, LB196, &#167; 1. </para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Planning board,</emphasis> extraterritorial member, see sections 14-373.01 and 14-373.02.</para></crossreference></law>
</legaldoc>