<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-545"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-545</statuteno><catchline>Special assessments; determination of amounts.</catchline><para>All special assessments to cover the cost of any public improvements herein authorized shall be levied and assessed on all lots, parts of lots, lands, and real estate specially benefited by such improvement, or within the district created for the purpose of making such improvement, to the extent of the benefits to such lots, parts of lots, lands, and real estate by reason of such improvements, such benefits to be determined by the council sitting as a board of equalization. Where they shall find such benefits to be equal and uniform, such assessment may be according to the foot frontage, and may be prorated and scaled back from the line of such improvements according to such rules as the board of equalization shall consider fair and equitable.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. IV, &#167; 33, p. 486; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3659; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-536; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-545.</para></source><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Benefits</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Powers</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Benefits</emphasis></para><para>Section was not unconstitutional as authorizing levy of the full cost of improvement according to front foot rule without regard to special benefits. Murphy v. Metropolitan Utilities Dist., 126 Neb. 663, 255 N.W. 20 (1934).</para><para>Determination by city council of special benefits may not be attacked in a collateral proceeding, except for fraud, a fundamental defect, or an entire want of jurisdiction. Wead v. City of Omaha, 124 Neb. 474, 247 N.W. 24 (1933).</para><para>All taxes for special improvements must be levied on property specially benefited by the improvement, but no taxes can be levied on property outside of the improvement district. McCaffrey v. City of Omaha, 91 Neb. 184, 135 N.W. 552 (1912).</para><para>Front footage cannot be adopted unless finding is made that benefits are equal and uniform. Morse v. City of Omaha, 67 Neb. 426, 93 N.W. 734 (1903).</para><para>Record of board must show affirmatively that council found that benefits were equal and uniform. John v. Connell, 64 Neb. 233, 89 N.W. 806 (1902).</para><para>Special benefits which may be set off against damages are such as increase the value of adjacent property, while common benefits are such as are enjoyed by the public at large without reference to the ownership of property adjacent to the public improvement. Barr v. City of Omaha, 42 Neb. 341, 60 N.W. 591 (1894); Kirkendall v. City of Omaha, 39 Neb. 1, 57 N.W. 752 (1894); City of Omaha v. Schaller, 26 Neb. 522, 42 N.W. 721 (1889).</para><para><emphasis>2. Powers</emphasis></para><para>Special assessments could be levied against railroad right-of-way. Chicago &amp; N.W. Ry. Co. v. City of Omaha, 154 Neb. 442, 48 N.W.2d 409 (1951).</para><para>Council will not be restrained from passing ordinance levying special taxes, equalized by it, in absence of proof of fraud or mistake in equalization. Richardson v. City of Omaha, 78 Neb. 79, 110 N.W. 648 (1907).</para><para>Board of equalization, when regularly in session, with due notices published of matters to come before it, acts judicially upon matters within its jurisdiction, and such action is not open to collateral attack. Portsmouth Savings Bank v. City of Omaha, 67 Neb. 50, 93 N.W. 231 (1903).</para><para>Compensation of appraiser's fees for assessment of damages may be included in special assessment. Kuhns v. City of Omaha, 55 Neb. 183, 75 N.W. 562 (1898).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>