
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-408"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-408</statuteno><catchline>Building zones; zoning board of appeals; members; term; vacancy; removal; meetings; oaths; subpoenas; record; public access.</catchline><para>(1) The city council of a city of the metropolitan class may provide for the appointment of a zoning board of appeals consisting of five regular members. Two additional alternate members shall be appointed and designated as first alternate and second alternate members, either or both of whom may attend any meeting and may serve as voting and participating members of the zoning board of appeals with the authority of a regular board member at any time when less than the full number of regular board members is present and capable of voting. If both alternate members are present when only a single regular member is absent, the first alternate member shall serve for the balance of the meeting.</para><para>(2) Upon the expiration of the initial terms of such regular and alternate members, all members and alternates shall be appointed for a term of five years. The city council shall have the power to remove any regular or alternate member of the zoning board of appeals for cause and after public hearing. Vacancies shall be filled for the unexpired term of a regular or alternate member whose place has become vacant.</para><para>(3) All meetings of the zoning board of appeals shall be held at the call of the chairperson and at such other times as such board may determine. Such chairperson, or in his or her absence the acting chairperson, may administer oaths and compel the attendance of witnesses. All meetings of the zoning board of appeals shall be open to the public. The zoning board of appeals shall keep minutes of its proceedings, showing the vote of each member upon every question, or if absent or failing to vote, indicating such fact, and shall also keep records of its examinations and other official actions.</para><para>(4) Every rule or regulation, every amendment or repeal of such rule or regulation, and every order, requirement, decision, or determination of the zoning board of appeals shall immediately be filed in the office of such board and shall be a public record.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 45, &#167; 8, p. 181; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-411; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-408; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 703, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 179, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 138. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Board of appeals is vested with discretion in determination of matters within its province subject to court review for abuse of discretion. Peterson v. Vasak, 162 Neb. 498, 76 N.W.2d 420 (1956).</para><para>This section provides for the appointment of members of a zoning board of appeals, their tenure of office, meetings, hearings, and records. Roncka v. Fogarty, 152 Neb. 467, 41 N.W.2d 745 (1950).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>