<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-365.03"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-365.03</statuteno><catchline>Sewerage systems and sewage disposal plants; rules and regulations; rates or charges; collection; special assessments.</catchline><para>(1) The city council of a city of the metropolitan class may make all necessary rules and regulations governing the use, operation, and control of a sewerage system established under section 14-365.01. The city council may establish just and equitable rates or charges to be paid to the city for the use of such sewage disposal plant and sewerage system by the owner of the property served or by the person, firm, or corporation using the services.</para><para>(2) If any service rate or charge so established is not paid when due, such sum may be:</para><para>(a) Recovered by the city in a civil action;</para><para>(b) Certified to the city treasurer, assessed against the premises served, and collected or returned in the same manner as other municipal taxes are certified, assessed, collected, and returned; or</para><para>(c) Assessed against the premises served in the same manner as special taxes or assessments are assessed by such city and be certified, enforced, collected, and returned as other special taxes or assessments of such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 24, &#167; 3, p. 100; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 32, &#167; 4, p. 187; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 30, &#167; 2, p. 147; </para><para>Laws 1965, c. 38, &#167; 1, p. 230; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 69. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Sewer use charge is not a special assessment; a city has authority to make necessary rules and regulations including a reasonable processing charge on delinquent accounts. Rutherford v. City of Omaha, 183 Neb. 398, 160 N.W.2d 223 (1968).</para><para>Metropolitan utilities district may establish just and equitable rates for use of sewer system. Metropolitan Utilities Dist. v. City of Omaha, 171 Neb. 609, 107 N.W.2d 397 (1961).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>