<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-3,113"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-3,113</statuteno><catchline>Intersections, certain lands; improvement by city; priority on use of funds; street improvement districts.</catchline><para>The city is authorized to improve intersections, spaces opposite alleys, and spaces opposite property not subject to special assessment, with the like material in the manner provided in sections 14-384 to 14-3,127 for improving streets whenever a street, highway, boulevard, main thoroughfare, controlled-access facility, major traffic street, or alley is ordered to be improved at the time of improving such street and in such event is authorized to include in such improvement of such intersection and spaces the construction, replacement, or repair of sidewalks therein and, except as may be otherwise provided, pay for all such improvements from funds provided for the purpose of improving intersections; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that the first priority in the expenditure of funds for such purposes shall be given to improvements within street improvement districts; <emphasis type="italic">and provided further,</emphasis> the city shall maintain, in a separate fund, not less than twenty-five thousand dollars to be expended solely for the purpose of improving intersections. Such sidewalk construction, replacement, or repair may be included either in the contract for curbings at an intersection or in the contract for paving the same; <emphasis type="italic">Provided,</emphasis> that such restrictions shall not apply to any funds derived from Chapter 66, articles 4 and 6, which accumulated prior to December 31, 1962.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1959, c. 36, &#167; 30, p. 206; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 47, &#167; 1, p. 223.</para></source></law></legaldoc>