<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-106"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-106</statuteno><catchline>City council; powers; regulation of utilities; rates.</catchline><para>The council shall have the power to regulate and provide for the lighting of streets, laying down gas and other pipes, and erection of lampposts, electric towers or other apparatus; to regulate the sale and use of gas and electric lights, and fix and determine from time to time the price of gas, the charge of electric lights and power, and the rents of gas meters within the city, when not furnished by public authority, and regulate the inspection thereof; to prohibit or regulate the erection of telegraph, telephone or electric wire poles or other poles for whatsoever purpose desired or used in the public grounds, streets or alleys, and the placing of wires thereon; and to require the removal from the public grounds, streets or alleys, of any or all such poles, and require the removal and placing under ground of any or all telegraph, telephone or electric wires.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. I, &#167; 6, p. 407; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3493; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-106; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-106. </para></source><annotation><para>Proper for city to grant permits for defendant's private use of streets. Dunmar Inv. Co. v. Northern Nat. Gas Co., 185 Neb. 400, 176 N.W.2d 4 (1970).</para><para>Under power conferred by this section, city could grant franchise for distribution of electric current for power and heating purposes as well as lighting purposes. Old Colony Trust Co. v. City of Omaha, 230 U.S. 100 (1913).</para><para>Mayor and council were authorized to grant a franchise for twenty-five years to furnish gas at a fixed rate. Omaha Gas Co. v. City of Omaha, 249 F. 350 (D. Neb. 1914).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>