<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-410"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-410</statuteno><catchline>Board of appeals; appeal; procedure; effect.</catchline><para>Such appeal may be taken by any person aggrieved or by an officer, department, board or bureau of the municipality. Such appeal shall be taken within such time as shall be prescribed by the board of appeals by general rule, by filing with the officer from whom the appeal is taken and with the board of appeals a notice of appeal, specifying the grounds thereof. The officer from whom the appeal is taken shall forthwith transmit to the board all the papers constituting the record upon which the action appealed from was taken. An appeal stays all proceedings in furtherance of the action appealed from, unless the officer from whom the appeal is taken certifies to the board of appeals, after the notice of appeal shall have been filed with him, that by reason of facts stated in the certificate a stay would, in his opinion, cause imminent peril to life or property, in which case proceedings shall not be stayed otherwise than by a restraining order which may be granted by the board of appeals or by a court of record on application, on notice to the officer from whom the appeal is taken and on due cause shown.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 45, &#167; 8, p. 182; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-411; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-410.</para></source><annotation><para>Regardless of whether a request for variances was termed an "appeal," a zoning board of appeals was exercising appellate jurisdiction when the board granted certain variances. Lamar Co. v. Omaha Zoning Bd. of Appeals, 271 Neb. 473, 713 N.W.2d 406 (2006).</para><para>Appeal procedure is provided. Peterson v. Vasak, 162 Neb. 498, 76 N.W.2d 420 (1956).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>