<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-374"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-374</statuteno><catchline>City plan; acquisition and disposition of property; public purposes.</catchline><para>Each city of the metropolitan class shall have the power to acquire by gift, purchase, condemnation, or bequest, such real estate within the corporate limits and within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of the city as may be necessary for any public use and may later convey, lease, sell, or otherwise dispose of any real estate so acquired and not necessary for present use or future development upon such terms as the city may deem appropriate. In addition to any other public uses, the following are declared to be for a public purpose and for the public health and welfare: Establishing, laying out, widening, and enlarging waterways, streets, bridges, boulevards, parkways, parks, playgrounds, sites for public buildings, and property for administrative, institutional, educational, and all other public uses, and for reservations in, about, along, or leading to any or all of such facilities. The powers provided in this section shall be in addition to and not in restriction of any other powers held by cities of the metropolitan class.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. III, &#167; 57b, p. 461; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3612; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-360; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-374; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 34, &#167; 2, p. 191; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 86. </para></source><annotation><para>A city has the power of eminent domain to acquire real estate for a public use and to later sell portions thereof no longer needed by it. Monarch Chemical Works, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 203 Neb. 33, 277 N.W.2d 423 (1979).</para><para>A request for injunction is a proper form in which to present the question of unlawful or improper exercise of the power of eminent domain, because the attempt to deprive a private citizen of an estate in his property, if successful, makes the resulting damage irreparable and legal remedies inadequate. Monarch Chemical Works, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 203 Neb. 33, 277 N.W.2d 423 (1979).</para><para>Cities of the metropolitan class are empowered to acquire real estate by gift. Bowley v. City of Omaha, 181 Neb. 515, 149 N.W.2d 417 (1967).</para><para>This section has application only to those condemnations within a city plan approved by the city council. Van Patten v. City of Omaha, 167 Neb. 741, 94 N.W.2d 664 (1959).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>