<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" id="id6" statutenumber="14-109"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>14-109</statuteno><catchline id="id9">City council; powers;
occupation and license taxes; motor vehicle fee; conditions; limitations.</catchline>
<para>(1)(a) The city council shall have power to tax for revenue,
license, and regulate any person within the limits of the city by ordinance
except as otherwise provided in this section. Such tax may include both a
tax for revenue and license. The city council may raise revenue by levying
and collecting a tax on any occupation or business within the limits of the
city. After March 27, 2014,
any occupation tax imposed pursuant to this section shall make a reasonable
classification of businesses, users of space, or kinds of transactions for
purposes of imposing such tax, except that no occupation tax shall be imposed
on any transaction which is subject to tax under section 53-160, 66-489, 66-489.02,
66-4,140, 66-4,145, 66-4,146, 77-2602, or 77-4008 or which is exempt from
tax under section 77-2704.24. The occupation tax shall be imposed
in the manner provided in section 18-1208, except that section 18-1208 does
not apply to an occupation tax subject to section 86-704. All such taxes shall
be uniform in respect to the class upon which they are imposed. All scientific
and literary lectures and entertainments shall be exempt from taxation, as
well as concerts and all other musical entertainments given exclusively by
the citizens of the city. It shall be the duty of the city clerk to deliver
to the city treasurer the certified copy of the ordinance levying such tax,
and the city clerk shall append thereto a warrant requiring the city treasurer
to collect such tax.</para>
<para>(b) For purposes of this subsection, limits of the city does
not include the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of such city.</para>
<para>(2)(a) Except as otherwise provided in subdivision (c) of
this subsection, the city council shall also have power to require any individual
whose primary residence or person who owns a place of business which is within
the limits of the city and that owns and operates a motor vehicle within such
limits to annually register such motor vehicle in such manner as may be provided
and to require such person to pay an annual motor vehicle fee therefor and
to require the payment of such fee upon the change of ownership of such vehicle.
All such fees which may be provided for under this subsection shall be credited
to a separate fund of the city, thereby created, to be used exclusively for
constructing, repairing, maintaining, or improving streets, roads, alleys,
public ways, or parts thereof or for the amortization of bonded indebtedness
when created for such purposes.</para>
<para>(b) No motor vehicle fee shall be required under this subsection
if (i) a vehicle is used or stored but temporarily in such city for a period
of six months or less in a twelve-month period, (ii) an individual does not
have a primary residence or a person does not own a place of business within
the limits of the city and does not own and operate a motor vehicle within
the limits of the city, or (iii) an individual is a full-time student attending
a postsecondary institution within the limits of the city and the motor vehicle's
situs under the Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act is different from the
place at which he or she is attending such institution.</para>
<para>(c) After December 31, 2012, no motor vehicle fee shall be
required of any individual whose primary residence is or person who owns a
place of business within the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of such
city.</para>
<para>(d) For purposes of this subsection, limits of the city includes
the extraterritorial zoning jurisdiction of such city.</para>
<para>(3) For purposes of this section, person includes bodies corporate,
societies, communities, the public generally, individuals, partnerships, limited
liability companies, joint-stock companies, cooperatives, and associations.
Person does not include any federal, state, or local government or any political
subdivision thereof.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. I, &#167; 9, p. 408; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3496; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-109; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-109; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 752, &#167; 73; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB81, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB745, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB474, &#167; 1.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Motor Vehicle Certificate of Title Act,</emphasis> see section 60-101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>An occupation tax is a tax upon the privilege of doing business in a particular jurisdiction or upon the act of exercising, undertaking, or operating a given occupation, trade, or profession. Anthony, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 283 Neb. 868, 813 N.W.2d 467 (2012).</para><para>Both occupation taxes and sales taxes can be "gross receipts taxes." Anthony, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 283 Neb. 868, 813 N.W.2d 467 (2012).</para><para>The legal incidence of an occupation tax falls upon the retailer, because it is a tax upon the act or privilege of engaging in business activities. Anthony, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 283 Neb. 868, 813 N.W.2d 467 (2012).</para><para>There is no statutory limit on the amount of municipal occupation taxes. Anthony, Inc. v. City of Omaha, 283 Neb. 868, 813 N.W.2d 467 (2012).</para><para>Statute does not deprive State Railway Commission of jurisdiction to control operation of taxicab companies in city of Omaha. In re Yellow Cab and Baggage Co., 126 Neb. 138, 253 N.W. 80 (1934).</para><para>City may, by ordinance, define "peddlers" and include in such term a "rolling store", and impose a permit fee and occupation tax. Erwin v. City of Omaha, 118 Neb. 331, 224 N.W. 692 (1929).</para><para>The municipal year may be declared coextensive with the fiscal year. Johnson v. Leidy, 86 Neb. 818, 126 N.W. 514 (1910).</para><para>License tax cannot be exacted from persons, the regulation of whose compensation is not permitted, and the attempt to tax vehicles rented out by the month is not authorized by this section. McCauley v. State, 83 Neb. 431, 119 N.W. 675 (1909).</para><para>An ordinance imposing an occupation tax is void if it can only be enforced by illegal methods. City of Omaha v. Harmon, 58 Neb. 339, 78 N.W. 623 (1899).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>