<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-366"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-366</statuteno><catchline>Property; purchase or acquisition by eminent domain; scope of power; exercise beyond corporate limits.</catchline><para>The city may purchase or acquire by the exercise of the power of eminent domain private property or public property which is not at the time devoted to a specific public use, for the following purposes and uses: (1) For streets, alleys, avenues, parks, recreational areas, parkways, playgrounds, boulevards, sewers, public squares, market places, and for other needed public uses or purposes authorized by this act, and for adding to, enlarging, widening, or extending any of the foregoing; and (2) for constructing or enlarging waterworks, gas plants, or other municipal utility purposes or enterprises authorized by this act. The power to so purchase or appropriate private property or public property, as in this act specified, for parks, recreational areas, parkways, boulevards, sewers, and for the purpose of constructing waterworks, gas works, light plants, or other municipal enterprises authorized by this act, may be exercised by the city within the corporate limits of the city or within seventy-five miles thereof. The power to so purchase or appropriate private property or public property, as in this act specified, for streets, alleys, avenues, and other construction of like kind may be exercised by the city within the corporate limits of the city or within three miles thereof.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. III, &#167; 57, p. 457; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3610; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-358; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-366; </para><para>Laws 1955, c. 21, &#167; 2, p. 99; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 189.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>"This act",</emphasis> defined, see section 14-101.</para></crossreference><annotation><para><emphasis>1. Authorized purposes</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>3. Damages</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para><emphasis>1. Authorized purposes</emphasis></para><para>A community college's use of an entrance/exit drive qualified as a "specific public use" under this section. Metropolitan Comm. College Area v. City of Omaha, 277 Neb. 782, 765 N.W.2d 440 (2009).</para><para>This section gives the city of Omaha the power to accept dedication of streets in subdivisions within three miles of its corporate limits. Baker v. Buglewicz, 205 Neb. 656, 289 N.W.2d 519 (1980).</para><para>City of metropolitan class may exercise power of eminent domain for street purposes. Phillips Petroleum Co. v. City of Omaha, 171 Neb. 457, 106 N.W.2d 727 (1960).</para><para>City is given power to acquire by condemnation real property for the purpose of extending streets. Van Patten v. City of Omaha, 167 Neb. 741, 94 N.W.2d 664 (1959).</para><para>City may purchase or acquire by the exercise of the power of eminent domain property for parks and playgrounds, and purchase must be authorized by ordinance. Ash v. City of Omaha, 152 Neb. 393, 41 N.W.2d 386 (1950).</para><para>Park board may designate real estate desirable for park purposes, and thereby initiate steps for condemnation. Shannon v. Bartholomew, 83 Neb. 821, 120 N.W. 460 (1909).</para><para>City was authorized to condemn property for waterworks outside of city limits. Omaha Water Co. v. City of Omaha, 162 F. 225 (8th Cir. 1908).</para><para><emphasis>2. Procedure</emphasis></para><para>Acquisition of property for park purposes must be made by ordinance. Reid v. City of Omaha, 150 Neb. 286, 34 N.W.2d 375 (1948).</para><para>Aggrieved property owner, failing to pursue statutory remedies, cannot attack validity of special assessments in collateral proceeding except for fraud or some fundamental defect or entire want of jurisdiction. Penn Mutual Life Ins. Co. v. City of Omaha, 129 Neb. 733, 262 N.W. 861 (1935).</para><para>This section sustained as constitutional, and city council authorized to sit as a board of equalization and ascertain and levy the amount of special benefits against property especially benefited. Burgess-Nash Bldg. Co. v. City of Omaha, 116 Neb. 862, 219 N.W. 394 (1928).</para><para><emphasis>3. Damages</emphasis></para><para>Measure of damages for land taken without condemnation for boulevard is value of land taken. City of Omaha v. Croft, 60 Neb. 57, 82 N.W. 120 (1900).</para><para><emphasis>4. Miscellaneous</emphasis></para><para>Cited but not discussed. Connor v. City of Omaha, 185 Neb. 146, 174 N.W.2d 205 (1970).</para><para>City taking title by eminent domain is estopped to deny the validity of liens deducted from appraisement of property sold at judicial sale. City Safe Deposit &amp; Agency Co. v. City of Omaha, 79 Neb. 446, 112 N.W. 598 (1907).</para><para>Where city acquired mortgaged land without making mortgagee party to proceedings and paid condemnation money to mortgagor, it is discharged from its obligation, but takes land subject to mortgage, if recorded. Rieck v. City of Omaha, 73 Neb. 600, 103 N.W. 283 (1905).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>