
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-566"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-566</statuteno><catchline>Matters published by city; printing; official newspaper; how designated; failure to print notice.</catchline><para>(1) At the beginning of the term of each city council in a city of the metropolitan class, the city clerk shall advertise for three days in each daily legal newspaper in or of general circulation in the city for proposals for publishing in such daily legal newspaper, published in the English language and otherwise meeting the requirements fixed by state law, all public advertisements, notices, ordinances, resolutions, city council proceedings, and all other matter published by the city. In addition to considering the rate bid for printing, the city clerk may give weight to the character of circulation, quality of printing, plant, delivery service, and responsibility of the bidders in determining the lowest and best bid. The city clerk may also consider the advantage of the same plant's combining publication of ordinances and providing an ordinance publishing service to subscribers.</para><para>(2) The city clerk shall notify the city council of the city clerk's selection of the official newspaper, which shall continue as such throughout the term of the city council. The city council may order additional publication of any of its proceedings in any other qualified legal newspaper or publication.</para><para>(3) If at any time, the designated official newspaper ceases regular publication or is not giving service satisfactory to the city council, the city clerk shall recommend another qualified legal newspaper to the city council and, upon approval of the city council, such legal newspaper shall become the official newspaper.</para><para>(4) In case of refusal or neglect of the official newspaper to publish any required notice, the city clerk shall post such notice on the city's website and in a conspicuous place in the city hall, and the city clerk shall keep a written record of such posting . The record of such posting shall be evidence that such posting was done as required and shall be sufficient to fulfill the requirement of publication.</para><para>(5) The city shall not be without an official newspaper more than thirty days at a time.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. IV, &#167; 55, p. 494; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3681; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-558; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-566; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 62, &#167; 1, p. 371; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 211. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Effect of posting notice raised but not decided. Chicago &amp; N.W. Ry. Co. v. City of Omaha, 156 Neb. 705, 57 N.W.2d 753 (1953).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>