<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-211"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-211</statuteno><catchline>Ordinances; repeal by referendum; procedure.</catchline><para>No ordinance passed by any such council, except when otherwise required by the general laws of the state, or by other provisions of sections 14-201 to 14-229, except ordinances appropriating money to pay the salary of officers and employees of the city, emergency ordinances for the immediate preservation of the public peace, health or safety, and which contain a statement of such emergency, shall go into effect before fifteen days from the time of its final passage. If during said fifteen days a petition, signed and verified, as hereinbefore provided, by electors of the city equal in number to at least fifteen percent of the highest number of votes cast for any of such councilmen at the last preceding general city election, protesting against the passage of such ordinance, shall be presented to such council, then such ordinance shall thereupon be suspended from going into operation, and it shall be the duty of the council to reconsider such ordinance. If the same be not entirely repealed by the council, then the council shall proceed to submit to the voters such ordinance at a special election to be called for that purpose or at a general city election, and such ordinance shall not go into effect or become operative unless a majority of the qualified electors voting on the same shall vote in favor thereof. Such petition shall be in all respects in accordance with the provisions of section 14-212 relating to signatures, verification, inspection and certification.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. II, &#167; 11, p. 426; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3536; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-211; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-211. </para></source><annotation><para>Where no referendum petition is filed as prescribed herein, it appears under the express terms of the statute that no action was taken to delay the effectiveness of the ordinance. State ex rel. Andersen v. Leahy, 189 Neb. 92, 199 N.W.2d 713 (1972).</para><para>Referendum did not apply to ordinance establishing location of city auditorium. State ex rel. Ballantyne v. Leeman, 149 Neb. 847, 32 N.W.2d 918 (1948).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>
