<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-402"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2022</bookinfo><statuteno>14-402</statuteno><catchline>Building zones; creation; powers of city council; uniformity; manufactured homes.</catchline><para>(1) For any or all of the purposes listed in section 14-401, the city council of a city of the metropolitan class may divide the city into districts of such number, shape, and area as may be deemed best suited to carry out the purposes of sections 14-401 to 14-418. Within such districts the city council may regulate, restrict, or prohibit the erection, construction, reconstruction, alteration, or use of buildings, structures, or land. All such regulations shall be uniform for each class or kind of buildings throughout each district, but the regulations applicable to one district may differ from those applicable to other districts.</para><para>(2)(a) The city council shall not adopt or enforce any zoning ordinance or regulation which prohibits the use of land for a proposed residential structure for the sole reason that the proposed structure is a manufactured home if such manufactured home bears an appropriate seal which indicates that it was constructed in accordance with the standards of the Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles, the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act, or the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development. The city council may require that a manufactured home be located and installed according to the same standards for foundation system, permanent utility connections, setback, and minimum square footage which would apply to a site-built, single-family dwelling on the same lot. The city council may also require that manufactured homes meet the following standards:</para><para>(i) The home shall have no less than nine hundred square feet of floor area;</para><para>(ii) The home shall have no less than an eighteen-foot exterior width;</para><para>(iii) The roof shall be pitched with a minimum vertical rise of two and one-half inches for each twelve inches of horizontal run;</para><para>(iv) The exterior material shall be of a color, material, and scale comparable with those existing in residential site-built, single-family construction;</para><para>(v) The home shall have a nonreflective roof material which is or simulates asphalt or wood shingles, tile, or rock; and</para><para>(vi) The home shall have wheels, axles, transporting lights, and removable towing apparatus removed.</para><para>(b) The city council may not require additional standards unless such standards are uniformly applied to all single-family dwellings in the zoning district.</para><para>(c) Nothing in this subsection shall be deemed to supersede any valid restrictive covenants of record.</para><para>(3) For purposes of this section, manufactured home means (a) a factory-built structure which is to be used as a place for human habitation, which is not constructed or equipped with a permanent hitch or other device allowing it to be moved other than to a permanent site, which does not have permanently attached to its body or frame any wheels or axles, and which bears a label certifying that it was built in compliance with National Manufactured Home Construction and Safety Standards, 24 C.F.R. 3280 et seq., promulgated by the United States Department of Housing and Urban Development, or (b) a modular housing unit as defined in section 71-1557 bearing a seal in accordance with the Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 45, &#167; 2, p. 179; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-405; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-402; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 298, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1985, LB 313, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 511, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1044, &#167; 54; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1073, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 133. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Standards for Modular Housing Units Act,</emphasis> see section 71-1555.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Standard Code for Manufactured Homes and Recreational Vehicles,</emphasis> see section 71-4601.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>The Nebraska Legislature has granted the City of Omaha the power to zone property lying within its jurisdiction. Giger v. City of Omaha, 232 Neb. 676, 442 N.W.2d 182 (1989).</para><para>The uniformity requirement in this section does not prohibit reasonable classifications within a district. Giger v. City of Omaha, 232 Neb. 676, 442 N.W.2d 182 (1989).</para><para>To successfully challenge a rezoning ordinance on the grounds it violates the uniformity requirement of this section, the challengers must prove that the actions of the city in adopting the rezoning ordinance were unreasonable, discriminatory, or arbitrary and that the regulation bears no relationship to the purpose or purposes sought to be accomplished by the ordinance. Giger v. City of Omaha, 232 Neb. 676, 442 N.W.2d 182 (1989).</para><para>This section is cited as a background for history of zoning power of city of Omaha. Wolf v. City of Omaha, 177 Neb. 545, 129 N.W.2d 501 (1964).</para><para>City is authorized to regulate the use of buildings and land within districts created in the city. Bucholz v. City of Omaha, 174 Neb. 862, 120 N.W.2d 270 (1963).</para><para>Spot zoning of block was not authorized. Davis v. City of Omaha, 153 Neb. 460, 45 N.W.2d 172 (1950).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>