<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-401"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-401</statuteno><catchline>Buildings and structures; regulations; board of appeals; powers of city council.</catchline><para>For the purpose of promoting the health, safety, and general welfare of the community, the city council in a city of the metropolitan class may regulate and restrict the height, number of stories, and size of buildings and other structures, the percentage of a lot that may be occupied, the size of yards, courts, and other open spaces, the density of population, and the location and use of buildings, structures, and land for trade, industry, residence, or other purposes. Such regulations may provide for a board of appeals that may determine and vary application of such regulations in harmony with their general purpose and intent, and in accordance with general or specific rules contained in such regulations.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 45, &#167; 1, p. 178; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-404; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-401; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 132. </para></source><annotation><para>The Nebraska Legislature has granted the City of Omaha the power to zone property lying within its jurisdiction. Giger v. City of Omaha, 232 Neb. 676, 442 N.W.2d 182 (1989).</para><para>Zoning ordinances enacted by a city, as a lawful exercise of police power, must be consistent with public health, safety, morals, and the general welfare. Giger v. City of Omaha, 232 Neb. 676, 442 N.W.2d 182 (1989).</para><para>This article sets forth the powers and duties of a metropolitan city with respect to planning and zoning. State v. Buttner, 180 Neb. 529, 143 N.W.2d 907 (1966).</para><para>This section is cited as a background for history of zoning power of city of Omaha. Wolf v. City of Omaha, 177 Neb. 545, 129 N.W.2d 501 (1964).</para><para>This section constitutes a grant of power to zone. Davis v. City of Omaha, 153 Neb. 460, 45 N.W.2d 172 (1950).</para><para>City council is empowered to regulate and restrict height and size of buildings, and the percentage of lot that may be occupied. Roncka v. Fogarty, 152 Neb. 467, 41 N.W.2d 745 (1950).</para><para>This and subsequent sections of this article became a part of city charter subsequent to provisions relating to gifts made to the city for parks and playground purposes. Ash v. City of Omaha, 152 Neb. 393, 41 N.W.2d 386 (1950).</para><para>Ordinance of city of metropolitan class prescribing a restricted zone for high-type residential use was sustained as constitutional under police power. Dundee Realty Co. v. City of Omaha, 144 Neb. 448, 13 N.W.2d 634 (1944).</para><para>Zoning ordinance, drafted in general terms and providing reasonable margin to secure effective enforcement, is within police power of state and constitutional. Pettis v. Alpha Alpha Chapter of Phi Beta Pi, 115 Neb. 525, 213 N.W. 835 (1927).</para><para>Cities of metropolitan class under this article are not authorized to impose unreasonable regulations upon the owners of city lots with respect to the area which may be occupied for building purposes. State ex rel. Westminster Presbyterian Church v. Edgecomb, 108 Neb. 859, 189 N.W. 617 (1922), 27 A.L.R. 437 (1922).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>