<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" id="id6" statutenumber="14-415"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2018</bookinfo><statuteno>14-415</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Building ordinance or regulations;
enforcement; inspection; violations; penalty.</catchline><para>The
city, in addition to other remedies, may institute any appropriate action
or proceedings to prevent an unlawful erection, construction, reconstruction,
alteration, conversion, maintenance, or
use of any building or structure in violation of any ordinance or regulations
enacted or issued pursuant to sections 14-401 to 14-418, to restrain, correct, or abate such violation,
to prevent the occupancy of the building, structure, or land, or to prevent any
illegal act, conduct, business, or
use in or about such premises. The ordinance or regulations
shall be enforced by the city as it may provide. In addition to and not in
restriction of any other powers, the city may cause any building, structure,
place, or premises
to be inspected and examined and to order in writing the remedying of any
condition found to exist therein or thereat in violation of any provision
of the ordinance or regulations
made under authority of such sections. The owner,
general agent, lessee, or tenant of a building or premises or of any part
of such building or premises where
a violation of any provision of the ordinance or regulations
has been committed or shall exist or
the general agent, architect, builder, contractor, or any other person who commits, takes part, or assists in any such violation
or who maintains any building or premises in which any such violation shall
exist shall be
guilty of a Class IV misdemeanor for
a first or second violation and a Class II misdemeanor for a third or subsequent
violation, if the third or subsequent violation is committed within two years
after the commission of the prior violation.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1925, c. 45, &#167; 9, p. 184; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-412; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-415; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 37, &#167; 3, p. 212; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB174, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>