<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-367"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-367</statuteno><catchline>Property; acquisition by eminent domain; procedure.</catchline><para>Whenever property is purchased for any of the purposes stated in section 14-366 the purchase thereof shall be made by ordinance. Whenever it becomes necessary to appropriate property for the purposes stated in section 14-366 the purpose and necessity for such appropriation shall be declared by ordinance. Thereupon the procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. III, &#167; 57, p. 457; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3610; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-358; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-367; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 35, p. 461.</para></source><annotation><para>Amendment to this section providing condemnation procedure be in manner of cited sections repealed by implication succeeding sections. Connor v. City of Omaha, 185 Neb. 146, 174 N.W.2d 205 (1970).</para><para>Where city purchases or condemns property for parks or playgrounds, appraisers must be appointed and their award reported to the city council. Ash v. City of Omaha, 152 Neb. 393, 41 N.W.2d 386 (1950).</para><para>Appraisal of property is required when acquired for park purposes. Reid v. City of Omaha, 150 Neb. 286, 34 N.W.2d 375 (1948).</para><para>Although board of appraisers does not constitute a court, it exercises functions judicial in their nature. In re Appraisement of Omaha Gas Plant, 102 Neb. 782, 169 N.W. 725 (1918).</para><para>Award of damages by appraisers, unless appealed from, is conclusive, and city having lien for special assessment and failing to have same established, cannot, after expiration of time for appeal, offset amount of same against warrants issued to property for damages. State ex rel. Katelman v. Fink, 84 Neb. 185, 120 N.W. 938 (1909).</para><para>Special tax for opening street cannot be levied until report of appraisement of damages has been confirmed by council. Merrill v. Shields, 57 Neb. 78, 77 N.W. 368 (1898).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>