<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-227</statuteno><catchline>Fines and penalties; collection; duty to pay to city treasurer; violation; penalty; duty of comptroller to audit.</catchline><para>All fines, penalties, and forfeitures collected for offenses against the ordinances of the city, or for misdemeanors against the laws of the state, committed within the city, shall, unless otherwise provided by law, be paid by the person receiving the same to the city treasurer. Any person receiving such fines, penalties and forfeitures, who shall fail to pay the same over as above provided within thirty days after the receipt of the same by him, or within ten days after being requested by the mayor so to do, shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor, and, upon conviction thereof shall be punished by a fine of not to exceed one thousand dollars and imprisonment not to exceed six months in the county jail. Such person shall be guilty of malfeasance in office and shall be removed from office. It shall be the duty of the comptroller to audit the accounts of all such officers at least once each month and to approve or disapprove their reports.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. II, &#167; 24, p. 432; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3550; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-225; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-227. </para></source><annotation><para>The disposition of forfeited cash bail bonds is controlled by the Constitution and not this section. School Dist. of Omaha v. City of Omaha, 175 Neb. 21, 120 N.W.2d 267 (1963).</para><para>This section did not control disposition of fines, penalties, and license money under general laws of the state. School Dist. No. 54 v. School Dist. of Omaha, 171 Neb. 769, 107 N.W.2d 744 (1961).</para><para>In charging violation of this section, the time elapsing during which failure to pay over existed, is material and must be stated. Grier v. State, 81 Neb. 129, 115 N.W. 551 (1908).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>