<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-508"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-508</statuteno><catchline>Funds; obligation and expenditure; limits upon; effect of exceeding; exceptions.</catchline><para>Neither the city council nor any officer of the city or superintendent of a department shall expend or incur obligations for the expenditure of more money than has been provided and appropriated for the purposes for which the expenditure or obligations for expenditure are made. Any contract or obligation calling for an expenditure in excess of the money and credits provided and appropriated to the purposes for which such contract or obligation is created, shall be void and shall not be enforceable against the city, and the city shall refuse to recognize the validity thereof or to pay or satisfy any such obligation. The foregoing limitations and those contained in sections 14-506 and 14-507 shall not apply to additional expenditures and obligations unavoidably made necessary in efforts to abate or control an extreme or unusual outbreak or epidemic of disease or to expenditures made imperatively necessary by the occurrence of some unforeseen or uncontrollable disaster to the city at large or a considerable section thereof. Expenditures for the emergency purposes in this section specified shall be made only in pursuance of an ordinance duly passed reciting the conditions making necessary the further appropriation of funds, and the expenditures of such appropriation, shall be limited exclusively to the purposes for which made.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. IV, &#167; 7, p. 471; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3631; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-508; </para><para>Laws 1935, Spec. Sess., c. 10, &#167; 9, p. 77; </para><para>Laws 1941, c. 130, &#167; 15, p. 499; </para><para>C.S.Supp.,1941, &#167; 14-508; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-508; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 30, &#167; 6, p. 149.</para></source></law></legaldoc>