<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-556"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-556</statuteno><catchline>City treasurer; authorized depositories;
securities; conflict of interest.</catchline><para>(1) The city treasurer
shall place all funds of the city, as the same accrue, on deposit in such
banks, capital stock financial institutions, or qualifying mutual financial
institutions within the city as shall agree to pay the highest rate of interest
for the use of such funds so deposited. The city council is hereby directed
to advertise for bids for rates for the deposit of such funds as is hereby
contemplated.</para>
<para>(2) The banks, capital stock financial institutions, or qualifying mutual
financial institutions referred to in subsection (1) of this section, so selected,
shall:</para>
<para>(a) Give bond to the city for the safekeeping of such funds, and such
city shall not have on deposit in any bank, capital stock financial institution,
or qualifying mutual financial institution giving a guaranty bond more than
the amount insured or guaranteed by
the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation plus the maximum amount of the bond
given by the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual
financial institution or in any bank, capital stock financial institution,
or qualifying mutual financial institution giving a personal bond more than
the amount insured or guaranteed by
the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation plus one-half of the amount of the
bond of the bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual
financial institution. All bonds of such banks, capital stock financial institutions,
or qualifying mutual financial institutions shall be deposited with and held
by the city treasurer; or</para>
<para>(b) Give security as provided in the Public Funds Deposit Security Act.</para>
<para>(3) The fact that a stockholder, director, or other officer of such
bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying mutual financial
institution is also serving as mayor, as a member of the city council, as
a member of a board of public works, or as any other officer of such municipality
shall not disqualify such bank, capital stock financial institution, or qualifying
mutual financial institution from acting as a depository for such municipal
funds.</para>
<para>(4) Section 77-2366 shall apply to deposits in capital stock financial
institutions.</para>
<para>(5) Section 77-2365.01 shall apply to deposits in qualifying mutual
financial institutions.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. IV, &#167; 44, p. 491; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3670; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-547; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-556; </para><para>Laws 1957, c. 54, &#167; 1, p. 263; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 35, &#167; 2, p. 193; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 33, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 157, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 1274, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 362, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2009, LB259, &#167; 4.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Public Funds Deposit Security Act,</emphasis> see section 77-2386.</para></crossreference><annotation><para>City of metropolitan class can make no deposit in bank unless the deposit is protected by bond, and while it may be implied, it is not expressly required, that the bank must pay the premium on the bond. State ex rel. Sorensen v. South Omaha State Bank, 128 Neb. 733, 260 N.W. 278 (1935).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>