<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-365.01"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-365.01</statuteno><catchline>Sewerage systems and sewage disposal plants; construction; operation; territorial limits; tax authorized.</catchline><para>Any city of the metropolitan class in this state is hereby authorized to own, construct, equip, and operate either within or without the corporate limits of such municipality a sewerage system, including any storm sewer system, and plant or plants for the treatment, purification, and disposal in a sanitary manner of the liquid and solid wastes, sewage, and night soil of the area or to extend or improve any existing sewerage system, including any storm sewer system. It shall have authority to acquire by gift, grant, purchase, or condemnation necessary lands therefor, either within or without the corporate limits of such municipality. For the purpose of owning, operating, constructing, maintaining, and equipping such sewage disposal plant and sewerage system, including any storm sewer system, or improving or extending such existing system, any city of the metropolitan class is also authorized and empowered to make a special levy each year of not to exceed three and five-tenths cents on each one hundred dollars upon the taxable value of all the taxable property in such city, as well as all taxable property within three miles of the corporate limits of such city, which property is within a district established under section 14-360, subject to sections 14-365.12 and 14-365.13. The proceeds of the tax shall be used for any of the purposes enumerated in this section and for no other purpose.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1953, c. 24, &#167; 1, p. 99; </para><para>Laws 1959, c. 30, &#167; 3, p. 184; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 29; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 719A, &#167; 34.</para></source> <annotation><para>The application of this entire act is discussed with reference to a lease-purchase agreement relating to financing a waste disposal plant. Cosentino v. City of Omaha, 186 Neb. 407, 183 N.W.2d 475 (1971).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc>