
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-601"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-601</statuteno><catchline>Police; appointment; powers and duties of city council.</catchline><para>The city council of a city of the metropolitan class shall have the power and the duty to appoint a chief of police and all other members of the police force to the extent that funds may be available to pay their salaries and as may be necessary to protect citizens and property and maintain peace and good order.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1921, c. 116, art. V, &#167; 1, p. 496; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3682; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-601; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-601; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 214. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Until particular event happens upon which pension is to be paid to police officer, there is no vested right in pension payments. Lickert v. City of Omaha, 144 Neb. 75, 12 N.W.2d 644 (1944).</para><para>Provisions of this article are subject to amendment by ordinance adopted by city council and submitted to electors of city of metropolitan class operating under home rule charter. Munch v. Tusa, 140 Neb. 457, 300 N.W. 385 (1941).</para><para>Provisions relative to appointment and discharge of fireman are substantially identical with those relating to policeman. Shandy v. City of Omaha, 127 Neb. 406, 255 N.W. 477 (1934).</para><para>City is empowered to appoint police officers and require them to give bonds, and persons injured by negligent acts may recover thereon, although bond runs to the city as obligee. Curnyn v. Kinney, 119 Neb. 478, 229 N.W. 894 (1930).</para><para>A member of the police department of a metropolitan city is an officer and in the service of a governmental agency of the state. Rooney v. City of Omaha, 104 Neb. 260, 177 N.W. 166 (1920), opinion modified 105 Neb. 447, 181 N.W. 143 (1920).</para><para>When policeman of metropolitan city is assigned work outside duties of peace officer, but falling within corporate functions of municipality, he becomes servant thereof in its corporate capacity. Levin v. City of Omaha, 102 Neb. 328, 167 N.W. 214 (1918).</para></annotation></law>
</legaldoc>