<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1239"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1239</statuteno><catchline>Bridge commission; property; condemnation; procedure.</catchline><para>Whenever it shall be necessary to condemn property in the State of Nebraska for the purpose of constructing, extending, or enlarging any portion of a bridge or the approaches to such bridge, or securing avenues of access or rights-of-way leading to such approaches, the bridge commission of a city of the metropolitan class may condemn any interests, franchises, easements, rights, privileges, land, or improvements which may, in the opinion of such commission, be necessary for the purpose of constructing such bridge or approaches, or necessary for rights-of-way or avenues of access leading to such approaches. Condemnation shall be certified to the city council for its action. The procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724. The bridge commission is further empowered to exercise in any adjoining state such powers of eminent domain as may be conferred upon the bridge commission by any act of Congress of the United States or as may be authorized by the law of that state. No payments of award in any condemnation proceedings or for the costs of such proceedings or the expense of such proceedings, shall be made except from funds provided under the authority of sections 14-1201 to 14-1252. Title to property condemned under this section shall be taken in the name of and vest in the city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 176, &#167; 17, p. 626; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-1217; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1239; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 41, p. 464; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 272. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>