
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1821"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1821</statuteno><catchline>Metropolitan transit authority; tax request; certification; levy; collection.</catchline><para>To assist in the defraying of all character of expense of the authority and to such extent as in its discretion and judgment may be necessary, the board shall annually certify a tax request for the fiscal year commencing on the following January 1. Such tax request shall not exceed in any one year ten cents on each one hundred dollars on the taxable value of the taxable property in the city of the metropolitan class or taxable property in any county in which such city is located, adjacent county, or city or village located within such counties served by the authority. The board shall by resolution, on or before September 30 of each year, certify such tax request to the city council of such city and the governing board of any county in which such city is located, adjacent county, or city or village located within such counties served by the authority. Such county, city, or village is hereby authorized to cause such tax to be levied and to be collected as are other taxes by the treasurer of such city or village or county treasurer and paid over by him or her to the treasurer of such board subject to the order of such board and subject to section 77-3443. If in any year the full amount so certified and collected is not needed for the current purposes of such authority, the balance shall be credited to reserves of such authority to be used for acquisition of necessary property and equipment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 23, &#167; 21, p. 173; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1275, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 1974, LB 875, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1979, LB 187, &#167; 35; </para><para>Laws 1986, LB 1012, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1987, LB 471, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1063, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1992, Second Spec. Sess., LB 1, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 734, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 452, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 19; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 720, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 2007, LB206, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 2021, LB644, &#167; 8. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>