
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1248"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1248</statuteno><catchline>Bridges; joint condemnation; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any city of the metropolitan class may acquire an existing bridge by entering into joint condemnation proceedings with other political units as authorized by section 14-1202. Where the property to be condemned is situated within the jurisdiction of more than one political unit or partly in the State of Nebraska and partly in an adjoining state, the political units cooperating shall first enter into a contract electing in what jurisdiction and in which state a single joint proceeding to condemn the property as an entirety shall be instituted and the proceedings shall be conducted subject to the law of and in the manner provided for that jurisdiction, or such proceedings may be conducted subject to the law and in the manner provided by an act of Congress conferring the power of condemnation where the property to be acquired is situated in more than one state.</para><para>(2) For purposes of this section, cities of the metropolitan class in this state are authorized to become parties to a single proceeding in an adjoining state and to subject themselves to the law of that state governing such proceedings. In the event of such joint proceedings in this state, the procedure to condemn property shall be exercised in the manner set forth in sections 76-704 to 76-724.</para><para>(3) The contract provided for in this section shall be similar to the contract provided for in section 14-1247, shall fix the proportionate contribution to be made by each political unit cooperating, and shall provide for the creation of a joint bridge commission to take over the operation of the property in the event of its acquisition, subject to the conditions provided in sections 14-1244 to 14-1250 with reference to such joint bridge commission.</para><para>(4) Title to the property condemned under this section shall vest in the political units cooperating as tenants in common when, as, and if the approval of the electors has been given as provided in section 14-1251.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 176, &#167; 24, p. 630; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-1224; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1248; </para><para>Laws 1951, c. 101, &#167; 44, p. 466; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 281. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>