<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1709"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1709</statuteno><catchline>Parking authority; construction and maintenance; duties; city and county cooperate.</catchline><para>The authority shall construct and maintain subsurface parking facilities at the location acquired under section 14-1708, with all necessary entrances, exits, air vents, and other appurtenances required for an efficient subsurface parking facility. In constructing and maintaining the parking facilities the surface above the facility shall not be disturbed more than shall be necessary. Any portion thereof not required by the facility shall, on completion of the facility, be restored to a good usable condition. If it is necessary to relocate or do other work to protect any sewer line or utility, the authority shall do the necessary work or bear the expense thereof and the authority shall reimburse the county and city for any expense or liability incurred as a result of the construction or maintenance of the facility. The authority shall also protect the owners of private property abutting the facility against loss of lateral support for improvements erected on their property at the time of the construction of the facilities or reimburse them for expenses incurred as a result of the removal of said support, but neither the state, county, city, nor authority shall be otherwise liable to such owners. The county and city shall cooperate with the authority and make available to the authority without cost any information it has that would be useful to the authority in the construction of the facilities. The parking authority shall not construct any private entrances or grant the right to others to construct private entrances to its parking facilities.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1955, c. 22, &#167; 9, p. 106.</para></source></law></legaldoc>