<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1813"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1813</statuteno><catchline>Metropolitan transit authority; board; appointment; term; vacancy; oath; bond; removal from office.</catchline><para>(1) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, whenever any city of the metropolitan class creates an authority, the board shall consist of five members to be selected as follows: (a) The mayor, with the approval of the city council and the county board of the county in which the city is located, shall appoint one member who shall serve for one year, one member who shall serve for two years, one member who shall serve for three years, one member who shall serve for four years, and one member who shall serve for five years; and (b) upon the expiration of the term of each appointed officer, the mayor, with the approval of the city council and the county board of the county in which the city is located, shall appoint a member who shall serve for a term of five years. Members of such board shall be residents of the transit authority territory described in section 14-1803 and one member of the board shall be nominated and selected as provided in subsection (2) of this section. In cities of the metropolitan class where a board has been heretofore appointed, the mayor, with the approval of the city council and the county board of the county in which the city is located, shall by resolution redesignate the terms of the members of such board in accordance with the provisions of sections 14-1803, 14-1805, 14-1812, and 14-1813, except that until such redesignation is made the terms shall stand as provided for in the original appointment.</para><para>(2) Notwithstanding any provisions of the city charter of the city of the metropolitan class to the contrary, when the next vacancy will occur on the board after August 31, 2003, resulting from the expiration of the term of office of a member of the board, notice of such vacancy shall be communicated to the clerk of each county, city, or village which is part of the transit authority territory. Such notice shall be provided at least forty-five days prior to the expiration of the term of office of the member. Each county, city, and village, other than the city of the metropolitan class, may, by majority vote of their governing bodies, recommend the appointment of one or more residents of their respective jurisdictions to fill the board position. Such nominations shall be filed with the mayor of the city of the metropolitan class not later than the thirtieth day following the date of receipt of notice of the vacancy. The mayor shall make the appointment to fill the board position from such nominations. The individual appointed by the mayor, upon approval by the city council of the city of the metropolitan class, shall become a member of the board. Thereafter, any successor to such board member, either by reason of vacancy or the expiration of such board member's term, shall possess the residence qualifications provided for in this subsection, and such board position shall be filled in the manner provided for in this subsection.</para><para>(3) Except as provided in subsection (2) of this section, any vacancy on such board, resulting other than from expiration of a term of office, shall be filled by the mayor of the city of the metropolitan class, with the approval of the city council and the county board of the county in which the city is located, and such appointee shall possess the same residence qualifications as the member whose office he or she is to fill and shall serve the unexpired portion, if any, of the term of the member whose office was vacated.</para><para>(4) Each member, before entering upon the duties of the office, shall file with the city clerk of the city of the metropolitan class an oath that he or she will duly and faithfully perform all the duties of the office to the best of his or her ability, and a bond in the penal sum of five thousand dollars executed by one or more qualified sureties for the faithful performance of his or her duties. If any member shall fail to file such oath and bond on or before the first day of the term for which he or she was appointed or elected, his or her office shall be deemed to be vacant.</para><para>(5) A member of such board may be removed from office for incompetence, neglect of duty, or malfeasance in office. An action for the removal of such officer may be brought, upon resolution of the city council of the city of the metropolitan class or the county board of the county in which the city is located, in the district court of the county in which such city is located.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 23, &#167; 13, p. 169; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1275, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1973, LB 69, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 269, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 720, &#167; 4.</para></source></law></legaldoc>