<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1814"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1814</statuteno><catchline>Metropolitan transit authority; board; organization; officers; quorum; meetings; resolutions; public records.</catchline><para>Not later than seven days after the qualification of the members, the board shall organize for the transaction of business, shall select a chairperson and vice-chairperson from among its members, and shall adopt bylaws, rules, and regulations to govern its proceedings. The chairperson and vice-chairperson and their successors shall be elected annually by the board and shall serve for a term of one year. Any vacancy in the offices of chairperson and vice-chairperson shall be filled by election by the board. A quorum for the transaction of business shall consist of three members of the board. Regular meetings of the board shall be held at least once in each calendar month at the time and place to be fixed by the board. All actions of the board shall be by resolution, except as may otherwise be provided in the Transit Authority Law, and the affirmative vote of at least three members shall be necessary for the adoption of any resolution. Any such resolution shall be approved by the chairperson of the board, or in his or her absence by the vice-chairperson of the board, before taking effect. If he or she shall approve thereof he or she shall sign the same. If he or she shall not approve thereof, he or she shall return the resolution to the board with his or her objections thereto in writing at the next regular meeting of the board occurring after the passage thereof. If the chairperson shall fail to return any resolution with his or her written objections to the board within the time aforesaid, he or she shall be deemed to have approved the same and it shall take effect; any resolution not approved by the chairperson may be passed by the affirmative vote of at least four members of the board. The board shall cause to be kept accurate minutes of all of its proceedings. All resolutions and all proceedings of the authority and all official documents and records of the authority shall be public records and open to public inspection, except such documents and records as shall be prepared and kept for use in negotiations, actions, or proceedings, to which the authority is a party.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1957, c. 23, &#167; 14, p. 170; </para><para>Laws 1972, LB 1275, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 1998, LB 1191, &#167; 13.</para></source></law></legaldoc>