
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities Of The Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-1227"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-1227</statuteno><catchline>Bridge commission; members; term; vacancies; compensation; officers and employees; office; powers and duties.</catchline><para>(1) When it has been determined by the city council of a city of the metropolitan class by resolution or ordinance in the exercise of its discretion, that in the exercise of the powers conferred by sections 14-1201 to 14-1252 it is expedient to create a bridge commission, the mayor of such city, with the approval of the city council, shall appoint four persons, who, with the mayor as an ex officio member, shall constitute a bridge commission which shall be a public body corporate and politic under the name of (insert name of city) Bridge Commission. Such bridge commission shall have power to contract, to sue and be sued, and to adopt a seal and alter such seal, but shall not have power to pledge the credit or taxing power of the city.</para><para>(2) No officer or employee of such city, except the mayor, whether holding a paid or unpaid office, shall be eligible to hold an appointment on such bridge commission. Such appointees shall be originally appointed for terms of four years. Upon the expiration of such terms, appointments shall be made in like manner except that the term of the four appointees shall be for one year, two years, three years, and four years, respectively. Not more than two of such appointees shall be members of the same political party. Vacancies shall be filled for any unexpired term in the same manner as the original appointment. Such bridge commission shall elect a chairperson and vice-chairperson from its members, and a secretary and treasurer who need not be a member of such commission. The members of the bridge commission shall receive no compensation and shall give such bonds as may be required from time to time by the city council. The bridge commission shall fix the compensation of the secretary and treasurer.</para><para>(3) The bridge commission shall have the power to establish bylaws, rules, and regulations for its own government, and to make and enter into all contracts or agreements necessary or incidental to the performance of its duties and the execution of its powers. The bridge commission may employ engineering, architectural, and construction experts and inspectors and attorneys, and such other employees as may be necessary in its opinion, and fix their compensation, and such employees shall do such work as the bridge commission shall direct. All salaries and compensation for such employees shall be obligations against and be paid solely from funds provided under the authority of sections 14-1201 to 14-1252. The office, records, books, and accounts of the bridge commission shall always be maintained in the city which the bridge commission represents. Such bridge commission may be charged by the city council with the construction of new bridges or the operation, maintenance, repair, renewal, reconstruction, replacement, extension, or enlargement of existing bridges.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1929, c. 176, &#167; 13, p. 622; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-1213; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1227; </para><para>Laws 2022, LB800, &#167; 260. </para><operativedate>July 21, 2022</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>