<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" statutenumber="14-2004"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>14-2004</statuteno><catchline>Landmark heritage preservation commission; membership; qualifications; appointed by mayor; terms; officers.</catchline><para>(1) A landmark heritage preservation commission created pursuant to sections 14-2001 to 14-2004 shall have nine members. If available, one of the members shall be an architect, one shall be a curator or director of an art or other museum, one shall be a professional artist or historian, three shall be interested and qualified persons chosen, as far as possible, from any existing historical society, preservation group, architectural, landscape architectural, interior design, or planning association, or cultural organization, two shall be laypersons, and one shall be an owner or operator of a business or property within a landmark heritage preservation district, which business or property may be owned or operated by a corporation of which such member is an officer, by a partnership in which such member is a partner, or by a limited liability company in which such member is a member.</para><para>(2) Members shall be appointed by the mayor and approved by the city council and shall serve for terms of three years. Members shall serve until their successors are appointed and qualified. Members may be appointed to successive terms.</para><para>(3) The commission shall select one of its members as chairperson. The director of the planning department of the city shall act as the executive director of such commission, and staff assistance for the commission shall be provided by the planning department of such city.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1976, LB 711, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1991, LB 247, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 129.</para></source></law></legaldoc>