<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id4">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Cities of the Metropolitan Class" id="id6" statutenumber="14-2138">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>14-2138</statuteno><catchline id="id9">Utilities district;
payment to city of the metropolitan class; allocation.</catchline><para>The
metropolitan utilities district shall pay to the city of the metropolitan
class a sum equivalent to two percent of the annual gross revenue derived
from all retail sales of water and gas sold by such district within such city, except that until January 1, 2020, retail
sales of gas shall not include the retail sale of natural gas used as vehicular
fuel. Such sum shall be paid on a quarterly basis, the last quarterly
payment to be made not later than the thirtieth day of January of the next
succeeding year, except that annual payments to such city shall not be less
than five hundred thousand dollars. Such city shall not levy or collect any
license, occupation, or excise tax upon or from such district. All payments
provided by this section shall be allocated by the district among the several
utilities operated by it upon such basis as the district shall determine.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1919, c. 187, &#167; 4, p. 421; </para><para>C.S.1922, &#167; 3774; </para><para>C.S.1929, &#167; 14-1030; </para><para>Laws 1943, c. 36, &#167; 23, p. 177; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 14-1041; </para><para>Laws 1945, c. 19, &#167; 5, p. 125; </para><para>Laws 1947, c. 21, &#167; 2, p. 112; </para><para>Laws 1961, c. 33, &#167; 1, p. 153; </para><para>Laws 1967, c. 47, &#167; 1, p. 179; </para><para>R.S.1943, (1991), &#167; 14-1041; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 746, &#167; 38; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB867, &#167; 4.</para><operativedate>January 1, 2015</operativedate></source><annotation><para>Revenue from sale of water and gas by metropolitan utilities district are not taxes and section as amended by L.B. 425 (Laws 1967) is constitutional. Evans v. Metropolitan Utilities Dist., 187 Neb. 261, 188 N.W.2d 851 (1971).</para><para>Class action could not be used to test constitutionality of section. Evans v. Metropolitan Utilities Dist., 185 Neb. 464, 176 N.W.2d 679 (1970).</para><para>Cited but not discussed. Evans v. Metropolitan Utilities Dist., 184 Neb. 172, 166 N.W.2d 411 (1969).</para><para>Allocation of cost of various utilities must be on a reasonable basis. Metropolitan Utilities Dist. v. City of Omaha, 171 Neb. 609, 107 N.W.2d 397 (1961).</para></annotation>  </law>
</legaldoc>