<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-415"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-415</statuteno><catchline>Statement of partnership authority.</catchline><para>(1) A partnership may file a statement of partnership authority, which:</para><para>(a) Must include:</para><para>(i) The name of the partnership;</para><para>(ii) The street address of its chief executive office and of one office in this state, if there is one;</para><para>(iii) The names and mailing addresses of all of the partners or the name and street address and post office box number, if any, of an agent appointed and maintained by the partnership for the purpose of subsection (2) of this section; and</para><para>(iv) The names of the partners authorized to execute an instrument transferring real property held in the name of the partnership; and</para><para>(b) May state the authority, or limitations on the authority, of some or all of the partners to enter into other transactions on behalf of the partnership and any other matter.</para><para>(2) If a statement of partnership authority names an agent, the agent shall maintain a list of the names and mailing addresses of all of the partners and make it available to any person on request for good cause shown.</para><para>(3) If a filed statement of partnership authority is executed pursuant to subsection (3) of section 67-406 and states the name of the partnership but does not contain all of the other information required by subsection (1) of this section, the statement nevertheless operates with respect to a person not a partner as provided in subsections (4) and (5) of this section.</para><para>(4) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (7) of this section, a filed statement of partnership authority supplements the authority of a partner to enter into transactions on behalf of the partnership as follows:</para><para>(a) Except for transfers of real property, a grant of authority contained in a filed statement of partnership authority is conclusive in favor of a person who gives value without knowledge to the contrary, so long as and to the extent that a limitation on that authority is not then contained in another filed statement. A filed cancellation of a limitation on authority revives the previous grant of authority; and</para><para>(b) A grant of authority to transfer real property held in the name of the partnership contained in a certified copy of a filed statement of partnership authority recorded in the office of the register of deeds is conclusive in favor of a person who gives value without knowledge to the contrary, so long as and to the extent that a certified copy of a filed statement containing a limitation on that authority is not then of record in the office of the register of deeds. The recording in the office of the register of deeds of a certified copy of a filed cancellation of a limitation on authority revives the previous grant of authority.</para><para>(5) A person not a partner is deemed to know of a limitation on the authority of a partner to transfer real property held in the name of the partnership if a certified copy of the filed statement containing the limitation on authority is of record in the office of the register of deeds.</para><para>(6) Except as otherwise provided in subsections (4) and (5) of this section and sections 67-437 and 67-443, a person not a partner is not deemed to know of a limitation on the authority of a partner merely because the limitation is contained in a filed statement.</para><para>(7) Unless earlier canceled, a filed statement of partnership authority is canceled by operation of law five years after the date on which the statement, or the most recent amendment, was filed with the Secretary of State.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 523, &#167; 15; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB383, &#167;  6.</para><effectivedate>July 18, 2008</effectivedate></source>  </law></legaldoc> 