<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-235"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-235</statuteno><catchline>Reservation of name.</catchline><para>(a) The exclusive right to the use of a name may be reserved by:</para><para>(1) Any person intending to organize a limited partnership under the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act and to adopt that name;</para><para>(2) Any domestic limited partnership or any foreign limited partnership registered in this state which, in either case, intends to adopt that name;</para><para>(3) Any foreign limited partnership intending to register in this state and currently using or intending to adopt that name; and</para><para>(4) Any person intending to organize a foreign limited partnership and intending to have it register in this state and adopt that name.</para><para>(b) The reservation shall be made by filing with the Secretary of State an application, executed by the applicant, to reserve a specified name. If the Secretary of State finds that the name is available for use by a domestic or foreign limited partnership, he or she shall reserve the name for the exclusive use of the applicant for a period of one hundred twenty days. Such reservation may be renewed or canceled by filing a notice of such fact on forms prescribed by the Secretary of State. The right to the exclusive use of a reserved name may be transferred to any other person by filing in the office of the Secretary of State a notice of the transfer executed by the applicant for whom the name was reserved and specifying the name and address of the transferee.</para><para>(c) A fee as set forth in section 67-293 shall be paid at the time of the initial reservation of any name, at the time of the renewal of any such reservation, and at the time of the filing of a notice of the transfer or cancellation of any such reservation.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 272, &#167; 3; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 8. </para></source></law></legaldoc>