<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<sectno opdate="January 1, 2011">Sec. 101.</sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-248.02"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2010</bookinfo><statuteno>67-248.02</statuteno><catchline>Merger, consolidation, or conversion; domestic
or foreign partnerships, limited partnerships, limited liability companies,
or corporations; procedure.</catchline><para>(a) One or more domestic or foreign
partnerships or limited partnerships may merge or consolidate with one or
more domestic or foreign partnerships or limited partnerships. Sections 67-446
to 67-453 shall govern the merger or consolidation.</para>
<para>(b) Pursuant to an agreement, one or more domestic or foreign limited
partnerships, limited liability companies, or corporations may merge into
or consolidate with one or more domestic or foreign limited partnerships,
limited liability companies, or corporations. If the resulting entity is a
domestic corporation, the Business Corporation Act shall govern the merger
or consolidation. If the surviving or resulting entity is a corporation, the
merger or consolidation shall be subject to sections 21-20,128 to 21-20,134.
If the surviving or resulting entity is not a domestic corporation or a limited
liability company, the board of directors of each domestic corporation party
to such merger or consolidation shall, by resolution adopted by each such
board, approve a plan of merger or plan of consolidation setting forth information
substantially similar to that required by sections 21-20,128 to 21-20,134.
If the surviving or resulting entity is a limited liability company, the Limited
Liability Company Act or the
Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act shall govern the
merger or consolidation. Unless otherwise provided in the partnership agreement,
a plan of merger or plan of consolidation shall be approved by each domestic
limited partnership which is to merge or consolidate (1) by all general partners
and (2) by limited partners or, if there is more than one class or group of
limited partners, then by limited partners of each class or group of limited
partners, in either case, who own more than fifty percent of the then current
percentage or other interest in the profits of the domestic limited partnership
owned by all of the limited partners or by the limited partners in each class
or group, as appropriate. Notwithstanding prior approval, an agreement or
plan of merger or agreement or plan of consolidation may be terminated or
amended pursuant to a provision for such termination or amendment contained
in the agreement or plan of merger or agreement or plan of consolidation.</para>
<para>(c) If the surviving or resulting entity of a merger or consolidation
pursuant to subsection (b) of this section is not a domestic limited partnership,
limited liability company, or corporation following a merger or consolidation
of one or more domestic limited partnerships, limited liability companies,
or corporations and one or more foreign limited partnerships, limited liability
companies, or corporations, the surviving or resulting entity shall comply
with sections 21-20,128 to 21-20,134 and, for each such domestic limited partnership,
a certificate shall be executed and filed in the office of the Secretary of
State by the surviving or resulting limited partnership, limited liability
company, or corporation stating that the surviving or resulting limited partnership,
limited liability company, or corporation agrees that it may be served with
process within or outside this state in any proceeding in the courts of this
state for the enforcement of any obligation of such former domestic limited
partnership.</para>
<para>(d) A merger or consolidation pursuant to subsection (b) of this section
to which a domestic corporation is a party shall become effective as provided
in sections 21-20,128 to 21-20,134. A merger, consolidation, or conversion  to which
a domestic limited liability company is a party shall become effective as
provided in sections 21-170
to 21-184 or 21-2647 to 21-2653. Any other merger or consolidation
provided for in the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act shall become
effective as provided in the agreement or plan of merger or consolidation.
When such merger, consolidation, or conversion  has become
effective, the terms of sections 21-20,128 to 21-20,134 shall apply if the
surviving or resulting entity is a corporation, the terms of section 21-174, 21-178, or 21-2651
shall apply if the surviving or resulting entity is a limited liability company,
and the following provisions shall apply if the surviving or resulting entity
is a limited partnership:</para>
<para>(1) The several limited partnerships, limited liability companies, or
corporations which are parties to the merger or consolidation agreement shall
be a single limited partnership which, in the case of a merger, shall be that
limited partnership designated in the merger agreement as the surviving limited
partnership and, in the case of a consolidation, shall be the new limited
partnership provided for in the consolidation agreement;</para>
<para>(2) The separate existence of all limited partnerships, limited liability
companies, and corporations which are parties to the merger or consolidation
agreement, except the surviving or new limited partnership, shall cease;</para>
<para>(3) If the surviving or new limited partnership is a domestic limited
partnership, it shall have all the rights, privileges, immunities, and powers
and shall be subject to all the duties and liabilities of a limited partnership
organized under the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act;</para>
<para>(4) The surviving or new limited partnership shall possess all the rights,
privileges, immunities, and powers, of a public as well as of a private nature,
of each of the merging or consolidating limited partnerships and, subject
to the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act, each of the merging or consolidating
corporations. All property, real, personal, and mixed, all debts due on whatever
account, all other things and causes of actions, and all and every other interest
belonging to or due to any of the limited partnerships, limited liability
companies, and corporations as merged or consolidated shall be taken and deemed
to be transferred to and vested in the surviving or new limited partnership
without further act and deed and shall thereafter be the property of the surviving
or new limited partnership as they were of any of such merging or consolidating
entities. The title to any real property or any interest in such property
vested in any of such merging or consolidating entities shall not revert or
be in any way impaired by reason of such merger or consolidation;</para>
<para>(5) Such surviving or new limited partnership shall be responsible and
liable for all the liabilities and obligations of each of the limited partnerships,
limited liability companies, or corporations so merged or consolidated. Any
claim existing or action or proceeding pending by or against any of such limited
partnerships, limited liability companies, or corporations may be prosecuted
as if such merger or consolidation had not taken place or such surviving or
new limited partnership may be substituted in its place. Neither the rights
of creditors nor any liens upon the property of any such limited partnerships,
limited liability companies, or corporations shall be impaired by such merger
or consolidation; and</para>
<para>(6) The equity securities of the corporation or corporations, limited
liability company or companies, and limited partnership or limited partnerships
party to the merger or consolidation that are, under the terms of the merger
or consolidation, to be converted or exchanged shall cease to exist, and the
holders of such equity securities shall thereafter be entitled only to the
cash, property, or securities into which they shall have been converted in
accordance with the terms of the merger or consolidation, subject to any rights
under sections 21-20,137 to 21-20,150, the Limited Liability Company
Act, or the Nebraska Uniform
Limited Liability Company Act.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 23; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1228, &#167; 6; </para><para>Laws 1994, LB 884, &#167; 84; </para><para>Laws 1995, LB 109, &#167; 227; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 523, &#167; 69; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB888, &#167; 101.</para></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Limited Liability Company Act,</emphasis> see section 21-2601.</para><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act,</emphasis> see section 21-101.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>