<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-245"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-245</statuteno><catchline>Filing in office of Secretary of State; facsimile signature.</catchline><para>(a) Two signed copies of the certificate of limited partnership and of any certificates of amendment or cancellation, of any restated certificates of limited partnership, or of any judicial decree of amendment or cancellation shall be delivered to the Secretary of State. A person who executes a certificate as an agent, attorney in fact, or fiduciary need not exhibit evidence of his or her authority as a prerequisite to filing. Unless the Secretary of State finds that any certificate does not conform to law, upon receipt of all filing fees required by law he or she shall:</para><para>(1) Certify that the certificate of limited partnership, the certificate of amendment, the restated certificate of limited partnership, or the certificate of cancellation or any judicial decree of amendment or cancellation has been filed in his or her office by endorsing upon both duplicate originals the word Filed and the date of the filing. This endorsement shall be conclusive of the date of its filing in the absence of proof of actual fraud;</para><para>(2) File one duplicate original in his or her office; and</para><para>(3) Return the other duplicate original to the person who filed it or his or her representative.</para><para>(b) Upon the later of the filing of a certificate of amendment or judicial decree of amendment in the office of the Secretary of State or the future effective date of a certificate of amendment or judicial decree of amendment, the certificate of limited partnership shall be amended as set forth in such certificate or decree, and upon the later of the filing of a certificate of cancellation or judicial decree of cancellation or upon the future effective date of a certificate of cancellation or a judicial decree of cancellation, the certificate of limited partnership shall be canceled.</para><para>(c) A fee as set forth in section 67-293 shall be paid at the time of the filing of a certificate of limited partnership, a certificate of amendment, or a certificate of cancellation.</para><para>(d) Any signature on any certificate authorized to be filed with the Secretary of State under any provision of the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act may be a facsimile.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 272, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 18; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1228, &#167; 4. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 