<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-439"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-439</statuteno><catchline>Events causing dissolution and winding up of partnership business.</catchline><para>A partnership is dissolved, and its business must be wound up, only upon the occurrence of any of the following events:</para><para>(1) In a partnership at will, the partnership's having notice from a partner, other than a partner who is dissociated under subdivisions (2) through (10) of section 67-431, of that partner's express will to withdraw as a partner, or on a later date specified by the partner;</para><para>(2) In a partnership for a definite term or particular undertaking:</para><para>(a) Within ninety days after a partner's dissociation by death or otherwise under subdivisions (6) through (10) of section 67-431 or wrongful dissociation under subsection (2) of section 67-432, the express will of at least a majority of the remaining partners to wind up the partnership business, for which purpose a partner's rightful dissociation pursuant to subdivision (2)(b)(i) of section 67-432 constitutes the expression of that partner's will to wind up the partnership business;</para><para>(b) The express will of all of the partners to wind up the partnership business; or</para><para>(c) The expiration of the term or the completion of the undertaking;</para><para>(3) An event agreed to in the partnership agreement resulting in the winding up of the partnership business;</para><para>(4) An event that makes it unlawful for all or substantially all of the business of the partnership to be continued, but a cure of illegality within ninety days after notice to the partnership of the event is effective retroactively to the date of the event for purposes of this section;</para><para>(5) On application by a partner, a judicial determination that:</para><para>(a) The economic purpose of the partnership is likely to be unreasonably frustrated;</para><para>(b) Another partner has engaged in conduct relating to the partnership business which makes it not reasonably practicable to carry on the business in partnership with that partner; or</para><para>(c) It is not otherwise reasonably practicable to carry on the partnership business in conformity with the partnership agreement; or</para><para>(6) On application by a transferee of a partner's transferable interest, a judicial determination that it is equitable to wind up the partnership business:</para><para>(a) After the expiration of the term or completion of the undertaking, if the partnership was for a definite term or particular undertaking at the time of the transfer or entry of the charging order that gave rise to the transfer; or</para><para>(b) At any time, if the partnership was a partnership at will at the time of the transfer or entry of the charging order that gave rise to the transfer.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 523, &#167; 39. </para></source><annotation><para>When grounds for both dissociation and dissolution of a partnership exist, a court may exercise its discretion to determine the appropriate remedy. Robertson v. Jacobs Cattle Co., 285 Neb. 859, 830 N.W.2d 191 (2013).</para><para>Dissolution of a partnership for a partner's voluntary withdrawal under subsection (1) of this section is a default rule that applies only when the partnership agreement does not provide for the partnership business to continue. Shoemaker v. Shoemaker, 275 Neb. 112, 745 N.W.2d 299 (2008).</para><para>The 1998 Uniform Partnership Act does not require remaining partners to strictly comply with a buyout provision in a partnership agreement to prevent dissolution upon the voluntary withdrawal of a partner; strict compliance is inconsistent with the act's provision of remedies for the withdrawing partner. Shoemaker v. Shoemaker, 275 Neb. 112, 745 N.W.2d 299 (2008).</para></annotation></law></legaldoc> 