<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" id="id192" publishedsource="CumulativeSupplement" statutenumber="67-298">
<bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2013</bookinfo><statuteno>67-298</statuteno><catchline>Conversion; articles of conversion.</catchline><para>(a) After a plan of conversion is approved, a domestic limited partnership
that is being converted shall deliver to the Secretary of State for filing
articles of conversion which shall include all of the following:</para>
<para>(1) A statement that the domestic limited partnership has been converted
into another entity;</para>
<para>(2) The name and form of the other entity and the jurisdiction of its
governing statute;</para>
<para>(3) The date the conversion is effective under the governing statute
of the converted entity;</para>
<para>(4) A statement that the conversion was approved as required by sections
67-446 to 67-453;</para>
<para>(5) A statement that the conversion was approved as required by the
governing statute of the converted entity; and</para>
<para>(6) A domestic limited partnership converting into a foreign limited
liability company shall deliver to the office of the Secretary of State for
filing (A) a certificate which sets forth all of the information required
to be in the certificate or other instrument of conversion filed pursuant
to the laws under which the resulting foreign limited liability company is
formed and (B) an agreement that the resulting foreign limited liability company
may be served with process within or outside this state in any proceeding
in the courts of this state for the enforcement of any obligation of the former
domestic corporation.</para>
<para>(b) The conversion shall become effective as provided by the Nebraska
Uniform Limited Liability Company Act, the Uniform Partnership Act of 1998,
or the governing statute of the foreign limited liability company.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2012, LB1018, &#167; 11; </para><para>Laws 2013, LB283, &#167; 3.</para><effectivedate>September 6, 2013</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Uniform Limited Liability Company Act,</emphasis> see section 21-101.</para><para><emphasis>Uniform Partnership Act of 1998,</emphasis> see section 67-401.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>