<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno></sectno><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-241"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-241</statuteno><catchline>Amendments to certificate; restated certificate.</catchline><para>(a) A certificate of limited partnership is amended by filing a certificate of amendment thereto in the office of the Secretary of State. The certificate of amendment shall be executed by any person who will be a general partner upon the effective date of the certificate of amendment and shall set forth:</para><para>(1) The name of the limited partnership;</para><para>(2) The date of filing the certificate; and</para><para>(3) The amendment to the certificate.</para><para>(b) Within ninety days after the happening of any of the following events, an amendment to a certificate of limited partnership reflecting the occurrence of the event or events shall be filed by any person who will be a general partner upon the effective date of the certificate of amendment and by each other general partner designated in the certificate of amendment as a new general partner:</para><para>(1) The admission of a new general partner;</para><para>(2) A general partner ceases to be a general partner as provided in section 67-255; or</para><para>(3) A change in the name of the limited partnership, a change in the address of its registered office, or a change in the name or street address or post office box number, if any, of the registered agent for service of process required to be maintained by section 67-236 which is not reflected in a certificate filed pursuant to section 67-236.</para><para>(c) A general partner who becomes aware that any statement in a certificate of limited partnership was false when made or that any matter described has changed, making the certificate false in any respect, shall promptly amend the certificate.</para><para>(d) A certificate of limited partnership may be amended at any time for any other proper purpose the general partners determine.</para><para>(e) No person has any liability because an amendment to a certificate of limited partnership has not been filed to reflect the occurrence of any event referred to in subsection (b) of this section if the amendment is filed within the ninety-day period specified in subsection (b) of this section.</para><para>(f) A certificate of amendment shall be effective at the time of its filing with the Secretary of State or at any later time specified in the certificate of amendment if, in either case, there has been substantial compliance with the requirements of this section.</para><para>(g) A restated certificate of limited partnership may be executed and filed in the same manner as a certificate of amendment.</para><para>(h) If after the dissolution of a limited partnership but prior to the filing of a certificate of cancellation as provided in section 67-242:</para><para>(1) A certificate of limited partnership has been amended to reflect the withdrawal of all general partners of a limited partnership, the certificate of limited partnership shall be amended to set forth the name and the business, residence, or mailing address of each person winding up the limited partnership affairs, each of whom shall execute and file such certificate of amendment, and each of whom shall not be subject to liability as a general partner by reason of such amendment; or</para><para>(2) A person shown on a certificate of limited partnership as a general partner is not winding up the limited partnership's affairs, the certificate of limited partnership shall be amended to add the name and the business, residence, or mailing address of each person winding up the limited partnership's affairs, each of whom shall execute and file such certificate of amendment, and each of whom shall not be subject to liability as a general partner by reason of such amendment.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 272, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 14; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB383, &#167; 3.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc> 