<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-236"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-236</statuteno><catchline>Specified office and agent.</catchline><para>(a) Each limited partnership shall have and maintain in this state:</para><para>(1) An office which may but need not be a place of its business in this state; and</para><para>(2) An agent for service of process on the limited partnership, which agent must be an individual resident of this state, a domestic corporation, a foreign corporation authorized to do business in this state, a domestic limited liability company, or a foreign limited liability company authorized to do business in this state.</para><para>(b) The agent for service of process may change his, her, or its street address and post office box number, if any, to another street address and post office box number, if any, in this state by paying a fee as set forth in section 67-293 and filing with the Secretary of State a certificate, executed by the agent, setting forth the names of the limited partnerships represented by the agent, the street address and post office box number, if any, at which the agent has maintained his, her, or its office as agent for each of such limited partnerships, and the new street address and post office box number, if any, to which the office will be changed on a given day, at which new street address and post office box number, if any, the agent will thereafter maintain his, her, or its office as agent for each of the limited partnerships recited in the certificate. Upon the filing of the certificate, the Secretary of State shall furnish to the agent a copy of the same, and thereafter or until further change of street address or post office box number, if any, as authorized by law, the office in this state of the agent for service of process for each of the limited partnerships recited in the certificate shall be located at the new street address and post office box number, if any. Filing of the certificate shall be deemed to be an amendment of the certificate of limited partnership of each limited partnership affected thereby, and each such limited partnership shall not be required to take any further action to amend its certificate of limited partnership. Any agent filing a certificate under this section shall promptly, upon the filing, deliver a copy of such certificate to each limited partnership affected thereby.</para><para>(c) The agent of one or more limited partnerships may resign and appoint a successor agent by paying a fee as set forth in section 67-293 and filing a certificate with the Secretary of State, stating that the agent is resigning and the name and street address and post office box number, if any, of the successor agent. There shall be attached to such certificate a statement executed by each affected limited partnership ratifying and approving such change of agent. Upon such filing, the successor agent shall become the agent of such limited partnerships as have ratified and approved such substitution and the successor agent's address, as stated in such certificate, shall become the address of each such limited partnership's office in this state. The Secretary of State shall furnish to the successor agent a copy of the certificate of resignation. Filing of the certificate of resignation shall be deemed to be an amendment of the certificate of limited partnership of each limited partnership affected thereby, and each such limited partnership shall not be required to take any further action to amend its certificate of limited partnership.</para><para>(d) The agent of one or more limited partnerships may resign without appointing a successor agent by paying a fee as set forth in section 67-293 and filing a certificate with the Secretary of State stating that the agent is resigning as agent for the limited partnerships identified in the certificate, but such resignation shall not become effective until one hundred twenty days after the certificate is filed. There shall be attached to the certificate an affidavit of the agent, if an individual, or of the president, a vice president, or the secretary, if a corporation, or of the manager or a member, if a limited liability company, that, at least thirty days prior to the date of filing of the certificate, notice of the resignation of the agent was sent by certified or registered mail to each limited partnership for which the agent is resigning as agent at the principal office thereof within or outside this state if known to such agent or, if not, to the last-known address of the attorney or other individual at whose request the agent was appointed for such limited partnership. After receipt of the notice of the resignation of its agent, the limited partnership for which the agent was acting shall obtain and designate a new agent to take the place of the agent so resigning. If the limited partnership fails to obtain and designate a new agent prior to the expiration of the period of one hundred twenty days after the filing of the certificate of resignation, the certificate of such limited partnership shall be deemed to be canceled.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 272, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 9; </para><para>Laws 1990, LB 1228, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 402; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB383, &#167; 1.</para></source>  </law></legaldoc>