<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-406"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-406</statuteno><catchline>Execution, filing, and recording of statements.</catchline><para>(1) A statement may be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. A certified copy of a statement that is filed in an office in another state may be filed in the office of the Secretary of State. Either filing has the effect provided in the Uniform Partnership Act of 1998 with respect to partnership property located in or transactions that occur in this state.</para><para>(2) For transfers of real property, a certified copy of a statement that has been filed in the office of the Secretary of State and recorded in the office of the register of deeds has the effect provided for recorded statements in the act. A recorded statement that is not a certified copy of a statement filed in the office of the Secretary of State does not have the effect provided for recorded statements in the act.</para><para>(3) A statement filed by a partnership must be executed by at least two partners. Other statements must be executed by a partner or other person authorized by the act. An individual who executes a statement as, or on behalf of, a partner or other person named as a partner in a statement shall personally declare under penalty of perjury that the contents of the statement are accurate.</para><para>(4) A person authorized by the act to file a statement may amend or cancel the statement by filing an amendment or cancellation that names the partnership, identifies the statement, and states the substance of the amendment or cancellation.</para><para>(5) A person who files a statement pursuant to this section shall promptly send a copy of the statement to every nonfiling partner and to any other person named as a partner in the statement. Failure to send a copy of a statement to a partner or other person does not limit the effectiveness of the statement as to a person not a partner.</para><para>(6) The Secretary of State may collect a fee for filing or providing a certified copy of a statement as provided in section 67-462. The register of deeds may collect a fee for recording a statement as provided in section 33-109.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 523, &#167; 6. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 