<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!DOCTYPE legaldoc PUBLIC "Nebraska Unicameral//DTD legaldoc XML v1.0//EN" "legaldoc.dtd"> <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><sectno/><amendatorysection chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-274"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-274</statuteno><catchline>Assignee becoming limited partner; rights and liabilities.</catchline><para>(a) An assignee of a partnership interest, including an assignee of a general partner, may become a limited partner if and to the extent that (1) the partnership agreement so provides or (2) all other partners consent. An assignee of a partnership interest becomes a limited partner at the time provided in and upon compliance with the partnership agreement or, if the partnership agreement does not so provide, when all other partners consent to such person's admission as a limited partner and such person's admission as a limited partner is reflected in the records of the limited partnership.</para><para>(b) An assignee who has become a limited partner has, to the extent assigned, the rights and powers, and is subject to the restrictions and liabilities, of a limited partner under the partnership agreement and the Nebraska Uniform Limited Partnership Act. An assignee who becomes a limited partner also is liable for the obligations of his or her assignor to make contributions as provided in section 67-260 but is not liable for the obligations of his or her assignor under section 67-270. However, the assignee is not obligated for liabilities unknown to the assignee at the time he or she became a limited partner and which could not be ascertained from the partnership agreement.</para><para>(c) Whether or not an assignee of a partnership interest becomes a limited partner, the assignor is not released from his or her liability to the limited partnership under section 67-260 unless otherwise provided in the partnership agreement.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 272, &#167; 42; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 47. </para></source></law></legaldoc> 