<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>  <legaldoc><law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-452"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-452</statuteno><catchline>Statement of merger.</catchline><para>(1) After a merger, the surviving partnership or limited partnership may file a statement that one or more partnerships or limited partnerships have merged into the surviving entity.</para><para>(2) A statement of merger must contain:</para><para>(a) The name of each partnership or limited partnership that is a party to the merger;</para><para>(b) The name of the surviving entity into which the other partnerships or limited partnership were merged;</para><para>(c) The street address of the surviving entity's chief executive office and of an office in this state, if any; and</para><para>(d) Whether the surviving entity is a partnership or a limited partnership.</para><para>(3) Except as otherwise provided in subsection (4) of this section, for the purposes of section 67-414, property of the surviving partnership or limited partnership which before the merger was held in the name of another party to the merger is property held in the name of the surviving entity upon filing a statement of merger.</para><para>(4) For the purposes of section 67-414, real property of the surviving partnership or limited partnership which before the merger was held in the name of another party to the merger is property held in the name of the surviving entity upon recording a certified copy of the statement of merger in the office of the register of deeds.</para><para>(5) A filed and, if appropriate, recorded statement of merger, executed and declared to be accurate pursuant to subsection (3) of section 67-406, stating the name of a partnership or limited partnership that is a party to the merger in whose name property was held before the merger and the name of the surviving entity, but not containing all of the other information required by subsection (2) of this section, operates with respect to the partnerships or limited partnerships named to the extent provided in subsections (3) and (4) of this section.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 523, &#167; 52. </para></source></law></legaldoc>