<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" statutenumber="67-456"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2014</bookinfo><statuteno>67-456</statuteno><catchline>Annual report; certificate of authority.</catchline>
<para>(1) A limited liability partnership, and a foreign limited liability
partnership authorized to transact business in this state, shall file an annual
report in the office of the Secretary of State which contains:</para>
<para>(a) The name of the limited liability partnership and the state or other
jurisdiction under whose laws the foreign limited liability partnership is
formed;</para>
<para>(b) The street address of the partnership's chief executive office and,
if different, the street address of an office of the partnership in this state,
if any; and</para>
<para>(c) If the partnership does not have an office in this state, the name
and street address and post office box number, if any, of the partnership's
current agent for service of process.</para>
<para>(2) Any limited liability partnership, or foreign limited liability
partnership authorized to transact business in this state, engaging in the
practice of law in this state shall file with its annual report a current
certificate of authority from the Nebraska Supreme Court.</para>
<para>(3) An annual report and certificate of authority, if applicable, must
be filed between January 1 and April 1 of each year following the calendar
year in which a partnership files a statement of qualification or a foreign
partnership becomes authorized to transact business in this state.</para>
<para>(4) The Secretary of State may revoke the statement of qualification
of a partnership that fails to file an annual report and certificate of authority,
if applicable, when due or pay the required filing fee provided in section
67-462. To do so, the Secretary of State shall provide the partnership at
least sixty days' written notice of intent to revoke the statement. The notice
must be mailed to the partnership at its chief executive office set forth
in the last filed statement of qualification or annual report. The notice
must specify the annual report or certificate of authority, if applicable,
that has not been filed, the fee that has not been paid, and the effective
date of the revocation. The revocation is not effective if the annual report
and certificate of authority, if applicable, is filed and the fee is paid
before the effective date of the revocation.</para>
<para>(5) A revocation under subsection (4) of this section only affects a
partnership's status as a limited liability partnership and is not an event
of dissolution of the partnership.</para>
<para>(6) A partnership whose statement of qualification has been revoked
may apply to the Secretary of State for reinstatement within two years after
the effective date of the revocation. The application must state:</para>
<para>(a) The name of the partnership and the effective date of the revocation;
and</para>
<para>(b) That the ground for revocation either did not exist or has been
corrected.</para>
<para>(7) A reinstatement under subsection (6) of this section relates back
to and takes effect as of the effective date of the revocation, and the partnership's
status as a limited liability partnership continues as if the revocation had
never occurred.</para>
<para>(8) A correction or an
amendment to the annual report may be filed at any time.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1997, LB 523, &#167; 56; </para><para>Laws 2004, LB 16, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2008, LB383, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 2014, LB774, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>