<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id93">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Partnerships" id="id95" statutenumber="67-234"><bookinfo>Reissue Revised Statutes of Nebraska</bookinfo><statuteno>67-234</statuteno><catchline id="id98">Limited partnership
name.</catchline><para>The name of each limited partnership as set
forth in its certificate of limited partnership:</para>
<para>(1) Shall contain the words limited partnership or limited
or the abbreviations L.P. or Ltd.;</para>
<para>(2) May not contain the name of a limited partner unless
(i) it is also the name of a general partner, the corporate name of a corporate
general partner, or the company name of a limited liability company general
partner, (ii) the business of the limited partnership had been carried on
under that name before the admission of that limited partner, or (iii) the
use of the name of a limited partner in the name of the limited partnership
is merely coincidental and not intended to mislead the public to believe that
such limited partner is a general partner;</para>
<para>(3) Shall not be the same as or deceptively similar to, upon
the records in the office of the Secretary of State, a trade name registered
in this state pursuant to sections 87-208 to 87-219.01;</para>
<para>(4) Shall not be the same as or deceptively similar to, upon
the records in the office of the Secretary of State, any other business entity
name registered or on file with the Secretary of State pursuant to Nebraska
law, except that a limited partnership may register under any name which is
deceptively similar to, upon the records in the office of the Secretary of
State, a business entity name registered or on file with the Secretary of
State pursuant to Nebraska law with the consent of the other business entity
or with the transfer of such name by the other business entity, which written
consent or transfer shall be filed with the Secretary of State; and</para>
<para>(5) May contain the following words or abbreviations of like
import: Company; association; club; foundation; fund; institute; society;
union; syndicate; or trust.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1981, LB 272, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1989, LB 482, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 1993, LB 121, &#167; 401; </para><para>Laws 1997, LB 44, &#167; 10; </para><para>Laws 2003, LB 464, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, LB462, &#167; 5.</para></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>