<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section>
<amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lettings And Contracts" statutenumber="73-107"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2016</bookinfo><statuteno>73-107</statuteno><catchline>Resident disabled veteran or business
located in designated enterprise zone; preference; contract not in compliance
with section; null and void.</catchline><para>(1) When a state contract is to be awarded to the lowest
responsible bidder, a resident disabled veteran or a business located in a
designated enterprise zone under the Enterprise Zone Act shall be allowed
a preference over any other resident or nonresident bidder if all other factors
are equal.</para>
<para>(2) For purposes of this
section, resident disabled veteran means any person (a) who resides in the
State of Nebraska, who served in the United States Armed Forces, including
any reserve component or the National Guard, who was discharged or otherwise
separated with a characterization of honorable or general (under honorable
conditions), and who possesses a disability rating letter issued by the United
States Department of Veterans Affairs establishing a service-connected disability
or a disability determination from the United States Department of Defense
and (b)(i) who owns and controls a business or, in the case of a publicly
owned business, more than fifty percent of the stock is owned by one or more
persons described in subdivision (a) of this subsection and (ii) the management
and daily business operations of the business are controlled by one or more
persons described in subdivision (a) of this subsection.</para>
<para>(3) Any contract entered
into without compliance with this section shall be null and void.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2013, LB224, &#167; 1.</para></source> <crossreference><para><emphasis>Enterprise Zone Act,</emphasis> see section 13-2101.01.</para></crossreference> </law>
</legaldoc>