<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id34">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lettings and Contracts" id="id36" statutenumber="73-507"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>73-507</statuteno><catchline id="id39">Exceptions.</catchline>
<para>(1) Subject to review by the Director of Administrative Services,
the materiel division shall provide procedures to grant limited exceptions
from the provisions of sections 73-504, 73-508, and 73-509 for:</para>
<para>(a) Sole source and emergency contracts; and</para>
<para>(b) Other circumstances or specific contracts when any of
the requirements of sections 73-504, 73-508, and 73-509 are not appropriate
for or are not compatible with the circumstances or contract. The materiel
division shall provide a written rationale which shall be kept on file when
granting an exception under this subdivision.</para>
<para>(2) The following types of contracts for services are not
subject to sections 73-504, 73-508, and 73-509:</para>
<para>(a) Contracts for services subject to the Nebraska Consultants'
Competitive Negotiation Act;</para>
<para>(b) Contracts for services subject to federal law, regulation,
or policy or state statute, under which a state agency is required to use
a different selection process or to contract with an identified contractor
or type of contractor;</para>
<para>(c) Contracts for professional legal services and services
of expert witnesses, hearing officers, or administrative law judges retained
by state agencies for administrative or court proceedings;</para>
<para>(d) Contracts involving state or federal financial assistance
passed through by a state agency to a political subdivision;</para>
<para>(e) Contracts with direct providers of medical, behavioral,
or developmental health services, child care, or child welfare services to
an individual;</para>
<para>(f) Agreements for services to be performed for a state agency
by another state or local government agency or contracts made by a state agency
with a local government agency for the direct provision of services to the
public;</para>
<para>(g) Agreements for services between a state agency and the
University of Nebraska, the Nebraska state colleges, the courts, the Legislature,
or other officers or agencies established by the Constitution of Nebraska;</para>
<para>(h) Department of Insurance contracts for financial or actuarial
examination, for rehabilitation, conservation, reorganization, or liquidation
of licensees, and for professional services related to residual pools or excess
funds under the agency's control;</para>
<para>(i) Department of Roads contracts for all road and bridge
projects;</para>
<para>(j) Nebraska Investment Council contracts; and</para>
<para>(k) Contracts
under section 57-1503.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 626, &#167; 7; </para><para>Laws 2011, First Spec. Sess., LB4, &#167; 5.</para><effectivedate>November 23, 2011</effectivedate></source><crossreference><para><emphasis>Nebraska Consultants' Competitive Negotiation Act,</emphasis> see section 81-1702.</para></crossreference>  </law>
</legaldoc>