<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lettings and Contracts" statutenumber="73-808"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>73-808</statuteno><catchline>Competitive bids; award to responsible bidders; considerations; responsibility; elements considered; energy star certified appliances.</catchline><para>(1) All contracts which by law are required to be based on competitive bids shall be made only to responsible bidders, taking into consideration, as applicable:</para><para>(a) The best interests of the state;</para><para>(b) The quality or performance of the personal property or services proposed to be supplied;</para><para>(c) The conformity with the solicitation;</para><para>(d) The purposes for which required;</para><para>(e) The times of delivery;</para><para>(f) The life-cycle costs of the personal property in relation to the purchase price and specific use of the item;</para><para>(g) The performance of the personal property, taking into consideration any commonly accepted tests and standards of product usability and user requirements;</para><para>(h) The energy efficiency ratio as stated by the bidder for alternative choices of appliances or equipment;</para><para>(i) The information furnished by each bidder concerning life-cycle costs between alternatives for all classes of equipment, evidence of expected life, repair and maintenance costs, and energy consumption on a per-year basis;</para><para>(j) The results of the United States Environmental Protection Agency tests on fleet performance of motor vehicles. Each bidder shall furnish information relating to such results; and</para><para>(k) Such other information as may be secured having a bearing on the decision to award the contract.</para><para>(2) In determining responsibility, the following elements shall be given consideration:</para><para>(a) The ability, capacity, and skill of the bidder to perform the contract required;</para><para>(b) The character, integrity, reputation, judgment, experience, and efficiency of the bidder;</para><para>(c) Whether the bidder can perform the contract within the time specified;</para><para>(d) The quality of performance of previous contracts; and</para><para>(e) The previous and existing compliance by the bidder with laws relating to the contract.</para><para>(3) Any appliance purchased or leased pursuant to this section shall be energy star certified, except that the materiel administrator may exempt the purchase or lease of an appliance from this subsection if he or she determines that the cost of compliance would exceed the projected energy cost savings.</para><para>(4) All political subdivisions may follow the procurement principles set forth in this section if they are deemed applicable by the official authorized to make purchases for such political subdivision.</para><para>(5) For purposes of this section, energy star certified means approval of energy usage by the United States Environmental Protection Agency and the United States Department of Energy. Such approval may be signified by the display of the energy star label.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1943, c. 215, &#167; 17, p. 709; </para><para>R.S.1943, &#167; 81-161; </para><para>Laws 1963, c. 508, &#167; 9, p. 1619; </para><para>Laws 1969, c. 780, &#167; 3, p. 2955; </para><para>Laws 1975, LB 359, &#167; 8; </para><para>Laws 1980, LB 954, &#167; 60; </para><para>Laws 1992, LB 1241, &#167; 17; </para><para>Laws 2000, LB 654, &#167; 13; </para><para>Laws 2010, LB978, &#167; 1; </para><para>R.S.1943, (2014), &#167; 81-161; </para><para>Laws 2024, LB461, &#167; 8. </para><effectivedate>July 19, 2024</effectivedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>