<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id512"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lettings and Contracts" statutenumber="73-907"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2024</bookinfo><statuteno>73-907</statuteno><catchline>Violations of act; contract; null and void; liability; action; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) Any contract entered into in violation of the Foreign Adversary Contracting Prohibition Act shall be null and void.</para><para>(2) Any scrutinized company that violates section 73-904 or that violates the certification provided pursuant to section 73-905:</para><para>(a) Shall be liable for a civil penalty in an amount equal to the highest of the following three amounts:</para><para>(i) Two hundred fifty thousand dollars;</para><para>(ii) Twice the amount of the contract for which a bid or proposal was submitted; or</para><para>(iii) The amount of any losses suffered by the public entity as a result of such violation; and</para><para>(b) Shall be ineligible to enter into any contract with any public entity for a period of five years.</para><para>(3) The Attorney General may bring an action in any court of competent jurisdiction against any person that violates the Foreign Adversary Contracting Prohibition Act.</para><para>(4) If a public entity believes that a company has violated the certification provided pursuant to section 73-905, the public entity shall give such company notice of the alleged violation. The company shall then have sixty days to respond to the notice. The public entity shall make a final determination on whether a violation of such certification has occurred within sixty days after receipt of the response from the company. If the public entity determines that a violation has occurred, the public entity may refer the matter to the Attorney General.</para><para>(5) Any individual may act as a whistleblower and report suspected violations of section 73-904 or suspected violations of the certification provided pursuant to section 73-905 to the Attorney General. If the reported violation results in a civil penalty under this section, the whistleblower shall be entitled to a reward equal to thirty percent of the civil penalty assessed.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2024, LB1300, &#167; 13. </para></source></law>
</legaldoc>