<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute">
<section id="id64">
<amendatorysection amended="yes" chaptername="Public Lettings and Contracts" id="id66" statutenumber="73-504"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Cumulative Supplement, 2012</bookinfo><statuteno>73-504</statuteno><catchline id="id69">Competitive bidding
requirements.</catchline><para>Except as provided in section 73-507:</para>
<para>(1) All state agencies shall comply with the review and competitive
bidding processes provided in this section for contracts for services. Unless
otherwise exempt, no state agency shall expend funds for contracts for services
without complying with this section;</para>
<para>(2) All proposed state agency contracts for services in excess
of fifty thousand dollars shall be bid in the manner prescribed by the division procurement
manual or a process approved by the Director of Administrative Services. Bidding
may be performed at the state agency level or by the division. Any state agency may request
that the division
conduct the competitive bidding process;</para>
<para>(3) If the bidding process is at the state agency level, then
state agency directors shall ensure that bid documents for each contract for
services in excess of fifty thousand dollars are prereviewed by the division and that
any changes to the proposed contract that differ from the bid documents in
the proposed contract for services are reviewed by the division before signature by the parties;</para>
<para>(4) State agency directors, in cooperation with the division, shall be
responsible for appropriate public notice of an impending contractual services
project in excess of fifty thousand dollars in accordance with the division's procurement
manual and sections 73-501 to 73-510; and</para>
<para>(5) State agency directors, in cooperation with the division, shall be
responsible for ensuring that a request for contractual services in excess
of fifty thousand dollars is filed with the division
for dissemination or web site access to vendors interested in competing for
contracts for services.</para>
</amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2003, LB 626, &#167; 4; </para><para>Laws 2012, LB858, &#167; 8.</para><effectivedate>July 19, 2012</effectivedate></source>  </law>
</legaldoc>