<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<legaldoc>
    <law type="statute"><section><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lettings And Contracts" statutenumber="73-106" amended="yes" id="id00"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2015</bookinfo><statuteno>73-106</statuteno><catchline id="id00">School district; construction, remodeling, or repair of building; advertise for bids; applicability.</catchline><para>(1) Whenever any public school district in the state expends public funds for the construction, remodeling, or repair of any school-owned building or for site improvements, other than those expenditures authorized by section 81-829.51 for emergency expenditures or section 79-10,104 for facilities which are not to be owned by the district following their completion, the school board or its representative shall advertise for bids in the regular manner established by the board and accept or reject bids pursuant to section 73-101.</para><para>(2) This section does not apply to any construction, remodeling, or repair of any school-owned building or site improvements in which the contemplated expenditure for the complete project does not exceed one hundred thousand dollars. The State Board of Education shall adjust the dollar amount in this subsection every fifth year. The first such adjustment after August 30, 2015, shall be effective on July 1, 2020. The adjusted amount shall be equal to the then current amount adjusted by the cumulative percentage change in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Federal Bureau of Labor Statistics for the five-year period preceding the adjustment date. The amount shall be rounded to the next highest one-thousand-dollar amount.</para><para>(3) This section does not apply to the acquisition of existing buildings, purchase of new sites, or site expansions by the school district.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 1979, LB 130, &#167; 1; </para><para>Laws 1981, LB 218, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 1996, LB 900, &#167; 1061; </para><para>Laws 2001, LB 420, &#167; 34; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB283, &#167; 2; </para><para>Laws 2015, LB431, &#167; 1. </para><note>The Revisor of Statutes has pursuant to section 49-769 correlated LB283, section 2, with LB431, section 1, to reflect all amendments.</note><note>Changes made by LB283 became effective May 27, 2015. Changes made by LB431 became effective August 30, 2015.</note></source></law>
</legaldoc>