<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id666"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lettings and Contracts" statutenumber="73-1113"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>73-1113</statuteno><catchline>Construction manager-general contractor contract; request for qualifications; content; publication; short list.</catchline><para>(1) An authorized agency shall prepare a request for qualifications for construction manager-general contractor contract proposals and shall prequalify construction managers. The request for qualifications shall describe the project in sufficient detail to permit a construction manager to respond. The request for qualifications shall identify the maximum number of eligible construction managers the authorized agency will place on a short list as qualified and eligible to receive a request for proposals.</para><para>(2)(a) The request for qualifications shall be published:</para><para>(i) In a newspaper of statewide circulation once a week for three consecutive weeks prior to the deadline for receiving requests for qualifications; or</para><para>(ii) For twenty-one consecutive calendar days prior to the deadline for receiving requests for qualifications on a website designated by the authorized agency that is accessible to the public.</para><para>(b) The authorized agency may publish notice both in such a newspaper and on such a website as described in this subsection.</para><para>(3) The authorized agency shall create a short list of qualified and eligible construction managers in accordance with the guidelines adopted pursuant to section 73-1106. The authorized agency shall select at least two construction managers, except that if only one construction manager has responded to the request for qualifications, the authorized agency may, in its discretion, proceed or cancel the procurement. The request for proposals shall be sent only to the construction managers placed on the short list.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB660, &#167; 13. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>