<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<legaldoc>
<law type="statute"><section id="id370"><amendatorysection chaptername="Public Lettings and Contracts" statutenumber="73-1104"><bookinfo>Revised Statutes Supplement, 2025</bookinfo><statuteno>73-1104</statuteno><catchline>Design-build contract or construction manager-general contractor contract; authorized; approval required; procedure.</catchline><para>(1) An authorized agency, in accordance with the State Building Construction Alternatives Act, may solicit and execute a design-build contract or a construction manager-general contractor contract for state buildings for which the authorized agency has responsibility except as otherwise provided in section 73-1103.</para><para>(2) Before executing a design-build contract or construction manager-general contractor contract, an authorized agency shall submit a request for approval from the Director of Administrative Services or his or her designee. The request shall include the following:</para><para>(a) A written determination that, due to the nature, detail, or circumstances of a project, the use of a design-build contract or construction manager-general contractor contract is justified. The determination shall include a description of facts justifying such use and state whether the authorized agency is planning to use a design-build contract or a construction manager-general contractor contract;</para><para>(b) The criteria for making such determination, including the following factors:</para><para>(i) The cost of the project;</para><para>(ii) The anticipated schedule for the project from preparation for contracting through completion of construction;</para><para>(iii) The overall complexity of the project;</para><para>(iv) The need to overlap design and construction phases of the project; or</para><para>(v) An emergency exists that requires the use of an accelerated schedule to make repairs; and</para><para>(c) An explanation of how using a design-build contract or construction manager-general contractor contract will not result in favoritism or substantially diminish competition in awarding such contract for such project.</para></amendatorysection></section><source><para>Laws 2025, LB660, &#167; 4. </para><operativedate>September 3, 2025</operativedate></source></law>
</legaldoc>